<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-21/chapter-96"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-21/chapter-96"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="21.96"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-21/chapter-96/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-21/chapter-96/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-21/chapter-96/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-21/chapter-96/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_21">
        <num>21</num>
        <heading>Insurance</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_21__chp_96">
          <num>96</num>
          <heading>Miscellaneous Provisions</heading>
          <section eId="sec_21-96-010">
            <num>21.96.010</num>
            <heading>Settlements.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 21.96.010.   Settlements.
A settlement made under a motor vehicle liability insurance policy of a claim against an insured arising under that policy from an accident or other event insured against for damage to or destruction of property owned by another person may not be construed as an admission of liability by the insured, or the insurer's recognition of that liability, with respect to any other claim arising from the same accident or event.  The settlement shall be inadmissable in evidence in any legal action.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_21-96-015">
            <num>21.96.015</num>
            <heading>Workplace safety program.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 21.96.015.   Workplace safety program.
An insurer who provides workers' compensation insurance in this state shall establish and maintain a workplace safety rate reduction program, subject to the approval of the division.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_21-96-018">
            <num>21.96.018</num>
            <heading>Transportation network company insurance provisions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="21-96-018__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Insurers that write automobile insurance in the state may, notwithstanding any requirement under
AS 28.20
, exclude any and all coverage afforded under the policy issued to an owner or operator of a personal vehicle for any loss or injury that occurs while a driver is logged onto the digital network of a transportation network company or while a driver provides a prearranged ride. The right to exclude all coverage may apply to any coverage included in an automobile insurance policy, including</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-018__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>liability coverage for bodily injury and property damage;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-018__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>uninsured and underinsured motorist coverage;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-018__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>medical payments coverage;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-018__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>comprehensive physical damage coverage; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-018__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>collision physical damage coverage.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-018__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing in this section</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-018__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>implies or requires that a personal automobile insurance policy provide coverage while the driver
(A) is logged onto the digital network of a transportation network company;
(B) is engaged in a prearranged ride; or
(C) otherwise uses a personal vehicle to transport passengers for compensation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-018__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>may be construed to require an insurer to use specific policy language or to refer to this section in order to exclude any and all coverage for any loss or injury that occurs while a driver
(A) is logged onto the digital network of a transportation network company; or
(B) provides a prearranged ride; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-018__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>precludes an insurer from providing coverage for the personal vehicle of a transportation network company driver if the insurer chooses to provide coverage by contract or endorsement.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-018__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Automobile insurers that exclude coverage under (a) of this section do not have a duty to defend or indemnify any claim expressly excluded under (a) of this section. Nothing in this section may be considered to invalidate or limit an exclusion contained in a policy, including any policy in use or approved for use in this state before the enactment of this section, that excludes coverage for vehicles used to carry persons or property for a charge or available for hire by the public.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-018__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An automobile insurer that defends or indemnifies a claim against a driver that is excluded under the terms of the automobile insurer's policy shall have a right of contribution against other insurers that provide automobile insurance to the same driver in satisfaction of the coverage requirements of
AS 28.23.050
at the time of loss.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-018__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In a claims coverage investigation, a transportation network company shall immediately provide, upon request by directly involved parties or any insurer of the transportation network company driver, if applicable, the precise times that a transportation network company driver logged onto and off of the digital network of a transportation network company in the 12-hour period immediately preceding and in the 12-hour period immediately following the accident. Insurers potentially providing coverage shall disclose, upon request of any insurer involved in the claim, the applicable coverages, exclusions, and limits provided under any automobile insurance maintained under
AS 28.23.050
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-018__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, digital network, driver, personal vehicle, prearranged ride, transportation network company, and transportation network company driver have the meanings given in
AS 28.23.180
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_21-96-020">
            <num>21.96.020</num>
            <heading>Required motor vehicle coverage.</heading>
            <subsection eId="21-96-020__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An automobile liability policy that insures an owner or operator of a motor vehicle against loss resulting from liability for bodily injury or death, or for property injury or destruction, or both, that is sold in the state, must contain limits in at least the amount prescribed for a motor vehicle liability policy in
AS 28.20.440
or
AS 28.22.101
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-020__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This section may not be construed to apply only to automobile liability policies obtained to satisfy a requirement of
AS 28.20
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-020__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An insurance company offering automobile liability insurance in this state for bodily injury or death shall, initially and at each renewal, offer coverage prescribed in
AS 28.20.440
and 28.20.445 or
AS 28.22
for the protection of the persons insured under the policy who are legally entitled to recover damages for bodily injury or death from owners or operators of uninsured or underinsured motor vehicles. The limit written may not be less than the limit in
AS 28.20.440
or
AS 28.22.101
. Coverage required to be offered under this section must include the following options:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-020__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>policy limits equal to the limits voluntarily purchased to cover the liability of the person insured for bodily injury or death; coverage for punitive damages that might otherwise be recoverable from an uninsured or underinsured person is not required under this paragraph;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-020__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>except when the coverage consists of motorcycle liability insurance, and except for a named insured required to file proof of financial responsibility under
AS 28.20
or an applicant required to file proof of financial responsibility under
AS 28.20
, policy limits in the following amounts when these limits are greater than those offered under (1) of this subsection:
(A) $100,000 because of bodily injury to or death of one person in one accident, and, subject to the same limit for one person, $300,000 because of bodily injury to or death of two or more persons in one accident;
(B) $300,000 because of bodily injury to or death of one person in one accident, and, subject to the same limit for one person, $500,000 because of bodily injury to or death of two or more persons in one accident;
(C) $500,000 because of bodily injury to or death of one person in one accident, and, subject to the same limit for one person, $500,000 because of bodily injury to or death of two or more persons in one accident;
(D) $500,000 because of bodily injury to or death of one person in one accident, and, subject to the same limit for one person, $1,000,000 because of bodily injury to or death of two or more persons in one accident;
(E) $1,000,000 because of bodily injury to or death of one person in one accident, and, subject to the same limit for one person, $2,000,000 because of bodily injury to or death of two or more persons in one accident;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-020__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>other policy limits at the option of the insurer.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-020__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An insurance company offering automobile liability insurance in this state for injury to or destruction of property shall offer coverage prescribed in
AS 28.20.440
and 28.20.445, or
AS 28.22
, with limits not less than those prescribed in
AS 28.20.440
or
AS 28.22.101
, to cover the insured person's liability for injury to or destruction of property, for the protection of the persons insured under the policy who are legally entitled to recover damages for injury to or destruction of the covered motor vehicle from owners or operators of uninsured or underinsured motor vehicles.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-020__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The coverage required under (c) and (d) of this section may be waived in writing by the insured in whole or in part.  After selection of the limits by the insured or the exercise of the option to waive the coverage in whole or in part, the insurer is not required to notify any policy holder in any renewal, supplemental, or replacement policy, as to the availability of the coverage or optional limits, and the waived coverage may not be included in any renewal, supplemental, or replacement policy. The insured may, at any time, make a written request for additional coverage or coverage more extensive than that provided on a prior policy.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-020__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An automobile liability insurance policy must provide</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-020__subsec_f__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>that all expenses and fees, not including counsel fees or adjuster fees, incurred because of arbitration or mediation shall be paid as determined by the arbitrator;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-020__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>liability coverage in the amount set out in
AS 28.22.101</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-020__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>for motor vehicles rented in the United States or Canada by a person insured under the policy;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-020__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>physical damage coverage for motor vehicles rented in the United States or Canada, if the policy provides physical damage coverage; if the insured declines physical damage coverage, the insurer shall offer physical damage coverage for rented vehicles;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-020__subsec_d__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>that payments from applicable coverage provided under (2) and (3) of this subsection will be made in the following order of priority:
(A) from a policy or coverage purchased by the operator from the person who has the vehicle available for rent;
(B) from a policy or coverage covering the operator of a rented vehicle but not purchased from the person who has the vehicle available for rent; and
(C) from a policy or coverage of the person who has the vehicle available for rent.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-020__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An insurance company offering automobile liability insurance in this state shall offer a short term policy valid for no more than seven days. The coverage available for the short term policy must be comparable to coverage available for longer term policies. The provisions of
AS 21.36.210
 21.36.310 do not apply to short term policies issued under this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-020__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The selection, rejection, or exercise of the option not to purchase, by a named insured or an applicant, shall be valid for all insureds under the policy.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-020__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, automobile liability insurance does not include coverage provided only on an excess or umbrella basis.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_21-96-025">
            <num>21.96.025</num>
            <heading>Motor vehicle insurance rate reductions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="21-96-025__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An insurer shall provide an appropriate reduction in the premium charged for a personal motor vehicle liability insurance policy when the principal operator of the motor vehicle covered by the insurance policy</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-025__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is 55 years of age or older;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-025__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>at renewal requests the insurer to provide the reduction;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-025__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has had no chargeable accidents as set by established underwriting guidelines in use by the insurer or moving motor vehicle citations within three years preceding the request for the discount;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-025__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provides the insurer with proof satisfactory to the director that the operator has within the three years before requesting the reduction taken and successfully completed a motor vehicle accident prevention course approved by the Department of Administration under
AS 28.05.035
; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-025__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>did not take and complete the accident prevention course described in (4) of this subsection as a result of an order or sentence imposed by a court.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-025__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An insurer may cancel a rate reduction provided under (a) of this section if during the policy period the principal operator of the insured motor vehicle is</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-025__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>involved in an accident caused by the operator; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-025__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>convicted of a moving traffic violation.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-025__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The reduced rate provided for an operator under (a) of this section may not extend beyond three years after the last day of the operator's most recently successfully completed motor vehicle accident prevention course described in (a)(4) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-025__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The director shall establish by regulation the manner in which insurers inform applicants and insureds of the rate reduction available under this section. An insurer shall inform applicants and insureds as required by this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_21-96-027">
            <num>21.96.027</num>
            <heading>Motor vehicle insurance following driver's license revocation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 21.96.027.   Motor vehicle insurance following driver's license revocation.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_21-96-027">
            <num>21.96.027</num>
            <heading>Motor vehicle insurance following driver's license revocation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 21.96.027.   Motor vehicle insurance following driver's license revocation.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_21-96-030">
            <num>21.96.030</num>
            <heading>Payment.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 21.96.030.   Payment.
Unless another form of payment is agreed to by the policyholder or beneficiary, an insurance company doing business in this state may not pay a judgment or settlement of a claim in this state for a loss incurred in this state with an instrument other than a negotiable bank check payable on demand and bearing even date with the date of writing or by electronic funds transfer.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_21-96-035">
            <num>21.96.035</num>
            <heading>Mandatory appraisal.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 21.96.035.   Mandatory appraisal.
A motor vehicle or similar policy, a policy providing property coverage, or any other policy providing first party property, casualty, or inland marine coverage, issued or delivered in this state, must include an appraisal clause providing a contractual means to resolve a dispute between the insured and the insurer over the value of a covered first party loss for real property, personal property, business property, or similar risks. If the insured and the insurer fail to agree on the amount of a covered first party loss, either may make written demand upon the other to submit the dispute for appraisal. Within 10 days of the written demand, the insured and insurer must notify the other of the competent appraiser each has selected. The two appraisers will promptly choose a competent and impartial umpire. Not later than 15 days after the umpire has been chosen, unless the time period is extended by the umpire, each appraiser will separately state in writing the amount of the loss. If the appraisers submit a written report of agreement on the amount of the loss, the agreed amount will be binding upon the insured and insurer. If the appraisers fail to agree, the appraisers will promptly submit their differences to the umpire. A decision agreed to by one of the appraisers and the umpire will be binding upon the insured and insurer. All expenses and fees, not including counsel or adjuster fees, incurred because of the appraisal shall be paid as determined by the umpire. Except as specifically provided, nothing in this section is intended to or shall in any manner limit or restrict the rights of insureds or insurers or confer any rights to an insured or insurer.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_21-96-050">
            <num>21.96.050</num>
            <heading>Arson information.</heading>
            <subsection eId="21-96-050__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When an insurer has reason to believe that a fire loss in which it has an interest may have been caused by other than accidental means, it shall immediately supply a written report of that fact to the Department of Public Safety.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-050__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When requested in writing by an authorized agency, an insurer shall supply all available information relating to a particular fire loss to the agency.  The information requested may include</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-050__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>insurance policy information pertaining to a fire loss under investigation and any application for the policy;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-050__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>policy premium payment records;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-050__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a history of previous claims made by the insured; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-050__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>material relating to the investigation of the loss, including statements of a person who may have information about the loss and any proof of the loss.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-050__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notification to the Department of Public Safety under (a) of this section does not relieve the insurer of the duty to respond to a request for information from an authorized agency under (b) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-050__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An authorized agency provided with information under (a) or (b) of this section may release the information to another authorized agency.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-050__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In (a)-(d) of this section, authorized agency means a fire department, a local or federal law enforcement agency responsible for the investigation of fires, the Department of Law, the state fire marshal, the United States attorney's office, and the Department of Public Safety.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-050__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An authorized agency shall share with the insurer all relevant information relating to an instance of suspected arson when</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-050__subsec_f__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Department of Law has determined that release of the information would not jeopardize the success of an ongoing investigation and that there are adequate safeguards to insure the confidentiality of the information;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-050__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the agency has completed its investigation and a decision not to prosecute has been made; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-050__subsec_f__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>criminal prosecution has been brought and the defendant has pled guilty, or the jury or other trier of fact has returned a verdict, and no appeal has been taken.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-050__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In (f) of this section, authorized agency means a fire department, a local law enforcement agency responsible for the investigation of fires, the Department of Law, the state fire marshal, and the Department of Public Safety.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-050__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person is not civilly liable or subject to criminal prosecution for releasing information under this section unless the act constitutes a malicious attempt to injure an insured.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_21-96-060">
            <num>21.96.060</num>
            <heading>Medicare supplemental insurance.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 21.96.060.   Medicare supplemental insurance.
The director shall adopt regulations necessary to comply with the requirements of 42 U.S.C. 1395ss, and any amendments to that section or federal regulations pertaining to that section, so that the state may retain full authority to set certain standards for Medicare supplemental insurance.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_21-96-070">
            <num>21.96.070</num>
            <heading>Insurance tax education credit.</heading>
            <subsection eId="21-96-070__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A taxpayer is allowed a credit against the tax due under
AS 21.09.210
or
AS 21.66.110
for</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-070__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>contributions of cash or equipment accepted for direct instruction, research, and educational support purposes, including library and museum acquisitions, and contributions to endowment, by an Alaska university foundation or by a nonprofit, public or private, Alaska two-year or four-year college accredited by a national or regional accreditation association;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-070__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>contributions of cash or equipment accepted for secondary school level vocational education courses, programs, and facilities by a school district in the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-070__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>contributions of cash or equipment accepted for vocational education courses, programs, and facilities by a state-operated vocational technical education and training school;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-070__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>contributions of cash or equipment accepted for a facility by a nonprofit, public or private, Alaska two-year or four-year college accredited by a national or regional accreditation association;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-070__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>contributions of cash or equipment accepted for Alaska Native cultural or heritage programs and educational support, including mentoring and tutoring, provided by a nonprofit agency for public school staff and for students who are in grades kindergarten through 12 in the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-070__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>contributions of cash or equipment accepted for education, research, rehabilitation, and facilities by an institution that is located in the state and that qualifies as a coastal ecosystem learning center under the Coastal America Partnership established by the federal government;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-070__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>contributions of cash or equipment accepted for the operation of a nonprofit educational resource center that supports academic achievement in grades nine through 12 by coordinating curricula and statewide competition in the subject areas of economics, science, social science, literature, music, art, mathematics, writing, speech, and interview skills and by providing student scholarships;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-070__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>expenditures made to operate a child care facility in the state for the children of the taxpayer's employees;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-070__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>contributions of cash or equipment accepted by a child care facility in the state operated by a nonprofit corporation and attended by one or more children of the taxpayer's employees; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-070__subsec_a__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a payment to an employee of the taxpayer made by the taxpayer for the purpose of offsetting the employee's child care costs incurred in the state.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-070__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The amount of the credit is 50 percent of contributions.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-070__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each public college and university shall include in its annual operating budget request contributions received and how the contributions were used.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-070__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A contribution claimed as a credit under this section may not</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-070__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>be the basis for a credit claimed under another provision of this title; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-070__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>when combined with contributions that are the basis for credits taken during the taxpayer's tax year under
AS 43.20.014
,
AS 43.55.019
,
AS 43.56.018
,
AS 43.65.018
,
AS 43.75.018
, or
AS 43.77.045
, result in the total amount of credits exceeding $3,000,000; if the taxpayer is a member of an affiliated group, then the total amount of credits may not exceed $3,000,000 for the affiliated group; in this paragraph, affiliated group has the meaning given in
AS 43.20.145
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-070__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The credit under this section may not reduce a person's tax liability under
AS 21.09.210
or
AS 21.66.110
to below zero for any tax year. An unused credit or portion of a credit not used under this section for a tax year may not be sold, traded, transferred, or applied in a subsequent tax year.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-070__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To qualify for a credit under this section, equipment must be appraised consistent with regulations adopted by the Department of Revenue to determine the value of the contribution for purposes of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-070__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Beginning January 1, 2030, and every five years thereafter, the Department of Labor and Workforce Development shall adjust the dollar limit on credits under (d) of this section for inflation, using 100 percent of the change over the preceding five calendar years in the Consumer Price Index for all urban consumers for urban Alaska, compiled by the Bureau of Labor Statistics, United States Department of Labor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-070__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-070__subsec_h__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>school district means a borough school district, a city school district, a regional educational attendance area, or a state boarding school;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-070__subsec_h__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>vocational education has the meaning given in
AS 43.20.014
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_21-96-075">
            <num>21.96.075</num>
            <heading>Insurance tax credit for gifts to the Alaska Fire Standards Council.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 21.96.075.   Insurance tax credit for gifts to the Alaska Fire Standards Council.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_21-96-075">
            <num>21.96.075</num>
            <heading>Insurance tax credit for gifts to the Alaska Fire Standards Council.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 21.96.075.   Insurance tax credit for gifts to the Alaska Fire Standards Council.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_21-96-080">
            <num>21.96.080</num>
            <heading>Electronic transactions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="21-96-080__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding any contrary provision of this title, the director may, by regulation or by order, provide for the electronic transaction of any information or written communication under this title.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-080__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An electronic transaction under this section must comply with
AS 09.80
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_21-96-090">
            <num>21.96.090</num>
            <heading>Risk retention groups and purchasing groups.</heading>
            <subsection eId="21-96-090__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A risk retention group or a purchasing group formed under and in compliance with 15 U.S.C. 3901  3906 (Liability Risk Retention Act) shall register with the director and shall at all times transact business in compliance with federal law and with the laws of this state that are not preempted by federal law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-090__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A risk retention group or a purchasing group shall apply for initial registration on forms prescribed by the director. Payment of a registration fee established under
AS 21.06.250
shall be submitted with the application.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-090__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A risk retention group or a purchasing group may continue its registration if it is in compliance with federal law. Payment of an annual continuation fee established under
AS 21.06.250
shall be submitted with the continuation application.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-090__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A risk retention group holding a valid certificate of authority as a domestic insurer or a purchasing group duly licensed under
AS 21.27
as a resident licensee is not required to be additionally registered under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-090__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to any other penalty provided by law, a person that the director determines under
AS 21.06.170
 21.06.240 has violated a provision of this title relative to a risk retention group or a purchasing group is subject to a civil penalty of not more than $10,000 for a violation or, if the director determines that the person wilfully violated a provision of this title, a civil penalty of not more than $25,000 for a violation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-090__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The director may adopt regulations on the operation and reporting requirements of a risk retention group that are not in conflict with 15 U.S.C. 3901  3906 (Liability Risk Retention Act).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_21-96-100">
            <num>21.96.100</num>
            <heading>Appointment of independent counsel; conflicts of interest; settlement.</heading>
            <subsection eId="21-96-100__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If an insurer has a duty to defend an insured under a policy of insurance and a conflict of interest arises that imposes a duty on the insurer to provide independent counsel to the insured, the insurer shall provide independent counsel to the insured unless the insured in writing waives the right to independent counsel. An insurance policy may contain a provision that provides a method of selecting independent counsel if the provision complies with this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-100__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of this section, the following do not constitute a conflict of interest:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-100__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a claim of punitive damages;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-100__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a claim of damages in excess of the policy limits;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-100__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>claims or facts in a civil action for which the insurer denies coverage.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-100__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (b) of this section, if the insurer reserves the insurer's rights on an issue for which coverage is denied, the insurer shall provide independent counsel to the insured as provided under (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-100__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the insured selects independent counsel at the insurer's expense, the insurer may require that the independent counsel have at least four years of experience in civil litigation, including defense experience in the general subject area at issue in the civil action, and malpractice insurance. Unless otherwise provided in the insurance policy, the obligation of the insurer to pay the fee charged by the independent counsel is limited to the rate that is actually paid by the insurer to an attorney in the ordinary course of business in the defense of a similar civil action in the community in which the claim arose or is being defended. In providing independent counsel, the insurer is not responsible for the fees and costs of defending an allegation for which coverage is properly denied and shall be responsible only for the fees and costs to defend those allegations for which the insurer either reserves its position as to coverage or accepts coverage. The independent counsel shall keep detailed records allocating fees and costs accordingly. A dispute between the insurer and insured regarding attorney fees that is not resolved by the insurance policy or this section shall be resolved by arbitration under
AS 09.43
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-100__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the insured selects independent counsel at the insurer's expense, the independent counsel and the insured shall consult with the insurer on all matters relating to the civil action and shall disclose to the insurer in a timely manner all information relevant to the civil action, except information that is privileged and relevant to disputed coverage. A claim of privilege is subject to review in the appropriate court. Information disclosed by the independent counsel or the insured does not waive another party's right to assert privilege.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-100__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An insured may waive the right to select independent counsel by signing a statement that reads substantially as follows:
I have been advised of my right to select independent counsel to represent me in this lawsuit and of my right under state law to have all reasonable expenses of an independent counsel paid by my insurer. I have also been advised that the Alaska Supreme Court has ruled that when an insurer defends an insured under a reservation of rights provision in an insurance policy, there are various conflicts of interest that arise between an insurer and an insured. I have considered this matter fully and at this time I am waiving my right to select independent counsel. I have authorized my insurer to select a defense counsel to represent me in this lawsuit.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-100__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If an insured selects independent counsel under this section, both the counsel representing the insurer and independent counsel representing the insured shall be allowed to participate in all aspects of the civil action. Counsel for the insurer and insured shall cooperate fully in exchanging information that is consistent with ethical and legal obligations to the insured. Nothing in this section relieves the insured of the duty to cooperate fully with the insurer as required by the terms of the insurance policy.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-100__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When an insured is represented by independent counsel, the insurer may settle directly with the plaintiff if the settlement includes all claims based upon the allegations for which the insurer previously reserved its position as to coverage or accepted coverage, regardless of whether the settlement extinguishes all claims against the insured.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_21-96-110">
            <num>21.96.110</num>
            <heading>Viatical settlement transactions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="21-96-110__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The director shall regulate the transaction of viatical settlement contracts for the protection of viators, insureds, and insurers. The authority of the director under this subsection extends to the regulation of transactions between a viator and a viatical settlement provider and between a viator and a person acting as an agent in viaticating a life insurance policy, while the authority of the commissioner extends to the regulation of viatical settlement investments as provided under
AS 45.56
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-110__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A viatical settlement provider, representative, or broker must apply for a license with the director, submit information required by the director, and pay the required fee established under
AS 21.06.250
with the application for licensure. A person may not act as or represent to be a viatical settlement provider, representative, or broker relative to a subject resident, located, or to be performed in this state unless licensed under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-110__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Viatical settlement contract forms, viator and insured disclosure statements, and viatical settlement advertising materials must be filed by the viatical settlement provider, representative, or broker with the director and must be approved by the director.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-110__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The director may examine a licensed viatical settlement provider, representative, or broker, or an applicant for a viatical settlement provider, representative, or broker license. The cost of the examination shall be paid by the person examined under
AS 21.06.160
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-110__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as may be required in the course of conduct of the division's responsibilities, a viatical settlement provider, representative, or broker may not disclose to another person the identity of the viator or insured of an insurance policy that is the subject of a viatical settlement contract. The viator may waive this prohibition against disclosure if the waiver is in writing and is signed by the viator.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-110__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The director may adopt regulations to implement this section, including standards for</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-110__subsec_f__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>viatical settlement provider, representative, and broker reporting requirements and records retention;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-110__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>viator and insured privacy protection;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-110__subsec_f__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>viatical settlement contract provisions, advertising materials, and filing requirements;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-110__subsec_f__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>payments to viators or insureds, including evaluating the reasonableness of payments under a viatical settlement contract;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-110__subsec_f__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>licensing requirements, including license qualification, disqualification, and renewal;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-110__subsec_f__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>financial accountability of viatical settlement providers;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-110__subsec_f__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the relationship and responsibilities of insurers, viators, insureds, and viatical settlement providers, representatives, and brokers in the transaction of a viatical settlement contract;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-110__subsec_f__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>viator, insured, and insurer protection, including full and fair disclosure setting out the manner and content of required disclosures and filing requirements; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-110__subsec_f__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>assessment of fees to cover the cost of regulating viatical settlement contracts, providers, representatives, and brokers.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-110__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A violation of this section or a regulation adopted under this section is an unfair trade practice and subject to penalty under
AS 21.36
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-110__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-110__subsec_h__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>transaction means, with respect to viatical settlement contracts,
(A) solicitation and inducement;
(B) preliminary negotiations;
(C) effectuation of a viatical settlement contract;
(D) transaction of matters subsequent to the effectuation of the viatical settlement contract and arising out of it;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-110__subsec_h__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>viatical settlement broker
(A) means a person that, on behalf of a viator or insured and for a fee, commission, or other valuable consideration, offers or attempts to negotiate viatical settlement contracts between a viator or insured and one or more viatical settlement providers;
(B) does not include a person acting as an attorney or accountant retained to represent a viator or insured and compensated by or at the direction of the viator or insured;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-110__subsec_h__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>viatical settlement contract
(A) means a written agreement between a viator or insured and a viatical settlement provider for the sale, assignment, transfer, devise, or bequest to the viatical settlement provider by the viator or insured of all or a portion of the death benefit or ownership of a life insurance policy for consideration that is less than the expected death benefit of the life insurance policy;
(B) includes a contract for a loan or other financial transaction secured primarily by an individual or group life insurance policy;
(C) does not include</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-110__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>a loan by a life insurance company under the terms of a life insurance contract;
(ii) a loan secured by the cash value of a policy;
(iii) the assignment of a life insurance policy as collateral for a loan to a bank, saving bank, savings and loan association, credit union, or other licensed lending institution;
(iv) the exercise by the viator or insured of an accelerated benefits provision under the terms of the life insurance contract; or</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-110__subsec_v">
              <num>(v)</num>
              <content>
                <p>the sale, assignment, transfer, devise, or bequest of a life insurance policy for less than the expected death benefit by a viator or insured to a friend or family member if the friend or family member does not enter into more than one agreement in a calendar year;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-110__subsec_v__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>viatical settlement provider means a person, other than a viator or insured, that enters into a viatical settlement contract, including a person that
(A) obtains financing for the purchase, acquisition, transfer, or other assignment of one or more viatical settlement contracts, viaticated policies, or interests in viatical settlement contracts or viaticated policies; or
(B) sells, assigns, transfers, pledges, hypothecates, or disposes of one or more viatical settlement contracts, viaticated policies, or interests in viatical settlement contracts or viaticated policies;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-110__subsec_v__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>viatical settlement representative
(A) means a person that is an authorized agent of a viatical settlement provider or broker and that acts or aids in any manner in the transaction of a viatical settlement contract;
(B) does not include</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-96-110__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>a person acting as an attorney or an accountant, or a person exercising a power of attorney granted by a viator or insured; or
(ii) a person retained to represent a viator or insured and compensated by or at the direction of the viator or insured;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-110__subsec_i__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>viaticated policy means a life insurance policy that has been acquired by a viatical settlement provider under a viatical settlement contract;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-96-110__subsec_i__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>viator means the owner of a life insurance policy insuring the life of an individual who enters or seeks to enter into a viatical settlement contract.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_21-96-120">
            <num>21.96.120</num>
            <heading>Waiver for state innovation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 21.96.120.   Waiver for state innovation.
The director may apply to the United States Secretary of Health and Human Services under 42 U.S.C. 18052 for a waiver of applicable provisions of P.L. 111-148 (Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act) with respect to health insurance coverage in the state for a plan year beginning on or after January 1, 2017. The director may implement a state plan meeting the waiver requirements in a manner consistent with state and federal law and as approved by the United States Secretary of Health and Human Services.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_21-96-200">
            <num>21.96.200</num>
            <heading>Good faith estimate.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 21.96.200.   Good faith estimate.
Upon request of a covered person who is receiving nonemergency health care services, a health care insurer shall provide a good faith estimate of the amount of the reasonably anticipated charges for treating the patient's specific condition under
AS 18.23.400
(g).</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>