<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-47/chapter-27"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-47/chapter-27"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="47.27"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-47/chapter-27/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-47/chapter-27/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-47/chapter-27/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-47/chapter-27/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_47">
        <num>47</num>
        <heading>Welfare, Social Services, and Institutions</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_47__chp_27">
          <num>27</num>
          <heading>Alaska Temporary Assistance Program</heading>
          <section eId="sec_47-27-005">
            <num>47.27.005</num>
            <heading>Duties of the department.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.27.005.   Duties of the department.
The department shall
(1) administer the Alaska temporary assistance program by providing cash assistance, diversion payments, and self-sufficiency services to needy children and their families under this chapter and, if appropriate, by establishing regional public assistance programs to provide effectively for varying conditions in regions of the state designated by the department;
(2) establish, by regulation, program standards for incentives to work, incentives for financial planning, cash assistance, diversion payments, self-sufficiency services, and other opportunities to develop self-sufficiency;
(3) prepare, submit to the federal government, and amend, if necessary, a state plan designed to ensure that federal money is available to the state for the operation of the program set out in this chapter to provide cash assistance, diversion payments, and self-sufficiency services to needy children and their families consistent with the state objectives identified in (2) of this section;
(4) adopt methods of program administration to ensure consistency with the federal requirements under the federal Temporary Assistance for Needy Families program;
(5) make reports regarding the program to the federal government as required under federal law, in the form and containing the information required, and comply with the provisions that the federal government determines are necessary to ensure correct and verifiable information on the program;
(6) provide to the legislature an annual executive summary of the information required to be reported to the federal government under (5) of this section;
(7) conduct studies and research in order to evaluate and monitor the effectiveness of the state program; and
(8) adopt regulations and take action to implement, interpret, and administer the provisions of this chapter.
Article 2. Alaska Temporary Assistance Program.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-27-010">
            <num>47.27.010</num>
            <heading>Eligible families.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.27.010.   Eligible families.
The following families may apply under the Alaska temporary assistance program:
(1) a single parent who has the physical custody of one or more related dependent children;
(2) a caretaker of one or more dependent children who is a relative to at least the fifth degree;
(3) a woman in the last trimester of pregnancy;
(4) a two-parent family with physical custody of one or more related dependent children.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-27-015">
            <num>47.27.015</num>
            <heading>Disqualifying conditions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-27-015__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A family is not eligible for cash assistance under the Alaska temporary assistance program if the family includes an adult who</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-015__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has received cash assistance under the Alaska temporary assistance program, or a program of another state operated under a federal assistance grant program for needy families, for a total of 60 months as the caretaker or spouse of a caretaker of a dependent child or as a pregnant woman, unless the caretaker or pregnant woman is
(A) a person who the department has reasonable cause to believe is or recently has been the victim of domestic violence, as defined in
AS 18.66.990
, and the physical, mental, or emotional well-being of the victim would be endangered by a strict application of the time limit otherwise applicable under this subsection;
(B) determined, under regulations of the department to be physically or mentally unable to perform gainful activity;
(C) a parent who is providing care for a child who is experiencing a disability; or
(D) a family determined by the department to be exempt from this paragraph by reason of hardship; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-015__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is determined to be fleeing to avoid prosecution, custody, or confinement after conviction, in this or another jurisdiction, for a crime that is classified as a felony or a class A misdemeanor under
AS 11
or the criminal laws of the jurisdiction where the criminal activity was committed.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-015__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A family is not eligible for cash assistance or self-sufficiency services under this chapter for a period of 120 months beginning on the date the adult applicant for the family is convicted of having fraudulently misrepresented the applicant's residence in order to receive cash assistance or self-sufficiency services in more than one state under a program financed with federal money under any successor federal program that replaces the aid to families with dependent children program.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-015__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A family is not eligible for cash assistance for the following time periods if the family's demonstrated need for cash assistance is due to a refusal of or voluntary separation from suitable employment by the adult applicant, or a custodial parent or caretaker, without good cause:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-015__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>one month for the first refusal or separation without good cause;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-015__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>six months for the second refusal or separation without good cause; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-015__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>12 months for the third and subsequent refusal or separation without good cause.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-015__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A family is not eligible for cash assistance or self-sufficiency services for up to 12 months if the family's demonstrated need is due to an intentional transfer of an asset or assets at less than fair market value for the purpose of establishing eligibility for cash assistance or self-sufficiency services. A period of ineligibility shall begin on the first day of the month following the transfer of the asset or assets and shall remain in effect for a number of months equal to the fair market value of the transferred asset or assets divided by the maximum payment amount for the family as established under
AS 47.27.025
, or for 12 months, whichever is less.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-015__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An Alaska temporary assistance program applicant or participant who is administratively disqualified for making a false statement or misrepresentation knowing it was false, or for knowingly failing to disclose a material fact, in order to obtain or increase cash assistance or self-sufficiency services under this chapter is not eligible to receive cash assistance or self-sufficiency services under this chapter for a period of</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-015__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>six months following the first disqualification;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-015__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>12 months following the second disqualification; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-015__subsec_e__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>permanently following the third disqualification.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-015__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The number of families for which an exemption is in effect under (a)(1) of this section may not exceed 25 percent of the number of families receiving cash assistance under this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-015__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who is an alien is not eligible for cash assistance under this chapter unless the person is a qualified alien under 8 U.S.C. 1641 or an alien excepted under 8 U.S.C. 1612(b). However, a qualified alien may only be eligible for cash assistance under this chapter if the person is not precluded by the limited eligibility provision of 8 U.S.C. 1613.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-015__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When determining under (a)(1) of this section whether an adult has received cash assistance for a total of 60 months, the department shall disregard the months that are required to be disregarded under 42 U.S.C. 608(a)(7)(D).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-015__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person convicted after August 22, 1996, of an offense that is classified as a felony under
AS 11.71.010
- 11.71.040 or by the law of another jurisdiction that has as an element the possession, use, or distribution of a controlled substance, as defined in
AS 11.71.900
, is disqualified from receiving temporary assistance under this chapter or food stamps under
AS 47.25
unless the person demonstrates, to the satisfaction of the department, that the person</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-015__subsec_i__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is satisfactorily serving, or has successfully completed, a period of probation or parole;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-015__subsec_i__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is in the process of serving, or has successfully completed, mandatory participation in a drug or alcohol treatment program;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-015__subsec_i__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has taken action toward rehabilitation, including participation in a drug or alcohol treatment program; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-015__subsec_i__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is successfully complying with the requirements of the person's reentry plan.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-27-020">
            <num>47.27.020</num>
            <heading>Application requirements.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-27-020__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An applicant under the Alaska temporary assistance program shall complete an application in writing, or by electronic means, and in a format specified in regulations adopted by the department. Regulations adopted under this subsection must establish an electronic application for the program and allow an applicant to submit an application in electronic format or in other formats required by state and federal law. The applicant must be a pregnant woman or an individual who has physical custody of the dependent child or children. The application must be complete and must provide all of the information about the family and the child or children that is requested by the department. The applicant shall provide all supporting documentation for verification that the department determines to be necessary to establish eligibility. The electronic application must inform an applicant that a false statement made on the application will be investigated and is punishable under
AS 11.56.210
. In this subsection, electronic application means an application for benefits or renewal of benefits, whether the department exclusively administers the benefits or administers the benefits in coordination with another state agency or federal agency, electronically completed and submitted through the department's Internet website.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-020__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>On the application, each applicant shall attest to whether the family, at any time, has received cash assistance or self-sufficiency services from another state program that was established with federal money under the federal Temporary Assistance for Needy Families program and whether the family has ever been disqualified from receiving cash assistance or self-sufficiency services under the federal Temporary Assistance for Needy Families program for the period for which the application has been submitted.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-020__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An applicant shall agree to cooperate with the department to establish a family self-sufficiency plan and to participate in work activities when assigned by the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-020__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An applicant shall acknowledge the assignment of support rights as required by
AS 47.27.040</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-020__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and shall agree to cooperate with the child support services agency of the Department of Revenue to the extent required under
AS 47.27.040
(b). The applicant shall agree to report all child support payments received directly by the family, during or for a period for which the family is receiving cash assistance under this chapter, to the department within 15 days after receipt of those payments.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-020__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An applicant shall update the information requested in the application at regular intervals as established by the department in regulation. The department may conduct reviews of an application and audit the information provided as necessary to determine eligibility.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-27-025">
            <num>47.27.025</num>
            <heading>Cash assistance.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-27-025__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall provide cash assistance to families that establish eligibility based on a determination of need that considers the family's available income, assets, and other resources, as established by the department in regulation. Each dependent child in the family is eligible for cash assistance except as otherwise provided in
AS 47.27.015
or 47.27.027(b), and cash assistance received as a dependent child does not count against eligibility for cash assistance under this chapter as a caretaker or spouse of a caretaker of a dependent child or as a pregnant woman.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-025__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The amounts of cash assistance may not exceed the following:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-025__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for a dependent child living with a nonneedy relative caretaker, $452 per month, plus $102 for each additional child;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-025__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for a dependent child living with at least one needy parent or relative caretaker, $821 per month, plus $102 for each additional child and $102 for a second needy parent if the second parent is physically or mentally unable to perform gainful activity as defined by department regulation; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-025__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for a family consisting solely of an eligible pregnant woman, $514 per month.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-025__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall, for the months of July, August, and September, reduce by 50 percent the maximum cash assistance for which the family is otherwise eligible if the family's eligibility for cash assistance is based on
AS 47.27.010</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-025__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall reduce cash assistance under this section to the extent that the family's shelter costs are lower than the standard shelter allowance used by the department for similar families. The shelter allowance for a family whose costs are below the standard allowance shall be an amount equal to the family's actual verified shelter costs. In this subsection,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-025__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shelter allowance means the portion of the cash assistance provided under this section that is allocated by the department for shelter costs;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-025__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shelter costs means
(A) rental payments or mortgage payments for the family's housing, including payments made for property or mortgage insurance and property taxes; and
(B) the cost of utilities, including heat, electricity, basic telephone service, water, sewer, and garbage services incurred for the family's housing; the department may establish different utility cost standards for different areas of the state and may use an average utility cost per month based on estimated level payments over a 12-month period.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-025__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may, instead of paying all of the cash assistance to a family under this section, use all or part of the cash assistance as a wage subsidy paid to an employer who employs a person in the family at a wage that is higher than the wage subsidy. If authorized under
AS 47.25.975
(b), the department may, instead of paying all of a family's food stamp allotment under
AS 47.25.975
 47.25.990 in a form restricted to buying food, use all or part of the value of the family's food stamp allotment as a wage subsidy paid to an employer who employs a person in the family at a wage that is higher than the total of the wage subsidies paid under this subsection for employment of the person. A subsidy under this subsection may not exceed one year in duration.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-27-026">
            <num>47.27.026</num>
            <heading>Diversion payments.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-27-026__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may offer a lump-sum diversion payment in place of ongoing cash assistance to an adult applicant who applies under
AS 47.27.020
if the adult applicant is job ready and is determined to need only short-term financial assistance and self-sufficiency services to meet critical needs in order to secure employment and support for the adult applicant's family. The department shall set standards and conditions for diversion payments and self-sufficiency services by regulation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-026__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may pay a diversion payment to an applicant's family only if that family appears to be eligible for cash assistance under
AS 47.27.020
and to include a job-ready individual based on the information provided to the department in the application completed under
AS 47.27.020
. The department may offer to an applicant with the potential to participate in the diversion project a choice between</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-026__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>having the Alaska temporary assistance program application processed under
AS 47.27.020
and the regulations adopted by the department; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-026__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>having the application referred to the diversion project of the Alaska temporary assistance program for a determination of eligibility for a diversion project payment and self-sufficiency services under this section.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-026__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The amount of a diversion payment with self-sufficiency services must be sufficient to meet the family's immediate needs as determined by the department and the participant. A diversion payment may not exceed the amount the family would be eligible to receive as cash assistance in the first three months of eligibility under
AS 47.27.025
if the family did not elect to receive a diversion payment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-026__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>As a condition of a family receiving a diversion payment under this section, the participant must sign an agreement that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-026__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>specifies
(A) the amount of the diversion payment and the needs it is intended to cover;
(B) the self-sufficiency services required to meet the family's immediate needs;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-026__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provides that, during the three-month period beginning with the month in which the diversion payment was received, child support collected on behalf of a child whose needs were considered in determining the diversion payment shall be paid to the family; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-026__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provides that if the family reapplies under
AS 47.27.020
during the three months beginning with the month in which the family received a diversion payment, the diversion payment shall be treated as unearned income, prorated over the three-month period, and deducted from any cash assistance that the family may be eligible for under the new application.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-026__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A family that receives a diversion payment may not receive another diversion payment before the 12th month following the month in which it last received a diversion payment. A family may not receive more than four diversion payments.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-026__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To the extent that (d)(2) of this section is inconsistent with
AS 25.27.120
or 25.27.130, or with another provision of this chapter, (d)(2) of this section governs.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-27-027">
            <num>47.27.027</num>
            <heading>Assistance to minors.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-27-027__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If an applicant under
AS 47.27.020
is not married, is under the age of 18, and has not been previously emancipated under
AS 09.55.590
, the applicant must</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-027__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>live in a home maintained by the applicant's parent, legal guardian, or other adult relative, unless the applicant establishes that there is good cause, as established by the department in regulation, to waive this requirement; if the department waives this requirement, the applicant must live in an approved, adult-supervised, supportive living environment;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-027__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>agree that cash assistance on behalf of the applicant's family may be paid to the applicant's parent, legal guardian, or other adult relative, or, if applicable, to the adult head of the adult-supervised, supportive living environment in which the applicant resides; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-027__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>maintain attendance in a secondary school or other appropriate training program unless the applicant has a high school diploma or general equivalent diploma.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-027__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall reduce the cash assistance for which an assistance unit is otherwise eligible under this chapter if a minor parent in the assistance unit fails, without good cause, to meet standards of adequate levels of school attendance, as defined in regulations of the department. The reduction under this subsection shall be achieved by disregarding the needs of the person who failed to meet the school attendance standards. The person's needs shall be disregarded until the minor parent complies.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-27-030">
            <num>47.27.030</num>
            <heading>Family self-sufficiency services.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-27-030__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A participant in the Alaska temporary assistance program shall cooperate with the department, or its designee, to develop and sign a family self-sufficiency plan that includes</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-030__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the steps the family will take towards the self-sufficiency of the family;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-030__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the self-sufficiency services the department will provide to assist the family to attain self-sufficiency;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-030__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>specific benchmarks to indicate the steps toward successful completion of the family plan;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-030__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a statement that the family may be subject to reductions in cash assistance or self-sufficiency services or other sanctions if the family fails to comply with the family plan; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-030__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a statement that describes the necessary conditions and the steps that must be taken to renegotiate the terms of the family plan.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-030__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The family self-sufficiency plan must set a time period for the achievement of self-sufficiency from cash assistance under the Alaska temporary assistance program. Initially, that time period may not provide for any more than a total of 60 months of cash assistance under the Alaska temporary assistance program even though the family may eventually be eligible for an exemption under
AS 47.27.015
(a)(1). Unless the members of the family who are not dependent children are all exempt under
AS 47.27.035</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-030__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p> (d), the time period for receiving cash assistance may not exceed a cumulative total of 24 months unless each nonexempt person is in compliance with the work activity assignment made under
AS 47.27.035
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-030__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A family is exempt from the requirement that the family have a self-sufficiency plan under this section if the family</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-030__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>does not include a needy adult; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-030__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>[Repealed, § 3 ch 75 SLA 2001.]</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-030__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is receiving a diversion payment under
AS 47.27.026
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-030__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may provide only self-sufficiency services to a family that no longer qualifies for cash assistance due to employment, a family that is disqualified from receiving cash assistance under
AS 47.27.015
(a)(1), (c), or (g), or a family that qualifies for cash assistance but requests only self-sufficiency services. Self-sufficiency services that are made available to a family under this subsection shall be based on a determination of need established by the department in regulation. If a family receives only self-sufficiency services, the department may waive the self-sufficiency plan requirements specified in (a) and (b) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-27-035">
            <num>47.27.035</num>
            <heading>Participation in work activities.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-27-035__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An Alaska temporary assistance program participant shall, after the participant's family has received a cumulative total of 24 months of cash assistance or sooner if assigned to do so by the department, participate in work activities as assigned by the department or its designee in order for the family to continue to receive cash assistance or self-sufficiency services from the department under the Alaska temporary assistance program, unless the participant is exempt from the work participation requirements under one or more of the exemptions set out in (b)  (d) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-035__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A parent or caretaker with a dependent child of up to 12 months of age may be exempt from work participation requirements for up to 12 months, as established in the family self-sufficiency plan.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-035__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A parent or caretaker may be exempt from work participation requirements in the family self-sufficiency plan if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-035__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the parent or caretaker is providing home care for a child who is experiencing a disability or a related, disabled person who requires 24-hour care;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-035__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the parent or caretaker establishes an inability to participate for medical reasons supported by documentation from a physician or other licensed medical professional;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-035__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the participation would impose an unreasonable hardship on the family; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-035__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>there is a dependent child in the home that has not yet attained six years of age and the parent or caretaker demonstrates an inability to obtain needed child care because appropriate child care is not available.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-035__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may not require a person to participate in work activities under (a) of this section</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-035__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if the person is the sole custodial parent for a child under six years of age unless the department agrees to pay for the costs of child care determined by the department to be necessary for the person's participation; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-035__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>unless the department agrees to pay for transportation expenses determined by the department to be necessary for the person's participation in the activity.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-035__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A participant in work activities under this section is not a state employee for purposes of
AS 39.25
(State Personnel Act).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-035__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A participant in work activities under this section is not considered an employee of the state or other public employer for purposes of
AS 23.40.070
 23.40.260 (Public Employment Relations Act) nor shall any provision of a collective bargaining agreement entered into under
AS 23.40.070
 23.40.260 be construed to interfere with the department's authority to assign participants to work activities as authorized under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-27-040">
            <num>47.27.040</num>
            <heading>Assignment of support rights; cooperation with child support services agency.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-27-040__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An Alaska temporary assistance program applicant is considered to have assigned to the state, through the child support services agency of the Department of Revenue, all rights to accrued and continuing child support, from all sources, that is due for the support of any individuals in the family for whom support is sought. The assignment takes effect upon a determination that the applicant's family is eligible for cash assistance under this chapter. Except with respect to the amount of any unpaid support obligation accrued under the assignment, the assignment terminates when the family ceases to receive cash assistance under the Alaska temporary assistance program.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-040__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An Alaska temporary assistance program participant shall cooperate with the child support services agency of the Department of Revenue in establishing paternity or establishing, modifying, or enforcing a child support order requiring the payment of support by the noncustodial parent for a dependent child for whom Alaska temporary assistance program cash assistance is received. The child support enforcement agency shall determine whether the participant is in good faith compliance with the requirements of this subsection and shall inform the Department of Health of its determination. The Department of Health shall establish whether the participant has good cause for refusing to cooperate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-040__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may distribute to an Alaska temporary assistance program participant $50 per month from a monthly child support payment, or the amount of the child support payment if it is less than $50, received by the child support services agency for the support of a child for whom Alaska temporary assistance program cash assistance is paid.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-27-045">
            <num>47.27.045</num>
            <heading>Alienation and attachment.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.27.045.   Alienation and attachment.
Cash assistance granted under this chapter is inalienable by assignment or transfer and is exempt from garnishment, levy, or execution as is provided in
AS 09.38
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-27-050">
            <num>47.27.050</num>
            <heading>Grants and contracts for services.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-27-050__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may contract with or award grants to qualified entities in the state to administer an Alaska temporary assistance program or a distinct part of the Alaska temporary assistance program. The department may establish standards for the administration of services under the grant or contract, including fees to be charged to applicants for or recipients of those services.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-050__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Contracts authorized under this section are to be administered in accordance with
AS 47.05.015
. Grants authorized under this section are to be awarded using requirements, established in regulation, that are substantially similar to those set out in
AS 47.05.015
for contracts.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-050__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This section may not be construed to expand the powers of a municipality.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-050__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, qualified entities include municipalities, other political subdivisions of the state, nonprofit corporations formed under
AS 10.20
, churches and religious organizations, and incorporated and unincorporated businesses operating within the state that meet the requirements established by the department in regulation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-27-055">
            <num>47.27.055</num>
            <heading>Agency collaboration.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-27-055__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall coordinate with other state agencies that provide assistance, benefits, or services to applicants that are eligible for and to participants in the Alaska temporary assistance program in order to facilitate the application for and delivery of assistance, benefits, or services to promote family self-sufficiency. Subject to appropriations, state agencies may locate their facilities and operations near each other in order to improve service delivery.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-055__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may provide information received under this chapter to other state agencies in order to facilitate the delivery of services. Information received from an applicant for or participant in the Alaska temporary assistance program shall be treated as confidential by all state agencies that share the information under this section and is not open to public inspection or copying under
AS 40.25.110
 40.25.125. Misuse of public assistance lists or information is punishable as a violation of
AS 47.05.030
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-055__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Departments in the executive branch shall cooperate in fulfilling the purposes of this chapter, including, subject to appropriations, the establishment of temporary positions that will provide job opportunities for families participating in the Alaska temporary assistance program. Temporary positions established for this purpose are in the exempt service under
AS 39.25.110
but are not subject to
AS 39.25.195
. An individual participating in the Alaska temporary assistance program who holds a temporary position established for purposes of this subsection is not a public employee for purposes of
AS 23.40.070
 23.40.260.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-27-060">
            <num>47.27.060</num>
            <heading>Job development.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.27.060.   Job development.
The department may establish cooperative agreements with the Department of Labor and Workforce Development, Department of Education and Early Development, and Department of Commerce, Community, and Economic Development, and with other public or private sector organizations for the purpose of developing job, training, and educational opportunities for families eligible for cash assistance or self-sufficiency services under this chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-27-065">
            <num>47.27.065</num>
            <heading>Federal-state cooperation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.27.065.   Federal-state cooperation.
In the administration of this chapter, the department shall cooperate with the Secretary of the United States Department of Health and Human Services and shall take actions necessary to comply with the requirements of federal law to obtain public assistance block grants or other federal assistance available for the purposes of this chapter. The department shall make reports in the form and containing the information required to the Secretary of the United States Department of Health and Human Services. The department may cooperate with federal agencies charged with the administration of the federal public assistance block grants and other financial assistance.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-27-070">
            <num>47.27.070</num>
            <heading>Alaska native organizations' family assistance programs.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-27-070__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may coordinate only with the following Alaska Native organizations, as designated under federal law, in the development of family assistance programs:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-070__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Arctic Slope Native Association;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-070__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Kawerak, Inc.;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-070__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Maniilaq Association;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-070__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Association of Village Council Presidents;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-070__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Tanana Chiefs Conference;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-070__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Cook Inlet Tribal Council;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-070__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Bristol Bay Native Association;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-070__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Aleutian and Pribilof Island Association;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-070__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Chugachmiut;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-070__subsec_a__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Tlingit Haida Central Council;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-070__subsec_a__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Kodiak Area Native Association;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-070__subsec_a__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Copper River Native Association; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-070__subsec_a__subsec_13">
                <num>(13)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Metlakatla Indian Community of the Annette Islands Reserve; however, the department may cooperate with the Metlakatla Indian Community under this chapter only if the community waives any claim to sovereign immunity with respect to matters involved with the family assistance program.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-070__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may cooperate with the Alaska Native organizations named in (a) of this section to propose program criteria to the Secretary of the United States Department of Health and Human Services in order to promote programs comparable to the state program in the same area.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-070__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 1 ch 13 31 SLA 2020.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-27-075">
            <num>47.27.075</num>
            <heading>Emergency account established.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.27.075.   Emergency account established.
There is established within the general fund the Alaska temporary assistance program emergency account. The account consists of appropriations that were made by the legislature from federal money available for cash assistance, diversion payments, and self-sufficiency services under this chapter, including lapsing money that was previously appropriated from federal money for the Alaska temporary assistance program, but that were not expended or obligated in the fiscal year for which they were appropriated.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-27-080">
            <num>47.27.080</num>
            <heading>Appeals; dispute resolution.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-27-080__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An applicant or participant who receives a determination from the department that denies, limits, or modifies the cash assistance, diversion payment, or self-sufficiency services provided under this chapter may request a hearing before the office of administrative hearings (
AS 44.64.010
). The office of administrative hearings (
AS 44.64.010
) shall conduct the hearing under the regulations adopted by the department. The appeal is not subject to
AS 44.62.330
 44.62.630.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-080__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may require an applicant or participant to participate in an informal dispute resolution process before a formal hearing. The department may adopt regulations establishing the informal dispute resolution process.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-27-085">
            <num>47.27.085</num>
            <heading>Sanctions; recovery of costs.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-27-085__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (b) of this section, the department shall reduce the amount of cash assistance provided to the family of an Alaska temporary assistance program applicant or participant who, without good cause, fails to comply with a condition of the family self-sufficiency plan, who fails to participate in work activities required as a part of the Alaska temporary assistance program, or who fails to cooperate with the child support services agency as required under
AS 47.27.040
. The reduction shall be,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-085__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>beginning on the date the department makes a finding that the family is not in compliance under this subsection, 40 percent of the maximum cash assistance that would be payable under
AS 47.27.025
for a family of the same size, assuming the family has no income counted for purposes of this chapter, until the date the department determines that the family is in compliance under this subsection if the family comes into compliance within the first four months after the date of the department's finding of noncompliance under this subsection; on the date the department determines that the family is in compliance, the department shall begin to pay the family the full amount of cash assistance for which the family is eligible;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-085__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>beginning five months after the date the department made the finding that the family was not in compliance under this subsection, 75 percent of the maximum cash assistance that would be payable under
AS 47.27.025
for a family of the same size, assuming the family has no income counted for purposes of this chapter, until the date the department determines that the family is in compliance under this subsection if the family comes into compliance during the fifth, sixth, seventh, or eighth month after the date the department initially determined that the family was not in compliance under this subsection; on the date the department determines that the family is in compliance, the department shall begin to pay the family the full amount of cash assistance for which the family is eligible;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-085__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>beginning nine months after the date the department made the finding that the family was not in compliance under this subsection, the full amount of the family's cash assistance if the noncompliance under this subsection is not corrected within eight months after the date of the department's initial finding of noncompliance under this subsection; in order to again receive cash assistance under this chapter, the family shall reapply under
AS 47.27.020
and satisfy all requirements applicable to applicants under that section.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-085__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (a) of this section, the department may not reduce a family's cash assistance under (a)(2) or (3) of this section unless there is, in the family's case record, (1) documented evidence that the department has attempted to visit the family's home after the imposition of a reduction under (a)(1) of this section and (2) a written finding by the department that, considering the results of any home visit attempted under (1) of this subsection and the availability of other services in the community that are appropriate to the family's needs, the health, safety, and well-being of the children in the family will not be significantly jeopardized by imposition of a reduction under (a)(2) or (3) of this section. If the department does not reduce a family's cash assistance based on the provisions of this subsection, the department may manage the family's cash assistance on behalf of the family under regulations that the department shall adopt concerning management of cash assistance under this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-085__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An Alaska temporary assistance program applicant or participant who receives cash assistance, a diversion payment, or self-sufficiency services when not entitled to them under this chapter because the information provided by the applicant or participant was inaccurate or incomplete is liable to the department for the value of the cash assistance, diversion payment, and self-sufficiency services improperly provided to the applicant or participant.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-085__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In a civil action brought by the state to recover the value of cash assistance, a diversion payment, or self-sufficiency services improperly provided under this chapter, the state may recover costs of investigation and prosecution of the civil action, including attorney fees as determined under court rules.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-085__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall adopt regulations necessary to implement this section.
Article 3. Alaska Native Family Assistance Grants.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-27-200">
            <num>47.27.200</num>
            <heading>Alaska Native family assistance grants.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-27-200__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding any contrary provision of this chapter, and in addition to grants awarded under
AS 47.27.050
, the Department of Health may award and administer Alaska Native family assistance grants in accordance with this section. Unless specified otherwise in this section, the provisions of
AS 47.27.010
 47.27.085 do not apply to grants under this section or to an Alaska Native family assistance program operated under such a grant. To be awarded a grant under this section, an applicant shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-200__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>meet the requirements of
AS 47.27.070
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-200__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>have received approval for, and have agreed to operate, a federally approved tribal family assistance plan in this state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-200__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>agree to operate the plan approved under this section on a state fiscal year basis; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-200__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>meet the other requirements of this section.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-200__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If an organization intends to apply for a grant under this section, the organization shall first submit to the department a letter of intent along with a copy of the proposed federal tribal family assistance plan that will be submitted to the federal government for approval. The organization shall make its submission to the department at least six months before the proposed effective date of the federal tribal family assistance plan. The department shall review the submission and notify the organization of significant deficiencies that would make the organization ineligible to be considered for an Alaska Native family assistance grant without significant changes to the federal tribal family assistance plan regardless of whether federal approval is received or whether federal grant money is awarded for implementation of that plan. The organization may make a supplemental submission to the department to resolve deficiencies noted by the department. If, after departmental review and supplemental revision, an organization's plan remains eligible for consideration for a grant award under this section, the department shall notify the organization that the organization may submit a proposal for a grant award after the organization has received notice of federal approval of the federal tribal family assistance plan and the pending award of federal grant money. The commissioner may waive the time deadline specified in this subsection if the commissioner</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-200__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>enters into a joint planning agreement between the department and the organization; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-200__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>finds good cause and the waiver is in the state's best interest.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-200__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the department awards a grant under this section, the grant must be in an amount that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-200__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for the first fiscal year under the plan accepted by the department, represents a fair and equitable portion of the state appropriations for the state public assistance program administered under this chapter intended to serve the state residents who will be served by the plan; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-200__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for the second and subsequent state fiscal years under the plan accepted by the department, represents a fair and equitable portion of state appropriations made for public assistance programs that is allocated for Alaska Native family assistance grants to be awarded under this section in order to serve the state residents who will be served by the plan; if the money is not allocated for these grants, the amounts shall be made in the same manner as described in (1) of this subsection.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-200__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For an organization to be eligible to be awarded a grant under this section, the organization's proposal must include</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-200__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>documentation that the organization
(A) has received federal approval of its federal tribal family assistance plan to operate a tribal assistance program in this state; and
(B) will receive a grant directly from the federal government to implement the federal tribal family assistance plan;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-200__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a plan for operation of the Alaska Native family assistance grant that meets the requirements of (e) of this section; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-200__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if the commissioner determines that a federally approved tribal family assistance plan would be a cost-effective and efficient means of administering the program established in this chapter in that region of the state and the needs of state public assistance recipients receiving assistance under this chapter can be met through a contract awarded under
AS 47.27.300
, the organization's agreement to enter into a contract with the department to provide state public assistance to those eligible state residents in the region who are not included in the population to be served by the federally approved tribal family assistance plan.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-200__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An organization's plan for operation of the Alaska Native family assistance grant must</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-200__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>be designed to facilitate self-sufficiency of assistance recipients in the region specified in the federally approved tribal family assistance plan by addressing the conditions specific to that region;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-200__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide for a reasonable pattern of service delivery from all providers serving that region;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-200__subsec_e__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>serve a specified region that consists of a geographically cohesive group of communities that share similar interests, resources, and traditions;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-200__subsec_e__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establish the same maximum number of months of benefits as is established for the state program under
AS 47.27.015</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-200__subsec_e__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide for administration of the grant money received under this section to establish a program in accordance with the plan accepted by the department and in compliance with other requirements of this section; the program must include the following standards for providing assistance to eligible families:
(A) only families with at least one dependent child or a woman in the last trimester of pregnancy are eligible for assistance paid from an Alaska Native family assistance grant;
(B) amounts for assistance provided from an Alaska Native family assistance grant to eligible families may not exceed the amounts specified under
AS 47.27.025</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-200__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>when combined with assistance provided under the federally approved tribal family assistance grant;
(C) to remain eligible for assistance paid from an Alaska Native family assistance grant, a minor parent of a dependent child must meet the requirements of
AS 47.27.027
;
(D) families receiving assistance paid from an Alaska Native family assistance grant shall comply with the provisions of
AS 47.27.035</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-200__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>regarding participation in work activities;
(E) families receiving assistance paid from Alaska Native family assistance grant money shall comply with the provisions of (l)  (n) of this section regarding assignment of support rights and cooperation with the child support services agency;
(F) the organization has an impartial appeals process to allow affected families in the region of the state covered by the plan accepted by the department to have a fair hearing.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-200__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may award a grant under this section only if the department determines that the proposal, including a plan for operation of the grant, meets the criteria specified in (d) and (e) of this section and that an award of the grant to the organization would be in the public interest. The grant agreement must state that the Alaska Native family assistance program will require all program participants to assign child support rights to the Alaska Native family assistance program unless the Alaska Native organization elects to require participants to assign those child support rights to the state. The department may not distribute grant money until a grant agreement between the organization and the department is executed that meets the requirements of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-200__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Records pertaining to recipients of assistance from an Alaska Native family assistance grant awarded under this section are confidential public assistance records under
AS 47.05.020
and regulations adopted under
AS 47.05.020
. Use and misuse of these records are subject to the provisions of
AS 47.05.030
. It is an official purpose under
AS 47.05.020
for an organization receiving a grant under this section and the department or another agency of the state to exchange information concerning recipients of assistance under this section if the information requested is for purposes directly connected with the administration of a grant under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-200__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An organization receiving a grant under this section shall provide to the department a copy of its quarterly report made under 42 U.S.C. 611. The organization shall have its financial records audited annually by a certified public accountant authorized to practice under
AS 08.04
. The department may prescribe the form and specify the information required to document compliance with this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-200__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If an organization wishes to terminate its program before the end of the time period for which the grant was awarded under this section, the organization must obtain the consent of the department or provide notice to the department 120 days before the anticipated date of termination. At the end of a grant agreement or by early termination under this section, the organization shall provide an inventory of property valued at $1,000 or over and purchased, in whole or in part, with grant money awarded under this section. The department shall notify the organization of the required disposition of the property listed on the inventory.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-200__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the department awards a grant under this section, a person applying for assistance under this chapter who is covered by the federally approved tribal family assistance plan in that region of the state may obtain assistance from the department only through the organization designated by the department to serve the region. A person aggrieved by a decision made by an organization under a grant awarded under this section may use the appeal procedure specified in
AS 47.27.300
(e).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-200__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (j) of this section, a person applying for assistance under this chapter in a region of the state that is served by both an Alaska Native family assistance program that receives a grant under this section and a program administered directly by the department may request to receive assistance under the program administered directly by the department by applying to the department under this subsection and in accordance with regulations adopted under this subsection. The department shall approve the application if the department finds that the applicant has shown that special circumstances exist that support the request to use the state program.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-200__subsec_l">
              <num>(l)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A participant in an Alaska Native family assistance program shall assign to the Alaska Native family assistance program, unless the program has elected to require assignment to the state, all rights to ongoing child support that accrues after the effective date of the assignment for the support of the individuals in the family for whom assistance is provided, but not to exceed the total amount of assistance paid by the Alaska Native family assistance program to the family. The assignment takes effect when information required under (n) of this section is provided to the child support services agency following the determination of eligibility. Except with respect to any unpaid support that accrued under the assignment, the assignment terminates when the family ceases to participate in the Alaska Native family assistance program. All assignments to an Alaska Native family assistance program of unpaid child support obligations transfer to the state upon the termination of an Alaska Native family assistance program.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-200__subsec_m">
              <num>(m)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An Alaska Native family assistance program participant shall cooperate with the child support services agency in the manner described in
AS 47.27.040</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-200__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>in establishing paternity or establishing, modifying, or enforcing a child support order requiring the payment of support by the noncustodial parent for a dependent child for whom assistance is received. The child support services agency shall inform the Alaska Native family assistance program if it determines that the participant is not in good faith compliance with the requirements of
AS 47.27.040
(b). The Alaska Native family assistance program shall determine whether the participant has good cause for refusing to cooperate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-200__subsec_n">
              <num>(n)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An Alaska Native family assistance program that receives assignments of ongoing child support shall provide public assistance information concerning those assignments to the child support services agency in a timely manner in order to establish a valid assignment. The information shall be provided by electronic means and in a format acceptable to the child support services agency. For the purposes of this subsection, timely manner means within the time constraints established for child support agency distributions under federal law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-200__subsec_o">
              <num>(o)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The applicability of
AS 25.27
in the case of a recipient under an Alaska Native family assistance program includes the following:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-200__subsec_o__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an obligor is liable to the Alaska Native family assistance program in the amount of the family assistance provided by the program to a child to whom the obligor owes a duty of support except that, if a support order has been entered, the liability of the obligor for assistance provided by an Alaska Native family assistance program may not exceed the amount of support provided for in the support order, and, if a medical support order, cash medical support order, or both, has been entered, the liability of the obligor for assistance granted under
AS 47.07
may not exceed the amount of support provided for in the medical support order, cash medical support order, or both; the child support services agency shall send notice of accruing liability under this paragraph in the same manner as required under
AS 25.27.120</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-200__subsec_o__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the child support services agency may appear in an action authorized under
AS 25.27.045
at the agency's own discretion if an obligor under
AS 25.27
is liable to the Alaska Native family assistance program under (1) of this subsection;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-200__subsec_o__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an Alaska Native family assistance program to which the child support services agency erroneously disburses an overpayment of child support under an income withholding order is liable to the state for the amount disbursed, plus interest at the rate imposed under
AS 25.27.062</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-200__subsec_o__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>when the right to receive child support has been assigned to an Alaska Native family assistance program, an agreement under
AS 25.27.065</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-200__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>that has not been adopted as an administrative order of the child support services agency is not effective during a period when the obligee is receiving assistance under an Alaska Native family assistance program;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-200__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the child support services agency, on behalf of an Alaska Native family assistance program, shall take all necessary action permitted by law to enforce child support orders entered under
AS 25.27
, including petitioning the court for orders to aid in the enforcement of child support;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-200__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if an obligor under
AS 25.27
is liable to an Alaska Native family assistance program under (1) of this subsection, the state is subrogated to the rights of the obligee to take actions authorized under
AS 25.27.130</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-200__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>notwithstanding
AS 25.27.130</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-200__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>except as provided in
AS 25.27.130</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-200__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or (1) of this subsection, the recovery of any amount for which the obligor is liable shall be distributed to the obligee for support payments, including medical support payments, that had become due and unpaid since the termination of assistance under
AS 47.07
or this chapter under a support order in favor of the obligee;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-200__subsec_d__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>after payment to the obligee under (8) of this subsection, the state may retain an amount not to exceed the total unreimbursed assistance paid on behalf of the obligee under
AS 47.07
or this chapter;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-200__subsec_d__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if an alleged obligor is liable to an Alaska Native family assistance program under (1) of this subsection, and a support order has not been entered, the child support services agency may, at its own discretion, undertake an action to establish paternity and a duty of support using the procedures prescribed in
AS 25.27
and may enforce a duty of support using the procedures prescribed in
AS 25.27
; the agency may also institute administrative proceedings to determine the paternity of a child born out of wedlock upon application of an Alaska Native family assistance program; the agency may not recover costs of genetic tests required under this paragraph from a person who is a recipient of assistance under an Alaska Native family assistance program;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-200__subsec_d__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>when a hearing officer makes a determination under
AS 25.27.170</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-200__subsec_d__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>notwithstanding
AS 25.27.255</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-200__subsec_p">
              <num>(p)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing in this section requires the department to continue to fund an Alaska Native family assistance grant program at a level funded before the current grant period or to replace federal funds for the program with state funding.
Article 4. Regional Programs.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-27-300">
            <num>47.27.300</num>
            <heading>Regional public assistance programs.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-27-300__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may develop a regional public assistance program for the administration of this chapter in order to provide state public assistance in a uniform and cost-effective manner in a region of this state if an Alaska Native organization is authorized to implement a federally approved tribal family assistance plan that includes that region and has been awarded an Alaska Native family assistance grant for a program that includes that region for the applicable fiscal year under
AS 47.27.200
. The regional public assistance program developed under this section must be designed to serve eligible state residents in the region covered by the program who are not already covered by a federally approved tribal family assistance plan in that region.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-300__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may award contracts to implement a program developed under (a) of this section. A contract authorized for delivery of state public assistance under a regional public assistance program under this section is exempt from the competitive bid requirements of
AS 36.30
(State Procurement Code). Subject to appropriation, a contract under this section must be in an amount that represents a fair and equitable share of the money appropriated under this chapter to serve the state residents specified in (a) of this section. This section provides additional authority to contract to that available under
AS 47.05.015
or other law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-300__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may award a contract under this section only to an organization that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-300__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has been awarded an Alaska Native family assistance grant under
AS 47.27.200
for a program that includes that region;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-300__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>agrees to administer state public assistance under this chapter to state residents in the region who are not served by the Alaska Native family assistance grant awarded under
AS 47.27.200
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-300__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>agrees to provide state public assistance identical to that provided under the federally approved tribal family assistance plan for which Alaska Native family assistance grant money has been awarded under
AS 47.27.200
; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-300__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>agrees to implement an appeals process as described in (e) of this section.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-300__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Records pertaining to recipients of state public assistance under a contract awarded under this section have the same confidential protections as are provided to recipients of assistance from Alaska Native family assistance grants under
AS 47.27.200
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-300__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An organization that receives a contract under this section shall provide an appeals process to applicants for or recipients of state public assistance covered by the contract awarded under this section. The appeals process must be the same as the method available under the federally approved tribal family assistance plan, except that the decision reached shall be considered as a recommended decision to the department. Within 30 days after receiving a recommended decision, the department shall review the recommended decision and issue a decision accepting or rejecting the recommended decision. If the department rejects the recommended decision, the department shall independently review the record and issue its final decision. The final decision of the department on the matter is appealable to the courts of this state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-27-300__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the department establishes a regional public assistance program and awards a contract to provide state public assistance under this section, a person applying for state public assistance under this chapter in the region of the state covered by the regional public assistance program may obtain state public assistance from the department only through the organization designated by the department to serve the region.
Article 5. General Provisions.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-27-900">
            <num>47.27.900</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-27-900__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>18 years of age; or
(ii) 19 years of age and is a full-time student in a secondary school or in the equivalent level of vocational or technical training; and
(B) is not an applicant under
AS 47.27.020
;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-900__subsec_i__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>diversion payment means a diversion payment paid under
AS 47.27.026
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-900__subsec_i__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>federally approved tribal family assistance plan means a plan that meets the requirements of 42 U.S.C. 612 and has been approved for financing through a tribal family assistance grant directly from the United States Department of Health and Human Services;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-900__subsec_i__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>self-sufficiency services means work-related services, community service work referrals, child care assistance, emergency assistance, service vouchers, equipment vouchers, work stipends, transportation assistance, wage subsidies, and other work supports and services determined by the department in regulation to promote family self-sufficiency;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-27-900__subsec_i__subsec_13">
                <num>(13)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>work activities includes job readiness assessments, on-the-job training, education and vocational training, job sampling, job search requirements, subsidized and unsubsidized work, and community work service.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-27-990">
            <num>47.27.990</num>
            <heading>Short title.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.27.990.   Short title.
This chapter may be cited as the Alaska temporary assistance program.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>