<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-34/chapter-27"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-34/chapter-27"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="34.27"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-34/chapter-27/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-34/chapter-27/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-34/chapter-27/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-34/chapter-27/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_34">
        <num>34</num>
        <heading>Property</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_34__chp_27">
          <num>27</num>
          <heading>Modification or Abolition of Common Law Property Rules</heading>
          <section eId="sec_34-27-020">
            <num>34.27.020</num>
            <heading>Abolition of the common law rule in Shelley's case.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.27.020.   Abolition of the common law rule in Shelley's case.
If real property is granted or devised to a person and after the person's death, to the person's heirs or the heirs of the person's body, however the grant or devise is expressed, an estate for life only vests in the person, and a remainder goes to the person's heirs or the heirs of the person's body as purchasers.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-27-030">
            <num>34.27.030</num>
            <heading>Abolition of the common law destructibility of contingent remainders.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.27.030.   Abolition of the common law destructibility of contingent remainders.
A contingent remainder is not defeated by the termination of a precedent estate before the occurrence of the contingency that was to cause the remainder to take effect. If the contingency occurs later, the remainder takes effect in the same way as a springing or shifting executory interest.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-27-051">
            <num>34.27.051</num>
            <heading>Statutory rule against perpetuities.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-27-051__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A general or nongeneral power of appointment not presently exercisable because of a condition precedent is invalid unless, within a period of 1,000 years after its creation, either the power is irrevocably exercised or the power terminates. For purposes of this subsection, the period in which the power must be exercised or the power terminated is computed from the time of creation of the original power of appointment under which a subsequent general power of appointment not presently exercisable or a subsequent nongeneral power of appointment not presently exercisable was created.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-27-051__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a nongeneral power of appointment is exercised to create a new presently exercisable general power of appointment, all property interests subject to that new presently exercisable general power of appointment are invalid unless, within 1,000 years after the creation of the new presently exercisable general power of appointment, the property interests that are subject to the new presently exercisable general power of appointment either vest or terminate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-27-051__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a nongeneral power of appointment is exercised to create a new or successive nongeneral power of appointment or a new or successive testamentary general power of appointment, all property interests subject to the exercise of that new or successive nongeneral or testamentary general power of appointment are invalid unless, within 1,000 years from the time of creation of the original instrument or conveyance creating the original nongeneral power of appointment that is exercised to create a new or successive nongeneral or testamentary general power of appointment, the property interests that are subject to the new or successive nongeneral or testamentary general power of appointment either vest or terminate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-27-053">
            <num>34.27.053</num>
            <heading>Savings provision.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-27-053__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>in the shares to which the persons are entitled to the income; or
(ii) equally among all persons who are entitled to the income if shares are not specified;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-27-053__subsec_i__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if income from the property interest is payable in the discretion of a trustee and is payable
(A) to one person, be distributed to the person then eligible to receive the income; or
(B) to more than one person, be distributed to the persons then eligible to receive the income</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-27-053__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>in the shares to which the persons are entitled to the income; or
(ii) equally among all persons who are entitled to the income if shares are not specified; or</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-27-053__subsec_i__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>when there is no person then living to whom the property interest may be distributed under (1) or (2) of this section, be payable to one or more organizations described in 26 U.S.C. 2055(a) (Internal Revenue Code), or to one or more organizations described in any successor provision to 26 U.S.C. 2055(a), in the shares or proportions that the trustee or trustees then acting may determine.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-27-070">
            <num>34.27.070</num>
            <heading>Application.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-27-070__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as extended by (b) of this section, the former provisions of
AS 34.27.051
 34.27.100 apply to a nonvested property interest or a power of appointment that is created on or after January 1, 1996, and before April 2, 1997. For purposes of this subsection, a nonvested property interest or a power of appointment created by the exercise of a power of appointment is created when the power is irrevocably exercised or when a revocable exercise becomes irrevocable.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-27-070__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a nonvested property interest or a power of appointment was created before January 1, 1996, and is determined in a judicial proceeding, commenced on or after that date, to violate this state's rule against perpetuities as that rule existed before January 1, 1996, or if a nonvested property interest or a power of appointment was created on or after January 1, 1996, but before April 2, 1997, and is determined in a judicial proceeding, commenced on or after that date, to violate this state's rule against perpetuities as that rule existed, on or after January 1, 1996, and before April 2, 1997, a court, upon the petition of an interested person, may reform the disposition in the manner that most closely approximates the transferor's manifested plan of distribution and is within the limits of the rule against perpetuities applicable when the nonvested property interest or power of appointment was created. For purposes of this subsection, a nonvested property interest or a power of appointment created by the exercise of a power of appointment is created when the power is irrevocably exercised or when a revocable exercise becomes irrevocable.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-27-070__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The provisions of
AS 34.27.051
apply to a trust instrument or conveyance executed on or after April 2, 1997, if the trust instrument or conveyance creates a contingent power of appointment or nonvested property interest subject to the exercise of a power of appointment that creates a new or successive power of appointment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-27-075">
            <num>34.27.075</num>
            <heading>Relationship to common law rule.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.27.075.   Relationship to common law rule.
AS 34.27.051
 34.27.100 supersede the rule of the common law known as the rule against perpetuities. The common law rule against perpetuities does not apply in this state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-27-100">
            <num>34.27.100</num>
            <heading>Suspension of the power of alienation.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-27-100__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A future interest or trust is void if, as to property subject to the future interest or trust,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-27-100__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the future interest or trust suspends the power of alienation of the property, the suspension of the power of alienation is for a period of at least 30 years after the death of an individual alive at the time of the creation of the future interest or trust, and the suspension of the power of alienation occurs in the document creating the future interest or trust;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-27-100__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the future interest or trust suspends the power of alienation of the property and the suspension of the power of alienation is for a period of at least 30 years after the death of an individual alive at the time of the creation of the future interest or trust as computed from the time of the termination of a settlor's power to revoke the trust;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-27-100__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the future interest or trust suspends the power of alienation of the property, the future interest or trust is created by the exercise of a presently exercisable general power of appointment, whether by will or otherwise, and the suspension of the power of alienation is for a period of at least 30 years after the death of an individual alive at the time of the creation of the future interest or trust as computed from the time of creation of the presently exercisable power of appointment; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-27-100__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the future interest or trust suspends the power of alienation of the property, the future interest or trust is created by the exercise of a nongeneral or testamentary general power of appointment, and the suspension of the power of alienation is for a period of at least 30 years after the death of an individual alive at the time of the creation of the future interest or trust as computed from the time of creation of the original instrument or conveyance creating the original power of appointment that was exercised to create a new or successive nongeneral or testamentary general power of appointment.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-27-100__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of (a) of this section, the power of alienation</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-27-100__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is suspended if there is no person alive who, alone or in combination with others, can, as to property that is part of the future interest or trust, convey
(A) title to real property in fee; or
(B) complete ownership of personal property;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-27-100__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is not suspended by a future interest or trust or by an equitable interest in a trust if
(A) the trustee of the trust has power, either express or implied, to sell the property; or
(B) at least one person alive at the time the trust was created has an unlimited power to terminate the trust.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-27-100__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The provisions of (a) of this section do not apply to a transfer</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-27-100__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>made outright or in trust for a charitable purpose;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-27-100__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to a literary or charitable organization;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-27-100__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to a veterans' memorial organization; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-27-100__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to a cemetery corporation, society, or association.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>