<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-44/chapter-66"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-44/chapter-66"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="44.66"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-44/chapter-66/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-44/chapter-66/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-44/chapter-66/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-44/chapter-66/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_44">
        <num>44</num>
        <heading>State Government</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_44__chp_66">
          <num>66</num>
          <heading>Review of the Activities of Agencies, Boards, and Commissions</heading>
          <section eId="sec_44-66-010">
            <num>44.66.010</num>
            <heading>Expiration of state boards and commissions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-66-010__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Boards and commissions listed in this subsection expire on the date set out after each:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-66-010__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Alcoholic Beverage Control Board (
AS 04.06.010
)  June 30, 2027;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-66-010__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Board of Parole (
AS 33.16.020
)  June 30, 2025;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-66-010__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Regulatory Commission of Alaska (
AS 42.04.010
)  June 30, 2030;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-66-010__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Alaska Commission on Aging (
AS 44.29.750
)  June 30, 2032;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-66-010__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Council on Domestic Violence and Sexual Assault (
AS 18.66.010
)  June 30, 2028;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-66-010__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>special education service agency (
AS 14.30.600
)  June 30, 2029;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-66-010__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Statewide Suicide Prevention Council (
AS 44.29.300
)  June 30, 2027;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-66-010__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Alaska Seismic Hazards Safety Commission (
AS 44.37.065
)  June 30, 2028;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-66-010__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Alaska Health Care Commission (
AS 18.09.010
)  June 30, 2017;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-66-010__subsec_a__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>[Repealed, § 6 ch 40 SLA 2024.]</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-66-010__subsec_a__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Alaska Tourism Marketing Board (
AS 44.33.136
)  June 30, 2018;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-66-010__subsec_a__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>[Repealed, § 17 ch 23, SLA 2022.]</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-66-010__subsec_a__subsec_13">
                <num>(13)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Marijuana Control Board (
AS 17.38.080
)  June 30, 2027;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-66-010__subsec_a__subsec_14">
                <num>(14)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Alaska Criminal Justice Data Analysis Commission (
AS 44.19.641
)  June 30, 2029.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-66-010__subsec_a__subsec_15">
                <num>(15)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Citizens' Advisory Commission on Federal Management Areas in Alaska (
AS 41.37.160
)  June 30, 2031.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-66-010__subsec_a__subsec_16">
                <num>(16)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Alaska Military Affairs Commission (
AS 44.19.851
)  June 30, 2030.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-66-010__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon termination, a commission listed in (a) of this section shall continue in existence until June 30 of the next succeeding year for the purpose of concluding its affairs.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-66-010__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A commission scheduled for termination under this chapter may be continued or reestablished by the legislature for a period not to exceed eight years.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-66-010__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (b) of this section, the powers and duties of the Regulatory Commission of Alaska in the year following expiration are not reduced or otherwise limited, and the commission shall continue in existence after expiration for one year. The commission shall continue to exercise all its powers and perform its duties and responsibilities under
AS 42
during the year following its expiration.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-66-050">
            <num>44.66.050</num>
            <heading>Legislative oversight.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-66-050__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before the termination, dissolution, continuation, or reestablishment of a board or commission under
AS 08.03.010
or
AS 44.66.010
, a committee of reference of each house, which shall be the standing committee of legislative jurisdiction as provided in the Uniform Rules of the Legislature, shall hold one or more hearings to receive testimony from the public, the commissioner of the department having administrative responsibility for each named board or commission, and the members of the board or commission involved. The hearings may be joint hearings. The committee shall also consider the proposed budget of the board or commission prepared in accordance with
AS 37.07.050</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-66-050__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and the performance audit of the activities of the board or commission prepared by the legislative audit division as prescribed in
AS 24.20.271</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-66-050__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>During a public hearing, the board or commission shall have the burden of demonstrating a public need for its continued existence or the continuation of the program and the extent to which any change in the manner of exercise of its functions or activities may increase efficiency of administration or operation consistent with the public interest.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-66-050__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A determination as to whether a board or commission has demonstrated a public need for its continued existence must take into consideration the following factors:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-66-050__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the extent to which the board or commission has operated in the public interest;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-66-050__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the extent to which the operation of the board or commission has been impeded or enhanced by existing statutes, procedures, and practices that it has adopted, and any other matter, including budgetary, resource, and personnel matters;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-66-050__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the extent to which the board or commission has recommended statutory changes that are generally of benefit to the public interest;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-66-050__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the extent to which the board or commission has encouraged interested persons to report to it concerning the effect of its regulations and decisions on the effectiveness of service, economy of service, and availability of service that it has provided;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-66-050__subsec_c__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the extent to which the board or commission has encouraged public participation in the making of its regulations and decisions;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-66-050__subsec_c__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the efficiency with which public inquiries or complaints regarding the activities of the board or commission filed with it, with the department to which a board or commission is administratively assigned, or with the office of victims' rights or the office of the ombudsman have been processed and resolved;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-66-050__subsec_c__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the extent to which a board or commission that regulates entry into an occupation or profession has presented qualified applicants to serve the public;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-66-050__subsec_c__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the extent to which state personnel practices, including affirmative action requirements, have been complied with by the board or commission in its own activities and in the area of activity or interest;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-66-050__subsec_c__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the extent to which statutory, regulatory, budgetary, or other changes are necessary to enable the board or commission to better serve the interests of the public and to comply with the factors enumerated in this subsection;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-66-050__subsec_c__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the extent to which the board or commission has effectively attained its objectives and purposes and the efficiency with which the board or commission has operated; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-66-050__subsec_c__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the extent to which the board or commission duplicates the activities of another governmental agency or the private sector.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-66-050__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>As to each board or commission assigned to it for purposes of review, the committee of reference shall, not later than the 60th day of the legislative session, submit a report to the presiding officer of the house. The report must contain a summary of the findings of the committee as to the compliance of the board or commission with the factors enumerated in (c) of this section, together with a summary or recommendations of the committee as to each of the following:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-66-050__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an identification of the problems or the needs that the programs and activities of the board or commission are intended to address;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-66-050__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a statement, to the extent practicable, of the objectives of the program of the board or commission and its anticipated accomplishments;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-66-050__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an identification of any other programs having similar, conflicting, or duplicate objectives;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-66-050__subsec_d__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an assessment of alternative methods of achieving the purposes of the program;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-66-050__subsec_d__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an assessment of the consequences of eliminating the board or commission and consolidating its activities with another program or of funding it at a lower level;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-66-050__subsec_d__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a justification for the recommended continuation or extension of the board or commission and an explanation of the manner in which it avoids duplication of or conflict with other efforts; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-66-050__subsec_d__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>any other information that, in the opinion of the committee, would improve the performance of the board or commission with respect to its representation of and responsiveness to the public interest.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-66-050__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The committee of reference may introduce a bill providing for the reorganization or continuation of the board or commission. Not more than one board or commission may be continued or reestablished in any legislative bill, and the board or commission must be mentioned in the title of the bill.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-66-060">
            <num>44.66.060</num>
            <heading>Existing claims.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.66.060.   Existing claims.
This chapter does not cause the termination or dismissal of a claim or right of a citizen against a board, commission, or program of an agency terminated by legislative action or under this chapter that is subject to litigation. Claims and rights shall be assumed by the department to which the board or commission terminated under this chapter was attached for administrative purposes.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-66-070">
            <num>44.66.070</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.66.070.   Definitions.
In this chapter,
(1) agency means a state department or agency, whether in the legislative, judicial, or executive branch, and includes the University of Alaska;
(2) [Repealed, § 11 ch 19 SLA 2013.]</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>