<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-44/chapter-83"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-44/chapter-83"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="44.83"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-44/chapter-83/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-44/chapter-83/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-44/chapter-83/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-44/chapter-83/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_44">
        <num>44</num>
        <heading>State Government</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_44__chp_83">
          <num>83</num>
          <heading>Alaska Energy Authority</heading>
          <section eId="sec_44-83-020">
            <num>44.83.020</num>
            <heading>Creation of authority.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.83.020.   Creation of authority.
There is created the Alaska Energy Authority. The authority is a public corporation of the state in the Department of Commerce, Community, and Economic Development but with separate and independent legal existence.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-83-030">
            <num>44.83.030</num>
            <heading>Members of the board.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-83-030__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The members of the board of directors of the authority are</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-83-030__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the commissioner of revenue;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-83-030__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the commissioner of commerce, community, and economic development; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-83-030__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>six public members appointed by the governor as follows:
(A)  one member with expertise or experience in managing or operating an electric utility that is not connected to an interconnected electric energy transmission network as defined in
AS 42.05.790
;
(B)  one member with expertise or experience in developing energy projects in rural communities;
(C)  one member with expertise or experience in managing or operating an electric utility connected to an interconnected electric energy transmission network as defined in
AS 42.05.790
;
(D)  one member with expertise or experience in managing a municipally owned utility located off the interconnected road system or joint action agency established under
AS 42.45.310
located off the interconnected road system;
(E)  one member with financial expertise in large power generation project development; and
(F)  one member with expertise or experience in finance, energy policy, energy technology, engineering, law, or economics.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-83-030__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the commissioner described in (a)(1) or (a)(2) of this section is unable to attend a meeting of the authority, the commissioner may, by an instrument in writing filed with the authority, designate a deputy or director to act in the commissioner's place as a member of the board at the meeting. For all purposes of this chapter, the designee is a member of the board at the meeting.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-83-030__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Public board members described in (a)(3) of this section serve for three-year terms.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-83-030__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a vacancy occurs in the membership of the board, the governor shall immediately appoint a member for the unexpired portion of the term.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-83-040">
            <num>44.83.040</num>
            <heading>Transaction of business.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-83-040__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board of directors of the authority shall elect a chair and vice-chair every two years from among its members. The powers of the authority are vested in the board of directors, and five board members constitute a quorum. Action may be taken and motions and resolutions adopted by the authority at a meeting by the affirmative vote of at least five board members. The members of the board of directors of the authority serve without compensation, but they shall receive the same travel pay and per diem as provided by law for board members under
AS 39.20.180
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-83-040__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board may meet and transact business by an electronic medium if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-83-040__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>public notice of the time and locations where the meeting will be held by an electronic medium has been given in the same manner as if the meeting were held in a single location;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-83-040__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>participants and members of the public in attendance can hear and have the same right to participate in the meeting as if the meeting were conducted in person; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-83-040__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>copies of pertinent reference materials, statutes, regulations, and audio-visual materials are reasonably available to participants and to the public.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-83-040__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A meeting by an electronic medium as provided in this section has the same legal effect as a meeting in person.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-83-040__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A director of the authority may not vote on a resolution of the authority relating to a lease or contract to be entered into by the authority under this chapter if the director is a party to the lease or contract or has a direct ownership or equity interest in a firm, partnership, corporation, or association that is a party to the contract or lease. When abstaining from voting, the director must disclose the reason for the abstention.  A director who is a member of an electric cooperative that is organized under or subject to
AS 10.25
(Electric and Telephone Cooperative Act) may vote on a resolution relating to a contract or lease to which that cooperative is a party.  The director shall disclose the cooperative membership at the time of voting.  A resolution of the authority that is approved by a majority of the directors present who are not barred from voting under this subsection is a valid action of the authority for all purposes.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-83-043">
            <num>44.83.043</num>
            <heading>Officers and employees.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.83.043.   Officers and employees.
The authority may, as the authority considers advisable, appoint persons as officers, including an executive director, and employ professional advisors, counsel, technical experts, agents, and other employees. The executive director and employees of the authority are in the exempt service under
AS 39.25
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-83-070">
            <num>44.83.070</num>
            <heading>Purpose of the authority.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.83.070.   Purpose of the authority.
The purpose of the authority is to promote, develop, and advance the general prosperity and economic welfare of the people of the state by providing a means of financing and operating power projects and facilities that recover and use waste energy and by carrying out the powers and duties assigned to it under
AS 42.45
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-83-080">
            <num>44.83.080</num>
            <heading>Powers of the authority.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-83-080__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>for debt service on bonds or other project purposes; or
(ii) to reduce the amount of debt financing for the project;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-83-080__subsec_i__subsec_15">
                <num>(15)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to carry out the powers and duties assigned to it under
AS 42.45
and
AS 44.83.700
 44.83.720;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-83-080__subsec_i__subsec_16">
                <num>(16)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to make grants or loans to any person and enter into contracts or other transactions regarding the grants or loans;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-83-080__subsec_i__subsec_17">
                <num>(17)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to promote energy conservation, energy efficiency, and alternative energy through training and public education;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-83-080__subsec_i__subsec_18">
                <num>(18)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to acquire a Susitna River power project, whether by construction, purchase, gift, or lease, including the acquisition of property rights and interests by eminent domain under
AS 09
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-83-080__subsec_i__subsec_19">
                <num>(19)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to perform feasibility studies and engineering and design with respect to power projects;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-83-080__subsec_i__subsec_20">
                <num>(20)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to acquire battery and other energy storage systems, whether by direct ownership, purchase, grant, gift, or lease.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-83-085">
            <num>44.83.085</num>
            <heading>Susitna River power project annual report.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.83.085.   Susitna River power project annual report.
The authority shall prepare, not later than the first day of each regular session of the legislature, an annual report summarizing the status of the Susitna River power project and shall notify the legislature that the report is available.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-83-090">
            <num>44.83.090</num>
            <heading>Power contracts and the Regulatory Commission of Alaska.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-83-090__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The authority shall, in addition to the other methods that it may find advantageous, provide a method by which municipal electric, rural electric, cooperative electric, or private electric utilities and regional electric authorities, or other persons authorized by law to engage in the distribution of electricity may secure a reasonable share of the power generated by a project, or any interest in a project, or for any right to the power and shall sell the power or cause the power to be sold at the lowest reasonable prices that cover the full cost of the electricity or services, including capital and operating costs, debt coverage as considered appropriate by the authority, and other charges that may be authorized by this chapter. Except for a contract or lease entered into under former
AS 44.83.380
 44.83.425, a contract or lease for the sale, transmission, and distribution of power generated by a project or any right to the capacity of it shall provide:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-83-090__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for payment of all operating and maintenance expenses of a project and costs of renewals, replacements, and improvements of it;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-83-090__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for interest on and amortization charges sufficient to retire bonds of the authority issued for the project and reserves for them, plus a debt service coverage factor as may be determined by the authority to be necessary for the marketability of its bonds;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-83-090__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for monitoring of the project by the authority or its agents;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-83-090__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for full and complete disclosure to the authority of all factors of costs in the transmission and distribution of power, so that rates to any persons may be fixed initially in the contract or lease and may be adjusted from time to time on the basis of true cost data;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-83-090__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for periodic revisions of the service and rates to persons on the basis of accurate cost data obtained by the accounting methods and systems approved by the directors and in furtherance and effectuation of the policy declared in this chapter;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-83-090__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for the cancellation and termination of a contract or lease upon violation of its terms by any person;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-83-090__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for security for performance as the authority may consider practicable and advisable, including provisions assuring the continuance of the distribution and transmission of power generated by a project and the use of its facilities for these purposes; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-83-090__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>other terms not inconsistent with the provisions and policy of this chapter as the authority may consider advisable.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-83-090__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The authority is not subject to the jurisdiction of the Regulatory Commission of Alaska, except as provided in
AS 44.83.700
(d). Nothing in this chapter, except as provided in
AS 44.83.700
 44.83.720, grants the authority jurisdiction over the services or rates of a public utility or diminishes or otherwise alters the jurisdiction of the Regulatory Commission of Alaska with respect to a public utility, including any right the commission may have to review and approve or disapprove contracts for the purchase of electricity by a public utility other than wholesale agreements and contracts described in
AS 42.05.431
(c)(1).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-83-092">
            <num>44.83.092</num>
            <heading>Authority for municipalities and utilities to enter into power sales contracts.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.83.092.   Authority for municipalities and utilities to enter into power sales contracts.
The authority and any municipality or public or private entity operating an electric utility, or a municipality or private entity and another municipality or private entity, may enter into a contract providing for or relating to the sale of electric power by the authority to the municipality or entity, or by the municipality or entity to another municipality or entity.  The contract may provide
(1) that the amounts payable under the contract are operating expenses of the utility and are valid and binding obligations of the municipality or other entity payable from the gross revenues of the utility;
(2) for one or more appropriations of the amounts payable under the contract;
(3) for the municipality or other entity to assume the obligations of another contracting party in the event of a default by that party;
(4) that after completion of a project the municipality or other entity is obligated to make payments notwithstanding a suspension or reduction in the amount of the power supplied by the project; or
(5) that payments under the contract are not subject to reduction by offset or otherwise.
Article 3. Financial Provisions.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-83-100">
            <num>44.83.100</num>
            <heading>Bonds of the authority.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-83-100__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The authority may borrow money and may issue bonds, including but not limited to bonds on which the principal and interest are payable (1) exclusively from the income and receipts or other money derived from the project financed with the proceeds of the bonds; (2) exclusively from the income and receipts or other money derived from designated projects whether or not they are financed in whole or in part with the proceeds of the bonds; (3) from its income and receipts or other assets generally, or a designated part or parts of them; or (4) from one or more revenue-producing contracts including a contract providing for the security of the bonds made by the authority with any person. The authority may issue bonds to pay, fund, or refund the principal of, or interest or redemption premiums on, bonds issued by it, whether or not the bonds or interest to be funded or refunded have become due.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-83-100__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Bonds shall be authorized by resolution of the authority, and shall be dated and shall mature as the resolution may provide, except that no bond may mature more than 50 years from the date of its issue.  Bonds shall bear interest at the rates, be in the denominations, be in the form, either coupon or registered, carry the registration privileges, be executed in the manner, be payable in the medium of payment, at the places, and be subject to the terms of redemption which the resolution or a subsequent resolution may provide.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-83-100__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>All bonds, regardless of form or character, shall be negotiable instruments for all the purposes of
AS 45.01

AS 45.08
,
AS 45.12
,
AS 45.14
, and
AS 45.29
(Uniform Commercial Code).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-83-100__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>All bonds may be sold at public or private sale in the manner, for the price or prices, and at the time or times which the authority may determine.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-83-110">
            <num>44.83.110</num>
            <heading>Trust indentures and trust agreements.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-83-110__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In the discretion of the authority, an issue of bonds may be secured by a trust indenture or trust agreement between the authority and a corporate trustee (which may be a trust company, bank, or national banking association, with corporate trust powers, located inside or outside the state) or by a secured loan agreement or other instrument or under a resolution giving powers to a corporate trustee by means of which the authority may</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-83-110__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>make and enter into any and all the covenants and agreements with the trustee or the holders of the bonds that the authority may determine to be necessary or desirable, including, without limitation, covenants, provisions, limitations, and agreements as to
(A) the application, investment, deposit, use, and disposition of the proceeds of bonds of the authority or of money or other property of the authority or in which it has an interest;
(B) the fixing and collection of rentals, charges, fees, or other consideration for, and the other terms to be incorporated in, contracts with respect to a project or to generated power;
(C) the assignment by the authority of its rights in contracts with respect to a project or to generated power or in a mortgage or other security interest created with respect to a project or generated power to a trustee for the benefit of bondholders;
(D) the terms and conditions upon which additional bonds of the authority may be issued;
(E) the vesting in a trustee of rights, powers, duties, funds, or property in trust for the benefit of bondholders, including, without limitation, the right to enforce payment, performance, and all other rights of the authority or of the bondholders, under a lease, power of contract, contract of sale, mortgage, security agreement, or trust agreement with respect to a project by injunction or other proceeding or by taking possession of by agent or otherwise and operating a project and collecting rents or other consideration and applying the same in accordance with the trust agreement;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-83-110__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>pledge, mortgage, or assign money, leases, agreements, property, or other rights or assets of the authority either presently in hand or to be received in the future, or both; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-83-110__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide for any other matters of like or different character that in any way affect the security or protection of the bonds.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-83-110__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding any other provisions of this chapter, the trust indenture, trust agreement, secured loan agreement, or other instrument or the resolution constituting a contract with bondholders shall contain a covenant by the authority that it will at all times maintain rates, fees, or charges sufficient to pay, and that a contract entered into by the authority for the sale, transmission, or distribution of power shall contain rates, fees, or charges sufficient to pay the costs of operation and maintenance of the project, the principal of and interest on bonds issued under the trust agreement as the same severally become due and payable, to provide for debt service coverage as considered necessary by the authority for the marketing of its bonds and to provide for renewals, replacements, and improvements of the project, and to maintain reserves required by the terms of the trust agreement. This subsection does not require a covenant that varies from a covenant entered into in accordance with the provisions of former
AS 44.83.380
 44.83.425.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-83-110__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For the purpose of securing any one or more issues of its bonds, the authority may establish one or more special funds, called capital reserve funds, and shall pay into those capital reserve funds the proceeds of the sale of its bonds and any other money that may be made available to the authority for the purposes of those funds from any other source.  The funds shall be established only if the authority determines that the establishment would enhance the marketability of the bonds.  All money held in a capital reserve fund, except as provided in this section, shall be used as required, solely for (1) the payment of the principal of, and interest on, bonds or of the sinking fund payments with respect to those bonds, (2) the purchase or redemption of bonds, or (3) the payment of a redemption premium required to be paid when those bonds are redeemed before maturity; however, money in a fund may not be withdrawn from it at any time in an amount that would reduce the amount of that fund to less than the capital reserve requirement set out in (2) of this subsection, except for the purpose of making, with respect to those bonds, payment, when due, of principal, interest, redemption premiums, and the sinking fund payments for the payment of which other money of the authority is not available.  Income or interest earned by, or increment to, a capital reserve fund, due to the investment of the fund or any other amounts in it, may be transferred by the authority to other funds or accounts of the authority to the extent that the transfer does not reduce the amount of the capital reserve fund below the capital reserve fund requirement.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-83-110__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the authority decides to issue bonds secured by such a capital reserve fund, the bonds may not be issued if the amount in the capital reserve fund is less than such an amount as may be established by resolution of the authority (called the capital reserve fund requirement), unless the authority, at the time of issuance of the obligations, deposits in the capital reserve fund from the proceeds of the obligations to be issued or from other sources, an amount which, together with the amount then in the fund, will not be less than the capital reserve fund requirement.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-83-110__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In computing the amount of a capital reserve fund for the purpose of this section, securities in which all or a portion of the funds are invested shall be valued by some reasonable method established by the authority by resolution.  Valuation on a particular date shall include the amount of any interest earned or accrued to that date.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-83-110__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The chairman of the authority shall annually, no later than January 2, make and deliver to the governor and the legislature a certificate stating the sum, if any, required to restore any capital reserve fund to the capital reserve fund requirement.  The legislature may appropriate such a sum, and all sums appropriated during the then current fiscal year by the legislature for such restoration shall be deposited by the authority in the proper capital reserve fund.  Nothing in this section creates a debt or liability of the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-83-110__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the authority has created and established a capital reserve fund, the commissioner of revenue may lend surplus money in the general fund to the authority for deposit in a capital reserve fund in an amount equal to the capital reserve fund requirement. The loans shall be made on such terms and conditions as may be agreed upon by the commissioner of revenue and the authority, including without limitation terms and conditions providing that the loans need not be repaid until the obligations of the authority secured and to be secured by the capital reserve fund are no longer outstanding.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-83-110__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the authority decides to covenant to issue or to issue bonds secured by a capital reserve fund, the bonds may not be issued until 10 days after the authority has mailed notification to the state bond committee and the Legislative Budget and Audit Committee by certified mail of its intention to establish a capital reserve fund to secure the bond issue. The notification shall include the amount of the capital reserve fund to be established, the amount of bonds proposed to be issued, and the total cost of the project for which the bonds are to be issued.  The notification shall be accompanied by an estimate by the authority of the need to withdraw money from the capital reserve fund during the term of the bond issue, the amount that it may be necessary to withdraw, and the time at which withdrawals are estimated to be needed.  The authority shall annually prepare a revised estimate, considering the same factors, and a statement of all withdrawals that have occurred from the date of issuance of the bonds to the end of the calendar year.  The revised estimate and statement shall be submitted to the state bond committee and the Legislative Budget and Audit Committee by January 30 of the succeeding year.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-83-120">
            <num>44.83.120</num>
            <heading>Validity of pledge.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.83.120.   Validity of pledge.
It is the intention of the legislature that a pledge made in respect of bonds is considered perfected and is valid and binding from the time the pledge is made; that the money or property so pledged and thereafter received by the authority shall immediately be subject to the lien of the pledge without physical delivery or further act; and that the lien of the pledge shall be valid and binding as against all parties having claims of any kind in tort, contract, or otherwise against the authority irrespective of whether the parties have notice. Neither the resolution, trust agreement, nor any other instrument by which a pledge is created need be recorded or filed under the provisions of
AS 45.01

AS 45.08
,
AS 45.12
,
AS 45.14
, and
AS 45.29
(Uniform Commercial Code) to be perfected or to be valid, binding, or effective against the parties.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-83-130">
            <num>44.83.130</num>
            <heading>Nonliability on bonds.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-83-130__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Neither the members of the authority nor a person executing the bonds is liable personally on the bonds or is subject to personal liability or accountability by reason of the issuance of the bonds.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-83-130__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The bonds issued by the authority do not constitute an indebtedness or other liability of the state or of a political subdivision of the state, except the authority, but shall be payable solely from the income and receipts or other funds or property of the authority.  The authority may not pledge the faith or credit of the state or of a political subdivision of the state, except the authority, to the payment of a bond and the issuance of a bond by the authority does not directly or indirectly or contingently obligate the state or a political subdivision of the state to apply money from, or levy or pledge any form of taxation whatever to the payment of the bond.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-83-140">
            <num>44.83.140</num>
            <heading>Pledge of the state.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.83.140.   Pledge of the state.
The state pledges to and agrees with the holders of bonds issued under this chapter and with the federal agency which loans or contributes funds in respect to a project, that the state will not limit or alter the rights and powers vested in the authority by this chapter to fulfill the terms of a contract made by the authority with the holders or federal agency, or in any way impair the rights and remedies of the holders until the bonds, together with the interest on them with interest on unpaid installments of interest, and all costs and expenses in connection with an action or proceeding by or on behalf of the holders, are fully met and discharged. The authority is authorized to include this pledge and agreement of the state, insofar as it refers to holders of bonds of the authority, in a contract with the holders, and insofar as it relates to a federal agency, in a contract with the federal agency.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-83-150">
            <num>44.83.150</num>
            <heading>Tax exemption.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.83.150.   Tax exemption.
All property of the authority is public property devoted to an essential public and governmental function and purpose and is exempt from all taxes of the state or a political subdivision of the state; however, the authority may make payments in place of taxes in amounts equal to the real and personal property taxes that would be assessed on its real and personal property by each political subdivision in which its property is located to the same extent as if that property were private property and the authority were a non-public corporation.  All bonds issued under this chapter are issued by a body corporate and public of this state and for an essential public and governmental purpose and the bonds and the interest and income on and from the bonds and all income of the authority are exempt from taxation except for transfer, inheritance, and estate taxes.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-83-160">
            <num>44.83.160</num>
            <heading>Bonds legal investments for fiduciaries.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.83.160.   Bonds legal investments for fiduciaries.
The bonds of the authority are securities in which all public officers and bodies of the state and all municipalities and municipal subdivisions, all insurance companies and associations and other persons carrying on any insurance business, all banks, bankers, trust companies, savings banks, savings associations, including savings and loan associations and building and loan associations, investment companies and other persons carrying on a banking business, all administrators, guardians, executors, trustees and other fiduciaries, and all other persons whatsoever who are now or may hereafter be authorized to invest in bonds or other obligations of the state, may properly and legally invest funds including capital in their control or belonging to them. Notwithstanding any other provisions of law, the bonds of the authority are also securities that may be deposited with and may be received by all public officers and bodies of this state and all municipalities and municipal subdivisions for any purpose for which the deposit of bonds or other obligations of the state is now or may hereafter be authorized.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-83-382">
            <num>44.83.382</num>
            <heading>Power development fund established.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-83-382__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A power development fund is established in the Alaska Energy Authority to carry out the purposes of former
AS 44.83.380
 44.83.425.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-83-382__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The fund includes money appropriated to it by the legislature.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-83-384">
            <num>44.83.384</num>
            <heading>Use of fund balance.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-83-384__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The fund may be used by the authority to provide money for</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-83-384__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the defeasance of bonds, or the payment of debt service on loans for or on an issue of bonds sold in connection with a power project constructed or acquired before August 11, 1993;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-83-384__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the cost of operating and maintaining power projects constructed or acquired before August 11, 1993; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-83-384__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>debt service on power projects constructed or acquired before August 11, 1993.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-83-384__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed § 28 ch 18 SLA 1993.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-83-384__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 28 ch 18 SLA 1993.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-83-386">
            <num>44.83.386</num>
            <heading>Investment of fund.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.83.386.   Investment of fund.
The authority shall invest the money in the fund in the manner provided in
AS 37.10.070
, 37.10.071, and 37.10.075. The authority may withdraw money from the fund only after costs have been incurred or amounts in the fund have been otherwise obligated under contracts for the acquisition and construction of a project.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-83-388">
            <num>44.83.388</num>
            <heading>Allotment to projects.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-83-388__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The authority shall maintain records of power project allocations from the fund for each power project</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-83-388__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>approved in accordance with former
AS 44.83.185
; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-83-388__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for which an allocation is made from an appropriation made by the legislature without specifying an appropriation to a project.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-83-388__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Income earned from investment of money appropriated to the fund shall be deposited in the general fund and may be appropriated to the fund by the legislature.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-83-396">
            <num>44.83.396</num>
            <heading>Operation of power project.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-83-396__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A power project that was acquired or constructed under
AS 44.83.080</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-83-396__subsec_a__subsec_18">
                <num>(18)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>or as part of the former energy program for Alaska is owned, and shall be administered, by the authority.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-83-396__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When a power project has been acquired or constructed by the authority, the project may be operated for the authority under a contract or lease entered into by a qualified utility and the authority.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-83-396__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The authority shall enter into a contract or lease under reasonable terms and conditions to permit the applicant utility to operate the power project when the applicant utility is the only wholesale power customer to be served directly by the power project unless the authority determines a utility making application for a contract or lease to operate a power project is not a qualified utility or is not capable of operating that power project efficiently and in a manner that is consistent with national standards for the industry and with agreements with bondholders.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-83-396__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The authority shall adopt regulations to determine the manner of selecting a qualified utility to operate a power project under a contract or lease when there is more than one wholesale power customer to be served directly by the power project.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-83-396__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the authority permits a power project to be operated by a qualified utility under a contract or lease, the authority shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-83-396__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>review and approve the annual budget for the operation and maintenance of the power project; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-83-396__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>assure that the project is being operated efficiently and in a manner that is consistent with national standards for the industry and agreements with bondholders.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-83-425">
            <num>44.83.425</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.83.425.   Definitions.
In
AS 44.83.382
 44.83.425,
(1) debt service means the amounts covenanted with respect to, or pledged to pay, bonds under a trust agreement securing bonds;
(2) fund means the power development fund established by
AS 44.83.382
;
(3) qualified utility means an electric utility or an electric operating entity established as an instrumentality of two or more electric utilities certified under
AS 42.05
to serve all or part of a market area that is served or will be served by the power project, that the authority determines is capable of operating and maintaining the power project.
Article 5. Power Development Revolving Loan Fund.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-83-510">
            <num>44.83.510</num>
            <heading>Powers and duties of authority in administering the fund.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-83-510__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Repayment of a loan from the former power development revolving loan fund must be made with the proceeds from the sale of power from projects in the former energy program for Alaska.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-83-510__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 28 ch 18 SLA 1993.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-83-530">
            <num>44.83.530</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.83.530.   Definitions.
In
AS 44.83.500
 44.83.530,
(1) fund means the former power development revolving loan fund; and
(2) power project means a project acquired or constructed under the former energy program for Alaska,
AS 44.83.380
 44.83.425.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-83-700">
            <num>44.83.700</num>
            <heading>Railbelt Transmission Organization.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-83-700__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Railbelt Transmission Organization is created for the purpose of establishing an open access transmission tariff that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-83-700__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provides for recovery of transmission costs and related ancillary services; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-83-700__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>replaces wholesale charges assessed by unit by each utility in the Railbelt with a new mechanism that fairly recovers and equitably allocates the costs of operating the backbone transmission system.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-83-700__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For administrative purposes, the transmission organization is a division of the Alaska Energy Authority.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-83-700__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To assist in administering the open access transmission tariff, the governance structure for the transmission organization must be made up of a representative from the authority, a representative from each Railbelt utility, and, as an ex officio nonvoting representative, the chief executive officer of the applicable electric reliability organization or the chief executive officer's designee.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-83-700__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding
AS 42.05.711</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-83-700__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and
AS 44.83.090
(b), the transmission organization is subject to the jurisdiction of the commission for the purposes of
AS 44.83.700
 44.83.720. The commission shall require the transmission organization to apply for a certificate under
AS 42.05.221
and file tariffs to achieve the purposes of
AS 44.83.700
 44.83.720.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-83-710">
            <num>44.83.710</num>
            <heading>Revenue mechanism.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-83-710__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The transmission organization shall hold and administer a commission-approved nondiscriminatory open access transmission tariff for the backbone transmission system.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-83-710__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The transmission organization shall file with the commission a nondiscriminatory open access transmission tariff consistent with Federal Energy Regulatory Commission standards to remove impediments to competition in the wholesale bulk power marketplace in the state. If the transmission organization does not file a nondiscriminatory open access transmission tariff with the commission on or before July 1, 2025, the commission shall, after notice and opportunity for public comment, establish a nondiscriminatory open access transmission tariff consistent with this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-83-710__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The nondiscriminatory open access transmission tariff must, as approved by the commission,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-83-710__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>pool backbone transmission system costs and allocate those costs through certificated load-serving entities on a coincident peak or load ratio share basis, or a combination of both; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-83-710__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>account for
(A) required backbone transmission system ancillary services;
(B) backbone transmission system congestion;
(C) disruptions to the backbone transmission system that result in the isolation of one geographical area of the backbone transmission system from another for more than 24 hours; and
(D) costs to own and operate the backbone transmission system, as established by the commission or by contract, including transmission costs associated with the Bradley Lake hydroelectric project.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-83-710__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A Railbelt utility shall pass the commission-approved transmission costs directly and transparently to the utility's customers.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-83-720">
            <num>44.83.720</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.83.720.   Definitions.
In
AS 44.83.700
 44.83.720,
(1) backbone transmission system means the transmission assets in the Railbelt that facilitate the transmission of electrical power under the standards established by the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission;
(2) commission means the Regulatory Commission of Alaska;
(3) Railbelt means the geographic region from the Kenai Peninsula to Interior Alaska that is connected to a common electric transmission backbone;
(4) Railbelt utility means a public electric utility certificated to operate in the Railbelt that operates backbone transmission system assets;
(5) transmission organization means the Railbelt Transmission Organization established by
AS 44.83.700
.
Article 7. Miscellaneous and General Provisions.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-83-900">
            <num>44.83.900</num>
            <heading>Annual audit.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.83.900.   Annual audit.
The authority shall have its financial records audited annually by a certified public accountant.  The legislative auditor may prescribe the form and content of the financial records of the authority and shall have access to these records at any time.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-83-910">
            <num>44.83.910</num>
            <heading>Limitations on issuance of bonds by the authority.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.83.910.   Limitations on issuance of bonds by the authority.
The authority may not issue bonds except after 60 days notification of its intent to issue bonds is given to the governor and to the legislature, if the legislature is in session, or to the Legislative Budget and Audit Committee, if the legislature is not in session.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-83-920">
            <num>44.83.920</num>
            <heading>Insurance requirements in construction contracts.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.83.920.   Insurance requirements in construction contracts.
In requesting bids and awarding construction contracts under this chapter the authority may not require a contractor to obtain workers' compensation, general liability, or other required insurance from a particular insurer, agent, or broker and may not agree to provide insurance to a contractor who is awarded a construction contract.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-83-930">
            <num>44.83.930</num>
            <heading>Operation of projects.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-83-930__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When a project is operated by the authority, the authority shall enter into one or more contracts for the sale of electrical power, energy, transmission capacity, or service from the project. Unless the contract is entered into under former
AS 44.83.380
 44.83.425, a contract entered into under this section must meet all requirements of
AS 44.83.090
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-83-930__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 27 ch 89 SLA 1983.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-83-930__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 92 ch 36 SLA 1990.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-83-940">
            <num>44.83.940</num>
            <heading>Annual report.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.83.940.   Annual report.
Before March 1 of each year, the authority shall submit to the governor a comprehensive report describing operations, income and expenditures for the preceding 12-month period. The authority shall notify the legislature that the report is available.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-83-950">
            <num>44.83.950</num>
            <heading>Appropriations and reports.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-83-950__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding any other provision in this chapter, the authority is subject to the provisions of
AS 37.07
(Executive Budget Act).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-83-950__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The authority shall, by the 15th day of each regular legislative session, prepare a report detailing project status, original costs, and projected costs, particularly highlighting any costs in excess of the original cost estimates submitted for each project when that project was originally approved by the legislature. The authority shall notify the legislature that the report is available.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-83-970">
            <num>44.83.970</num>
            <heading>Public records; open meetings.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.83.970.   Public records; open meetings.
The provisions of
AS 40.25.110
 40.25.120 and
AS 44.62.310
 44.62.319 (Open Meetings Act) apply to the authority.  The authority shall publish a proposed agenda of its meetings and afford the public an opportunity to be heard in accordance with
AS 44.62.312
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-83-990">
            <num>44.83.990</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.83.990.   Definitions.
In this chapter, unless the context requires otherwise,
(1) authority means the Alaska Energy Authority established by this chapter;
(2) bonds means bonds, notes, or other obligations of the authority issued under this chapter;
(3) feasibility study
(A) means a study conducted for the purpose of establishing the economic and environmental practicality of completing a proposed power project;
(B) includes engineering and design work to meet the requirements for submission of a license application for a proposed new project to the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission;
(4) person includes a public agency in addition to the entities set out in
AS 01.10.060
(a)(8);
(5) power includes any and all electrical energy generated, distributed, bought, or sold for purposes of lighting, heating, power, and every other useful purpose;
(6) power project or project means a plant, works, system, or facility, together with related or necessary facilities and appurtenances, including a divided or undivided interest in or a right to the capacity of a power project or project, that is used or is useful for the purpose of
(A) electrical or thermal energy production;
(B) waste energy utilization and energy conservation; or
(C) transmission, purchase, sale, exchange, and interchange of electrical or thermal energy, including district heating or interties;
(7) public agency means any city or other municipal corporation, political subdivision, governmental unit, or public corporation created by or under the laws of this state or of another state of the United States, and any state or the United States, and any person, board, or other body declared by the laws of any state or the United States to be a department, agency, or instrumentality of them.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-83-995">
            <num>44.83.995</num>
            <heading>Short title.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.83.995.   Short title.
This chapter may be cited as the Alaska Energy Authority Act.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>