<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-42/chapter-04"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-42/chapter-04"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="42.04"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-42/chapter-04/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-42/chapter-04/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-42/chapter-04/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-42/chapter-04/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_42">
        <num>42</num>
        <heading>Public Utilities and Carriers and Energy Programs</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_42__chp_04">
          <num>04</num>
          <heading>Regulatory Commission of Alaska</heading>
          <section eId="sec_42-04-010">
            <num>42.04.010</num>
            <heading>Regulatory Commission of Alaska created.</heading>
            <subsection eId="42-04-010__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>There is created within the Department of Commerce, Community, and Economic Development as an independent agency of the state the Regulatory Commission of Alaska.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="42-04-010__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall annually elect one of its members to serve as chair for the following fiscal year. When a vacancy occurs in the office of chair, the commission shall elect one of its members to serve the remaining term as chair. The term as chair is one year. The chair may be elected to not more than three successive terms as chair. After a year of not serving as chair, the commissioner is eligible for election as chair again.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_42-04-020">
            <num>42.04.020</num>
            <heading>Commissioners.</heading>
            <subsection eId="42-04-020__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission consists of five commissioners appointed by the governor and confirmed by the legislature in joint session. To qualify for appointment as a commissioner, a person must</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="42-04-020__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>be a member in good standing of the Alaska Bar Association with at least five years of actual experience in the practice of law;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="42-04-020__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>be a professional engineer registered under
AS 08.48
; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="42-04-020__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>have a degree from an accredited college or university with a major in finance, economics, accounting, business administration, or public administration and at least five years of actual experience in the field associated with the degree.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="42-04-020__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The term of office of each member is six years. A commissioner, upon the expiration of a term, shall continue to hold office until a successor is appointed and qualified.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="42-04-020__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A vacancy arising in the office of a commissioner shall be filled by appointment by the governor and confirmed by the legislature in joint session, and, except as provided in
AS 39.05.080</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="42-04-020__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A vacancy in the commission does not impair the authority of a quorum of commissioners to exercise all the powers and perform all the duties of the commission.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="42-04-020__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The governor may remove a commissioner from office for cause, including incompetence, neglect of duty, inability to serve, or misconduct in office or because the member, while serving on the commission, is convicted of a misdemeanor for violating a statute or regulation related to public utilities or is convicted of a felony. A commissioner, to be removed for cause, shall be given a copy of the charges and afforded an opportunity to be publicly heard in person or by counsel in the commissioner's own defense upon not less than 10 days' notice. If a commissioner is removed for cause, the governor shall file with the lieutenant governor a complete statement of all charges made against the commissioner and the governor's finding based on the charges, together with a complete record of the proceedings.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="42-04-020__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Members of the commission are in the exempt service and are entitled to a monthly salary equal to a step in Range 29 of the salary schedule in
AS 39.27.011</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="42-04-020__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>for Juneau, Alaska. The chair of the commission is entitled to a monthly salary equal to a step in Range 29 of the salary schedule in
AS 39.27.011</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="42-04-020__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>for Juneau, Alaska.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="42-04-020__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each commissioner, before entering upon the duties of office, shall take and subscribe to the oath prescribed for principal officers of the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_42-04-030">
            <num>42.04.030</num>
            <heading>Principal office; seal.</heading>
            <subsection eId="42-04-030__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall establish a principal office and branch offices necessary to discharge its business efficiently. For the convenience of the public or of parties to a proceeding, the commission may hold meetings, hearings, or other proceedings at other locations.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="42-04-030__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall have an official seal.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_42-04-040">
            <num>42.04.040</num>
            <heading>Legal counsel.</heading>
            <subsection eId="42-04-040__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Law shall provide full-time legal counsel to the commission.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="42-04-040__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission may, subject to the approval of the attorney general, contract for the services of specialized legal counsel or legal consultants.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_42-04-050">
            <num>42.04.050</num>
            <heading>Employment of commission personnel.</heading>
            <subsection eId="42-04-050__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The chair of the commission is responsible for directing the administrative functions of the commission and carrying out the policies as set by the commission. The commission chair may employ engineers, hearing examiners, administrative law judges, arbitrators, mediators, experts, clerks, accountants, a number of utilities analyst masters, not to exceed five, and other agents and assistants considered necessary. Employees of the commission who are not in the exempt service under
AS 39.25.110
or the partially exempt service under
AS 39.25.120
are in the classified service under
AS 39.25.100
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="42-04-050__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The chair of the commission may enter into a contract for no more than $5,000 to engage the services of a consultant or expert the chair considers necessary. The commission may contract for and engage the services of consultants and experts the commission considers necessary.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="42-04-050__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>At the request of the Alaska Oil and Gas Conservation Commission and to the extent workload permits, the Regulatory Commission of Alaska shall make available to the Alaska Oil and Gas Conservation Commission the services of a hearing examiner.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_42-04-060">
            <num>42.04.060</num>
            <heading>Restrictions on members and employees.</heading>
            <subsection eId="42-04-060__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A member of the commission or an employee of the commission may not have an official connection with, hold stock or securities in, or have a pecuniary interest in a public utility or pipeline carrier within the state. Membership in a cooperative association is not a pecuniary interest within the meaning of this section; however, a member or employee of the commission may not be an officer, board member, or employee of a cooperative association. A member or employee may not act upon a matter in which a relationship of the member or employee with any person creates a conflict of interest.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="42-04-060__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A member or employee of the commission may not, after leaving the position as a member or employee of the commission, act as agent for or on behalf of a public utility in any matter before the commission that was before the commission during the employee's employment or the member's term of office. A violation of this subsection is a class A misdemeanor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="42-04-060__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Members and employees of the commission, except clerical and secretarial staff, are subject to
AS 39.50
. Members and employees of the commission are subject to
AS 39.52
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="42-04-060__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A member of the commission is disqualified from voting upon any matter before the commission in which the member has a conflict of interest.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_42-04-070">
            <num>42.04.070</num>
            <heading>Powers and duties of commission chair.</heading>
            <subsection eId="42-04-070__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The chair of the commission shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="42-04-070__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>employ the commission staff;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="42-04-070__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establish and implement a time management system for the commission;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="42-04-070__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>assign the work of the commission to members and staff of the commission so that matters before the commission are resolved as expeditiously and competently as possible; when assigning a matter, the chair shall also set a date by which time the matter should be completed.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="42-04-070__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The chair of the commission may appoint a hearing examiner or an administrative law judge to hear a matter that has come before the commission; a member of the commission may serve as hearing examiner or, if qualified, as an administrative law judge.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="42-04-070__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The chair of the commission shall request the attorney general to participate as a party in a matter when the commission believes that it is in the public interest for the attorney general to do so.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_42-04-080">
            <num>42.04.080</num>
            <heading>Decision-making procedures.</heading>
            <subsection eId="42-04-080__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in
AS 42.05.171
or
AS 42.06.140
, when a matter comes for decision before the commission under
AS 42.05
,
AS 42.06
, or
AS 42.08
, the chair shall appoint a hearing panel composed of three or more members to hear, or if a hearing is not required, to otherwise consider, and decide the case. The panel shall exercise the powers of the commission with respect to the matter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="42-04-080__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall adopt regulations that establish standards of timeliness for the types of cases that come before the commission. The commission shall establish standards based in part on degrees of complexity of the cases.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_42-04-100">
            <num>42.04.100</num>
            <heading>Communications carriers section.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 42.04.100.   Communications carriers section.
There is established within the commission a communications carriers section that shall develop, recommend, and administer policies and programs with respect to the regulation of rates, services, accounting, and facilities of communications common carriers within the state involving the use of wire, cable, radio, and space satellites.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>