<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-23/chapter-40"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-23/chapter-40"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="23.40"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-23/chapter-40/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-23/chapter-40/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-23/chapter-40/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-23/chapter-40/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_23">
        <num>23</num>
        <heading>Labor and Workers' Compensation</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_23__chp_40">
          <num>40</num>
          <heading>Labor Organizations</heading>
          <section eId="sec_23-40-020">
            <num>23.40.020</num>
            <heading>Enforcement of certain contracts only if union registers.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 23.40.020.   Enforcement of certain contracts only if union registers.
A labor contract executed in this state by a labor organization that has no local in this state or which contract is not to be executed by one or more of its locals in this state may not be enforced in the courts of this state unless the labor organization has registered with the department and complied with all regulations adopted by it.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_23-40-030">
            <num>23.40.030</num>
            <heading>Definition of labor organization.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 23.40.030.   Definition of labor organization.
For the purpose of
AS 23.40.020
 23.40.040 labor organization includes an organization constituted wholly or partly to bargain collectively or deal with employers, including the state and its political subdivisions, concerning grievances, terms, or conditions of employment or other mutual aid or protection in connection with employees.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_23-40-040">
            <num>23.40.040</num>
            <heading>Collective bargaining agreement.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 23.40.040.   Collective bargaining agreement.
The commissioner of transportation and public facilities or an authorized representative, in accordance with
AS 23.40.020
 23.40.030, may negotiate and enter into collective bargaining agreements concerning wages, hours, working conditions, and other employment benefits with the employees of the division of marine transportation engaged in operating the state ferry system as masters or members of the crews of vessels or their bargaining agent.  A collective bargaining agreement is not final without the concurrence of the commissioner of transportation and public facilities.  The commissioner of transportation and public facilities may make provision in the collective bargaining agreement for the settlement of labor disputes by arbitration.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_23-40-070">
            <num>23.40.070</num>
            <heading>Declaration of policy.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 23.40.070.   Declaration of policy.
The legislature finds that joint decision-making is the modern way of administering government.  If public employees have been granted the right to share in the decision-making process affecting wages and working conditions, they have become more responsive and better able to exchange ideas and information on operations with their administrators.  Accordingly, government is made more effective. The legislature further finds that the enactment of positive legislation establishing guidelines for public employment relations is the best way to harness and direct the energies of public employees eager to have a voice in determining their conditions of work, to provide a rational method for dealing with disputes and work stoppages, to strengthen the merit principle where civil service is in effect, and to maintain a favorable political and social environment.  The legislature declares that it is the public policy of the state to promote harmonious and cooperative relations between government and its employees and to protect the public by assuring effective and orderly operations of government.  These policies are to be effectuated by
(1) recognizing the right of public employees to organize for the purpose of collective bargaining;
(2) requiring public employers to negotiate with and enter into written agreements with employee organizations on matters of wages, hours, and other terms and conditions of employment;
(3) maintaining merit-system principles among public employees.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_23-40-075">
            <num>23.40.075</num>
            <heading>Items not subject to bargaining.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 23.40.075.   Items not subject to bargaining.
The parties may not negotiate terms contrary to the
(1) reemployment rights for injured state employees under
AS 39.25.158
;
(2) reemployment rights of the organized militia under
AS 26.05.075
;
(3) authority of the Department of Health under
AS 47.27.035
to assign Alaska temporary assistance program participants to a work activity considered appropriate by the Department of Health;
(4) authority for agencies to create temporary positions under
AS 47.27.055
(c); or
(5) provisions contained in a contract under
AS 14.40.210
(a)(4).</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_23-40-080">
            <num>23.40.080</num>
            <heading>Rights of public employees.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 23.40.080.   Rights of public employees.
Public employees may self-organize and form, join, or assist an organization to bargain collectively through representatives of their own choosing, and engage in concerted activities for the purpose of collective bargaining or other mutual aid or protection.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_23-40-090">
            <num>23.40.090</num>
            <heading>Collective bargaining unit.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 23.40.090.   Collective bargaining unit.
The labor relations agency shall decide in each case, in order to assure to employees the fullest freedom in exercising the rights guaranteed by
AS 23.40.070
 23.40.260, the unit appropriate for the purposes of collective bargaining, based on such factors as community of interest, wages, hours, and other working conditions of the employees involved, the history of collective bargaining, and the desires of the employees.  Bargaining units shall be as large as is reasonable, and unnecessary fragmenting shall be avoided.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_23-40-100">
            <num>23.40.100</num>
            <heading>Representatives and elections.</heading>
            <subsection eId="23-40-100__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The labor relations agency shall investigate a petition if it is submitted in a manner prescribed by the labor relations agency and is</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="23-40-100__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>by an employee or group of employees or an organization acting in their behalf alleging that 30 percent of the employees of a proposed bargaining unit
(A) want to be represented for collective bargaining by a labor or employee organization as exclusive representative, or
(B) assert that the organization which has been certified or is currently being recognized by the public employer as bargaining representative is no longer the representative of the majority of employees in the bargaining unit; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="23-40-100__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>by the public employer alleging that one or more organizations have presented to it a claim to be recognized as a representative of a majority of employees in an appropriate unit.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="23-40-100__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the labor relations agency has reasonable cause to believe that a question of representation exists, it shall provide for an appropriate hearing upon due notice.  If the labor relations agency finds that there is a question of representation, it shall direct an election by secret ballot to determine whether or by which organization the employees desire to be represented and shall certify the results of the election. Nothing in this section prohibits the waiving of hearings by stipulation for the purpose of a consent election in conformity with the regulations of the labor relations agency or an election in a bargaining unit agreed upon by the parties.  The labor relations agency shall determine who is eligible to vote in an election and shall establish rules governing the election.  In an election in which none of the choices on the ballot receives a majority of the votes cast, a runoff election shall be conducted, the ballot providing for selection between the two choices receiving the largest and the second largest number of valid votes cast in the election.  If an organization receives the majority of the votes cast in the election it shall be certified by the labor relations agency as exclusive representative of all the employees in the bargaining unit.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="23-40-100__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An election may not be held in a bargaining unit or in a subdivision of a bargaining unit if a valid election has been held within the preceding 12 months.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="23-40-100__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing in this chapter prohibits recognition of an organization as the exclusive representative by a public agency by mutual consent.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="23-40-100__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An election may not be directed by the labor relations agency in a bargaining unit in which there is in force a valid collective bargaining agreement, except during a 90-day period preceding the expiration date.  However, a collective bargaining agreement may not bar an election upon petition of persons in the bargaining unit but not parties to the agreement if more than three years have elapsed since the execution of the agreement or the last timely renewal, whichever was later.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_23-40-110">
            <num>23.40.110</num>
            <heading>Unfair labor practices.</heading>
            <subsection eId="23-40-110__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A public employer or an agent of a public employer may not</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="23-40-110__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>interfere with, restrain, or coerce an employee in the exercise of the employee's rights guaranteed in
AS 23.40.080
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="23-40-110__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>dominate or interfere with the formation, existence, or administration of an organization;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="23-40-110__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>discriminate in regard to hire or tenure of employment or a term or condition of employment to encourage or discourage membership in an organization;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="23-40-110__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>discharge or discriminate against an employee because the employee has signed or filed an affidavit, petition, or complaint or given testimony under
AS 23.40.070
 23.40.260;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="23-40-110__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>refuse to bargain collectively in good faith with an organization which is the exclusive representative of employees in an appropriate unit, including but not limited to the discussing of grievances with the exclusive representative.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="23-40-110__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing in this chapter prohibits a public employer from making an agreement with an organization to require as a condition of employment</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="23-40-110__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>membership in the organization which represents the unit on or after the 30th day following the beginning of employment or on the effective date of the agreement, whichever is later; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="23-40-110__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>payment by the employee to the exclusive bargaining agent of a service fee to reimburse the exclusive bargaining agent for the expense of representing the members of the bargaining unit.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="23-40-110__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A labor or employee organization or its agents may not</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="23-40-110__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>restrain or coerce
(A) an employee in the exercise of the rights guaranteed in
AS 23.40.080
; or
(B) a public employer in the selection of the employer's representative for the purposes of collective bargaining or the adjustment of grievances;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="23-40-110__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>refuse to bargain collectively in good faith with a public employer, if it has been designated in accordance with the provisions of
AS 23.40.070
 23.40.260 as the exclusive representative of employees in an appropriate unit.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_23-40-120">
            <num>23.40.120</num>
            <heading>Investigation and conciliation of complaints.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 23.40.120.   Investigation and conciliation of complaints.
If a verified written complaint by or for a person claiming to be aggrieved by a practice prohibited by
AS 23.40.110
, or a written accusation that a person subject to
AS 23.40.070
 23.40.260 has engaged in a prohibited practice, is filed with the labor relations agency, it shall investigate the complaint or accusation.  If it determines after the preliminary investigation that probable cause exists in support of the complaint or accusation, it shall try to eliminate the prohibited practice by informal methods of conference, conciliation, and persuasion. Nothing said or done during this endeavor may be used as evidence in a subsequent proceeding.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_23-40-130">
            <num>23.40.130</num>
            <heading>Complaint and accusation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 23.40.130.   Complaint and accusation.
If the labor relations agency fails to eliminate the prohibited practice by conciliation and to obtain voluntary compliance with
AS 23.40.070
 23.40.260, or, before it attempts conciliation, it may serve a copy of the complaint or accusation upon the respondent.  The complaint or accusation and the subsequent procedures shall be handled in accordance with the administrative adjudication portion of
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act).</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_23-40-140">
            <num>23.40.140</num>
            <heading>Orders and decisions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 23.40.140.   Orders and decisions.
If the labor relations agency finds that a person named in the written complaint or accusation has engaged in a prohibited practice, the labor relations agency shall issue and serve on the person an order or decision requiring the person to cease and desist from the prohibited practice and to take affirmative action which will carry out the provisions of
AS 23.40.070
 23.40.260.  If the labor relations agency finds that a person named in the complaint or accusation has not engaged or is not engaging in a prohibited practice, the labor relations agency shall state its findings of fact and issue an order dismissing the complaint or accusation.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_23-40-150">
            <num>23.40.150</num>
            <heading>Enforcement by injunction.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 23.40.150.   Enforcement by injunction.
The labor relations agency may apply to the superior court in the judicial district in which the prohibited practice occurred for an order enjoining the prohibited acts specified in the order or decision of the labor relations agency.  Upon a showing by the labor relations agency that the person has engaged or is about to engage in the practice, an injunction, restraining order, or other order which is appropriate may be granted by the court and shall be without bond.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_23-40-160">
            <num>23.40.160</num>
            <heading>Power to investigate and compel testimony.</heading>
            <subsection eId="23-40-160__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For the purpose of the investigations, proceedings, or hearings which the labor relations agency considers necessary to carry out the provisions of
AS 23.40.070
 23.40.260, the labor relations agency may issue subpoenas requiring the attendance and testimony of witnesses and the production of relevant evidence.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="23-40-160__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The labor relations agency may administer oaths, examine witnesses, and receive evidence.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="23-40-160__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The attendance of witnesses and the production of evidence may be required from any place in the state at any designated place of hearing.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="23-40-160__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a person refuses to obey a subpoena issued under
AS 23.40.070
 23.40.260, the superior court in the district in which the person resides or is found may, upon application by the labor relations agency, issue an order requiring the person to comply with the subpoena.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_23-40-170">
            <num>23.40.170</num>
            <heading>Regulations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 23.40.170.   Regulations.
The labor relations agency may adopt regulations under
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act) to carry out the provisions of
AS 23.40.070
 23.40.260.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_23-40-180">
            <num>23.40.180</num>
            <heading>Penalty for violation of order or decision.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 23.40.180.   Penalty for violation of order or decision.
A person who violates a provision of an order or decision of the labor relations agency is guilty of a misdemeanor and is punishable by a fine of not more than $500.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_23-40-190">
            <num>23.40.190</num>
            <heading>Mediation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 23.40.190.   Mediation.
If, after a reasonable period of negotiation over the terms of a collective bargaining agreement, a deadlock exists between a public employer and an organization, the labor relations agency may appoint a competent, impartial, disinterested person to act as mediator in any dispute either on its own initiative or on the request of one of the parties to the dispute.  The parties may also select a mediator by agreement or mutual consent.  It is the function of the mediator to bring the parties together voluntarily under such favorable auspices as will tend to effectuate settlement of the dispute, but neither the mediator nor the labor relations agency has any power of compulsion in mediation proceedings.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_23-40-200">
            <num>23.40.200</num>
            <heading>Classes of public employees; arbitration.</heading>
            <subsection eId="23-40-200__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of this section, public employees are employed to perform services in one of the three following classes:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="23-40-200__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>those services which may not be given up for even the shortest period of time;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="23-40-200__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>those services which may be interrupted for a limited period but not for an indefinite period of time; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="23-40-200__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>those services in which work stoppages may be sustained for extended periods without serious effects on the public.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="23-40-200__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The class in (a)(1) of this section is composed of police and fire protection employees, jail, prison, and other correctional institution employees, and hospital employees. Employees in this class may not engage in strikes. Upon a showing by a public employer or the labor relations agency that employees in this class are engaging or about to engage in a strike, an injunction, restraining order, or other order that may be appropriate shall be granted by the superior court in the judicial district in which the strike is occurring or is about to occur. If an impasse or deadlock is reached in collective bargaining between the public employer and employees in this class, and mediation has been utilized without resolving the deadlock, the parties shall submit to arbitration to be carried out under
AS 09.43.030
or 09.43.480 to the extent permitted by
AS 09.43.010
and 09.43.300.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="23-40-200__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The class in (a)(2) of this section is composed of public utility, snow removal, sanitation, and educational institution employees other than employees of a school district, a regional educational attendance area, or a state boarding school. Employees in this class may engage in a strike after mediation, subject to the voting requirement of (d) of this section, for a limited time. The limit is determined by the interests of the health, safety, or welfare of the public. The public employer or the labor relations agency may apply to the superior court in the judicial district in which the strike is occurring for an order enjoining the strike. A strike may not be enjoined unless it can be shown that it has begun to threaten the health, safety, or welfare of the public. A court, in deciding whether or not to enjoin the strike, shall consider the total equities in the particular class. Total equities includes not only the effect of a strike on the public but also the extent to which employee organizations and public employers have met their statutory obligations. If an impasse or deadlock still exists after the issuance of an injunction, the parties shall submit to arbitration to be carried out under
AS 09.43.030
or 09.43.480 to the extent permitted by
AS 09.43.010
and 09.43.300.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="23-40-200__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The class in (a)(3) of this section includes all other public employees who are not included in the classes in (a)(1) or (2) of this section. Subject to (g) of this section, employees in this class may engage in a strike if a majority of the employees in a collective bargaining unit vote by secret ballot to do so.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="23-40-200__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding the provisions of (b), (c), and (d) of this section, the employees with the concurrence of the employer may agree in writing to submit a dispute arising from interpretation or application of a collective bargaining agreement to arbitration.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="23-40-200__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The parties to a collective bargaining agreement may provide in the agreement a contract for arbitration to be conducted solely according to
AS 09.43.010
 09.43.180 (Uniform Arbitration Act) or
AS 09.43.300
 09.43.595 (Revised Uniform Arbitration Act) to the extent permitted by
AS 09.43.010
and 09.43.300 if either Act is incorporated into the agreement or contract by reference.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="23-40-200__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Under the provisions of (d) of this section, if an impasse or deadlock is reached in collective bargaining negotiations between a municipal school district, a regional educational attendance area, or a state boarding school and its employees,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="23-40-200__subsec_g__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the parties shall submit to advisory arbitration before the employees may vote to engage in a strike; the arbitrator shall
(A) be a member of the American Arbitration Association, Panel of Labor Arbitrators, or the Federal Mediation and Conciliation Service;
(B) have knowledge of and recent experience in the local conditions in the school district, regional educational attendance area, or state boarding school; and
(C) be determined from a list containing at least five nominees who meet the qualifications of this subsection; this list shall be considered a complete list for the purpose of striking names and selecting the arbitrator;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="23-40-200__subsec_g__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if, under (1) of this subsection, advisory arbitration fails, a strike may not begin until at least 72 hours after notice of the strike is given to the other party; in any event, a strike may not begin on or after the first day of the school term, as that term is described in
AS 14.03.030
, unless at least one day in session with students in attendance has passed after notice of the strike is given by the employees to the other party.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_23-40-205">
            <num>23.40.205</num>
            <heading>Family leave.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 23.40.205.   Family leave.
Notwithstanding any provision of
AS 23.40.070
 23.40.260 to the contrary, an agreement between the employer subject to
AS 39.20.500
 39.20.550 and an employee bargaining organization that does not contain benefit provisions at least as beneficial to the employee as those provided by
AS 39.20.500
 39.20.550 shall be considered to contain the benefit provisions of those statutes.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_23-40-210">
            <num>23.40.210</num>
            <heading>Agreement; cost-of-living differential.</heading>
            <subsection eId="23-40-210__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon the completion of negotiations between an organization and a public employer, if a settlement is reached, the employer shall reduce it to writing in the form of an agreement.  The agreement may include a term for which it will remain in effect, not to exceed three years.  The agreement shall include a pay plan designed to provide for a cost-of-living differential between the salaries paid employees residing in the state and employees residing outside the state. The plan shall provide that the salaries paid, as of August 26, 1977, to employees residing outside the state shall remain unchanged until the difference between those salaries and the salaries paid employees residing in the state reflects the difference between the cost of living in Alaska and living in Seattle, Washington.  The agreement shall include a grievance procedure which shall have binding arbitration as its final step. Either party to the agreement has a right of action to enforce the agreement by petition to the labor relations agency.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="23-40-210__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An employee is eligible for the cost-of-living differential under (a) of this section only if the individual is a state resident. The required presence of an employee at a work station where room and board are provided or reimbursed by the employer may not be considered to be physical presence in the state or physical absence from the state for purposes of determining eligibility for the cost-of-living differential.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="23-40-210__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner of administration may adopt regulations under
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act) to clarify and implement the criteria for establishing and maintaining eligibility for the cost-of-living differential.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="23-40-210__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An agreement entered into under
AS 23.40.070
 23.40.260 must require compliance with the eligibility criteria for receiving the cost-of-living differential contained in this section and the regulations adopted by the commissioner under (c) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="23-40-210__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, state resident means an individual who is physically present in the state with the intent to remain permanently in the state under the requirements of
AS 01.10.055
or, if the individual is not physically present in the state, intends to return to the state and remain permanently in the state under the requirements of
AS 01.10.055
and is absent only temporarily for reasons allowed under
AS 43.23.008
or a successor statute.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_23-40-212">
            <num>23.40.212</num>
            <heading>Agreement with the Board of Regents.</heading>
            <subsection eId="23-40-212__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Board of Regents of the University of Alaska may delegate to the Department of Administration its authority under
AS 23.40.070
 23.40.260 to negotiate with an organization for an agreement.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="23-40-212__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Administration shall participate in the negotiations between the Board of Regents and an organization.  An agreement between the board and an organization requires the approval of the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_23-40-215">
            <num>23.40.215</num>
            <heading>Monetary terms subject to legislative funding.</heading>
            <subsection eId="23-40-215__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The monetary terms of any agreement entered into under
AS 23.40.070
 23.40.260 are subject to funding through legislative appropriation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="23-40-215__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Administration shall submit the monetary terms of an agreement to the legislature within 10 legislative days after the agreement of the parties, if the legislature is in session, or within 10 legislative days after the convening of the next regular session. The complete monetary and nonmonetary terms of a tentative agreement shall be submitted to the legislature no later than the 60th day of the legislative session to receive legislative consideration during that calendar year. However, if the department has submitted a tentative agreement in a timely manner and the parties to the agreement decide to renegotiate the terms, the renegotiated agreement shall be considered to have been submitted in a timely manner. In this subsection, tentative agreement means an agreement that has been reached by the negotiators for the employer and the bargaining unit but that may not yet have been ratified by the members of the bargaining unit.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="23-40-215__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (b) of this section, the monetary terms of an agreement entered into between a school district or regional educational attendance area and its employees are not required to be submitted to the legislature.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_23-40-220">
            <num>23.40.220</num>
            <heading>Labor or employee organization dues and employee benefits, deduction and authorization.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 23.40.220.   Labor or employee organization dues and employee benefits, deduction and authorization.
Upon written authorization of a public employee within a bargaining unit, the public employer shall deduct from the payroll of the public employee the monthly amount of dues, fees, and other employee benefits as certified by the secretary of the exclusive bargaining representative and shall deliver it to the chief fiscal officer of the exclusive bargaining representative.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_23-40-225">
            <num>23.40.225</num>
            <heading>Exemption based on religious convictions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 23.40.225.   Exemption based on religious convictions.
Notwithstanding the provisions of
AS 23.40.220
, a collective bargaining settlement reached, or agreement entered into, under
AS 23.40.210
that incorporates union security provisions, including a union shop or agency shop provision or agreement, shall safeguard the rights of nonassociation of employees having bona fide religious convictions based on tenets or teachings of a church or religious body of which an employee is a member. Upon submission of proper proof of religious conviction to the labor relations agency, the agency shall declare the employee exempt from becoming a member of a labor organization or employee association. The employee shall pay an amount of money equivalent to regular union or association dues, initiation fees, and assessments to the union or association. Nonpayment of this money subjects the employee to the same penalty as if it were nonpayment of dues. The receiving union or association shall contribute an equivalent amount of money to a charity of its choice not affiliated with a religious, labor, or employee organization. The union or association shall submit proof of contribution to the labor relations agency.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_23-40-235">
            <num>23.40.235</num>
            <heading>Public involvement in school district negotiations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 23.40.235.   Public involvement in school district negotiations.
Before beginning bargaining, the school board of a city or borough school district or a regional educational attendance area shall provide opportunities for public comment on the issues to be addressed in the collective bargaining process. Initial proposals, last-best-offer proposals, tentative agreements before ratification, and final agreements reached by the parties are public documents and are subject to inspection and copying under
AS 40.25.110
 40.25.140.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_23-40-240">
            <num>23.40.240</num>
            <heading>Effect on certain units, representatives, and agreements.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 23.40.240.   Effect on certain units, representatives, and agreements.
Nothing in this chapter terminates or modifies a collective bargaining unit, recognition of exclusive bargaining representative, or collective bargaining agreement if the unit, recognition, or agreement is in effect on September 5, 1972.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_23-40-245">
            <num>23.40.245</num>
            <heading>Postsecondary student involvement in collective bargaining.</heading>
            <subsection eId="23-40-245__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When a bargaining unit includes members of the faculty or other employees of a public institution of postsecondary education, the public employer and the representative of the bargaining unit shall permit student representatives of that institution to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="23-40-245__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>attend and observe all meetings between the public employer and the representative of the bargaining unit which are involved with collective bargaining;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="23-40-245__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>have access to all documents pertaining to collective bargaining exchanged by the employer and the representative of the bargaining unit, including copies of transcripts of the meetings.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="23-40-245__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Student representatives may not disclose information concerning the substance of collective bargaining obtained in the course of their activities under (a) of this section, unless that information is released by the employer or the representative of the bargaining unit.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="23-40-245__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For the purpose of this section, the students of the institution involved in negotiations shall select their representatives from the institution directly involved in negotiations.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="23-40-245__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the institutions are negotiating with bargaining units representing more than one major geographic area of the state, the student representatives shall be from those areas.  No more than three student representatives may attend meetings at any time.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_23-40-250">
            <num>23.40.250</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 23.40.250.   Definitions.
In
AS 23.40.070
 23.40.260, unless the context otherwise requires,
(1) collective bargaining means the performance of the mutual obligation of the public employer or the employer's designated representatives and the representative of the employees to meet at reasonable times, including meetings in advance of the budget making process, and negotiate in good faith with respect to wages, hours, and other terms and conditions of employment, or the negotiation of an agreement, or negotiation of a question arising under an agreement and the execution of a written contract incorporating an agreement reached if requested by either party, but these obligations do not compel either party to agree to a proposal or require the making of a concession;
(2) election means a proceeding conducted by the labor relations agency in which the employees in a collective bargaining unit cast a secret ballot for collective bargaining representatives, or for any other purpose specified in
AS 23.40.070
 23.40.260;
(3) labor relations agency means the Alaska labor relations agency established in
AS 23.05.360
;
(4) monetary terms of an agreement means the changes in the terms and conditions of employment resulting from an agreement that
(A) will require an appropriation for their implementation;
(B) will result in a change in state revenues or productive work hours for state employees; or
(C) address employee compensation, leave benefits, or health insurance benefits, whether or not an appropriation is required for implementation;
(5) organization means a labor or employee organization of any kind in which employees participate and which exists for the primary purpose of dealing with employers concerning grievances, labor disputes, wages, rates of pay, hours of employment, and conditions of employment;
(6) public employee means any employee of a public employer, whether or not in the classified service of the public employer, except elected or appointed officials or superintendents of schools;
(7) public employer means the state or a political subdivision of the state, including without limitation, a municipality, district, school district, regional educational attendance area, board of regents, public and quasi-public corporation, housing authority, or other authority established by law, and a person designated by the public employer to act in its interest in dealing with public employees;
(8) regional educational attendance area means an educational service area in the unorganized borough that may or may not include a military reservation, and that contains one or more public schools of grade levels K  12 or any portion of those grade levels that are to be operated under the management and control of a single regional school board;
(9) terms and conditions of employment means the hours of employment, the compensation and fringe benefits, and the employer's personnel policies affecting the working conditions of the employees; but does not mean the general policies describing the function and purposes of a public employer.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_23-40-255">
            <num>23.40.255</num>
            <heading>Applicability to political subdivisions, including school districts.</heading>
            <subsection eId="23-40-255__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>AS 23.40.070
 23.40.260 is applicable to organized boroughs and political subdivisions of the state, home rule or otherwise, unless the legislative body of the political subdivision, by ordinance or resolution, rejects having the provisions of
AS 23.40.070
 23.40.260 apply.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="23-40-255__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (a) of this section, a municipal school district or regional educational attendance area may not reject application of
AS 23.40.070
 23.40.260 to employment relations with public school employees.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_23-40-260">
            <num>23.40.260</num>
            <heading>Short title.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 23.40.260.   Short title.
AS 23.40.070
 23.40.260 may be cited as the Public Employment Relations Act.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>