<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-35/chapter-27"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-35/chapter-27"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="35.27"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-35/chapter-27/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-35/chapter-27/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-35/chapter-27/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-35/chapter-27/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_35">
        <num>35</num>
        <heading>Public Buildings, Works, and Improvements</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_35__chp_27">
          <num>27</num>
          <heading>Art Works in Public Buildings and Facilities</heading>
          <section eId="sec_35-27-010">
            <num>35.27.010</num>
            <heading>Purpose.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 35.27.010.   Purpose.
The state recognizes its responsibility to foster culture and the arts and the necessity for the viable development of its artists and craftsmen.  The legislature declares it to be a state policy that a portion of appropriations for capital expenditures be set aside for the acquisition of works of art to be used for state buildings and other public facilities.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-27-020">
            <num>35.27.020</num>
            <heading>Art requirements for public buildings and facilities.</heading>
            <subsection eId="35-27-020__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A building or facility constructed after June 30, 1975, or remodeled or renovated after June 30, 1975, shall include works of art, including but not limited to sculptures, paintings, murals or objects relating to Native art.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="35-27-020__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department, before preparing plans and specifications for buildings and facilities, shall consult with the Alaska State Council on the Arts regarding the desirability of inclusion of works of art.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="35-27-020__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>At least one percent or, in the case of a rural school facility, at least one-half of one percent of the construction cost of a building or facility approved for construction by the legislature will be reserved for the following purposes: the design, construction, mounting, and administration of works of art in a school, office building, court building, vessel of the marine highway system, or other building or facility that is subject to substantial public use.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="35-27-020__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A building or facility with an estimated construction cost of less than $250,000 is exempt from the requirements of this chapter unless inclusion of works of art in the design and construction of the building or facility is specifically authorized by the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="35-27-020__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The artist who executes these works of art shall be selected by the architect for the department with the approval of the department, after consultation with the Alaska State Council on the Arts and the principal user of the public buildings or facilities.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="35-27-020__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The artist who executes these works of art in the public schools shall be selected by the superintendent of a school district in which a public school is to be built with the approval of the school board.  Should the department find in the best interest of the state that the selection of the artist who executes these works of art by the superintendent may result in a cost overrun to the state or delay of construction, the department shall make the selection of the artist in consultation with the superintendent.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="35-27-020__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The architect, superintendent, department, and the Alaska State Council on the Arts shall encourage the use of state cultural resources in these art works and the selection of Alaska resident artists for the commission of these art works.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="35-27-020__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Alaska State Council on the Arts shall manage the relocation, disposition, and exchange of works of art acquired under this chapter as provided in
AS 44.27.050</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-27-030">
            <num>35.27.030</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="35-27-030__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>schools, office buildings, and court buildings;
(ii) other buildings which the commissioner determines are designed for substantial public use;
(iii) boats and vessels of the marine highway system;
(iv) transportation facilities which accommodate traveling passengers;
(B) excludes other transportation facilities;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="35-27-030__subsec_i__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>construction cost is that cost expended for the actual construction of the facility, exclusive of the costs of land acquisition, site investigation, design services, administrative costs, equipment purchases, and any other costs not specifically incurred within the construction contract or contracts awarded for the construction of the facility.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>