<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-29/chapter-55"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-29/chapter-55"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="29.55"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-29/chapter-55/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-29/chapter-55/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-29/chapter-55/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-29/chapter-55/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_29">
        <num>29</num>
        <heading>Municipal Government</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_29__chp_55">
          <num>55</num>
          <heading>Municipal Programs</heading>
          <section eId="sec_29-55-010">
            <num>29.55.010</num>
            <heading>Creation of local historical district commissions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 29.55.010.   Creation of local historical district commissions.
The governing body of a municipality may establish a local historical district commission or designate the planning commission or itself to serve as the historical district commission.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-55-020">
            <num>29.55.020</num>
            <heading>Establishment of historical districts.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-55-020__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to existing municipal authority providing for the preservation, protection, and maintenance of historic sites, the local historical district commission, in consultation with the Alaska Historical Commission in the Department of Natural Resources, may establish historical districts within the boundaries of the municipality.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-55-020__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A historical district shall be a reasonably compact area of historical significance in which two or more structures important in state or national history, and related by physical proximity or historical association, are located. For purposes of this subsection, structures important in state or national history means properties recommended by historical district commissions that are listed in the National Register of Historic Places or are characteristic of the Russian-American period before October 18, 1867, the early territorial period before 1930, or early Native heritage, reflecting the indigenous characteristics of Native culture in Alaska. On recommendation of the governing body of a municipality and the Alaska Historical Commission, the Department of Natural Resources may by regulation formulate additional criteria for the establishment of historical districts not inconsistent with this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-55-020__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The establishment of a historical district under this section shall be consistent with any applicable comprehensive plan for the municipality.
Article 2. Municipal Property Assessed Clean Energy and Resilience Act.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-55-100">
            <num>29.55.100</num>
            <heading>Establishment of program.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-55-100__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may establish an energy and resilience improvement assessment program under
AS 29.55.100
 29.55.165 to finance the construction, installation, or modification of permanent improvements that are fixed to new construction or existing privately owned commercial or industrial property and that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-100__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>are energy improvement projects designed to reduce energy consumption or demand, energy costs, or emissions affecting local air quality, including a product, device, or interacting group of products or devices that use energy technology to generate electricity, provide thermal energy, or regulate temperature; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-100__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>improve building resilience; resilience improvement projects include projects for seismic improvements, stormwater management, flood mitigation and protection, fire hardening, fire or wind resistance, erosion management, snow load management, microgrids for energy storage and backup power generation, water or wastewater efficiency including reuse and energy recovery, electric vehicle charging stations, retrofitting that improves the envelope, structure, or systems of the building, and any other improvement project approved by a municipality as a resilience improvement project.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-55-100__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To establish a program under
AS 29.55.100
 29.55.165, the governing body of a municipality shall take the following actions in the following order:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-100__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>adopt a resolution of intent that includes
(A) a finding that financing energy and resilience improvement projects through assessments serves a valid public purpose;
(B) a statement that the municipality intends to allow privately owned commercial or industrial property owners to make assessments to repay financing for energy and resilience improvement projects;
(C) a description of energy and resilience improvement projects that may be subject to assessments;
(D) a description of the boundaries of a region within the municipality's boundaries in which the program is available;
(E) a description of any proposed arrangements to make third-party financing available or any financing the municipality will provide for energy and resilience improvement projects; and
(F) a description of municipal debt servicing procedures for any third-party financing and assessments;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-100__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>prepare the report required under
AS 29.55.110
and provide notice of the report with the
(A) location where the report is available for public inspection;
(B) time and place for a public hearing on the proposed program; and
(C) name of the local official who administers the program and the appropriate assessor or person who collects the proposed assessments with property taxes imposed on the assessed property;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-100__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>hold a public hearing at which the public may comment on the proposed program and the report prepared under
AS 29.55.110
; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-100__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>adopt an ordinance establishing the program and the terms of the program, including each item included in the report required under
AS 29.55.110
, which may be incorporated by reference.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-55-100__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-100__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>hire and set the compensation of a program administrator and program staff; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-100__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>contract for professional services necessary to administer a program.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-55-100__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may impose fees to offset the costs of administering a program. The fees authorized under this subsection may be imposed as a</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-100__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>program application fee paid by the property owner applying to the program;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-100__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>servicing fee included in the assessment in the written contract between the municipality and the property owner; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-100__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>combination of (1) and (2) of this subsection.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-55-105">
            <num>29.55.105</num>
            <heading>Assessment.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-55-105__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality that establishes a program under
AS 29.55.100
may</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-105__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>enter into a written contract with a record owner of privately owned commercial or industrial property in a region designated under
AS 29.55.100
to impose an assessment to repay the financing of an energy or resilience improvement project on that property;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-105__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>contract with the governing body of another taxing unit to perform the duties of the municipality relating to collection of assessments imposed by the municipality under this section.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-55-105__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Financing repaid by an assessment may</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-105__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>be provided by a third party under a written contract with the municipality that authorizes the municipality to service the debt by assessment; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-105__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if authorized by municipal ordinance, be provided by the municipality.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-55-105__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An assessment under this section may repay financing for costs of an energy or resilience improvement project, including</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-105__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the cost of materials and labor necessary for the energy or resilience improvement project;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-105__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>permit fees;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-105__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>inspection fees;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-105__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>lender's fees;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-105__subsec_c__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>program application and administrative fees;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-105__subsec_c__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>energy or resilience improvement project development and engineering fees;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-105__subsec_c__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>third-party review fees, including verification review fees, under
AS 29.55.120
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-105__subsec_c__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>capitalized interest;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-105__subsec_c__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>interest reserves;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-105__subsec_c__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>escrow for prepaid property tax or insurance;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-105__subsec_c__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>capitalized extended manufacturer's warranty or maintenance agreement costs during the period of assessment; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-105__subsec_c__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>any other fees or costs that may be incurred by the property owner incident to the installation, modification, or improvement on a specific or pro rata basis, as determined by the municipality.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-55-105__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An assessment under this section may not repay financing for the costs of</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-105__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>[Repealed, § 24 ch 28, SLA 2022.]</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-105__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the purchase or installation of products or devices not permanently fixed to the privately owned commercial or industrial property; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-105__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a utility's purchase or installation of a product, device, or improvement, if the product, device, or improvement will generate electricity or provide thermal energy distributed or used outside of the assessed property; in this paragraph, utility has the meaning given in
AS 42.05.990
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-55-105__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may establish more than one region. The boundaries of each region may be separate, overlapping, or coterminous.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-55-105__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may not impose a period of assessment under this section on privately owned commercial or industrial property that exceeds 30 years or the useful life of the project that is the basis for the assessment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-55-105__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The total financing  for costs of an energy or resilience improvement project may not exceed 25 percent of the market value of the property at the time of program application or completion of the proposed energy or resilience improvement project.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-55-105__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 24 ch 28, SLA 2022.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-55-105__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An assessment under this section may repay financing for costs of a proposed energy or resilience improvement project or an energy or resilience improvement project completed within the past two years.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-55-110">
            <num>29.55.110</num>
            <heading>Report regarding assessment program.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-55-110__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The municipality shall prepare a report for a proposed program required by
AS 29.55.100
that includes</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-110__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a map showing the boundaries of each proposed region within which the program is available;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-110__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a form for a contract between the municipality and a property owner specifying the terms of
(A) assessment under the program; and
(B) financing provided by a third party or the municipality, as appropriate;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-110__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if the proposed program provides for third-party financing, a form for a contract between the municipality and the third party regarding the servicing of the debt through assessments;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-110__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a description of energy and resilience improvement projects that may qualify for assessments;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-110__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a plan for ensuring sufficient capital for third-party financing and, if appropriate, raising capital for municipal financing for energy and resilience improvement projects;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-110__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if bonds will be issued to provide capital to finance energy and resilience improvement projects as part of the program as provided by
AS 29.55.140
,
(A) a maximum aggregate annual dollar amount for municipal financing repaid by assessments under the program;
(B) if requests appear likely to exceed the authorization amount, a priority order for ranking a property owner's application for financing repaid by assessments; and
(C) a formula for calculating</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-55-110__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>the interest rate and period during which contracting owners would pay an assessment; and
(ii) the maximum amount of an assessment;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-110__subsec_i__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a method to calculate a period of assessment consistent with
AS 29.55.105</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-110__subsec_i__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a description of the application process and eligibility requirements for financing repaid by assessments under the program;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-110__subsec_i__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a method for a property owner applying to participate in the program to demonstrate the property owner's ability to fulfill financial obligations and pay assessments; the method must be based on appropriate underwriting factors, including
(A) verification that the property owner</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-55-110__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>is the legal owner of the benefited property;
(ii) is current on mortgage and property tax payments; and
(iii) is not insolvent or in bankruptcy proceedings; and
(B) an appropriate ratio between the amount of the assessment and the market value of the property;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-110__subsec_i__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an explanation of the manner in which the municipality shall assess the property and collect assessments;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-110__subsec_i__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the lender notice requirement under
AS 29.55.115
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-110__subsec_i__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the review requirement under
AS 29.55.120
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-110__subsec_i__subsec_13">
                <num>(13)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a description of marketing and participant education services provided by the municipality for the program;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-110__subsec_i__subsec_14">
                <num>(14)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a description of quality assurance and antifraud measures instituted by the municipality for the program and the consequence or penalty prescribed by the municipality for a property owner who participates in the program but does not complete an energy or resilience improvement project as proposed; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-110__subsec_i__subsec_15">
                <num>(15)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a description of the insurance requirements, including a requirement that the property owner have insurance against damage to the energy or resilience improvement project for the life of the assessment.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-55-110__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The municipality shall make the report available for public inspection</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-110__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>on the Internet website of the municipality; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-110__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>at the primary governing offices of the municipality.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-55-115">
            <num>29.55.115</num>
            <heading>Notice to mortgage holder required for participation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 29.55.115.   Notice to mortgage holder required for participation.
Before a municipality may enter into a written contract with a record owner of property to impose an assessment to repay the financing of an energy or resilience improvement project under
AS 29.55.100
, the property owner shall
(1) give each holder of a mortgage lien on the property at least 30 days' written notice of the intention of the property owner to participate in a program under
AS 29.55.100
; and
(2) obtain written consent from each holder of a mortgage lien on the property.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-55-120">
            <num>29.55.120</num>
            <heading>Review required.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 29.55.120.   Review required.
The record owner of property on which an assessment is imposed under
AS 29.55.105
shall obtain
(1) for each proposed energy or resilience improvement project,
(A) a review of the energy, emissions, or resilience baseline conditions, as appropriate; and
(B) the projected reduction in energy costs, energy consumption or demand, or emissions affecting local air quality, or increase in resilience, as appropriate; and
(2) for each completed energy or resilience improvement project, verification that the energy or resilience improvement project was properly completed and is operating as intended.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-55-125">
            <num>29.55.125</num>
            <heading>Direct acquisition by owner.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 29.55.125.   Direct acquisition by owner.
The proposed arrangements for financing an energy or resilience improvement project may authorize the property owner to
(1) purchase directly the related equipment and materials for the energy or resilience improvement project; and
(2) contract directly, including through lease, a power purchase agreement, or other service contract, for the energy or resilience improvement project.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-55-130">
            <num>29.55.130</num>
            <heading>Recording of notice of assessment.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-55-130__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality that authorizes financing through assessments under
AS 29.55.105
shall file written notice of each assessment in the property records of the recording district in which the property is located.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-55-130__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The notice under (a) of this section must contain</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-130__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the amount of the assessment;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-130__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the legal description of the property;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-130__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name of each property owner; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-130__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a reference to the statutory assessment lien provided under
AS 29.55.135
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-55-135">
            <num>29.55.135</num>
            <heading>Lien.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-55-135__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Assessments under
AS 29.55.105
and any interest or penalties on the assessments are liens on the property assessed and are prior and paramount to all liens except municipal tax liens and special assessments. Assessment liens may be enforced as provided in
AS 29.45.320
 29.45.470 for enforcement of property tax liens.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-55-135__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Assessment liens run with the land, and that portion of the assessment under the assessment contract that has not yet become due is not eliminated by foreclosure of a property tax lien or a lien for an assessment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-55-135__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Penalties and interest may be added to delinquent installments of the assessments in the same manner as provided in
AS 29.45.250
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-55-135__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may recover costs and expenses, including attorney fees, in a suit to collect a delinquent installment of an assessment in the same manner as in a suit to collect a delinquent property tax.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-55-140">
            <num>29.55.140</num>
            <heading>Bonds or notes.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-55-140__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may issue bonds or notes to finance energy and resilience improvement projects subject to assessment under
AS 29.55.105
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-55-140__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Bonds or notes issued under this section may not be general obligations of the municipality. The bonds or notes must be secured by one or more of the following, as provided by the governing body of the municipality in the resolution or ordinance approving the bonds or notes:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-140__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>payments of assessments on benefited property in one or more specified regions designated under
AS 29.55.100
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-140__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>reserves established by the municipality from grants, bonds, or net proceeds or other lawfully available funds;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-140__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>municipal bond insurance, lines of credit, public or private guaranties, standby bond purchase agreements, collateral assignments, mortgages, or any other available means of providing credit support or liquidity; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-140__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>any other funds lawfully available for purposes consistent with
AS 29.55.100
 29.55.165.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-55-140__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipal pledge of assessments, funds, or contractual rights in connection with the issuance of bonds or notes by the municipality under this section is a first lien on the assessments, funds, or contractual rights pledged in favor of the person to whom the pledge is given, without further action by the municipality. The lien is valid and binding against any other person, with or without notice.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-55-140__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Bonds or notes issued under this section must further one or more of the following essential public and governmental purposes:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-140__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>improvement of the reliability of local electrical systems;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-140__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>reduction of energy costs;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-140__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>reduction of energy demand on local utilities;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-140__subsec_d__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>reduction of emissions affecting local air quality;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-140__subsec_d__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>economic stimulation and development;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-140__subsec_d__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>enhancement of property values;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-140__subsec_d__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>enhancement of employment opportunities;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-55-140__subsec_d__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>improvement of building resilience.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-55-145">
            <num>29.55.145</num>
            <heading>Joint implementation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 29.55.145.   Joint implementation.
A municipality may enter into an agreement with
(1) a third party to administer a program under
AS 29.55.100
;
(2) one or more municipalities to implement or administer jointly a program under
AS 29.55.100
; if two or more municipalities jointly implement a program, a single public hearing held jointly by the cooperating municipalities is sufficient to satisfy the requirement of
AS 29.55.100
(b)(3).</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-55-150">
            <num>29.55.150</num>
            <heading>Prohibited acts.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 29.55.150.   Prohibited acts.
A municipality that establishes a region under
AS 29.55.100
may not make the issuance of a permit, license, or other authorization from the municipality to a person who owns property in the region contingent on the person entering into a written contract to repay the financing of an energy or resilience improvement project through assessments under
AS 29.55.105
, or otherwise compel a person who owns property in the region to enter into a written contract to repay the financing of an energy or resilience improvement project through assessments under
AS 29.55.105
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-55-155">
            <num>29.55.155</num>
            <heading>Application.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 29.55.155.   Application.
AS 29.55.100
 29.55.165 apply to home rule and general law municipalities.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-55-160">
            <num>29.55.160</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 29.55.160.   Definitions.
In
AS 29.55.100
 29.55.165,
(1) finance and financing include refinancing an existing project;
(2) mortgage has the meaning given in
AS 13.06.050
;
(3) program means a program established under
AS 29.55.100
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-55-165">
            <num>29.55.165</num>
            <heading>Short title.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 29.55.165.   Short title.
AS 29.55.100
 29.55.165 may be cited as the Municipal Property Assessed Clean Energy and Resilience Act.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>