<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-19/chapter-65"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-19/chapter-65"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="19.65"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-19/chapter-65/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-19/chapter-65/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-19/chapter-65/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-19/chapter-65/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_19">
        <num>19</num>
        <heading>Highways and Ferries</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_19__chp_65">
          <num>65</num>
          <heading>Alaska Marine Highway System</heading>
          <section eId="sec_19-65-011">
            <num>19.65.011</num>
            <heading>Short-term and comprehensive long-range plans.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.65.011.   Short-term and comprehensive long-range plans.
The Department of Transportation and Public Facilities, in consultation with the Alaska Marine Highway Operations Board, shall prepare a short-term plan and a comprehensive long-range plan for the development and improvement of the Alaska marine highway system and shall, in consultation with the Alaska Marine Highway Operations Board, revise and update the short-term plan annually and the comprehensive long-range plan at least every five years. The short-term plan must describe the means by which effective and efficient progress toward priorities and goals defined in the comprehensive long-range plan will be attained, must include recommendations for the state operating and capital budgets, and must include a description of skill or competency gaps in the membership of the Alaska Marine Highway Operations Board. The comprehensive long-range plan must include priorities and goals for the Alaska marine highway system and a proposed strategic maintenance and vessel replacement plan and may recommend performance measures, including output, efficiency, and effectiveness measures. The department shall submit both the short-term and the comprehensive long-range plans and revisions and updates of the plans to the legislature and the governor and make the plans available to the public.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-65-020">
            <num>19.65.020</num>
            <heading>Naming of vessel or facility.</heading>
            <subsection eId="19-65-020__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A vessel or facility of the Alaska marine highway system constructed or acquired by the Department of Transportation and Public Facilities under this chapter may be given a name only by law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-65-020__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A maritime vessel shall bear the name of an Alaska glacier.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-65-020__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A vessel used principally on the inland waterways of the state shall bear the name of a historical vessel which used the rivers of the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-65-020__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The new maritime vessel to be delivered to the Alaska marine highway system in 1998 is named the Motor Vessel Kennicott.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-65-020__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Motor Vessel Fairweather and the Motor Vessel Chenega are authorized names for state ferries first operating as part of the Alaska marine highway system on or after August 8, 2002. The commissioner of transportation and public facilities shall select between the names for the one most appropriate to the route served by the ferry and shall publicly announce the selection.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-65-020__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Motor Vessel Lituya is the authorized name for the state ferry first operating as part of the Alaska marine highway system to serve between Metlakatla and Ketchikan on or after August 9, 2003.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-65-020__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Motor Vessel Tazlina and the Motor Vessel Hubbard are authorized names for the state ferries first entering Alaska marine highway system service on or after 2017.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-65-030">
            <num>19.65.030</num>
            <heading>Acquisition and maintenance of ferry terminal facilities.</heading>
            <subsection eId="19-65-030__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall construct, purchase, or lease ferry terminal facilities at locations it selects for the loading and unloading of passengers, and vehicles under their own power, on and off ferries. The department shall repair and maintain these facilities. Construction and purchasing under this subsection are governed by
AS 36.30
(State Procurement Code).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-65-030__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may connect ferry terminal facilities with local highway systems.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-65-030__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may adopt regulations governing the use of ferry terminal facilities by the public that it considers necessary and proper in the public interest. The department may charge a fee for the use of ferry terminal facilities, whether the use is under a permit or otherwise, and whether it is by one or more individuals.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-65-030__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may construct a ferry terminal facility upon obtaining the approval of the department as to its location. A ferry terminal facility constructed by a person other than the department is subject to reasonable regulations governing its use that the department considers necessary and proper in the public interest.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-65-030__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A ferry terminal facility may not be constructed without the approval of the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-65-030__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A ferry terminal facility in existence and serving the public on January 1, 1959, is not affected by this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-65-030__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="19-65-030__subsec_g__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>department means the Department of Transportation and Public Facilities;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="19-65-030__subsec_g__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>ferry means a vessel used in the common carriage of passengers and self-propelled vehicles in intrastate commerce.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-65-035">
            <num>19.65.035</num>
            <heading>Transportation of members of the Alaska organized militia.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.65.035.   Transportation of members of the Alaska organized militia.
To the extent that space is available, the commissioner of transportation and public facilities shall provide free transportation on vessels of the Alaska marine highway system for a member of the Alaska National Guard, the Alaska Naval Militia, or the Alaska State Defense Force who is en route to or from drill, training, or other official militia activities.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-65-050">
            <num>19.65.050</num>
            <heading>Legislative findings, purpose, and intent.</heading>
            <subsection eId="19-65-050__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The legislature finds that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="19-65-050__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Alaska marine highway system is an essential part of the state transportation system, and that it warrants continued and predictable state support;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="19-65-050__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>many communities' economies are dependent on a steady and stable marine highway system service level;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="19-65-050__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the state's tourism industry is greatly enhanced by a dependable marine highway transportation network; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="19-65-050__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>efficient and prudent management of the system will benefit the state's economy and foster economic development.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-65-050__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>It is the purpose of
AS 19.65.050
 19.65.100 to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="19-65-050__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>enable the Alaska marine highway system to manage and operate in a manner that will enhance performance and accountability by allowing the system to account for and spend its generated revenue;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="19-65-050__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide the management tools necessary to efficiently operate the Alaska marine highway system;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="19-65-050__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>within constitutional constraints, provide for a predictable funding base for system operations; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="19-65-050__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide for predictability and stability in the service level furnished to communities served by the system.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-65-050__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>It is the intent of
AS 19.65.050
 19.65.100 to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="19-65-050__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>encourage prudent administration through cost management and accurate budgeting by managers of the Alaska marine highway system;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="19-65-050__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>increase revenue from the operation of the system consistent with the public interest, increase service consistent with sound fiscal policy, and assist the prudent management and operation of the system; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="19-65-050__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>achieve stability in the level of service communities can anticipate through accurate planning and scheduling.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-65-060">
            <num>19.65.060</num>
            <heading>Alaska marine highway system fund.</heading>
            <subsection eId="19-65-060__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Alaska marine highway system fund is established as a separate fund in the state treasury, into which shall be deposited</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="19-65-060__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the gross revenue of the Alaska marine highway system;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="19-65-060__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>money that is appropriated to the Alaska marine highway system fund by the legislature in an amount that is consistent from year to year and is the amount necessary, after consideration of gross revenue, to provide stable services to the public consistent with the provisions of
AS 19.65.050</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="19-65-060__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>any other money that is appropriated to the Alaska marine highway system fund by the legislature, which appropriations are not one-year appropriations and the balances of which do not lapse under
AS 37.25.010
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-65-060__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing in this chapter exempts money deposited into the Alaska marine highway system fund from the requirements of
AS 37.07
(Executive Budget Act) or dedicates that money for a specific purpose.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-65-070">
            <num>19.65.070</num>
            <heading>Revenue accounting.</heading>
            <subsection eId="19-65-070__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Alaska marine highway system shall account for and remit to the Department of Revenue in accordance with
AS 37.10.050
all gross revenue generated from the operation of the Alaska marine highway system during each annual operating cycle. The money shall then be deposited in the Alaska marine highway system fund.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-65-070__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Alaska marine highway system shall prepare a written report, no later than the 10th day of each regular legislative session, regarding the previous annual operating cycle and notify the legislature that the report is available. The report must identify</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="19-65-070__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>gross revenue generated during the previous annual operating cycle;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="19-65-070__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>gross revenue generated during the current annual operating cycle and an estimate of gross revenue for the remainder of the current annual operating cycle;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="19-65-070__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>projections of the gross revenue to be generated during the next annual operating cycle; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="19-65-070__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the difference between previous gross revenue estimates prepared under this section and the revenues actually generated.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-65-070__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Revenue shall prepare a written report, no later than the 10th legislative day of each regular legislative session, regarding the earnings on gross revenue of the Alaska marine highway system that was deposited into the Alaska marine highway system fund during the prior fiscal year and projected earnings on gross revenue of the Alaska marine highway system that is projected to be deposited into the Alaska marine highway system fund for the current fiscal year and the next fiscal year. The Department of Revenue shall notify the legislature that the report is available.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-65-080">
            <num>19.65.080</num>
            <heading>Annual appropriation.</heading>
            <subsection eId="19-65-080__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Commencing with appropriations for the fiscal year that begins July 1, 1991, on an annual basis and under
AS 37.07
(Executive Budget Act), the legislature may appropriate amounts from the Alaska marine highway system fund to the Alaska marine highway system.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-65-080__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Transportation and Public Facilities may request the legislature to appropriate money from the Alaska marine highway system fund to the marine highway system for capital improvements, if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="19-65-080__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the appropriation under (a) of this section has been made;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="19-65-080__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the amount in the fund, without regard to the appropriation under (a) of this section, exceeds the total of gross revenue deposited in the fund and the general fund appropriations under
AS 19.65.060</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="19-65-080__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the amount requested for appropriation under this subsection does not exceed 50 percent of the balance remaining after the appropriation for annual management and operations is made under (a) of this section.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-65-080__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The unexpended and unobligated balance of money appropriated from the Alaska marine highway system fund lapses into the Alaska marine highway system fund at the end of the fiscal year for which it was appropriated.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-65-100">
            <num>19.65.100</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.65.100.   Definitions.
In
AS 19.65.050
 19.65.100,
(1) annual operating cycle means the annual state fiscal year beginning on July 1 and ending at midnight on the following June 30;
(2) gross revenue means all money, except money refunded to ticket holders and others for unused services, that is generated from the operation of the Alaska marine highway system, including that derived from vessel operations and uses of Alaska marine highway system facilities.
Article 3. Alaska Marine Highway Operations Board.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-65-110">
            <num>19.65.110</num>
            <heading>Alaska Marine Highway Operations Board.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.65.110.   Alaska Marine Highway Operations Board.
There is established in the Department of Transportation and Public Facilities the Alaska Marine Highway Operations Board.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-65-120">
            <num>19.65.120</num>
            <heading>Board composition.</heading>
            <subsection eId="19-65-120__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board is composed of the deputy commissioner of transportation and public facilities assigned to the Alaska marine highway system and the following eight public members, each of whom must be a resident of the state:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="19-65-120__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>one representative, who may be retired, of a recognized union that represents employees of the Alaska marine highway system, appointed by the governor;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="19-65-120__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>one representative of an Alaska Native organization or tribe who is from a community served by the Alaska marine highway system, appointed by the governor;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="19-65-120__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>six public members
(A) who collectively have experience in enterprise, architecture, business operations, financial management, risk management, logistics, supply chain management, engineering, project management and controls, marine operations, strategy, regulatory compliance, ship maintenance, construction, and repair, quality management, continuous improvement, sales, marketing, communications, customer interface, or experience management;
(B) two of whom are appointed by the governor, two of whom are appointed by the speaker of the house of representatives and who serve at the pleasure of the speaker of the house of representatives, and two of whom are appointed by the president of the senate and who serve at the pleasure of the president of the senate.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-65-120__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 11 ch 20 SLA 2021.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-65-120__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The members of the board, except for the deputy commissioner of transportation and public facilities, shall serve staggered six-year terms. If a vacancy arises on the board, the governor, the president of the senate, or the speaker of the house of representatives, as applicable, shall, within 30 days after the vacancy arises, appoint a person to serve the balance of the unexpired term. A person appointed to fill the balance of an unexpired term shall serve on the board from the date of appointment until the expiration of the term.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-65-120__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A majority of the membership of the board may remove a member, except for the deputy commissioner of transportation and public facilities, if that member misses more than two meetings in a calendar year and has not been previously excused.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-65-130">
            <num>19.65.130</num>
            <heading>Officers and quorum.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.65.130.   Officers and quorum.
The members of the board shall select a chair and a vice-chair from among the members of the board each year. The vice-chair presides over meetings in the absence of the chair. A majority of the members of the board constitutes a quorum. A vacancy in the board does not impair the right of a quorum to exercise all the powers and perform all the duties of the board.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-65-140">
            <num>19.65.140</num>
            <heading>Meetings.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.65.140.   Meetings.
The board shall meet at least four times each year. Meetings may be called by the chair or by a majority of the members of the board. At least one meeting each year must be attended by the board members in person, but all other meetings may be conducted by teleconference. All meetings are open to the public unless an executive session is called based on the criteria in
AS 44.62.310
(b).</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-65-150">
            <num>19.65.150</num>
            <heading>Per diem and expenses.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.65.150.   Per diem and expenses.
Members of the board do not receive a salary, but are entitled to per diem and travel expenses authorized for boards and commissions under
AS 39.20.180
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-65-160">
            <num>19.65.160</num>
            <heading>Records.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.65.160.   Records.
Records of the board are subject to inspection and copying under
AS 40.25.110
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-65-170">
            <num>19.65.170</num>
            <heading>Legal assistance.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.65.170.   Legal assistance.
The Department of Law shall provide all legal services for the board.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-65-180">
            <num>19.65.180</num>
            <heading>Powers, duties, and functions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="19-65-180__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After the commissioner of transportation and public facilities has considered one or more candidates for the position of director or deputy commissioner of the Alaska marine highway system, the commissioner shall confer with the board regarding that candidate or those candidates before making an appointment to that position. The selection of those candidates shall be without regard to political affiliation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-65-180__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board may establish volunteer regional advisory committees. The purpose of the advisory committees is to provide recommendations to the board regarding concerns from the region of the members who constitute the advisory committee.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-65-180__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board may issue reports and recommendations and shall, in cooperation with the Department of Transportation and Public Facilities, prepare and submit to the department and the governor for review a strategic plan that includes the mission, core values, objectives, initiatives, and performance goals of the Alaska marine highway system.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-65-180__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board may receive information from the department as the board considers necessary to carry out its duties, and the department shall provide information requested by the board in a timely and responsive manner.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-65-180__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board shall provide advice and recommendations to the commissioner of transportation and public facilities concerning the operation and management of the Alaska marine highway system, including advice and recommendations regarding business to enhance revenue and reduce costs, personnel management, commercial service options, ship maintenance, construction, and repair, fleet strategy, reliability, and regulatory compliance, and other service objectives.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-65-180__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the board determines that the Alaska marine highway system has deviated from a plan, policy, or procedure described in the short-term plan or comprehensive long-range plan prepared under
AS 19.65.011
, the board may prepare a report recommending corrective action. The board shall submit an electronic report prepared under this subsection to the legislature and the governor and shall make the report available to the public.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-65-180__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board may establish a task force that includes members who are not members of the board and that is tasked with investigating matters relevant to the Alaska marine highway system and reporting to the board. Members of a task force established under this subsection are not entitled to receive a salary, per diem, or travel expenses.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-65-180__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board shall annually submit recommendations to the Department of Transportation and Public Facilities regarding the preparation of the statewide transportation improvement program.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-65-190">
            <num>19.65.190</num>
            <heading>Staff.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.65.190.   Staff.
The department shall provide staff for the board.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-65-195">
            <num>19.65.195</num>
            <heading>Definition.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.65.195.   Definition.
In
AS 19.65.110
 19.65.195, board means the Alaska Marine Highway Operations Board.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>