<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-41/chapter-21"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-41/chapter-21"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="41.21"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-41/chapter-21/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-41/chapter-21/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-41/chapter-21/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-41/chapter-21/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_41">
        <num>41</num>
        <heading>Public Resources</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_41__chp_21">
          <num>21</num>
          <heading>Parks and Recreational Facilities</heading>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-010">
            <num>41.21.010</num>
            <heading>Purpose.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.010.   Purpose.
It is the purpose of
AS 41.21.010
 41.21.040 to foster the growth and development of a system of parks and recreational facilities and opportunities in the state, for the general health, welfare, education, and enjoyment of its citizens and for the attraction of visitors to the state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-020">
            <num>41.21.020</num>
            <heading>Duties and powers of Department of Natural Resources; limitations.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-020__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-020__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>develop a continuing plan for the conservation and maximum use in the public interest of the scenic, historic, archaeologic, scientific, biological, and recreational resources of the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-020__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>plan for and develop a system of state parks and recreational facilities, to be established as the legislature authorizes and directs;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-020__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>acquire by gift, purchase, or transfer from state or federal agencies, or from individuals, corporations, partnerships, or associations, land necessary, suitable, and proper for roadside, picnic, recreational, or park purposes;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-020__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>develop, manage, and maintain state parks and recreational areas;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-020__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide for the acquisition, care, management, supervision, improvement, development, extension, and maintenance of public recreational land, and make necessary arrangements, contracts, or commitments for the improvement and development of land acquired under
AS 41.21.010
 41.21.040; contracting for improvement and development under this paragraph is governed by
AS 36.30
(State Procurement Code);</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-020__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>adopt, in accordance with this section and
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act), regulations governing the use and designating incompatible uses within the boundaries of state park and recreational areas to protect the property and to preserve the peace;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-020__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>cooperate with the United States and its agencies and local subdivisions of the state to secure the effective supervision, improvement, development, extension, and maintenance of state parks, state monuments, state historical areas, and state recreational areas and secure agreements or contracts for the purpose of
AS 41.21.010
 41.21.040;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-020__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>encourage the organization of state public park and recreational activities in the local political subdivisions of the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-020__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide for consulting service designed to develop local park and recreation facilities and programs;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-020__subsec_a__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide clearinghouse services for other state agencies concerned with park and recreation matters;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-020__subsec_a__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>perform other duties as are prescribed by executive order or by law;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-020__subsec_a__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>maintain memorials to Alaska veterans located in state parks;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-020__subsec_a__subsec_13">
                <num>(13)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>adopt, in accordance with
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act), regulations governing the use of the Chena River State Recreation Area and designating incompatible uses within the boundaries of the Chena River State Recreation Area in accordance with
AS 41.21.490
; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-020__subsec_a__subsec_14">
                <num>(14)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>annually, by the first day of each regular session of the legislature, submit a report to the legislature on each designation of an incompatible use under this chapter, or other action, that prohibits or restricts a traditional means of access in or to a park, area, or preserve established under this chapter for a traditional recreational activity on or within the park, area, or preserve; for each prohibition or restriction, the report must state reasons for the designation of incompatibility or prohibition or restriction of a traditional means of access, the specific area of the prohibition or restriction, and the time period during which the incompatibility or prohibition or restriction is expected to exist; in this paragraph,
(A) traditional means of access means those types of transportation on, to, or in the state land, water, or land and water, for which a popular pattern of use has developed; the term includes general or commercial aviation, ballooning, motorized and nonmotorized boating, snowmachining, operation of all-terrain vehicles, mushing, use of pack animals, skiing, snowshoeing, and walking;
(B) traditional recreational activity means those personal or commercial types of activities that people may use for sport, exercise, subsistence, or personal enjoyment, including hunting, fishing, trapping, or gathering, and that have historically been conducted as part of an individual, family, or community life pattern on or in the state land, water, or land and water.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-020__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In adopting regulations under (a)(6) of this section, the department shall consider whether the use of dogs, horses, and other animals for packing gear, pulling sleds, or for other recreational use is a compatible use within a state park or recreational area.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-020__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may accept cash and other donations from public or private sources to assist and support the department in carrying out the purposes of this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-020__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (a)(3) of this section, the department may not manage as part of a park, area, or preserve established under
AS 41.21.110
 41.21.630, land, water, or land and water that is not within the boundaries, as designated by the legislature, of the park, area, or preserve.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-020__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except for reasons which create an immediate threat to public safety or as otherwise provided in
AS 41.21.110
 41.21.630, the department may not close or restrict traditional access to land, water, or land and water, managed under this chapter unless the closure or restriction (1) is limited to a period of not more than 90 days in a calendar year, or (2) is submitted to the legislature for approval at the next regular session of the legislature. A closure or restriction under (1) of this subsection may not be repeated in the subsequent calendar year unless the closure or restriction is approved by the legislature under (2) of this subsection. If the legislature fails to approve a closure or restriction under (2) of this subsection by the last day of that regular session, the closure or restriction ends and cannot be enforced after the last day of that regular session.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-022">
            <num>41.21.022</num>
            <heading>Discharge of firearms.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.022.   Discharge of firearms.
The discharge of firearms during lawful hunting, trapping, and fishing is permitted within the boundaries of: (1) Caines Head State Recreation Area; (2) Chena River State Recreation Area; (3) Chugach State Park; (4) Denali State Park; (5) Kachemak Bay State Park; (6) Kachemak Bay State Wilderness Park; (7) Marine Parks established in
AS 41.21.300
  41.21.306; (8) Quartz Lake State Recreation Area; and (9) Wood-Tikchik State Park, except that all or part of a state park, marine park, wildlife preserve, or recreation area may be closed to the discharge of firearms by regulations adopted by the department for purposes of public safety or, with the concurrence of the Board of Game, for limited areas of Chugach State Park for public display of local wildlife under
AS 41.21.121
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-024">
            <num>41.21.024</num>
            <heading>Easements and rights-of-way for access to private land.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.024.   Easements and rights-of-way for access to private land.
The department may grant a public easement or public right-of-way within a state park unit for access to private property if the commissioner determines that the easement or right-of-way
(1) will not unduly affect park resources; and
(2) is in the public interest.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-025">
            <num>41.21.025</num>
            <heading>Zoning of private land within state parks.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-025__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may adopt, under
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act), zoning regulations governing private property within the boundaries of state parks established under this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-025__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Land patented to or under interim conveyance to a regional or village Native corporation under 43 U.S.C. 1601 et seq. (Alaska Native Claims Settlement Act) that falls within a state park boundary is subject to the zoning regulations provided for under (a) of this section only if the affected regional or village Native corporation consents to or fails to reject the zoning regulations within 60 days from the date they are submitted to the affected corporation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-025__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Uses existing on June 25, 1976, are not affected by zoning regulations adopted after June 25, 1976.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-026">
            <num>41.21.026</num>
            <heading>Fees for the use of state park system facilities.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-026__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (b) of this section, the department may charge or collect a fee for</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-026__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>rental of public use cabins or other overnight lodgings;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-026__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>overnight use of a developed campsite;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-026__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>special park use permits;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-026__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>competitive and exclusive commercial use permits;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-026__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>noncompetitive and nonexclusive commercial use permits;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-026__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>use of a sewage holding tank dump station;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-026__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>admission to or guided tours of visitor centers and historic sites;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-026__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>use of an improved boat ramp in a park facility developed principally for boat launching;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-026__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>sale of firewood;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-026__subsec_a__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>use of a developed facility that has developed parking and rest rooms; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-026__subsec_a__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>presentation or attendance at programs related to natural or cultural history, outdoor skills or education, or other topics concerned with public use, enjoyment, or understanding of parks.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-026__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may not charge or collect a fee for an ordinary use of a park unit or the use of a restroom in a park unit.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-026__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall establish the fees that may be charged or collected under (a) of this section by regulation. Before setting the fees, the department shall consider at public hearings</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-026__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the cost to the state of operating the facility or managing the activity;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-026__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the normal fees charged for similar facilities or activities by governmental and nongovernmental entities;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-026__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the cost of administering a fee collection program for the facility or activity; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-026__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the public interest.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-026__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall issue free of charge to disabled veterans of this country an annual state park developed campsite permit. The permit shall allow a disabled veteran to use a state park developed campsite for personal recreation use without a charge or fee under (a)(2) of this section. While utilizing a developed campsite without charge under this subsection, the disabled veteran shall comply with all other statutes or regulations pertaining to the use of the developed campsite. The department shall provide a form for use by a disabled veteran when applying for a permit under this section. Not later than February 1 of each year, the department shall prepare a report on the number of permits issued to disabled veterans under this subsection during the previous calendar year and notify the legislature that the report is available.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-026__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, developed campsite means a campsite having access to the following public facilities:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-026__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>restrooms;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-026__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a picnic table;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-026__subsec_e__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an outdoor cooking facility; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-026__subsec_e__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an approved water source.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-026__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to the activities, services, and products for which the department may charge or collect a fee under (a) of this section, the department may sell informational, educational, or promotional merchandise. The department shall price merchandise sold under this subsection in a manner that ensures a reasonable monetary return to the state. To the extent practicable, the department shall sell only merchandise produced or manufactured, including printing, screen printing, and embroidery, in the United States that, subject to
AS 36.30
, is procured from either an Alaska bidder or a person that employs prisoners under
AS 33.30.191
(b).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-027">
            <num>41.21.027</num>
            <heading>Concession contracts in the state park system.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-027__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subject to the restrictions in this section, the state may enter into concession contracts under
AS 36
to provide services or construct facilities in a park unit.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-027__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The state may not enter into a concession contract under (a) of this section if the proposed contract involves estimated annual gross receipts of more than $100,000, construction of facilities, a term longer than four years, or the provision of services other than those normally provided at similar facilities managed by the state, unless the commissioner finds that the proposed concession contract</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-027__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>will implement the purposes of the park unit and is authorized by the park management plan, if any, that applies to the park unit;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-027__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>will enhance public use and enjoyment of the park unit while maintaining a high quality environment and the opportunity for high quality recreational experiences;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-027__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>will provide services or facilities that are not feasible or affordable for the state to provide directly;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-027__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>will not create unacceptable adverse environmental effects;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-027__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is based on a need and desire of the public;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-027__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>recognizes and accommodates, at no cost, ordinary uses in a park unit;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-027__subsec_b__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>requires the contractor to hire residents of the state, to the extent available and qualified, when hiring persons to work in the park under the contract;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-027__subsec_b__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provides the state with a fair and equitable portion, in money or services, of the contractor's receipts from the provision of the service or the operation of the facility;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-027__subsec_b__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provides that the department retains control over the level of fees and the design and appearance of any facility to be constructed;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-027__subsec_b__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>encourages the contractor to accommodate visitors with special circumstances, including persons with disabilities, senior citizens, and school children; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-027__subsec_b__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provides that the contract may be terminated if the contractor fails to fulfill the requirements of this section or the contract.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-027__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before bids or proposals are sought or contract negotiations begun for a concession contract under (b) of this section, the commissioner shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-027__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>make a preliminary inquiry at the local level to identify community concerns;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-027__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if it is appropriate to proceed further, make a preliminary decision that includes the findings required by (b) of this section and
(A) an assessment of existing visitor uses that may be affected by the activities of the contractor;
(B) an assessment of the potential conflicts or significant effects on park wildlife, water, scenic values, or other resources;
(C) an identification of the types of services or goods that the contractor is to provide;
(D) the terms and conditions of the contract;
(E) a determination of whether the contract activity would be more appropriately located on land outside of the park or on private land within the park; and
(F) the views and comments of the park advisory board, when one exists, for the park unit in which the activity is being considered;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-027__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>after making a preliminary decision under (2) of this subsection,
(A) seek public comment on the preliminary decision through reasonable public notice and, if facilities may be built under the concession contract, conduct public hearings;
(B) after considering the public comment obtained under this paragraph, issue a final decision on whether or not the state will proceed into a concession contract award process.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-027__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall provide for public review and comment before a concession contract under this section is renewed or extended.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-027__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner may adopt regulations to implement this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-027__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who enters into a concession contract with the state under this section may not charge or collect a fee for an ordinary use of a park unit or for the use of a restroom in a park unit.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-027__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>With the exception of guided tours and noncompetitive commercial use permits, concessions or commercial activities are not permitted within the Alaska Chilkat Bald Eagle Preserve.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-028">
            <num>41.21.028</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.028.   Definitions.
In
AS 41.21.026
 41.21.028,
(1) ordinary use means a use that is not generally associated with developed facilities, including fishing, hunting, walking, swimming in a natural body of water, picnicking, or automobile parking associated with another ordinary use;
(2) park unit means a unit of the state park system.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-030">
            <num>41.21.030</num>
            <heading>Disposition of funds.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-030__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>All money received from the operation of parks and recreational facilities, including money from concessions, rentals, or donations, shall be deposited in the general fund of the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-030__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 28 ch 90 SLA 1991.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-030__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In (a) of this section, money from concessions means, for a concession contract under
AS 41.21.027
, the consideration received by the state from the contract.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-040">
            <num>41.21.040</num>
            <heading>Division within department.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.040.   Division within department.
The commissioner may establish within the department a separate division to perform the functions relative to parks and recreational facilities specified in
AS 41.21.010
 41.21.040 and related or additional functions as are otherwise assigned to the department by law.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-110">
            <num>41.21.110</num>
            <heading>Purpose ofAS 41.21.110 41.21.113.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.110.   Purpose of
AS 41.21.110
 41.21.113.
The purpose of
AS 41.21.110
 41.21.113 is to empower the governor to restrict state-owned land and water described in
AS 41.21.111
to use as a state park.  Under
AS 38.05.300
, state land, water, or land and water containing more than 640 acres may be closed to multiple purpose use only by act of the legislature.  Because the area described in
AS 41.21.111
exceeds 640 acres,
AS 41.21.110
 41.21.113 are intended to provide for the closing of the described land and water to multiple purpose use in conformity with
AS 38.05.300
and its subsequent designation as a special purpose site in accordance with art. VIII, § 7, of the Constitution of the State of Alaska.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-111">
            <num>41.21.111</num>
            <heading>Authority to designate Chilkat State Park.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.111.   Authority to designate Chilkat State Park.
The governor may designate by proclamation the state-owned land and water and all that acquired in the future by the state, lying within the parcels described in this section, as the Chilkat State Park. The proclamation may include the entire area or portions of the area at different times, shall reserve the areas included from all uses incompatible with their primary function as public recreation land and water, and shall assign them to the department for control, development, and maintenance. Land covered by
AS 41.21.110
 41.21.113 has a total acreage of 6,056.30 acres, including approximately 610 acres of federal land, and is described as follows:
(1) Township 31 South, Range 60 East, Copper River Meridian
U.S.S. 1599: the portions of Sections 6-8 known as Battery Point Light House Reserve;
(2) Township 31 South, Range 59 East, Copper River Meridian
Section 1, excluding the portions of Lots 2 and 3 within the Chilkoot Inlet Alaska Subdivision
Section 12: NW1/4, NE1/4, SE1/4
Township 31 South, Range 60 East, Copper River Meridian
Section 6: Lots 1-3
Section 7: Lots 1-7
Section 8: Lot 1
Sections 17 and 18
Section 19: NE1/4NW1/4, N1/2NE1/4;
(3) Township 31 South, Range 60 East, Copper River Meridian
Section 30: Lots 8 and 9
Section 31
Section 32: SW1/4, W1/2NW1/4SE1/4,
W1/2SE1/4NW1/4SE1/4, Lots 9  16 including
W1/2SW1/4SE1/4SE1/4;
(4) Township 32 South, Range 60 East, Copper River Meridian
Section 5: W1/2, W1/2SE1/4
Sections 6-9, 15-17, 21 and 22, excluding Tongass National Forest; and
(5) the following particularly described parcels:
(A) approximately 6.49 acres in U.S. Survey 1243, Haines Recording District, described as: begin on the South line of said survey South 88 degrees 31 minutes 45 seconds East 1950.84 feet from Southwest corner (corner 4 M.C.) of said survey, said point being the Southeast corner of the tract in said survey excepted in the decree in Case No. 68-328 of the Superior Court at Juneau, in which the distance is recited as being 29.55 chains (1950.30 feet), run thence North 01 degree 12 minutes 00 seconds East, on the East line of said excepted tract, 1028.77 feet, recited as 15.59 chains (1028.94 feet) in said decree, to the Northeast corner of said excepted tract; thence North 88 degrees 31 minutes 45 seconds West 24.38 feet; thence North 01 degree 27 minutes 45 seconds East 1.85 feet; thence on a 126.92 foot radius curve to the left through a central angle of 72 degrees 04 minutes 30 seconds a distance of 159.57 feet, the chord of which bears North 34 degrees 34 minutes 30 seconds West 149.27 feet; thence North 70 degrees 25 minutes 15 seconds West 119.52 feet; thence on a 208.11 foot radius curve to the right through a central angle of 62 degrees 04 minutes 00 seconds a distance of 225.48 feet, the chord of which bears North 39 degrees 23 minutes 15 seconds West 214.61 feet to the South line of Mud Bay Road; thence North 86 degrees 46 minutes 30 seconds East, on said line of Mud Bay Road, 230.54 feet; thence South 70 degrees 25 minutes 15 seconds East 90.95 feet; thence on a 326.92 foot radius curve to the right through a central angle of 71 degrees 57 minutes 00 seconds a distance of 410.55 feet, the chord of which bears South 34 degrees 30 minutes 45 seconds 384.10 feet; thence South 01 degree 27 minutes 45 seconds West 1030.62 feet to the South line of said survey; thence North 88 degrees 31 minutes 45 seconds West 175.38 feet to the point of beginning;
(B) approximately 92 acres in Tract D, C. McRae Subdivision according to Plat 77-12, Haines Recording District, described as: begin at the Southwest corner of said Tract D which is also the Southwest corner of the North one-half of the Southwest one-quarter of the Northwest one-quarter of Section 32, Township 31 South, Range 60 East of the Copper River Meridian, which bears North 01 degree 26 minutes 00 seconds West (Alaska State Plane Grid Bearings) 660.00 feet from the one-quarter corner on the West line of said section and South 01 degree 26 minutes 00 seconds East 660.00 feet from the North one-sixteenth corner on the West line of said section, run thence North 01 degree 26 minutes 00 seconds East, on the West line of said section, 347.81 feet to the Northeasterly line of Chilkat State Park Roadway; thence South 32 degrees 56 minutes 15 seconds East 70.04 feet to a point of curve; thence Southerly on a 0 degrees 58 minutes 58 seconds curve to the right (Radius = 5,829.65 feet) through an arc of 03 degrees 23 minutes 12 seconds (344.58 feet), the chord of which bears South 31 degrees 14 minutes 45 seconds East 344.53 feet, to the South line of said tract and the South line of the North one-half of the Southwest one-quarter of the Northwest one-quarter of said section; thence North 88 degrees 34 minutes 00 seconds West 225.56 feet to the point of beginning;
(C) approximately 3.44 acres in Tract E, C. McRae Subdivision according to Plat 77-12, Haines Recording District, described as: begin at the Northwest corner of said tract which is also the one-sixty-fourth corner on the West line of said section which bears North 01 degree 26 minutes 00 seconds East (Alaska State Plane Grid Bearings) 660.00 feet from the one-quarter corner on the West line of Section 32, Township 31 South, Range 60 East of the Copper River Meridian and South 01 degree 26 minutes 00 seconds West 660.00 feet from the North one-sixteenth corner of said section, run thence South 88 degrees 34 minutes 00 seconds East, on the North line of said tract which is also the South line of the North one-half of the Southwest one-quarter of the Northwest one-quarter of said section, 225.56 feet to a point on the Easterly line of Chilkat State Park Roadway; thence Southerly on a 0 degrees 58 minutes 58 seconds curve to the right (Radius = 5,829.65 feet) through an arc of 01 degree 46 minutes 48 seconds (181.10 feet), the chord of which bears South 28 degrees 39 minutes 39 seconds East 181.10 feet, to a point of tangency; thence South 27 degrees 46 minutes 15 seconds East 268.21 feet to a point of curve; thence on a 14 degrees 16 minutes 06 seconds curve to the right (Radius = 401.56) through an arc of 40 degrees 06 minutes 37 seconds (281.12 feet), the chord of which bears South 07 degrees 43 minutes 00 seconds East 275.41 feet to the South line of said tract which is also the South line of the Southwest one-quarter of the Northwest one-quarter of said section; thence North 88 degrees 15 minutes 00 seconds West, on said South line, to the Westerly line of Chilkat State Park Roadway; thence Northerly on a 28 degrees 25 minutes 34 seconds curve to the left (Radius = 201.56 feet) through an arc of 50 degrees 59 minutes 51 seconds (179.40 feet), the chord of which bears North 02 degrees 15 minutes 15 seconds West 173.54 feet to a point of tangency; thence North 27 degrees 46 minutes 15 seconds West 268.21 feet to a point of curve; thence on a 01 degree 01 minute 04 seconds curve to the left (Radius = 5,629.65 feet) through an arc of 02 degrees 50 minutes 00 seconds (278.39 feet), the chord of which bears North 29 degrees 11 minutes 15 seconds West 278.37 feet to the West line of said section; thence North 01 degree 26 minutes 00 seconds East 14.72 feet to the point of beginning.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-112">
            <num>41.21.112</num>
            <heading>Incompatible uses.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.112.   Incompatible uses.
The commissioner shall designate by regulation incompatible uses within the boundaries of the Chilkat State Park in accordance with
AS 41.21.110
, and those incompatible uses designated shall be prohibited or restricted, as provided by regulation.  Nothing in this section affects the rights and uses of water and facilities of the city of Haines located within the boundaries of this area.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-113">
            <num>41.21.113</num>
            <heading>Eminent domain prohibited.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.113.   Eminent domain prohibited.
The state may not acquire by eminent domain privately owned land for inclusion in Chilkat State Park.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-120">
            <num>41.21.120</num>
            <heading>Purpose ofAS 41.21.120 41.21.125.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.120.   Purpose of
AS 41.21.120
 41.21.125.
The purpose of
AS 41.21.120
 41.21.125 is to restrict state-owned land and water described in
AS 41.21.121
to use as a state park. Under
AS 38.05.300
, state land, water, or land and water containing more than 640 acres may be closed to multiple purpose use only by act of the legislature.  Because the area described in
AS 41.21.121
exceeds 640 acres,
AS 41.21.120
 41.21.125 are intended to provide for the closing of the described land and water to multiple purpose use in conformity with
AS 38.05.300
and its subsequent designation as a special purpose site in accordance with art. VIII, § 7, of the Constitution of the State of Alaska.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-121">
            <num>41.21.121</num>
            <heading>Chugach State Park established.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.121.   Chugach State Park established.
The presently state-owned land and water, and all that acquired in the future by the state, lying within the parcels described in this section are designated as the Chugach State Park. The park is established to protect and supply a satisfactory water supply for the use of the people, to provide recreational opportunities for the people by providing areas for specified uses and constructing the necessary facilities in those areas, to protect areas of unique and exceptional scenic value, to provide areas for the public display of local wildlife, and to protect the existing wilderness characteristics of the easterly interior area. The eastern area of the park shall be operated as a wilderness area, the central area as a scenic area, and the periphery areas as recreational areas. The land and water designated as the Chugach State Park and reserved from all uses incompatible with its primary function as a state park is that within the following described parcels excluding valid entries:
(1) Township 11 North, Range 3 West, Seward Meridian Section 10: Lots 19, 24, 25, 28, 29, 33, 34, 37; and SE1/4, and E1/2 SW1/4
Section 14: SW1/4
Sections 15, 22, 23, 24, 25 and 26;
(2) Township 10 North, Range 2 West, Seward Meridian Sections 1  4;
(3) Township 11 North, Range 2 West, Seward Meridian Sections 1  3 (protracted)
Sections 4 and 5
Section 7: E1/2 NE1/4 and SE1/4
Sections 8 and 9
Section 10  17 (protracted)
Section 18: Lot 4; and NE1/4, SE1/4, and E1/2 SW1/4
Section 19 (protracted), except Lot 1 USS 4909.
Sections 20  26 (protracted)
Sections 27  28
Sections 29  32 (protracted)
Section 33 (protracted), except USS 2891
Sections 34  36 (protracted);
(4) Township 12 North, Range 2 West, Seward Meridian
Section 3: W1/2, SE1/4, and SW1/4 NE1/4
Sections 4, 5, and 7  10
Section 11: sw1/4, w1/2 nw1/4, se1/4 nw1/4, and sw1/4 se1/4
Section 13: sw1/4 nw1/4, sw1/4, and sw1/4 se1/4
Sections 14  29
Section 31: S1/2 SE1/4 and SE1/4 NE1/4
Sections 32  36;
(5) Township 14 North, Range 2 West, Seward Meridian
Section 11: Lots 74 and 75
Section 13, except NE1/4 NE1/4
Section 14: Lots 1  3, 13  16, 31, 32; and E1/2 ne1/4 ne1/4, And sw1/4 ne1/4 ne1/4
Section 24: N1/2 N1/2;
(6) Township 10 North, Range 1 West, Seward Meridian
Sections 1  4 (protracted)
Section 5 (protracted), except Uss 1868, uss 3215, and Indian Valley Subdivision
Section 6 (protracted), except Lots 2, 3, and 4, uss 1868, uss 3200, and uss 3200b
Section 8 (protracted)
Section 9, except USS 3680, Lots 2  8, uss 3201, uss 1069, and Bird Creek East Subdivision, as shown on Plat 94-147, Anchorage Recording District, December 16, 1994
Section 10, except USS 3201, USS 3202, Uss 3680, lots 7  19, and USS 3382
Sections 11  14 and 23  25 (protracted);
(7) Township 11 North, Range 1 West, Seward Meridian
Sections 1  30
Section 31, except USS 3200, USS 1868 and First Addition Indian Valley Subdivision
Sections 32  36;
(8) Township 12 North, Range 1 West, Seward Meridian, except lands withdrawn for military purposes;
(9) Township 13 North, Range 1 West, Seward Meridian;
(10) Township 14 North, Range 1 West, Seward Meridian
Sections 1  4 (protracted)
Section 5: lots 1  4; and s1/2 ne1/4, se1/4 nw1/4, n1/2 sw1/4 nw1/4, se1/4 sw1/4 nw1/4, e1/2 sw1/4 sw1/4 nw1/4, Se1/4 sw1/4, e1/2 se1/4, S1/2 sw1/4 se1/4, and n1/2 nw1/4 se1/4
Section 6: Lot 1
Section 9: E1/2
Sections 10  13 (protracted)
Section 14 N1/2 (protracted), e1/2 se1/4, and n1/2 sw1/4
Section 15: ne1/4, n1/2 nw1/4, se1/4 nw1/4, and sw1/4 sw1/4
Section 16: sw1/4, s1/2 se1/4, and nw1/4 se1/4
Section 17: S1/2
Section 18: S1/2
Section 19: N1/2 N1/2
Section 20: N1/2 and SW1/4
Section 21: E1/2 SW1/4, SW1/4 SW1/4, SW1/4 SE1/4, Tracts B, C1, and C2, Eagle River Greenbelt Subdivision, as shown on Plat 88-34, Anchorage Recording District, June 24, 1988, Tract D, Eagle Valley Subdivision, as shown on Plat 87-36, Anchorage Recording District, May 4, 1987, and Lot 4A, Block 10, Riverview Estates Subdivision, as shown on Plat 90-45, Anchorage Recording District, July 9, 1990
Section 22, except E1/2 NE1/4
Section 23: sw1/4 nw1/4, sw1/4, sw1/4 se1/4, And s1/2 se1/4 se1/4
Section 24: N1/2, ne1/4 sw1/4, e1/2 nw1/4 sw1/4, nw1/4 nw1/4 sw1/4, e1/2 se1/4, nw1/4 se1/4, and Tract B, Eagle River Greenbelt, Plat 88-34, Anchorage Recording District
Section 25: Tract B, Eagle River Greenbelt, Plat 88-34, Anchorage Recording District
Sections 26  36;
(11) Township 15 North, Range 1 West, Seward Meridian
Section 1
Section 2: SE1/4
Section 11: e1/2, n1/2 sw1/4, e1/2 nw1/4, and sw1/4 nw1/4
Sections 12 and 13
Section 14: s1/2, ne1/4, e1/2 nw1/4, and sw1/4 nw1/4
Section 15: SE1/4 and S1/2 NE1/4
Sections 21  28
Section 29: E1/2, E1/2 SW1/4, and SW1/4 SW1/4
Section 31: E1/2 and E1/2 SW1/4
Section 32: N1/2, E1/2 SE1/4, and S1/2 SW1/4
Sections 33  36;
(12) Township 16 North, Range 1 West, Seward Meridian
Section 25: ne1/4se1/4se1/4 and n1/2se1/4se1/4se1/4; and
Tract B, Thunderbird Heights Subdivision, as shown on Plat 77-226, Anchorage Recording District, October 10, 1977;
(13) Township 10 North, Range 1 East, Seward Meridian;
(14) Township 11 North, Range 1 East, Seward Meridian;
(15) Township 12 North, Range 1 East, Seward Meridian;
(16) Township 13 North, Range 1 East, Seward Meridian;
(17) Township 14 North, Range 1 East, Seward Meridian
Sections 1  29 (protracted)
Section 30: Lots 2  6; and Ne1/4, n1/2 nw1/4, n1/2 se1/4, n1/2 se1/4 se1/4, n1/2 ne1/4 sw1/4, and Tract B, Eagle River Greenbelt Subdivision, as shown on Plat 88-34, Anchorage Recording District, June 24, 1988
Section 31: Tract B, Eagle River Greenbelt Subdivision, as shown on Plat 88-34, Anchorage Recording District, June 24, 1988
Section 32: n1/2 ne1/4, w1/2 se1/4 ne1/4, NE1/4 SE1/4 NE1/4, and Tract B, Eagle River Greenbelt Subdivision, as shown on Plat 88-34, Anchorage Recording District, June 24, 1988
Section 33: n1/2 ne1/4, ne1/4 nw1/4, and n1/2 nw1/4 nw1/4
Sections 34  36;
(18) Township 15 North, Range 1 East, Seward Meridian;
(19) Township 16 North, Range 1 East, Seward Meridian
Sections 26  29 and 31  36
Section 30: SW1/4 SW1/4;
(20) Township 10 North, Range 2 East, Seward Meridian
Sections 4  6, except Chugach National Forest and Tract A of ASLS 81-149
Section 7, except Tract A of ASLS 81-149
Section 8: W1/2 W1/2, except Tract A of ASLS 81-149
Section 18: N1/2 and SW1/4, except USS 3043, uss 3042, and Tract A of ASLS 81-149;
(21) Township 11 North, Range 2 East, Seward Meridian
Sections 1  7, 18, 19, 30, and 31, except Chugach National Forest;
(22) Township 12 North, Range 2 East, Seward Meridian;
(23) Township 13 North, Range 2 East, Seward Meridian;
(24) Township 14 North, Range 2 East, Seward Meridian;
(25) Township 15 North, Range 2 East, Seward Meridian
Sections 1  4, 6, 7, and 10  36
Section 9: E1/2;
(26) Township 16 North, Range 2 East, Seward Meridian
Section 1: S1/2 that portion south of Knik River Road, except Uss 2491, uss 3257, uss 3914, uss 4789, and Uss 3289
Section 2: that portion south of the Old Glenn Highway, except USS 2491
Section 9: that portion south of the Old Glenn Highway, except USS 2942, USS 3070, USS 3076, USS 3077, USS 3160, USS 3236, USS 3237, USS 3239, USS 3240, USS 3363, USS 3561, USS 3568, and USS 5554
Sections 10 and 11: that portion south of the Glenn Highway except USS 3236, USS 3238, USS 3363, and USS 5554
Sections 12  15
Section 16: excluding USS 3239 and USS 3561
Section 17: that portion of the E1/2 south of the Glenn Highway
Section 19: S1/2
Section 20: NE1/4
Sections 21  28
Sections 30 and 31
Sections 33  36;
(27) Township 11 North, Range 3 East, except Chugach National Forest;
(28) Township 12 North, Range 3 East, Seward Meridian;
(29) Township 13 North, Range 3 East, Seward Meridian;
(30) Township 14 North, Range 3 East, Seward Meridian;
(31) Township 15 North, Range 3 East, Seward Meridian;
(32) Township 16 North, Range 3 East, Seward Meridian
Section 7
Section 8, excluding N1/2 NE1/4
Sections 17  21
Sections 27  35.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-122">
            <num>41.21.122</num>
            <heading>Management responsibility.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.122.   Management responsibility.
The state land and water described in
AS 41.21.121
as the Chugach State Park is assigned to the department for control, development and maintenance, except that the Department of Transportation and Public Facilities is responsible for the repair and maintenance of all existing public roads within the park.  The control of highway access and roadside structures within the Chugach State Park is the responsibility of the department.  The Department of Fish and Game shall cooperate with the department to provide for those purposes under
AS 41.21.121
relevant to the duties of the Department of Fish and Game.  If, in the exercise of management responsibility under this section, conflicts of land ownership, jurisdiction, or authority are unreconcilable or unmanageable other than at an unreasonable cost and expense to the state, the commissioner after public hearing in accordance with
AS 44.62
may modify, subject to the approval of the legislature, the boundaries of the Chugach State Park not to exceed 20 percent of the total acreage described in
AS 41.21.121
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-123">
            <num>41.21.123</num>
            <heading>Incompatible uses.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-123__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall designate by regulation, adopted in accordance with
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act), incompatible uses within the boundaries of the Chugach State Park in accordance with
AS 41.21.120
 41.21.125, and those incompatible uses designated are prohibited or restricted as provided by regulation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-123__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In adopting regulations under this section and in complying with
AS 44.62.210
, the commissioner shall provide the opportunity for the oral presentation of statements, arguments or contentions.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-125">
            <num>41.21.125</num>
            <heading>Purchase authorized.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.125.   Purchase authorized.
The commissioner may acquire, by purchase in the name of the state, title to or interest in real property lying within or abutting the boundaries of the Chugach State Park.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-130">
            <num>41.21.130</num>
            <heading>Purpose ofAS 41.21.130 41.21.142.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.130.   Purpose of
AS 41.21.130
 41.21.142.
The purpose of
AS 41.21.130
 41.21.142 is to restrict state-owned land and water described in
AS 41.21.131
to use as a state park. Under
AS 38.05.300
, state land, water, or land and water containing more than 640 acres may be closed to multiple purpose use only by act of the legislature.  Because the area described in
AS 41.21.131
exceeds 640 acres,
AS 41.21.130
 41.21.142 are intended to provide for the closing of the described land and water to multiple purpose use in conformity with
AS 38.05.300
and its subsequent designation as a special purpose site in accordance with art. VIII, § 7, of the Constitution of the State of Alaska.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-131">
            <num>41.21.131</num>
            <heading>Kachemak Bay State Park established.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-131__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The presently state-owned land and water, and all that acquired in the future by the state, lying within the parcels described in this section are designated as the Kachemak Bay State Park. In order to protect and preserve this land and water for its unique and exceptional scenic value, the park is established and shall be managed as a scenic park. The land and water lying within the following described parcels is reserved from all uses incompatible with its primary function as a scenic park and is assigned to the department for control, development, and maintenance:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-131__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 5 South, Range 10 West, Seward Meridian Chugachik Island
Sections 31  32;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-131__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 5 South, Range 11 West, Seward Meridian
Section 2: Lot 1, excluding Tract A
Section 3: Lots 1  8, SW1/4NE1/4, S1/2NW1/4, N1/2SW1/4
Section 4: Lots 1  4, S1/2N1/2, SE1/4, E1/2SW1/4
Section 8: E1/2NE1/4, SE1/4
Section 9: Lots 1 and 2, NW1/4NE1/4, NE1/4NW1/4, W1/2NW1/4, N1/2NE1/4SW1/4, SW1/4NE1/4SW1/4, excluding Lot 6
Section 10: Lot 1
Section 16: Lot 1
Section 17: Lots 1, 3, 4, NW1/4SW1/4, S1/2NW1/4
Section 18: Lot 4, SE1/4, E1/2NE1/4
Section 19: Lots 1  6, NW1/4NE1/4, NE1/4NW1/4
Section 20: Lot 1
Sections 24  25, excluding tide and submerged land within the Kachemak Bay Critical Habitat Area
Section 26: SE1/4, excluding tide and submerged land within the Kachemak Bay Critical Habitat Area
Section 35, excluding tide and submerged land within the Kachemak Bay Critical Habitat Area
Section 36;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-131__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 6 South, Range 11 West, Seward Meridian;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-131__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 7 South, Range 11 West, Seward Meridian
Sections 1  4
Section 5: N1/2
Sections 7  36;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-131__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 7 South, Range 12 West, Seward Meridian
Section 12, except N1/2NE1/4
Section 13
Sections 19  36;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-131__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 7 South, Range 13 West, Seward Meridian
Sections 25  26
Sections 35  36;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-131__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 8 South, Range 11 West, Seward Meridian
Sections 1  8
Section 9: N1/2
Section 10: N1/2
Section 11: N1/2
Section 12: N1/2
Sections 17  18;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-131__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 8 South, Range 12 West, Seward Meridian;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-131__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 8 South, Range 13 West, Seward Meridian
Sections 1  2
Sections 10  14
Section 15: E1/2
Section 23: N1/2 and SE1/4
Sections 24  25
Section 26: E1/2
Section 35: E1/2
Section 36;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-131__subsec_a__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 9 South, Range 8 West, Seward Meridian
Section 2: W1/2
Section 3  10
Sections 15  22
Sections 27  34;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-131__subsec_a__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 9 South, Range 9 West, Seward Meridian;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-131__subsec_a__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 9 South, Range 10 West, Seward Meridian
Sections 10  15
Sections 22  27
Sections 34  36;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-131__subsec_a__subsec_13">
                <num>(13)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 9 South, Range 12 West, Seward Meridian
Sections 1  6
Section 8: NE1/4
Sections 9  12
Section 13: N1/2
Section 14: N1/2;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-131__subsec_a__subsec_14">
                <num>(14)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 9 South, Range 13 West, Seward Meridian
Sections 1  2;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-131__subsec_a__subsec_15">
                <num>(15)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 10 South, Range 8 West, Seward Meridian
Sections 4  8
Sections 17  19;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-131__subsec_a__subsec_16">
                <num>(16)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 10 South, Range 9 West, Seward Meridian
Sections 1  4
Sections 10  15
Sections 22  24.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-131__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The following public domain land shall be selected by the state, and classified as scenic park land and designated as part of Kachemak Bay State Park immediately upon receipt of management authority by the state:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-131__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 6 South, Range 10 West, Seward Meridian: W1/2;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-131__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 7 South, Range 10 West, Seward Meridian: W1/2;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-131__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 8 South, Range 10 West, Seward Meridian
Section 6
Section 7: N1/2.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-131__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Land lying within the parcels described in (a) and (b) of this section upon which there are valid entries or upon which there are valid applications for lease filed under
AS 38.05
before May 9, 1970, is excepted from (a) and (b) of this section. However, if any land excepted under this subsection is subsequently relinquished to the state, it shall be included as part of Kachemak Bay State Park.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-132">
            <num>41.21.132</num>
            <heading>Incompatible uses.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.132.   Incompatible uses.
The commissioner shall designate by regulation incompatible uses within the boundaries of the Kachemak Bay State Park in accordance with the requirements of
AS 41.21.130
 41.21.142, and those incompatible uses designated shall be prohibited or restricted, as provided by regulation.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-134">
            <num>41.21.134</num>
            <heading>Purchase authorized; eminent domain prohibited.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.134.   Purchase authorized; eminent domain prohibited.
The commissioner may acquire, by purchase in the name of the state, title to or interest in real property lying within the boundaries of the Kachemak Bay State Park.  The state may not acquire by eminent domain privately owned land for inclusion in the Kachemak Bay State Park.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-140">
            <num>41.21.140</num>
            <heading>Kachemak Bay State Wilderness Park established.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-140__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The presently state-owned land and water, and all that acquired in the future by the state, lying within the parcels described in this section are designated as the Kachemak Bay State Wilderness Park. In order to protect and preserve this land and water for its unique and exceptional wilderness value, the park is established and shall be managed as a wilderness park. The land and water lying within the following described parcels is reserved from all uses incompatible with its primary function as a wilderness park and is assigned to the department for control and maintenance:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-140__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 8 South, Range 11 West, Seward Meridian
Section 9: S1/2
Section 10: S1/2
Section 11: S1/2
Section 12: S1/2
Sections 13  16
Sections 19  36;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-140__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 9 South, Range 10 West, Seward Meridian
Sections 1  3;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-140__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 9 South, Range 12 West, Seward Meridian
Section 7
Section 8: S1/2 and NW1/4
Section 13: S1/2
Section 14: S1/2
Sections 15  36;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-140__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 9 South, Range 13 West, Seward Meridian
Section 11: NE1/4
Sections 12  13;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-140__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 10 South, Range 9 West, Seward Meridian
Sections 5  7;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-140__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 10 South, Range 10 West, Seward Meridian;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-140__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 10 South, Range 11 West, Seward Meridian;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-140__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 10 South, Range 12 West, Seward Meridian;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-140__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 11 South, Range 10 West, Seward Meridian;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-140__subsec_a__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 11 South, Range 11 West, Seward Meridian;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-140__subsec_a__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 11 South, Range 12 West, Seward Meridian
Sections 1  10
Section 11: W1/2 and E1/2
Sections 12  17
Sections 21  24.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-140__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The following public domain land shall be selected by the state, and classified as wilderness park land and designated as part of Kachemak Bay State Park immediately upon receipt of management authority by the state:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-140__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 8 South, Range 10 West, Seward Meridian
Sections 4  5
Section 7: S1/2
Sections 8  9
Sections 16  21
Sections 28  33;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-140__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 9 South, Range 10 West, Seward Meridian: W1/2;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-140__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 9 South, Range 11 West, Seward Meridian.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-141">
            <num>41.21.141</num>
            <heading>Certain land excepted.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.141.   Certain land excepted.
Land lying within the parcels described in
AS 41.21.140
upon which there are valid entries or upon which there are valid applications for leases filed under
AS 38.05
before March 9, 1972, or that is withdrawn for or selected by Native village or regional corporations under 43 U.S.C. 1610, 1611, and 1613 (P.L. 92-203, §§ 11, 12, and 14 of the Alaska Native Claims Settlement Act), is excepted from
AS 41.21.140
. However, if any land excepted under this subsection is subsequently relinquished to the state, it shall be included as part of Kachemak Bay State Wilderness Park.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-142">
            <num>41.21.142</num>
            <heading>Stream rehabilitation permitted.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.142.   Stream rehabilitation permitted.
Nothing in
AS 41.21.140
 41.21.142 prohibits the Department of Fish and Game from engaging in stream rehabilitation enhancement and development under
AS 16.05.092
on land lying within the parcels described in
AS 41.21.140
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-150">
            <num>41.21.150</num>
            <heading>Purpose ofAS 41.21.150 41.21.153.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.150.   Purpose of
AS 41.21.150
 41.21.153.
The purpose of
AS 41.21.150
 41.21.153 is to restrict state-owned land and water described in
AS 41.21.151
, except as provided in
AS 41.21.153
, to use as a state park. Under
AS 38.05.300
, state land, water, or land and water containing more than 640 acres may be closed to multiple use only by act of the legislature. Because the area described in
AS 41.21.151
exceeds 640 acres,
AS 41.21.150
 41.21.153 are intended to provide for the closing of the land and water described in
AS 41.21.151
, as that description is modified by
AS 41.21.153
, to multiple use in conformity with
AS 38.05.300
and its designation as a special purpose area in accord with art. VIII, sec. 7 of the Constitution of the State of Alaska.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-151">
            <num>41.21.151</num>
            <heading>Denali State Park established.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.151.   Denali State Park established.
The state-owned land and water and that acquired in the future by the state lying within the parcels described in this section are designated as the Denali State Park.  This land and water is reserved from all uses incompatible with its primary function as park area.  Land covered by
AS 41.21.150
 41.21.152 is that within the following described parcels:
(1) Township 29N Range 6W, Range 5W, and that portion of Range 4W lying north and west of the Alaska Railroad right-of-way; Township 30N Range 5W and that portion of Range 3W and 4W lying north and west of the Alaska Railroad right-of-way; Township 31N Range 5W, Range 4W and that portion of Range 3W and Range 2W lying north and west of the Alaska Railroad right-of-way; Township 32N Range 4W, Range 3W and that portion of Range 2W lying north and west of the Alaska Railroad right-of-way; and Township 33N Range 4W, Range 3W and that portion of Range 2W lying west of the Alaska Railroad right-of-way, all in the Seward Meridian;
(2) Township 29N, Range 7W; Sections 1-27 and 34-36, Township 29N, Range 8W; containing approximately 42,240 acres, all in the Seward Meridian.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-152">
            <num>41.21.152</num>
            <heading>Eminent domain prohibited.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.152.   Eminent domain prohibited.
The state may not acquire by eminent domain privately owned land for inclusion in the Denali State Park.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-153">
            <num>41.21.153</num>
            <heading>Certain land excepted.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-153__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding
AS 41.21.020
(a)(6), 41.21.150, or 41.21.151, state-owned land in the following described parcels may be leased in accordance with
AS 38.35
(Right-of-Way Leasing Act) for the purpose of construction and operation of a natural gas pipeline from the North Slope:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-153__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 29 North, Range 5 West, Seward Meridian
Section 4: N1/2, SW1/4
Section 5: E1/2
Section 7: E1/2, SW1/4
Section 8
Section 9: NW1/4
Section 18: E1/2
Section 19: E1/2
Section 29: SW1/4
Section 30: E1/2
Section 31: E1/2
Section 32: W1/2;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-153__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 30 North, Range 5 West, Seward Meridian
Section 2: NW1/4
Section 3
Section 4: SE1/4
Section 8: E1/2
Section 9
Section 10: W1/2
Section 16: W1/2
Section 17: E1/2
Section 20: E1/2
Section 21: W1/2
Section 28
Section 33;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-153__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 31 North, Range 4 West, Seward Meridian
Section 1: NW1/4, N1/2NE1/4
Section 2
Section 3: SE1/4
Section 9: SE1/4
Section 10
Section 11: W1/2
Section 14: NW1/4
Section 15: N1/2
Section 16
Section 17: S1/2
Section 19: NE1/4, S1/2
Section 20: N1/2, SW1/4
Section 21: NW1/4
Section 30: N1/2;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-153__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 31 North, Range 5 West, Seward Meridian
Section 24: SE1/4
Section 25
Section 26: E1/2
Section 34: SE1/4
Section 35
Section 36: NW1/4;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-153__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 32 North, Range 2 West, Seward Meridian
Section 6: NW1/4;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-153__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 32 North, Range 3 West, Seward Meridian
Section 1: N1/2, SW1/4
Section 2
Section 3: SE1/4
Section 8: SE1/4
Section 9
Section 10: N1/2, SW1/4, N1/2SE1/4
Section 11: NW1/4
Section 16: N1/2
Section 17
Section 19: S1/2, NE1/4
Section 20: N1/2, SW1/4, N1/2SE1/4
Section 29: NW1/4
Section 30
Section 31: N1/2, SW1/4;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-153__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 32 North, Range 4 West, Seward Meridian
Section 25: SE1/4
Section 35: SE1/4
Section 36;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-153__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 33 North, Range 2 West, Seward Meridian
Section 16
Section 17: SE1/4
Section 20: NE1/4, S1/2, S1/2NW1/4
Section 21: W1/2
Section 29: N1/2, SW1/4
Section 30: S1/2, NE1/4
Section 31;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-153__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 33 North, Range 3 West, Seward Meridian
Section 36: S1/2.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-153__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A state or federal survey does not remove land from the parcels described in (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-153__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall manage any state-owned land described in this section and within the exterior boundaries of Denali State Park as part of Denali State Park until the land is leased under
AS 38.35
. State-owned land described in this section will revert to Denali State Park upon release of the land from a right-of-way through termination of the lease or otherwise and upon satisfaction of the lessee's obligations to restore and revegetate the land.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-153__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Any right-of-way lease issued under
AS 38.35
across land described in this section and within the exterior boundaries of Denali State Park must</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-153__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>reserve to the state the interests necessary to provide for public access by foot, snow machine, dog sled, and other traditional means of access along and across the leased corridor;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-153__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>preserve, to the maximum extent practicable, the recreational, scenic, cultural, historical, and habitat values consistent with the leasehold's location within the exterior boundaries of Denali State Park; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-153__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide for termination of the lease if construction of the pipeline has not begun 10 years after the effective date of the lease.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-153__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>AS 38.35.130
does not apply to land within the exterior boundaries of Denali State Park.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-153__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A natural gas pipeline right-of-way lease may not be issued across land described in this section unless the lease becomes effective before January 1, 2025.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-160">
            <num>41.21.160</num>
            <heading>Purpose ofAS 41.21.160 41.21.167.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.160.   Purpose of
AS 41.21.160
 41.21.167.
The purpose of
AS 41.21.160
 41.21.167 is to establish the state-owned land and water areas described in
AS 41.21.161
as the Wood-Tikchik State Park.  The primary purposes of creating the Wood-Tikchik State Park are to protect the area's fish and wildlife breeding and support systems and to preserve the continued use of the area for subsistence and recreational activities.  The state park is also created to protect the area's recreational and scenic resources.
AS 41.21.160
 41.21.167 are intended to close the described land and water to multiple-purpose use in conformity with
AS 38.05.300
and to dedicate it as a special purpose site in accordance with art. VIII, § 7 of the Constitution of the State of Alaska.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-161">
            <num>41.21.161</num>
            <heading>Wood-Tikchik State Park established.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-161__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The state-owned or acquired land and water lying within the following parcel, containing approximately 1,428,320 acres, is designated as the Wood-Tikchik State Park: beginning at the SE corner of T7S, R54W, S.M., which is the true point of beginning; thence westerly to the NE corner of T8S, R58W, S.M.; thence southerly to the SE corner of T8S, R58W, S.M.; thence westerly to the SW corner of T8S, R58W, S.M.; thence northerly to the NW corner of T5S, R58W, S.M.; thence westerly to the SW corner of Section 34, T4S, R58W, S.M.; thence northerly to the NE corner of Section 4, T1S, R58W, S.M.; thence westerly to the SW corner of T1N, R57W, S.M.; thence northerly to the NW corner of T2N, R57W, S.M.; thence easterly to the NE corner of T2N, R57W, S.M.; thence northerly to the NW corner of T4N, R56W, S.M.; thence easterly to the SW corner of T5N, R55W, S.M.; thence northerly to the NW corner of T5N, R55W, S.M.; thence easterly to the NE corner of T5N, R55W, S.M.; thence southerly to the SE corner of T5N, R55W, S.M.; thence easterly to the NE corner of T4N, R54W, S.M.; thence southerly to the SE corner of T4N, R54W, S.M.; thence easterly to the NE corner of T3N, R53W, S.M.; thence southerly to the SE corner of T3N, R53W, S.M.; thence easterly to the NE corner of T2N, R52W, S.M.; thence southerly to the SW corner of T1N, R51W, S.M.; thence easterly to the NE corner of T1S, R52W, S.M.; thence southerly to the SE corner of T2S, R52W, S.M.; thence easterly to the NE corner of T3S, R51W, S.M.; thence southerly to the SE corner of T3S, R51W, S.M.; thence westerly to the NE corner of T4S, R53W, S.M.; thence southerly to the SE corner of T4S, R53W, S.M.; thence westerly to the NE corner of T5S, R54W, S.M.; thence southerly to the SE corner of T7S, R54W, S.M., which point is the true point of beginning.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-161__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>All or part of the state-owned or acquired land and water within the following adjacent parcel, containing approximately 126,720 acres may be added to the Wood-Tikchik State Park by proclamation of the governor: beginning at the SE corner of T7S, R54W, S.M., which point is the true point of beginning; thence southerly to the SE corner of T8S, R54W, S.M.; thence westerly to the NE corner of T9S, R55W, S.M.; thence southerly to the SE corner of the NE quarter of T9S, R55W, S.M.; thence westerly to the SW corner of the NW quarter of T9S, R57W, S.M.; thence northerly to the NW corner of T9S, R57W, S.M.; thence westerly to the SE corner of T8S, R58W, S.M.; thence northerly to the NE corner of T8S, R58W, S.M.; thence easterly to the SE corner of T7S, R54W, S.M., which point is the true point of beginning.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-161__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Land lying within the parcels described in (a) or (b) of this section upon which there are valid entries or that is withdrawn for or selected by Native village or regional corporations under 43 U.S.C. 1610, 1611, and 1613 (P.L. 92-203, §§ 11, 12, and 14 of the Alaska Native Claims Settlement Act), is excepted from (a) and (b) of this section. However, if any land excepted under this subsection is subsequently relinquished to the state, it shall be included as part of the Wood-Tikchik State Park.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-162">
            <num>41.21.162</num>
            <heading>Designation of management responsibility.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.162.   Designation of management responsibility.
The land and water described in
AS 41.21.161
is assigned to the department for control, maintenance, and development consistent with the purposes and provisions of this chapter. The Department of Fish and Game is responsible for the management of fish and game resources in the Wood-Tikchik State Park, consistent with the purposes and provisions of this chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-163">
            <num>41.21.163</num>
            <heading>Management Council created.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.163.   Management Council created.
A seven-member Wood-Tikchik State Park Management Council is created and shall be appointed by the governor.  Management council members may, subject to appropriations, receive the same per diem and travel expenses authorized for members of state boards.  The governor shall appoint one member of the council from three nominations submitted to the governor by each of the following:
(1) the village council of Koliganek;
(2) the village council of New Stuyahok;
(3) the village council of Aleknagik;
(4) the city council of Dillingham;
(5) the Bristol Bay Native Association, Inc.;
(6) the commissioner of natural resources;
(7) the commissioner of fish and game.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-164">
            <num>41.21.164</num>
            <heading>Management plan.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.164.   Management plan.
The Wood-Tikchik State Park Management Council shall develop a management plan for the park with the advice and assistance of the department.  The management plan shall be presented at a public meeting before approval and implementation.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-165">
            <num>41.21.165</num>
            <heading>Regulations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.165.   Regulations.
The department shall consult with Department of Fish and Game and the management council before adoption of regulations governing the public use of the park.  The Department of Fish and Game shall consult with the department and the management council before adoption of regulations governing fish and wildlife management in the park. Regulations may not be adopted by either department without prior review at public hearings.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-166">
            <num>41.21.166</num>
            <heading>Fish and wildlife breeding areas.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.166.   Fish and wildlife breeding areas.
The fish and wildlife habitat breeding areas in the Wood-Tikchik State Park shall be managed to sustain the fish and wildlife resources of the park in perpetuity.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-167">
            <num>41.21.167</num>
            <heading>Compatible and incompatible uses.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-167__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The land and water areas described in
AS 41.21.161
are not open to mineral entry under
AS 38.05.135
 38.05.275 or 38.05.700  38.05.795.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-167__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The regulations adopted under
AS 41.21.165
shall recognize that the current practice of traditional subsistence and recreational activities includes the use of small outboard motors and snow machines.  Reasonable access by aircraft for recreational purposes shall be permitted.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-167__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Development and operation of a hydroelectric site at Lake Elva or Grant Lake is not considered an incompatible use.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-167__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Development and operation of campsites on or adjacent to major spawning and breeding areas are incompatible uses unless it can be shown by a preponderance of evidence that the fishery and wildlife habitat and breeding areas will not be adversely affected to a significant degree by the development and operation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-167__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The development and operation of a hydroelectric site at the Nuyakuk River Falls is a compatible use if the development and operation</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-167__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>does not include a dam that fully spans a river;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-167__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>maintains at least 70 percent of the daily upstream water flow of an affected river along the natural course of the river; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-167__subsec_e__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>after July 1, 2024, is licensed by the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-170">
            <num>41.21.170</num>
            <heading>Declaration of purpose.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-170__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The purpose of
AS 41.21.170
 41.21.178 is to establish, subject to valid existing rights, the state-owned or acquired land and water described in
AS 41.21.172
as the Shuyak Island State Park. In accordance with the covenants and deed restrictions set by the Kodiak Island Borough that support the basic tenets of the Alaska lifestyle, the primary purpose of establishing the Shuyak Island State Park is to preserve, protect, and enhance traditional public access to and use of the area's natural resources for various activities including sport and subsistence hunting, sport, subsistence, and commercial fishing, and trapping.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-170__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Under the provisions of
AS 38.05.300
, state land, water, or land and water containing more than 640 acres may be closed to multiple purpose use only by act of the legislature. Because the area described in
AS 41.21.172
exceeds 640 acres,
AS 41.21.170
  41.21.178 are intended to close the described land and water to multiple purpose use in conformity with
AS 38.05.300
and to dedicate them as a special purpose site in accordance with art. VIII, § 7, Constitution of the State of Alaska.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-172">
            <num>41.21.172</num>
            <heading>Designated state land and water.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.172.   Designated state land and water.
The upland, shoreland, tideland, land underlying tidally influenced inland water, and water overlying this land, including both the surface and subsurface estate, owned or acquired by the state within the following described parcels are designated as the Shuyak Island State Park:
(1) Township 17 South, Range 19 West, Seward Meridian
Section 18
Section 19
Section 30;
(2) Township 17 South, Range 20 West, Seward Meridian
Section 24
Section 25;
(3) Township 18 South, Range 18 West, Seward Meridian
Section 6
Section 7
Section 20
Section 28
Section 29;
(4) Township 18 South, Range 19 West, Seward Meridian
Section 1
Section 2
Section 4
Section 5
Sections 736;
(5) Township 18 South, Range 20 West, Seward Meridian
Section 2
Section 3
Sections 911
Sections 1317
Sections 1936;
(6) Township 18 South, Range 21 West, Seward Meridian
Section 36;
(7) Township 19 South, Range 19 West, Seward Meridian
Sections 124
Sections 2634;
(8) Township 19 South, Range 20 West, Seward Meridian
Sections 1-30
Section 32: N1/2
Sections 3336;
(9) Township 19 South, Range 21 West, Seward Meridian
Section 1
Sections 1214
Section 24
Section 25;
(10) Township 20 South, Range 19 West, Seward Meridian
Section 4
Section 5
Section 6: N1/2, N1/2S1/2;
(11) Township 20 South, Range 20 West, Seward Meridian
Section 1: N1/2, N1/2S1/2
Section 2: N1/2
Section 3: N1/2.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-174">
            <num>41.21.174</num>
            <heading>Designation of management responsibility.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-174__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The state land and water described in
AS 41.21.172
are assigned to the department for control, maintenance, and development consistent with the purposes and provisions of
AS 41.21.170
 41.21.178.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-174__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Fish and Game is responsible for the management of fish and game resources in the Shuyak Island State Park, consistent with the sustained yield principle and the purposes and provisions of this chapter. The Board of Fisheries, the Board of Game, and the commissioner of fish and game are responsible for adopting regulations governing uses of fish and game in accordance with
AS 16
. The fish and game habitat and breeding areas shall be managed to ensure that the fish and game resources of the park continue on a sustained yield basis. In managing the fish and game resources of the Shuyak Island State Park and adopting regulations governing uses of the fish and game, the Board of Fisheries, the Board of Game, or the commissioner of fish and game may not permanently close any fishing, hunting, or trapping within the park unless the closure is implemented because of a biological emergency. A closure implemented because of a biological emergency (1) may continue in effect only as long as the biological emergency continues to exist, and (2) must be reevaluated on a regular basis, not less than annually, to justify that the closure continues to be necessary.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-174__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall consult with the Department of Fish and Game before adoption of regulations governing public use of the Shuyak Island State Park.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-174__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Fish and Game shall consult with the department before adoption of regulations governing fish and game management in Shuyak Island State Park.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-174__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The regulations established under this section shall be adopted in accordance with
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-174__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall permit reasonable camping within the Shuyak Island State Park on an extended basis on request.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-174__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing in
AS 41.21.170
 41.21.178 prohibits the Department of Fish and Game from engaging in rehabilitation, enhancement, and development of fish and game habitat under
AS 16.05
on land and water within the Shuyak Island State Park.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-174__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Public Safety and the Department of Fish and Game shall have necessary access for fish and game management, research, and enforcement purposes.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-176">
            <num>41.21.176</num>
            <heading>Incompatible uses; access.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-176__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in this section, the commissioner may designate by regulation incompatible uses within the land and water of the Shuyak Island State Park.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-176__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Possession and use of a weapon in the Shuyak Island State Park shall be allowed at all times and use of the weapon may be restricted only under extraordinary circumstances and only in such areas where public safety is threatened.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-176__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner may not restrict lawful sport, subsistence, or commercial fishing, sport or subsistence hunting, or trapping permitted under law or under a regulation of the Board of Fisheries or the Board of Game within the Shuyak Island State Park.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-176__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall allow traditional access to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-176__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Shuyak Island State Park for recreational purposes and for lawful sport, subsistence, and commercial fishing, sport and subsistence hunting, and trapping;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-176__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>private land within the park.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-176__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the commissioner determines that a use is incompatible with one or more other uses in a portion of the Shuyak Island State Park, the commissioner shall state</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-176__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>each determination of incompatibility;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-176__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the specific area where the incompatibility is determined to exist;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-176__subsec_e__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the time within which the incompatibility is determined to exist; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-176__subsec_e__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the reasons for each determination of incompatibility.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-178">
            <num>41.21.178</num>
            <heading>Additions to park.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.178.   Additions to park.
Land and water outside of the boundaries established in
AS 41.21.172
may be added to the Shuyak Island State Park only by an act of the legislature. The commissioner may not acquire land and water within the boundaries of the Shuyak Island State Park by eminent domain.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-180">
            <num>41.21.180</num>
            <heading>Purpose ofAS 41.21.180 41.21.183.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-180__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The purpose of
AS 41.21.180
 41.21.183 is to establish, subject to valid existing rights, the state-owned or acquired land described in
AS 41.21.181
as the Point Bridget State Park. The primary purposes of establishing the Point Bridget State Park are to protect the area's recreational and scenic resources and to preserve and enhance the continued use of the area for hunting and fishing and recreational activities.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-180__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The legislature recognizes the rights of the owners of the private land that adjoin the Point Bridget State Park established in
AS 41.21.180
 41.21.183. The legislature further recognizes the value of the services provided by the owners of the adjacent land to the residents of the state. The establishment of the park will not impair the use of the private land by the owners of the private land or the right of a riparian owner of private land to seek title to accreted land.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-181">
            <num>41.21.181</num>
            <heading>Point Bridget State Park established.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.181.   Point Bridget State Park established.
The state-owned land and water within the following described parcels and any land acquired by the state under
AS 41.21.182
are established as the Point Bridget State Park:
All state land lying within the following unsurveyed sections:
Township 37 South, Range 63 East, Copper River Meridian
Section 10: E1/2
Section 11: excluding Native Allotment A-061005
Section 12: W1/2, excluding USS 2925, Interim Conveyance 408, and Native Allotment A-061005
Section 13: W1/2 and W1/2E1/2, excluding USS 1154, USS 1157, and Interim Conveyance 408
Section 14
Section 15: E1/2
Section 23: N1/2
Section 24: NE1/4, excluding Interim Conveyance 408 and the Glacier Highway right-of-way.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-182">
            <num>41.21.182</num>
            <heading>Purchase or exchange authorized.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.182.   Purchase or exchange authorized.
If requested by an owner of land, the department may purchase or enter into an exchange under
AS 38.50
if the purchase or exchange will improve access to the park, consolidate the ownership of land, or otherwise enhance the purposes of the park as expressed in
AS 41.21.180
. Land acquired by the department under this subsection becomes a part of the Point Bridget State Park.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-183">
            <num>41.21.183</num>
            <heading>Designation of management responsibility.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-183__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The state-owned land and water described in
AS 41.21.181
is assigned to the department for control, maintenance, and development consistent with the purposes and provisions of
AS 41.21.180
 41.21.183.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-183__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Fish and Game is responsible for the management of fish and game resources in the Point Bridget State Park, consistent with the sustained-yield principle and the purposes and provisions of this chapter. The Board of Fisheries, the Board of Game, and the commissioner of fish and game are responsible for adopting regulations governing uses of fish and game under
AS 16
. The fish and game habitat and breeding areas shall be managed to ensure that the fish and game resources of the park continue on a sustained-yield basis.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-183__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall consult with the Department of Fish and Game before adoption of regulations governing public use of the Point Bridget State Park.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-183__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Fish and Game shall consult with the department before adoption of regulations governing fish and game management in the Point Bridget State Park.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-185">
            <num>41.21.185</num>
            <heading>Purpose ofAS 41.21.185 41.21.189.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-185__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The purpose of
AS 41.21.185
 41.21.189 is to establish, subject to valid existing rights including those rights created by the Afognak Island Road Use Agreement executed on July 24, 1991, and as amended from time to time, the state-owned or acquired land and water described in
AS 41.21.186
as the Afognak Island State Park. The primary purposes of establishing the Afognak Island State Park are to protect the area's recreational and scenic resources; to protect the area's fish and wildlife habitat; to preserve and enhance the continued use of the area for sport and subsistence hunting and fishing, personal use fishing, trapping, recreational activities, and commercial fishing; and to restore and enhance resources and services injured by the Exxon Valdez oil spill.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-185__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Under the provisions of
AS 38.05.300
, state land, water, or land and water containing more than 640 acres may be closed to multiple purpose use only by act of the legislature. Because the area described in
AS 41.21.186
exceeds 640 acres,
AS 41.21.185
 41.21.189 are intended to close the described land and water to multiple purpose use in conformity with
AS 38.05.300
and to dedicate them as a special purpose site in accordance with art. VIII, sec. 7, Constitution of the State of Alaska.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-185__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The legislature recognizes the rights of the owners of the private land that adjoins the Afognak Island State Park established in
AS 41.21.185
 41.21.189. The status of the land as a park will not impair the uses to which private land that adjoins the park may be put in the future.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-186">
            <num>41.21.186</num>
            <heading>Afognak Island State Park established.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.186.   Afognak Island State Park established.
The upland, shoreland, tideland, land underlying tidally influenced inland water, and water overlying this land, including both the surface and subsurface estate, owned or acquired by the state within the following described parcels are established as the Afognak Island State Park:
(1) Township 21 South, Range 16 West, Seward Meridian according to the United States of America, Department of the Interior, Bureau of Land Management plat accepted December 6, 1989, and filed December 22, 1989
Section 19: Lots 1  3
Sections 30  31: (fractional) all;
(2) Township 22 South, Range 16 West, Seward Meridian according to the United States of America, Department of the Interior, Bureau of Land Management plat accepted December 6, 1989, and filed December 22, 1989
Section 6: (fractional) all
Section 7: Lots 1  2
Sections 18  19: (fractional) all
Section 31: (fractional) all;
(3) Township 20 South, Range 17 West, Seward Meridian according to the United States of America, Department of the Interior, Bureau of Land Management plat accepted December 6, 1989, and filed December 22, 1989
Section 32: (fractional) all;
(4) Township 21 South, Range 17 West, Seward Meridian according to the United States of America, Department of the Interior, Bureau of Land Management plat accepted December 6, 1989, and filed December 22, 1989
Sections 6  8: (fractional) all
Section 13: (fractional) all
Section 17: (fractional) all
Section 18: all
Sections 19  20: (fractional) all
Sections 23  24: (fractional) all
Section 25: all
Section 26: (fractional) all
Sections 29  31: (fractional) all
Sections 33  35: (fractional) all
Section 36: all;
(5) Township 22 South, Range 17 West, Seward Meridian according to the United States of America, Department of the Interior, Bureau of Land Management plat accepted December 6, 1989, and filed December 22, 1989
Section 1: all
Sections 2  5: (fractional) all
Sections 8  9: (fractional) all
Section 11: all
Section 12: (fractional) all
Sections 13  14: all
Section 17: (fractional) all
Sections 19  20: (fractional) all
Section 23: all
Sections 24  25: (fractional) all
Sections 26  29: all
Sections 30  31: (fractional) all
Sections 32  35: all
Section 36: (fractional) all;
(6) All of Township 23 South, Range 17 West, Seward Meridian according to the United States of America, Department of the Interior, Bureau of Land Management plat accepted December 6, 1989, and filed December 22, 1989; and the supplemental plat for Section 3 accepted April 11, 1990, and filed April 19, 1990, and the supplemental plat for Section 19 accepted November 9, 1990, and filed November 23, 1990;
(7) Township 21 South, Range 18 West, Seward Meridian according to the United States of America, Department of the Interior, Bureau of Land Management plat accepted December 6, 1989, and filed December 22, 1989
Section 1: Lots 1  3
Sections 11  12: (fractional) all
Section 13: all
Section 14: (fractional) all
Section 15: Lots 1 and 2
Section 16: Lots 1 and 2
Section 17: Lot 1, excepting the property described as follows:
Commencing at the monument set for the northwest corner of Section 6, Township 21 South, Range 18 West, Seward Meridian, proceed South a distance of 10,560 feet along the westerly boundaries of Sections 6 and 7; thence proceed East along the section line common to Sections 7 and 18 a distance of 4,999 feet, more or less, to the protracted section corner common to Sections 7, 8, 17, and 18, said corner being the True Point of Beginning; thence continuing East a distance of 1,320 feet along the north boundary of Lot 1 of Section 17; thence South a distance of 2,640 feet; thence West a distance of 1,320 feet, more or less, to the westerly boundary of Lot 1 of Section 17; thence North a distance of 2,640 feet, more or less, along the westerly boundary of said Lot 1 of Section 17 to the True Point of Beginning; the foregoing exception having an area of 80 acres, more or les
Section 17: Lot 2: all
Sections 20  22: (fractional) all
Sections 23  29: all
Sections 31  36: all;
(8) Township 22 South, Range 18 West, Seward Meridian according to the United States of America, Department of the Interior, Bureau of Land Management plat accepted December 6, 1989, and filed December 22, 1989
Section 36: Lot 2;
(9) Township 23 South, Range 18 West, Seward Meridian according to the United States of America, Department of the Interior, Bureau of Land Management plat accepted December 6, 1989, and filed December 22, 1989
Section 1: Lot 1
Section 12: Lot 1
Section 13: Lots 1, 2, and 3
Sections 24  25: (fractional) all;
(10) Township 21 South, Range 19 West, Seward Meridian according to the United States of America, Department of the Interior, Bureau of Land Management plat accepted December 6, 1989, and filed December 22, 1989
Sections 35  36: all
All of plat no. 93-40 within portions of Sections 26, 27, and 34, as filed in the Kodiak Recording District October 19, 1993;
(11) All of Alaska Tideland Survey No. 1474.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-187">
            <num>41.21.187</num>
            <heading>Designation of management responsibility.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-187__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The state land and water described in
AS 41.21.186
is assigned to the department as a unit of the state park system for control, maintenance, and development consistent with the purposes and provisions of
AS 41.21.185
 41.21.189.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-187__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Fish and Game is responsible for the management of fish and game resources in the Afognak Island State Park, consistent with the sustained yield principle and the purposes and provisions of this chapter. The Board of Fisheries, the Board of Game, and the commissioner of fish and game are responsible for adopting regulations governing uses of fish and game in accordance with
AS 16
. The fish and game habitat and breeding areas shall be managed to ensure that the fish and game resources of the park and habitat are maintained or enhanced.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-187__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Natural Resources shall consult with the Department of Fish and Game before adoption of regulations governing public use of the Afognak Island State Park.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-187__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Board of Fisheries, the Board of Game, and the commissioner of fish and game shall consult with the Department of Natural Resources before adoption of regulations governing fish and game use in the Afognak Island State Park.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-187__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Regulations under this section shall be adopted under
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-187__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Public Safety and the Department of Fish and Game shall have necessary access to the Afognak Island State Park for fish and game management, research, and enforcement purposes.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-188">
            <num>41.21.188</num>
            <heading>Incompatible uses.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-188__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner may designate by regulation incompatible uses within the land and water of the Afognak Island State Park.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-188__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Lawful use of a weapon in the Afognak Island State Park shall be allowed except in areas that may be closed for purposes of public safety by regulation by the commissioner.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-188__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The regulations governing public use of the Afognak Island State Park must provide reasonable access for lawful sport and subsistence hunting and fishing, personal use fishing, trapping, recreational uses, and commercial fishing. Except to protect public safety, the commissioner may not restrict the exercise of sport or subsistence hunting or fishing, personal use fishing, trapping, or commercial fishing permitted under law or under a regulation of the Board of Fisheries or the Board of Game within the Afognak Island State Park.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-188__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner may not designate as an incompatible use a use permitted by the Afognak Island Road Use Agreement executed on July 24, 1991, as amended.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-189">
            <num>41.21.189</num>
            <heading>Additions to park.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.189.   Additions to park.
Land and water outside of the boundaries established under
AS 41.21.186
may be added to the Afognak Island State Park only by an act of the legislature. The commissioner may acquire land and water within the boundaries of the Afognak Island State Park except by eminent domain.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-190">
            <num>41.21.190</num>
            <heading>Purpose ofAS 41.21.190 41.21.194.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.190.   Purpose of
AS 41.21.190
 41.21.194.
The purpose of
AS 41.21.190
 41.21.194 is to establish, subject to valid existing rights, the state-owned or acquired land and water described in
AS 41.21.191
as the Fort Rousseau Causeway State Historical Park. The primary purposes of establishing the land and water areas described in
AS 41.21.191
as the Fort Rousseau Causeway State Historical Park are to promote, support, and preserve public use by maintaining and protecting the area's fish and wildlife habitat, cultural resources, and scenic values.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-191">
            <num>41.21.191</num>
            <heading>Fort Rousseau Causeway State Historical Park established.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.191.   Fort Rousseau Causeway State Historical Park established.
Except for upland, shoreland, tideland, and water overlying the land lying northeasterly of a line running parallel to and 1100 feet offset southwesterly from the runway centerline of the Sitka Airport, the upland, shoreland, tideland, and water overlying the land owned or acquired by the state within the following described parcels are established as the Fort Rousseau Causeway State Historical Park:
Township 56 South, Range 63 East, Copper River Meridian, described as:
The following lots located within United States Survey 3926:
Section 2: That portion of Lot 86 within Section 2
That portion of Lot 86A within Section 2
That portion of Lot 90 within Section 2
Lot 91
Lot 92
Section 3: E1/2SE1/4NW1/4NE1/4NW1/4
E1/2NE1/4SW1/4NE1/4NW1/4
NW1/4SE1/4NE1/4NW1/4
SW1/4NE1/4NE1/4NW1/4
Lot 74
Lot 75
Lot 75A
Lot 76
That portion of Lot 77 within Section 3
Lot 78
Lot 78A
Lot 79
Lot 80
Lot 80A
Lot 81
Lot 81A
Lot 82
Lot 82A
That portion of Lot 83 within Section 3
Lot 84
Lot 84A
Lot 85
Lot 85A
That portion of Lot 86 within Section 3
That portion of Lot 86A within Section 3
Lot 87
Lot 88
Lot 89
That portion of Lot 90 within Section 3
Section 4: That portion of Lot 77 within Section 4
That portion of Lot 83 within Section 4.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-192">
            <num>41.21.192</num>
            <heading>Designation of management responsibility.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.192.   Designation of management responsibility.
The state-owned land and water described in
AS 41.21.191
is assigned to the department for control, maintenance, and development consistent with the purposes and provisions of
AS 41.21.190
 41.21.194.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-193">
            <num>41.21.193</num>
            <heading>Incompatible uses.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.193.   Incompatible uses.
The commissioner may designate by regulation incompatible uses within the land and water of the Fort Rousseau Causeway State Historical Park.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-194">
            <num>41.21.194</num>
            <heading>Additions to park.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.194.   Additions to park.
Land and water outside of the boundaries established under
AS 41.21.191
may be added to the Fort Rousseau Causeway State Historical Park only by an act of the legislature.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-300">
            <num>41.21.300</num>
            <heading>Declaration of purpose.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-300__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The purpose of
AS 41.21.300
 41.21.306 is to establish, subject to valid existing rights, the state-owned or acquired land and water described in
AS 41.21.304
as marine park units of the Alaska state park system.  The primary purposes in establishing the land and water areas described in
AS 41.21.304
as marine park units of the Alaska state park system are to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-300__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>maintain natural, cultural, and scenic values;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-300__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>maintain fish and wildlife resources and lawful existing uses of these resources;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-300__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>promote and support recreation and tourism in the state.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-300__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The land and water described in
AS 41.21.304
is dedicated as special purpose sites under art. VIII, § 7 of the state constitution.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-302">
            <num>41.21.302</num>
            <heading>Management of marine parks.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-302__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The state land and water described in
AS 41.21.304
is assigned to the department for control, maintenance, and development consistent with the purposes and provisions of
AS 41.21.300
 41.21.306.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-302__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Fish and Game is responsible for the management of fish and game resources on the state land and water described in
AS 41.21.304
consistent with the purposes of
AS 41.21.300
 41.21.306.  The Department of Fish and Game shall give written notice to and consult with the department before adoption of regulations governing fish and game management in a marine park unit of the Alaska state park system.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-302__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall develop a management plan for each marine park unit of the Alaska state park system to determine the specific purposes and uses for the unit.  The commissioner shall give written notice and consult with the Department of Fish and Game, proximately located municipalities of the state, proximately located private landowners, the United States Forest Service, organizations concerned with conservation, recreation, and tourism, and other interested parties during the preparation of a management plan for a marine park unit of the Alaska state park system.  A management plan required under this subsection shall be completed by June 14, 1995, for each marine park unit established before June 14, 1990, and within five years of the establishment of the unit for units established after June 13, 1990.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-302__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner may not prohibit fishing, hunting, or trapping within a marine park unit of the Alaska state park system. The commissioner may not restrict the exercise of fishing, hunting, or trapping rights permitted under law or under a regulation of the Board of Fisheries or the Board of Game within a marine park unit of the Alaska state park system.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-302__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall allow the development of aquaculture facilities within a marine park unit of the Alaska state park system under terms and conditions that ensure that the development is compatible with
AS 41.21.300
 41.21.306.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-302__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner may enter into a cooperative agreement for</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-302__subsec_f__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the management of a marine park unit of the Alaska state park system with a federal agency, a municipality of the state, or a proximately located private landowner for a purpose stated under
AS 41.21.020</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-302__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the management of proximately located federal, municipal, or private land as part of a marine park unit of the Alaska state park system.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-302__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In the management of a marine park unit of the Alaska state park system the commissioner shall consult and cooperate with a Native corporation that owns an historical or cultural site granted under 43 U.S.C. 1613(h)(1) (sec. 14(h)(1) of the Alaska Native Claims Settlement Act) and that is proximately located to a marine park unit of the Alaska state park system.  In the management of a marine park unit of the Alaska state park system the commissioner shall address the potential conflicts with the cultural and historical values of land granted to a Native corporation under 43 U.S.C. 1613(h)(1) (sec. 14(h)(1) of the Alaska Native Claims Settlement Act) and shall provide for appropriate protection to these values.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-302__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing in
AS 41.21.300
 41.21.306 precludes the use of or access to land proximately located to a marine park unit of the Alaska state park system or to mineral claims and leases. The commissioner shall permit adequate and feasible access across state land within a marine park unit of the Alaska state park system to and from private and public land within or outside a unit.  In the granting of such access the commissioner may adopt reasonable regulations to protect the natural and other values of the marine park unit land and water.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-302__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner may enter into a concession contract under
AS 41.21.027
and
AS 36
to provide services or construct facilities in a marine park unit of the Alaska state park system.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-304">
            <num>41.21.304</num>
            <heading>Designated land and water.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-304__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Beginning at Corner No. 4, Lone Star Lode claim, U.S. Mineral Survey No. (M.S.) 1492 proceed N. 70 degrees 00 feet E. along the north boundary of said claim a distance of 359.15 feet more or less to Corner No. 3, Otter Lode claim, M.S. 1492; thence N. 5 degrees 50 feet E. a distance of 666.60 feet more or less along the west boundary of the Otter Lode claim to Corner No. 4 of said claim; thence N. 70 degrees 00 feet E. a distance of 1,500.00 feet more or less along the north boundary of the Otter Lode claim, M.S. 1492 to Corner No. 1 of said claim, said Corner being common to Corner No. 2, Mill Site claim, M.S. 2191; thence N. 5 degrees 27 feet W. to an intersect with the southwest boundary of ISH NIC claim, M.S. 2191; thence N. 44 degrees 00 feet W. along said boundary to Corner No. 4 of ISH NIC claim; thence N. 46 degrees 00 feet E. along the northwest boundary of ISH NIC claim a distance of 321.62 feet more or less to Corner No. 3 of Beach No. 4 claim, M.S. 2191, common with Corner No. 2 of Beach No. 1 claim, M.S. 2191; thence N. 44 degrees 00 feet W. along the southwest boundary of Beach No. 4 claim a distance of 600.00 feet more or less to Corner No. 4 of Beach No. 4 claim; thence N. 46 degrees 00 feet E. along the northwest boundary of Beach No. 4 claim a distance of 1,099.47 feet more or less to Corner No. 1 of Beach No. 4 claim, common with Corner No. 1 of Beach No. 5 claim, M.S. 2191; thence N. 44 degrees 00 feet W. along the southwest boundaries of Beach No's. 6 and 7 claims, M.S. 2191 a distance of 1,200.00 feet more or less to Corner No. 1 of Beach No. 7 claim; thence N. 46 degrees 00 feet E. along the northwest boundary of Beach No. 7 claim a distance of 135.10 feet more or less to Corner No. 4 U.S. Survey No. (U.S.S.) 3149; thence continue N. 46 degrees 00 feet E. along the northwest boundaries of Beach No's. 7 and 8 claims, M.S. 2191 a distance of 2,864.90 feet more or less to Corner No. 2, Beach No. 8 claim; thence due west a distance of 3,300 feet m</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-304__subsec_v">
              <num>(v)</num>
              <content>
                <p>That portion of Beach No. 3, Mineral Survey (M.S.) No. 2191, described as follows: beginning at Corner No. 1, Beach No. 3, thence N. 70 degrees 00 feet E., 637.07 feet, along a portion of line 1-2, to the intersection of line 1-4, Beach No. 7, M.S. 2191; thence S. 44 degrees 00 feet E., 279.27 feet, along a portion of line 1-4 of Beach No. 7, to Corner No. 4, Beach No. 7, identical to Corner No. 1, Beach No. 6, M.S. 2191, thence continue S. 44 degrees 00 feet E., 376.60 feet, along a portion of line 1-4 of Beach No. 6, to the intersection of line 3-4, Beach No. 3; thence S. 70 degrees 00 feet W., 1,139.45 feet, along a portion of line 3-4 of Beach No. 3, to Corner No. 4, Beach No. 3; thence N. 1 degree 30 feet E., 644.00 feet, along the mean-high tide line of Funter Bay, on line 4-1, to Corner No. 1, Beach No. 3, to point of beginning. Containing 12.22 acres.
Section 2:  W1/2
Section 3:  S1/2 SW1/4, NW1/4 SW1/4
Section 4:  S1/2 NE1/4, E1/2 SE1/4
Section 10:  N1/2 N1/2, S1/2 NE1/4
Section 11:  NW1/4, NW1/4 NE1/4, including all tide and submerged land;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-304__subsec_v__subsec_15">
                <num>(15)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Joe Mace Island
Township 64 South, Range 75 East, Copper River Meridian Lot 4, U.S. Survey 3854 and adjacent tideland;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-304__subsec_v__subsec_16">
                <num>(16)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Thoms Place
Township 65 South, Range 86 East, Copper River Meridian
Section 32:  S1/2
Township 66 South, Range 86 East, Copper River Meridian
Section 4:  SW1/4, S1/2 NW1/4, NW1/4 NW1/4, S1/2 SE1/4, NW1/4SE1/4
Section 5:  All except for land within ASLS 81-234
Section 8:  NE1/4
Section 9:  N1/2, SE1/4;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-304__subsec_v__subsec_17">
                <num>(17)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Beecher Pass
Township 61 South, Range 79 East, Copper River Meridian
Section 1:  NE1/4SW1/4, Lots 5  8
Section 10:  Lots 1  2, including all adjacent tideland
Section 11:  Lots 1  11, including all adjacent tideland
Section 12:  Lots 3  11, including all adjacent tideland
Section 14:  Lot 2, including all adjacent tideland
Section 15:  Lot 1, including all adjacent tideland
Township 61 South, Range 80 East, Copper River Meridian
Section 6:  Lot 11, including all adjacent tideland
Section 7: Lots 1  2, including all adjacent tideland;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-304__subsec_v__subsec_18">
                <num>(18)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Dall Bay
Township 77 South, Range 91 East, Copper River Meridian
Section 29:  W1/2 SW1/4, SW1/4 NW1/4
Section 30:  SE1/4, E1/2 SW1/4
Section 31:  NE1/4, N1/2 SE1/4, NE1/4 SW1/4, E1/2 NW1/4 subject to USS 3525 and A.T.S. 155
Section 32:  NW1/4, N1/2 SW1/4;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-304__subsec_v__subsec_19">
                <num>(19)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Security Bay
Township 58 South, Range 70 East, Copper River Meridian
Section 1:  SW1/4 SW1/4
Section 2:  S1/2
Section 11:  N1/2, SE1/4, E1/2 SW1/4
Section 12:  W1/2 W1/2, E1/2 SW1/4 subject to Forest Service Preference 103521
Section 13:  All subject to Historic Place Application AA-6569, Parcel A
Section 14:  NE1/4;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-304__subsec_v__subsec_20">
                <num>(20)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Boswell Bay Beaches
Township 17 South, Range 5 West, Copper River Meridian
Section 10:  Above the mean high tide line
Section 15:  Above the mean high tide line, except South of Point Bentinck South of a line bearing South 68 degrees East, below the mean high tide line
Sections 19  22;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-304__subsec_v__subsec_21">
                <num>(21)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Canoe Passage
Township 15 South, Range 5 West, Copper River Meridian
Section 31:  E1/2E1/2
Section 32
Township 16 South, Range 4 West, Copper River Meridian
Section 6:  S1/2, S1/2N1/2
Township 16 South, Range 5 West, Copper River Meridian
Section 3:  The land South and West of the mid-channel of Canoe Passage
Section 4:  The land and water south of the mid-channel of Canoe Passage in N1/2
Section 5:  N1/2N1/2, SE1/4NE1/4
Section 10: N1/2NE1/4
Sections 11  12: N1/2N1/2;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-304__subsec_v__subsec_22">
                <num>(22)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Decision Point
Township 8 North, Range 6 East, Seward Meridian
Section 5: SW1/4SW1/4
Section 6:  S1/2S1/2
Section 7:  N1/2, N1/2S1/2
Section 8:  W1/2NW1/4, NW1/4SW1/4;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-304__subsec_v__subsec_23">
                <num>(23)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Driftwood Bay
Township 3 South, Range 1 East, Seward Meridian
Section 14:  SW1/4
Section 15
Section 16:  E1/2E1/2
Section 21:  NE1/4NE1/4
Section 22:  N1/2
Section 23: NW1/4;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-304__subsec_v__subsec_24">
                <num>(24)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Entry Cove
Township 8 North, Range 6 East, Seward Meridian
Section 2:  S1/2
Section 3:  SE1/4, S1/2SW1/4
Sections 10  11: N1/2;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-304__subsec_v__subsec_25">
                <num>(25)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Granite Bay
Township 9 North, Range 8 East, Seward Meridian
Sections 4  6:  S1/2
Sections 7  8
Section 9:  N1/2, SW1/4
Section 17: W1/2W1/2
Section 18:  E1/2, E1/2NW1/4;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-304__subsec_v__subsec_26">
                <num>(26)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Kayak Island
Township 22 South, Range 5 East, Copper River Meridian
Section 25
Section 36:  N1/2, SW1/4, W1/2SE1/4
Township 22 South, Range 6 East, Copper River Meridian
Section 16:  N1/2, SW1/4, N1/2SE1/4, SW1/4SE1/4
Section 20
Section 21:  NW1/4, NW1/4SW1/4
Section 29:  NW1/4
Section 30:  W1/2
Township 23 South, Range 5 East, Copper River Meridian
Section 1: N1/2NW1/4, SW1/4NW1/4
Section 2
Sections 10  11;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-304__subsec_v__subsec_27">
                <num>(27)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Jack Bay
Township 9 South, Range 7 West, Copper River Meridian
Section 31:  S1/2SW1/4
Township 9 South, Range 8 West, Copper River Meridian
Section 35:  SE1/4SE1/4
Section 36:  S1/2S1/2
Township 10 South, Range 7 West, Copper River Meridian
Section 6:  N1/2NW1/4
Township 10 South, Range 8 West, Copper River Meridian
Section 1
Section 2:  N1/2, N1/2N1/2S1/2
Section 3: NE1/4NE1/4
Section 12:  E1/2NE1/4, E1/2W1/2NE1/4;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-304__subsec_v__subsec_28">
                <num>(28)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Safety Cove
Township 2 South, Range 1 East, Seward Meridian
Section 23:  S1/2
Section 24:  SW1/4
Section 25:  NW1/4
Section 26: N1/2;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-304__subsec_v__subsec_29">
                <num>(29)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Sandspit Point
Township 3 South, Range 1 East, Seward Meridian
Section 5:  SW1/4, S1/2SE1/4
Section 8:  N1/2;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-304__subsec_v__subsec_30">
                <num>(30)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Sunny Cove
Township 3 South, Range 1 East, Seward Meridian
Section 19
Section 20:  W1/2W1/2
Township 3 South, Range 1 West, Seward Meridian
Section 24:  E1/2E1/2;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-304__subsec_v__subsec_31">
                <num>(31)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Thumb Cove
Township 2 South, Range 1 East, Seward Meridian
Section 16:  W1/2, W1/2NE1/4
Section 17:  E1/2;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-304__subsec_v__subsec_32">
                <num>(32)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Magoun Islands
Township 54 South, Range 62 East, Copper River Meridian
Section 20:  S1/2NE1/4, SE1/4
Section 21: Excluding Krestof Island
Section 22: W1/2SW1/4, excluding Krestof Island
Section 28:  N1/2, N1/2SW1/4, excluding Krestof Island
Section 29
Section 32:  N1/2, N1/2S1/2;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-304__subsec_v__subsec_33">
                <num>(33)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Big Bear/Baby Bear Bays
Township 51 South, Range 61 East, Copper River Meridian
Section 13:  S1/2N1/2, S1/2
Section 14: SE1/4SE1/4
Section 23: E1/2
Section 24:  W1/2E1/2, W1/2
Section 25:  NW1/4NE1/4, NW1/4, NW1/4SW1/4
Section 26:  N1/2, N1/2S1/2.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-304__subsec_v__subsec_34">
                <num>(34)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Juneau Area Islands: Aaron, Battleship, Benjamin, Bird, Coghlan, Cohen, Gull, Indian, Lincoln, Little, North, Portland, Ralston, and Suedla Islands: the following described parcels excluding submerged land seaward of the 10 fathom bathymetric line:
Township 38 South, Range 63 East, Copper River Meridian
Section 13
Section 24: E1/2NE1/4
Section 32:  E1/2
Section 33:  SW1/4
Township 38 South, Range 64 East, Copper River Meridian
Section 18:  SW1/4
Section 19
Section 20:  W1/2SW1/4
Section 29:  NW1/4NW1/4
Section 30:  N1/2
Township 39 South, Range 63 East, Copper River Meridian
Section 4
Section 9
Section 10
Section 11
Section 13:  E1/2
Section 14
Section 15
Section 16:  E1/2
Section 22:  N1/2
Section 23
Section 24
Township 39 South, Range 64 East, Copper River Meridian
Section 8:  SE1/4
Section 9:  SW1/4
Section 16
Section 17:  NE1/4
Section 18: S1/2
Section 19
Section 20: SW1/4
Section 30: except for USS 354
Section 34:  S1/2
Township 40 South, Range 64 East, Copper River Meridian
Section 1:  W1/2NW1/4
Section 3:  NE1/4
Section 4
Section 5
Section 9
Section 10
Section 15
Section 16
Section 17: NE1/4
Section 36: SE1/4SE1/4
Township 40 South, Range 65 East, Copper River Meridian
Section 28: SW1/4
Section 31:  SW1/4SW1/4
Section 32:  E1/2
Section 33:  W1/2
Section 34: W1/2E1/2, W1/2
Township 41 South, Range 65 East, Copper River Meridian
Section 1:  NE1/4
Section 2:  W1/2NW1/4, SW1/4
Section 3:  NE1/4
Section 11
Township 41 South, Range 66 East, Copper River Meridian
Section 5: NW1/2NW1/4, NW1/4NW1/4NE1/4
Section 6:  NW1/4.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-306">
            <num>41.21.306</num>
            <heading>Incompatible uses.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-306__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner may prohibit or restrict by regulation except as provided in
AS 41.21.302</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-306__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>incompatible uses within the state-owned land and water described in
AS 41.21.304
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-306__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 2 ch 126 SLA 1984.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-306__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing in
AS 41.21.300
  41.21.306 prohibits the Department of Fish and Game from engaging in rehabilitation, enhancement, and development under
AS 16.05.092
within an area described in
AS 41.21.304
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-306__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Reasonable access shall be permitted to and across a marine park unit of the Alaska state park system for lawful hunting, fishing, trapping and recreational purposes, and other lawful purposes.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-306__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Public Safety and the Department of Fish and Game shall be allowed reasonable access for fish and game management, research, and enforcement purposes.
Article 4. State Recreation Areas.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-410">
            <num>41.21.410</num>
            <heading>Purpose ofAS 41.21.410 41.21.426.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.410.   Purpose of
AS 41.21.410
 41.21.426.
The purpose of
AS 41.21.410
 41.21.426 is to empower the governor to restrict state owned land and water described in
AS 41.21.415
, except as provided in
AS 41.21.426
, to use as a public recreation area. Under
AS 38.05.300
, state land, water, or land and water containing more than 640 acres may be closed to multiple purpose use only by act of the legislature. Because the area described in
AS 41.21.415
exceeds 640 acres,
AS 41.21.410
 41.21.426 are intended to provide for the closing of the land and water described in
AS 41.21.415
, as that description is modified by
AS 41.21.426
, to multiple purpose use in conformity with
AS 38.05.300
and its subsequent designation as a special purpose site in accordance with art. VIII, sec. 7, of the Constitution of the State of Alaska.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-415">
            <num>41.21.415</num>
            <heading>Authority to designate Captain Cook State Recreation Area.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.415.   Authority to designate Captain Cook State Recreation Area.
The governor may designate by proclamation the state-owned land and water and all that acquired in the future by the state, lying within the parcels described in this section, as the Captain Cook State Recreation Area.  The proclamation may include the entire area or portions of the area at different times, shall reserve the areas included from all uses incompatible with their primary function as public recreation land and water, and shall assign them to the department for control, development and maintenance.  Land covered by
AS 41.21.410
 41.21.425 is that within the following described parcels:
Township 8 North, Range 10 West, Seward Meridian
Section 3
Section 9
Section 10: NW1/4, NE1/4, SW1/4, W1/2 SE1/4
Section 15: W1/2 W1/2
Sections 16 and 17
All tideland abutting the above and all of Stormy Lake.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-420">
            <num>41.21.420</num>
            <heading>Incompatible uses.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.420.   Incompatible uses.
The commissioner shall designate by regulation incompatible uses within the boundaries of the Captain Cook State Recreation Area in accordance with
AS 41.21.410
, and those incompatible uses designated shall be prohibited or restricted, as provided by regulation.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-425">
            <num>41.21.425</num>
            <heading>Negotiated purchase authorized.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.425.   Negotiated purchase authorized.
The commissioner may acquire, by negotiated purchase only in the name of the state, title to or interest in real property lying within the boundaries of the Captain Cook State Recreation Area.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-426">
            <num>41.21.426</num>
            <heading>Certain land excepted.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-426__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding
AS 41.21.020
(a)(6), 41.21.410  41.21.425, or a regulation issued implementing
AS 41.21.420
, state-owned land in the following described parcels may be leased in accordance with
AS 38.35
(Right-of-Way Leasing Act) for the purpose of construction and operation of a natural gas pipeline from the North Slope:
Township 8 North, Range 10 West, Seward Meridian
Section 3: SE1/4
Section 9: SE1/4
Section 10: N1/2, SW1/4, W1/2SE1/4
Section 15: W1/2W1/2
Section 16
Section 17: S1/2, S1/2NE1/4.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-426__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A state or federal survey does not remove land from the parcels described in (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-426__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall manage any state-owned land described in this section and within the exterior boundaries of Captain Cook State Recreation Area as part of Captain Cook State Recreation Area until the land is leased under
AS 38.35
. State-owned land described in this section will revert to Captain Cook State Recreation Area upon release of the land from a right-of-way through termination of the lease or otherwise and upon satisfaction of the lessee's obligations to restore and revegetate the land.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-426__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Any right-of-way lease issued under
AS 38.35
across land described in this section and within the exterior boundaries of Captain Cook State Recreation Area must</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-426__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>reserve to the state the interests necessary to provide for public access by foot, snow machine, dog sled, and other traditional means of access along and across the leased corridor;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-426__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>preserve, to the maximum extent practicable, the recreational, scenic, cultural, historical, and habitat values consistent with the leasehold's location within the exterior boundaries of Captain Cook State Recreation Area; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-426__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide for termination of the lease if construction of the pipeline has not begun 10 years after the effective date of the lease.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-426__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>AS 38.35.130
does not apply to land within the exterior boundaries of Captain Cook State Recreation Area.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-426__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A natural gas pipeline right-of-way lease may not be issued across land described in this section unless the lease becomes effective before January 1, 2025.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-430">
            <num>41.21.430</num>
            <heading>Purpose ofAS 41.21.430 41.21.445.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.430.   Purpose of
AS 41.21.430
 41.21.445.
The purpose of
AS 41.21.430
 41.21.445 is to empower the governor to restrict state-owned land and water described in
AS 41.21.435
to use as a public recreation area.  Under
AS 38.05.300
, state land, water, or land and water containing more than 640 acres may be closed to multiple purpose use only by act of the legislature. Because the area described in
AS 41.21.435
exceeds 640 acres,
AS 41.21.430
 41.21.445 are intended to provide for the closing of the described land and water to multiple purpose use in conformity with
AS 38.05.300
and its subsequent designation as a special purpose site in accordance with art. VIII, § 7, of the Constitution of the State of Alaska.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-435">
            <num>41.21.435</num>
            <heading>Authority to designate Caines Head State Recreation Area.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.435.   Authority to designate Caines Head State Recreation Area.
The governor may designate by proclamation the state-owned land and water and all that acquired in the future by the state, lying within the parcels described in this section, as the Caines Head State Recreation Area.  The proclamation may include the entire area or portions of the area at different times, shall reserve the areas included from all uses incompatible with their primary function as public recreation land and water, and shall assign them to the department for control, development and maintenance.  Land covered by (1)  (4) of this section has a total acreage of 1801.11 acres, including approximately 221.11 acres of federal land.  Land covered by (5) of this section has a total acreage of approximately 4,160 acres.  Land covered by
AS 41.21.430
 41.21.445 is that within the following described parcels:
(1) U.S.S. 2742: portions of Sections 22 and 27 T2S, R1W, Seward Meridian;
(2) U.S.S. 2744: in Section 14 T2S, R1W, Seward Meridian;
(3) U.S.S. 4830: portions of Sections 14, 23 and 24 T2S, R1W, Seward Meridian (E.O. 3406 Lighthouse Reserve);
(4) Section 10 T2S, R1W, Seward Meridian E1/2; Section 11 T2S, R1W, Seward Meridian SW1/4; Section 14 T2S, R1W, Seward Meridian NW1/4, SW1/4, SE1/4 and portions of NE1/4 above mean low tide; Section 15 T2S, R1W, Seward Meridian E1/2; Section 22 T2S, R1W, Seward Meridian E1/2; Section 23 T2S, R1W, Seward Meridian NW1/4, NE1/4 and portions of SW1/4 above mean low tide and portions of SE1/4 above mean low tide; Section 24 T2S, R1W, Seward Meridian W1/2 portion above mean low tide; Section 27 T2S, R1W, Seward Meridian N1/2, NE1/4 above mean low tide;
(5) Section 9, T2S, R1W, Seward Meridian; Section 10, T2S, R1W, Seward Meridian, West 1/2; Section 15, T2S, R1W, Seward Meridian, West 1/2; Section 16, T2S, R1W, Seward Meridian; Section 21, T2S, R1W, Seward Meridian; Section 22, T2S, R1W, Seward Meridian, West 1/2; Section 27, T2S, R1W, Seward Meridian; Section 28, T2S, R1W, Seward Meridian.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-440">
            <num>41.21.440</num>
            <heading>Incompatible uses.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.440.   Incompatible uses.
The commissioner shall designate by regulation incompatible uses within the boundaries of the Caines Head State Recreation Area in accordance with
AS 41.21.435
, and those incompatible uses designated are prohibited or restricted, as provided by regulation.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-445">
            <num>41.21.445</num>
            <heading>Purchase authorized; eminent domain prohibited.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.445.   Purchase authorized; eminent domain prohibited.
The commissioner may acquire, by purchase in the name of the state, title to or interest in real property lying within the boundaries of the Caines Head State Recreation Area.  The state may not acquire by eminent domain privately owned land for inclusion in the Caines Head State Recreation Area.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-450">
            <num>41.21.450</num>
            <heading>Purpose ofAS 41.21.450 41.21.466.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.450.   Purpose of
AS 41.21.450
 41.21.466.
The purpose of
AS 41.21.450
 41.21.466 is to restrict state-owned land and water within the boundaries described in
AS 41.21.455
, except as provided in
AS 41.21.466
, to use as a public recreation area. Under the provisions of
AS 38.05.300
, state land, water, or land and water containing more than 640 acres may be closed to multiple purpose use only by act of the legislature. Inasmuch as the area described in
AS 41.21.455
exceeds 640 acres,
AS 41.21.450
 41.21.466 are intended to except the area described in
AS 41.21.455
, as that description is modified by
AS 41.21.466
, from the provisions of
AS 38.05.300
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-455">
            <num>41.21.455</num>
            <heading>Nancy Lake State Recreation Area established.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-455__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The presently state-owned land and water and all that acquired in the future by the state, lying within the following described boundary, are hereby designated as the Nancy Lake State Recreation Area, are reserved from all uses incompatible with their primary function as public recreation land, and are assigned to the department for control, development, and maintenance:
Beginning at the brass capped monument marking the one quarter corner position, common to Section 34 and Section 35, Township 19 North, Range 5 West, Seward Meridian, Alaska, which is the true point of beginning; thence easterly along the 1/4 line of Section 35 to the west shore of an unnamed lake; thence meandering said lake clockwise in a northerly and southerly direction to a point where said meanders intersect the east-west 1/4 line of Section 35; thence easterly along the 1/4 line of Section 35 to the west shore of an unnamed lake; thence meandering said lake clockwise in a northerly and easterly direction to a point where said meanders intersect the east-west 1/4 line of Section 35; thence easterly along the 1/4 line of Section 35 to the 1/4 corner position common to Section 35 and Section 36; thence southerly along the section line common to Sections 35 and 36 to the common corner between Sections 35 and 36, Township 19 North, Range 5 West, Seward Meridian and Sections 1 and 2, Township 18 North, Range 5 West, Seward Meridian; thence easterly along the common line between said Sections 1 and 36 to the common corner of Section 1, Township 18 North, Range 5 West and Section 36, Township 19 North, Range 5 West and Section 31, Township 19 North, Range 4 West and Section 6, Township 18 North, Range 4 West; thence easterly along the common line between said Sections 31 and 6 to the 1/4 corner position common to Sections 31 and 6; thence northerly along the 1/4 line of Section 31 to the C 1/4 corner positions; thence easterly along the 1/4 line of Section 31 and Section 32 to the C 1/4 corner positi</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-455__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing in this section affects the right of an organized borough to extract gravel from land that is located within the recreation area and that has been selected by the borough before April 22, 1970, under former
AS 07.10.150
 07.10.160.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-460">
            <num>41.21.460</num>
            <heading>Incompatible uses.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.460.   Incompatible uses.
The commissioner shall designate by regulation incompatible uses within the boundaries of the Nancy Lake State Recreation Area in accordance with the requirements of
AS 41.21.450
, and those incompatible uses designated shall be prohibited or restricted, as provided by regulation.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-465">
            <num>41.21.465</num>
            <heading>Purchase authorized.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.465.   Purchase authorized.
The commissioner may acquire, by purchase in the name of the state, title to or interest in real property lying within the boundaries of the Nancy Lake State Recreation Area.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-466">
            <num>41.21.466</num>
            <heading>Certain land excepted.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-466__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding
AS 41.21.020
(a)(6) or 41.21.450  41.21.465, state-owned land in the following described parcels may be leased in accordance with
AS 38.35
(Right-of-Way Leasing Act) for the purpose of construction and operation of a natural gas pipeline from the North Slope:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-466__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 18 North, Range 5 West, Seward Meridian
Section 10: E1/2
Section 11: NW1/4
Section 15: NW1/4
Section 16: SE1/4
Section 21: W1/2;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-466__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 19 North, Range 5 West, Seward Meridian
Section 35: SW1/4.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-466__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A state or federal survey does not remove land from the parcels described in (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-466__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall manage any state-owned land described in this section and within the exterior boundaries of Nancy Lake State Recreation Area as part of Nancy Lake State Recreation Area until the land is leased under
AS 38.35
. State-owned land described in this section will revert to Nancy Lake State Recreation Area upon release of the land from a right-of-way through termination of the lease or otherwise and upon satisfaction of the lessee's obligations to restore and revegetate the land.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-466__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Any right-of-way lease issued under
AS 38.35
across land described in this section and within the exterior boundaries of Nancy Lake State Recreation Area must</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-466__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>reserve to the state the interests necessary to provide for public access by foot, snow machine, dog sled, and other traditional means of access along and across the leased corridor;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-466__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>preserve, to the maximum extent practicable, the recreational, scenic, cultural, historical, and habitat values consistent with the leasehold's location within the exterior boundaries of Nancy Lake State Recreation Area; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-466__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide for termination of the lease if construction of the pipeline has not begun 10 years after the effective date of the lease.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-466__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>AS 38.35.130
does not apply to land within the exterior boundaries of Nancy Lake State Recreation Area.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-466__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A natural gas pipeline right-of-way lease may not be issued across land described in this section unless the lease becomes effective before January 1, 2025.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-470">
            <num>41.21.470</num>
            <heading>Purpose ofAS 41.21.470 41.21.490.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.470.   Purpose of
AS 41.21.470
 41.21.490.
The purpose of
AS 41.21.470
 41.21.490 is to restrict all vacant and unappropriated state-owned land, water, and stream crossings within the boundaries described in
AS 41.21.475
to use as a public recreation area.  Under the provisions of
AS 38.05.300
, state land, water, or land and water containing more than 640 acres may be closed to multiple purpose use only by act of the legislature. Inasmuch as the area described in
AS 41.21.475
exceeds 640 acres,
AS 41.21.470
 41.21.490 are intended to except the area described from the provisions of
AS 38.05.300
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-475">
            <num>41.21.475</num>
            <heading>Chena River State Recreation Area established.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.475.   Chena River State Recreation Area established.
The presently state-owned land and water, vacant and unappropriated, and all that acquired in the future by the state, lying within the following described boundary, are hereby designated as the Chena River State Recreation Area, are reserved from all uses incompatible with their primary function as public recreation land, and are assigned to the department for control, development and maintenance:
(1) Protracted Sections and Townships.  Township 1 North, Range 6 East, Fairbanks Meridian, Section 24; Township 1 North, Range 7 East, Fairbanks Meridian, Sections 1, 2, 3, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 15, 16, 17, 19, 20 and 21; Township 2 North, Range 7 East, Fairbanks Meridian, Sections 12, 13, 24, 25, 35, and 36; Township 2 North, Range 8 East, Fairbanks Meridian, Sections 6, 7, and 18;
(2) Beginning at the N.W. corner of the area designated in (1) of this section, said point being the N.W. corner of Section 6, T2N, R8E, Fairbanks Meridian; thence north along the section line to the N.E. corner of Section 25, T3N, R7E; thence west along the section line to the S.W. corner of the S.E. 1/4 of Section 20, T3N, R7E; thence north along the 1/4 section line to the N.E. corner of the N.W. 1/4, Section 17, T3N, R7E; thence west along the section line to the N.W. corner of Section 16, T3N, R6E; thence south along the section line to the N.W. corner of Section 16, T2N, R6E; thence west along the section line to the N.W. corner of Section 14, T2N, R5E; thence south along the section line to the N.W. corner of Section 23, T1N, R5E; thence west along the section line to the N.W. corner of Section 20, T1N, R5E; thence south along the section line to the S.W. corner of Section 32, T1N, R5E; thence east to the N.W. corner of Section 2, T1S, R5E; thence south along the section line to the S.W. corner of Section 11, T1S, R5E; thence east along the section line to the S.W. corner of Section 10, T1S, R6E; thence south along the section line to the S.W. corner of Section 10, T2S, R6E; thence east along the section line to the S.W. corner of Section 7, T2S, R9E; thence north along the section line to the N.W. corner of Section 6, T1S, R9E; thence east to the S.E. corner of Section 36, T1N, R8E; thence north along the section line to the N.E. corner of Section 12, T2N, R8E; thence west along the section line to the N.E. corner of Section 7, T2N, R8E; thence north along the section line to the N.E. corner of Section 6, T2N, R8E; thence west along the section line to the point of beginning, containing approximately 254,080 acres.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-480">
            <num>41.21.480</num>
            <heading>Eminent domain authorized to acquire necessary access.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.480.   Eminent domain authorized to acquire necessary access.
The state may not acquire by eminent domain privately owned land within the Chena River State Recreation Area unless it is for the purpose of providing necessary access to state land.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-485">
            <num>41.21.485</num>
            <heading>Zoning of private land.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.485.   Zoning of private land.
The department may adopt, in accordance with
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act), zoning regulations governing privately owned land in the Chena River State Recreation Area.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-490">
            <num>41.21.490</num>
            <heading>Incompatible uses.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.490.   Incompatible uses.
The commissioner shall designate by regulation incompatible uses within the boundaries of the Chena River State Recreation Area in accordance with the requirements of
AS 41.21.020
(a)(13) and 41.21.470, and those incompatible uses designated shall be prohibited or restricted, as provided by regulation.  The regulations may not prohibit
(1) work on valid mineral leases or mining claims;
(2) the legal taking of fur-bearing animals;
(3) the traditional use of roads and trails by any means of transportation, including a vehicle propelled by machinery, if the use occurred regularly in the area of the state recreation area before June 18, 1967;
(4) the cutting of dead and down or burnt timber.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-491">
            <num>41.21.491</num>
            <heading>Willow Creek State Recreation Area.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-491__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The surface estate in the land and water owned by the state as of June 9, 1987, and all land and water acquired by the state in the future, including shore and submerged land, lying within the parcels described in this subsection is designated as the Willow Creek State Recreation Area:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-491__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 19 North, Range 4 West, Seward Meridian
section 5: lot 3, lot 4, s1/2ne1/4ne1/4, se1/4nw1/4ne1/4, sw1/4ne1/4, n1/2nw1/4se1/4, s1/2nw1/4
Section 6: Lot 3, Lot 4, Lot 5, SE1/4NW1/4;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-491__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 19 North, Range 5 West, Seward Meridian
Section 1: SE1/4, W1/2, Tract A, Tract B, Tract C
Section 2
Section 3: N1/2;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-491__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 20 North, Range 5 West, Seward Meridian
Section 34
Section 35
Section 36: S1/2.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-491__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may agree to manage land owned by the Matanuska-Susitna Borough that is within the parcels described in (a) of this section and that is designated by ordinance or resolution of the borough as a part of the Willow Creek State Recreation Area.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-491__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subject to valid existing rights, the land and water described in (a) of this section is designated as a special purpose area under art. VIII, sec. 7, Constitution of the State of Alaska.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-491__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except for oil and gas leasing under
AS 38.05.180
and carbon storage licensing and leasing under
AS 38.05.700
 38.05.795, the mineral estate in the state-owned land and water described in (a) of this section is closed to mineral entry under
AS 38.05.181
 38.05.275.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-492">
            <num>41.21.492</num>
            <heading>Designation of management responsibilities.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-492__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The land and water described in
AS 41.21.491
(a), including land and water owned by the Matanuska-Susitna Borough and designated by the borough in a management agreement under
AS 41.21.491
(b), is assigned to the department for control, maintenance, and development, consistent with the purposes of
AS 41.21.491
 41.21.495.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-492__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing in
AS 41.21.491
 41.21.495 affects the responsibilities of</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-492__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Department of Fish and Game, the Board of Fisheries, or the Board of Game under
AS 16
and
AS 41.99.010
; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-492__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Department of Environmental Conservation under
AS 46.03
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-493">
            <num>41.21.493</num>
            <heading>Comprehensive management plan.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.493.   Comprehensive management plan.
The commissioner shall develop and adopt a comprehensive management plan for the Willow Creek State Recreation Area with the concurrence of the Matanuska-Susitna Borough.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-494">
            <num>41.21.494</num>
            <heading>Regulations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.494.   Regulations.
The commissioner shall adopt regulations under
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act) that are necessary to achieve the purposes of
AS 41.21.491
 41.21.495 and to implement the plan adopted under
AS 41.21.493
. The regulations must
(1) designate incompatible uses and prohibit or restrict them;
(2) allow road, railroad, and utility crossing of Willow Creek so as to minimize disturbance to the river's habitat and scenic and recreation values;
(3) allow fishery rehabilitation or enhancement practices under terms that are compatible with
AS 41.21.491
 41.21.495;
(4) allow the legal taking of fur-bearing animals; and
(5) allow for hunting, except where it must be prohibited for reasons of public safety.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-495">
            <num>41.21.495</num>
            <heading>Cooperative management agreements.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.495.   Cooperative management agreements.
The commissioner may enter into cooperative management agreements with a federal agency, a municipality, another state agency, or a private landowner to achieve the purposes of
AS 41.21.491
 41.21.495.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-496">
            <num>41.21.496</num>
            <heading>Certain lands excepted.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-496__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding
AS 41.21.020
(a)(6) or 41.21.491  41.21.495, state-owned land in the following described parcels may be leased in accordance with
AS 38.35
(Right-of-Way Leasing Act) for the purpose of construction and operation of a natural gas pipeline from the North Slope: the East 1/2 of Section 2, Township 19 North, Range 5 West, Seward Meridian and the East 1/2 of Section 35, Township 20 North, Range 5 West, Seward Meridian.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-496__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A state or federal survey does not remove land from the parcels described in (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-496__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall manage any state-owned land described in this section and within the exterior boundaries of Willow Creek State Recreation Area as part of Willow Creek State Recreation Area until the land is leased under
AS 38.35
. State-owned land described in this section will revert to Willow Creek State Recreation Area upon release of the land from a right-of-way through termination of the lease or otherwise and upon satisfaction of the lessee's obligations to restore and revegetate the land.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-496__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Any right-of-way lease issued under
AS 38.35
across land described in this section and within the exterior boundaries of Willow Creek State Recreation Area must</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-496__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>reserve to the state the interests necessary to provide for public access by foot, snow machine, dog sled, and other traditional means of access along and across the leased corridor;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-496__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>preserve, to the maximum extent practicable, the recreational, scenic, cultural, historical, and habitat values consistent with the leasehold's location within the exterior boundaries of Willow Creek State Recreation Area; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-496__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide for termination of the lease if construction of the pipeline has not begun 10 years after the effective date of the lease.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-496__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>AS 38.35.130
does not apply to land within the exterior boundaries of Willow Creek State Recreation Area.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-496__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A natural gas pipeline right-of-way lease may not be issued across land described in this section unless the lease becomes effective before January 1, 2025.
Article 5. Special Management Areas.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-500">
            <num>41.21.500</num>
            <heading>Purpose ofAS 41.21.500  41.21.514.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.500.   Purpose of
AS 41.21.500
  41.21.514.
The purpose of
AS 41.21.500
  41.21.514 is
(1) to designate as a unit of the state park system under this chapter the land and water described in
AS 41.21.502
(a);
(2) to protect and perpetuate the fishery and wildlife resources and habitat in the unit and adjacent area; and
(3) to manage recreational uses and development activities in the unit and adjacent area.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-502">
            <num>41.21.502</num>
            <heading>Kenai River Special Management Area.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-502__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The surface estate in the land and water presently owned by the state and all land and water acquired by the state in the future, including shore, tide, and submerged land, lying within the parcels described in this section is designated as the Kenai River Special Management Area:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-502__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Kenai River at the common section line of Sections 16 and 17, Township 5 North, Range 11 West, Seward Meridian, upstream to and including the waters of the Kenai and Skilak Lakes;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-502__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Moose River from its confluence with the Kenai River upstream to the Sterling Highway Bridge;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-502__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Funny River from its confluence with the Kenai River upstream to the Funny River Road Bridge;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-502__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the state land in the Kenai Recording District that is located within the following parcels:
(A) Kenai Keys
Township 5 North, Range 8 West, Seward Meridian
Section 26: General Land Office Lot 9
Section 36:
According to the Stephenkie Alaska Subdivision,
Alaska State Land Survey No. 73-146:
Lots 2, 3, 5  8 and 12  33 of Block 2
Tract B
A small un-meandered island located within the
SE1/4SE1/4 of Section 36
General Land Office Lots 2, 3
Sw1/4ne1/4
ne1/4nw1/4
Excluding the Kenai Keys Road Right-of-Way and Stephenkie Alaska Subdivision, Alaska State Land Survey No. 73-146
(B) Bing's Landing
Township 5 North, Range 8 West, Seward Meridian
Section 16: Portion of W1/2W1/2 lying south of the Sterling Highway
Section 20: Lot 1
Section 21: Lot 3
(C) Izaak Walton
Township 5 North, Range 8 West, Seward Meridian
Section 7:
Parcel #1: Starting at the Southwest corner of Lot 6, Section 7, T5N, R8W, go South 0° 08´ East a distance of 888.1 feet to the center of road to corner no. 1, which is the true point of beginning; then North 73° 5´ West along the center of the road a distance of 727 feet to corner no. 2; then in a southwesterly direction a distance of 515.6 feet plus or minus, along the line of mean high water of Moose River to point no. 3; then a distance of 108 feet plus or minus, to point no. 4 along the line of mean high water of Moose River to Kenai River; then a distance of 75.3 feet plus or minus, to point no. 5 along that river; then upstream a distance of 808.6 feet plus or minus, at mean high water along Kenai River to point no. 6; then North 0° 8´ West 150 feet to point no. 7; then south 89° 57´ East a distance of 208 feet to point no. 8; then North 0° 08´ West 213.9 feet to point no. 1, which is the true point of beginning.
Parcel #2: Starting at the Southwest corner of Lot 6, Section 7, T5N, R8W, go South 0° 08´ East a distance of 1102.0 feet to corner no. 1, which is the true point of beginning; then North 89° 57´ West 208.0 feet to corner no. 2; then South 0°</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-502__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subject to valid existing rights, the land and water described in (a) of this section is designated as a special purpose area under art. VIII, § 7, of the Alaska Constitution.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-502__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The mineral estate in the state-owned land and water described in (a) of this section is open to oil and gas leasing under
AS 38.05.180
and carbon storage licensing and leasing under
AS 38.05.700
 38.05.795. The mineral estate in the state-owned land and water described in (a) of this section is closed to mineral entry under
AS 38.05.181
 38.05.275.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-504">
            <num>41.21.504</num>
            <heading>Designation of management responsibilities.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-504__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The land and water described in
AS 41.21.502</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-504__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>is assigned to the department for control, maintenance, and development consistent with the purposes of
AS 41.21.500
  41.21.514.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-504__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing in
AS 41.21.500
 41.21.514 affects the applicability of</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-504__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>AS 41.99.010
and
AS 16
regarding the responsibilities of the Department of Fish and Game or the Board of Fisheries or the Board of Game; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-504__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>AS 46.03
regarding the responsibilities of the Department of Environmental Conservation.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-506">
            <num>41.21.506</num>
            <heading>Comprehensive management plan; regulations.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-506__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall develop and adopt a comprehensive management plan for the Kenai River Special Management Area in consultation with the Kenai Peninsula Borough.  The plan may include the land adjacent to the rivers described in
AS 41.21.502
(a)(1)  (3) whether the land is owned by the state or privately owned and may include other land considered appropriate by the commissioner and the Kenai Peninsula Borough.  The commissioner shall periodically review the plan and adopt changes to the plan in consultation with the Kenai Peninsula Borough.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-506__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall adopt regulations under
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act) that are necessary to achieve the purposes of
AS 41.21.500
  41.21.514 and to implement the plan adopted under (a) of this section. The regulations must</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-506__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>designate incompatible uses and prohibit or restrict them; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-506__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establish a registration, licensing, or comparable procedure for professional fishing guides and such additional fishing guide controls as the commissioner considers necessary.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-506__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Until regulations adopted under
AS 41.21.500
  41.21.514 take effect, existing state regulations otherwise applicable to the Kenai River Special Management Area remain in effect.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-506__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A regulation adopted under this section applies to land owned by the state but does not apply to land not owned by the state that is located within the boundaries of a municipality unless the regulation has been approved by the municipality.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-506__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The provisions of
AS 41.21.025</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-506__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and (c) do not apply to the land and water described in
AS 41.21.502
(a).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-508">
            <num>41.21.508</num>
            <heading>Acquisition of additional land; adjustment of boundaries.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-508__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner may acquire title to or an interest in land or improvements on land that is adjacent to or within the boundaries of the Kenai River Special Management Area in the name of the state in order to achieve the purposes of
AS 41.21.500
  41.21.514, by lease, purchase, exchange under
AS 38.50
, bequest, gift, or other lawful means but not by eminent domain.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-508__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner may adjust the boundaries of the Kenai River Special Management Area under
AS 38.05.295
 38.05.300 by adding state-owned land and water to the Kenai River Special Management Area to achieve the purposes of
AS 41.21.500
 41.21.514.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-510">
            <num>41.21.510</num>
            <heading>Advisory committee.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-510__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In developing and implementing the management plan required by
AS 41.21.506
(a), the commissioner shall appoint an advisory board.  The commissioner and the advisory board shall jointly hold public meetings during development of the management plan in the areas affected.  The commissioner shall consult with and solicit recommendations from the advisory board and from federal and state agencies, interest groups, and other interested members of the public.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-510__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The advisory board appointed under this section shall be representative of user groups, resident property owners, municipalities adjacent to the Kenai River and other interest groups. Unless appointed as a representative of a user group, resident property owners, a municipality adjacent to the Kenai River, or another interest group, an employee, elected official, or other representative of a federal or state government may be appointed to the advisory board only as an ex officio member serving without a vote. A majority of the voting members of the advisory group shall be residents of the Kenai Peninsula Borough.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-512">
            <num>41.21.512</num>
            <heading>Cooperative management agreements.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.512.   Cooperative management agreements.
The commissioner may enter into cooperative management agreements with a federal agency, a municipality, another state agency, or a private landowner to achieve the purposes of
AS 41.21.500
 41.21.514.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-514">
            <num>41.21.514</num>
            <heading>Civil enforcement.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.514.   Civil enforcement.
In addition to any other remedy provided by law, the attorney general may seek an injunction and damages at the request of the commissioner for a violation of a regulation adopted under
AS 41.21.500
 41.21.514 or a regulation that is applicable to the Kenai River Special Management Area established under
AS 41.21.502
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-518">
            <num>41.21.518</num>
            <heading>Business Park Wetlands Special Management Area established.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.518.   Business Park Wetlands Special Management Area established.
The present and future state-owned land and water within the parcels described in this section, are designated as the Business Park Wetlands Special Management Area. The special management area is established to protect and preserve this land and water for its unique and exceptional fishery and wildlife resources and habitat and recreational and scenic resource values, and to designate it as a special purpose site in accordance with art. VIII, sec. 7, of the Constitution of the State of Alaska. The state-owned land and water within the following parcels is reserved from all uses incompatible with its primary function as a special management area, except for utility easements, and is assigned to the department:
Township 13 North, Range 3 West, Seward Meridian
Section 31: N1/2SW1/4NW1/4 Parcel 25
N1/2SE1/4NW1/4 Tract A Doubletree Center Subdivision
N1/2S1/2NW1/4NW1/4 Parcel 28
South 375 feet of Government Lot 1 except that portion included within the boundaries of the Pyhala Subdivision according to plat P  197.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-520">
            <num>41.21.520</num>
            <heading>Incompatible uses.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-520__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner may designate by regulation incompatible uses for the state-owned land and water within the Business Park Wetlands Special Management Area in accordance with the requirements of
AS 41.21.518
 41.21.522.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-520__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In designating incompatible uses by regulation under (a) of this section, the commissioner shall consult with the public, the Business Park Wetlands Coalition, or any successor organization.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-522">
            <num>41.21.522</num>
            <heading>Acquisitions authorized; eminent domain prohibited.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.522.   Acquisitions authorized; eminent domain prohibited.
The commissioner may acquire by gift or purchase in the name of the state title to or interest in real property within the Business Park Wetlands Special Management Area. The state may not acquire by eminent domain privately owned land for inclusion in the Business Park Wetlands Special Management Area.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-610">
            <num>41.21.610</num>
            <heading>Purpose ofAS 41.21.610 41.21.630.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-610__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The purpose of
AS 41.21.610
 41.21.630 is to establish the state-owned land and water described in
AS 41.21.611</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-610__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>as the Alaska Chilkat Bald Eagle Preserve as part of the state park system.  The primary purpose for establishing the Alaska Chilkat Bald Eagle Preserve is to protect and perpetuate the Chilkat bald eagles and their essential habitats within the Alaska Chilkat Bald Eagle Preserve in recognition of their statewide, nationally, and internationally significant values in perpetuity.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-610__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Alaska Chilkat Bald Eagle Preserve is also established to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-610__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>protect and sustain the natural salmon spawning and rearing areas of the Chilkat River and Chilkoot River systems within the preserve in perpetuity;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-610__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide continued opportunities for research, study, and enjoyment of bald eagles and other wildlife;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-610__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>ensure to the maximum extent practicable water quality and necessary water quantity under applicable laws;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-610__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide for other public uses consistent with the primary purpose for which the Alaska Chilkat Bald Eagle Preserve is established; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-610__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide an opportunity for the continued traditional and natural resource based lifestyle of the people living in the general areas described in
AS 41.21.611</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-610__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>It is the intent of the legislature in enacting
AS 41.21.610
 41.21.630 to provide sufficient protection for the purposes for which the Alaska Chilkat Bald Eagle Preserve is established. Accordingly, the establishment of the Alaska Chilkat Bald Eagle Preserve and the Haines State Forest Resource Management Area under
AS 41.15.305
is determined to represent a proper balance between the reservation of state public domain land and water for bald eagle preserve purposes and state public domain land and water more appropriate for multiple use. Therefore, the legislature determines that there is no need for legislation expanding or contracting the boundary of the Alaska Chilkat Bald Eagle Preserve in the future; the legislature further determines that study by a state agency of the expansion or contracting of the boundary of the preserve shall be conducted under
AS 41.21.621
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-610__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Inasmuch as the area described in
AS 41.21.611</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-610__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>exceeds 640 acres,
AS 41.21.610
 41.21.630 are intended to close the area to multiple use in conformity with
AS 38.05.300
and the land is dedicated as a special purpose site under art. VIII, § 7 of the state constitution.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-611">
            <num>41.21.611</num>
            <heading>Alaska Chilkat Bald Eagle Preserve established.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-611__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subject to valid existing rights, the land and water presently owned by the state and all land and water acquired in the future by the state lying within the boundaries described in (b) of this section are designated the Alaska Chilkat Bald Eagle Preserve and assigned to the department for control, development, and maintenance.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-611__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except for University of Alaska grant land, the land and water owned by the state and all land and water acquired by the state in the future lying within the following described parcels are designated as the Alaska Chilkat Bald Eagle Preserve:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-611__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 26 South, Range 55 East, Copper River Meridian
Section 12: that portion within USS 3708
Section 13: that portion within USS 3708
Section 23: SE1/4NE1/4, NE1/4SE1/4, E1/2NW1/4SE1/4, S1/2SE1/4
Sections 24 and 25
Section 26: E1/2
Section 33: SE1/4SE1/4SE1/4
Section 34: E1/2NE1/4, E1/2SW1/4NE1/4, SE1/4NE1/4SW1/4, E1/2SW1/4SW1/4, SW1/4SW1/4SW1/4, SE1/4SW1/4, SE1/4
Section 35
Section 36: NE1/4NW1/4NE1/4, W1/2W1/2NE1/4, NW1/4, N1/2SW1/4, N1/2SW1/4SW1/4, SW1/4SW1/4SW1/4, NW1/4SE1/4SW1/4, NW1/4SE1/4;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-611__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 26 South, Range 56 East, Copper River Meridian
Section 7: SW1/4NE1/4, that portion of the S1/2NW1/4 within USS 3708, S1/2
Section 8: SE1/4SW1/4NW1/4, SE1/4NW1/4, SW1/4, that portion of the S1/2NE1/4 within USS 3708
Section 17: W1/2NW1/4
Section 18
Section 19: W1/2, SW1/4SE1/4
Section 30: NE1/4NW1/4NE1/4, W1/2NW1/4NE1/4, NW1/4, W1/2SW1/4;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-611__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 27 South, Range 55 East, Copper River Meridian
Section 2: NW1/4, W1/2NE1/4SW1/4, NW1/4SW1/4, N1/2SW1/4SW1/4, SW1/4SW1/4SW1/4, NW1/4SE1/4SW1/4, except USS 3744
Section 3
Section 4: NE1/4NE1/4NE1/4, S1/2NE1/4NE1/4, E1/2SW1/4NE1/4, SE1/4NE1/4, E1/2SE1/4SW1/4, SE1/4
Section 8: SE1/4SE1/4SW1/4, S1/2S1/2SE1/4, N1/2SE1/4SE1/4
Section 9: E1/2, E1/2NW1/4, N1/2NE1/4SW1/4, SE1/4NE1/4SW1/4, NW1/4SW1/4SW1/4, S1/2S1/2SW1/4
Section 10: W1/2W1/2NE1/4, W1/2
Section 15: NW1/4NW1/4NE1/4, S1/2NW1/4NE1/4, SW1/4NE1/4, W1/2, W1/2SE1/4
Section 16: E1/2, NW1/4, N1/2SW1/4, NW1/4SE1/4SW1/4, E1/2SE1/4SW1/4
Section 17: N1/2NE1/4, NE1/4SW1/4NE1/4, SE1/4NE1/4, E1/2NE1/4NW1/4, N1/2NE1/4SE1/4, SE1/4NE1/4SE1/4
Section 21: E1/2, E1/2E1/2NW1/4, SW1/4SE1/4NW1/4, E1/2SW1/4, SE1/4SW1/4SW1/4
Section 22: SW1/4NE1/4NE1/4, W1/2E1/2, W1/2SE1/4NE1/4, W1/2, W1/2E1/2SE1/4
Section 26: NW1/4NW1/4NW1/4, S1/2NW1/4NW1/4, SW1/4NW1/4, W1/2E1/2SW1/4, W1/2SW1/4
Section 27
Section 28: E1/2, E1/2W1/2, E1/2W1/2W1/2
Section 33: N1/2NE1/4, E1/2SW1/4NE1/4, NW1/4SW1/4NE1/4, SE1/4NE1/4, E1/2NE1/4NW1/4, NE1/4SE1/4, E1/2NW1/4SE1/4, N1/2SE1/4SE1/4, SE1/4SE1/4SE1/4
Section 34
Section 35: NW1/4NW1/4NE1/4, S1/2NW1/4NE1/4, SW1/4NE1/4, NW1/4SE1/4NE1/4, S1/2SE1/4NE1/4, W1/2, SE1/4
Section 36: W1/2SW1/4SW1/4;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-611__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 28 South, Range 55 East, Copper River Meridian
Section 1: S1/2SW1/4NW1/4, SW1/4
Section 2
Section 3: NE1/4, N1/2NW1/4, N1/2SW1/4NW1/4, SE1/4NW1/4, NE1/4NE1/4SW1/4, N1/2SE1/4, SE1/4SE1/4
Section 4: E1/2NE1/4NE1/4
Section 10: that portion of Mosquito Lake within the NE1/4
Section 11: N1/2, N1/2SE1/4, NE1/4SW1/4SE1/4, SE1/4SE1/4, except USS 3431
Section 12
Section 13: E1/2, NE1/4NW1/4, E1/2NW1/4NW1/4, NW1/4NW1/4NW1/4, NW1/4SE1/4NW1/4, E1/2SE1/4NW1/4
Section 19: Lot 13
Section 24: E1/2E1/2, NE1/4NW1/4NE1/4
Section 25: except that portion north of the Haines Highway
Section 26: that portion south of the Haines Highway except Lots 2, 3, and the SW1/4SW1/4
Section 27: that portion south of the Haines Highway except S1/2S1/2
Section 28: except S1/2S1/2, the south 660 feet of Lots 5  7, and that portion north of the Haines Highway
Section 29: except S1/2S1/2S1/2, NE1/4SE1/4SE1/4, and Lots 9, 14, 15, and 18
Section 30: E1/2NE1/4, N1/2NE1/4SE1/4
Section 34: S1/2S1/2S1/2
Section 35: except NW1/4NE1/4, S1/2NE1/4, NW1/4, S1/2
Section 36: except SW1/4NW1/4, S1/2, and the south 660 feet of Lots 3  4;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-611__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 28 South, Range 56 East, Copper River Meridian
Section 7: SW1/4NW1/4NW1/4, SW1/4NW1/4, SW1/4SE1/4NW1/4, W1/2NE1/4SW1/4, SE1/4NE1/4SW1/4, NW1/4SW1/4, S1/2SW1/4, SW1/4SW1/4SE1/4
Section 17: W1/2SW1/4SW1/4, SE1/4SW1/4SW1/4
Section 18: W1/2W1/2NE1/4, E1/2SW1/4NE1/4, SW1/4SE1/4NE1/4, W1/2, SE1/4
Section 19
Section 20: W1/2W1/2
Section 29: except USS 948, USS 991, Lots 1, 2, and 4  7, NE1/4, E1/2NW1/4
Section 30: except Lots 1, 4, 5, 8, 15-17, and the NE1/4SW1/4
Section 31
Section 32: except USS 991, USS 2455, and Lots 1, 2, and 24
Section 33: S1/2 except USS 2455 and Lots 18  21
Section 34: W1/2SW1/4SE1/4, SE1/4SW1/4SE1/4, SW1/4 except NE1/4SW1/4 and Lots 1 and 2;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-611__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 28 South, Range 57 East, Copper River Meridian
Section 22: NE1/4SW1/4, E1/2SE1/4SW1/4, W1/2NW1/4SE1/4, SW1/4SE1/4, NW1/4SE1/4SE1/4, S1/2SE1/4SE1/4
Section 26: W1/2SW1/4NW1/4, W1/2W1/2SW1/4
Section 27: E1/2E1/2, N1/2NW1/4NE1/4, SE1/4NW1/4NE1/4
Section 34: NE1/4NE1/4, NE1/4SE1/4NE1/4
Section 35: SW1/4SW1/4NE1/4, NW1/4NW1/4NW1/4, S1/2NW1/4NW1/4, S1/2NW1/4, E1/2SW1/4, NW1/4NW1/4SE1/4, S1/2NW1/4SE1/4, S1/2SE1/4, SW1/4NE1/4SE1/4;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-611__subsec_b__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 29 South, Range 55 East, Copper River Meridian
Section 1: S1/2NE1/4NE1/4, E1/2SW1/4NE1/4, N1/2SE1/4NE1/4, SW1/4SE1/4NE1/4, NW1/4NE1/4SE1/4, NE1/4NW1/4SE1/4;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-611__subsec_b__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 29 South, Range 56 East, Copper River Meridian
Section 1
Section 2: N1/2NE1/4, E1/2SE1/4NE1/4, NE1/4NW1/4, E1/2NE1/4SE1/4, NE1/4SE1/4SE1/4
Section 4: W1/2NW1/4, W1/2SE1/4NW1/4, SE1/4SE1/4NW1/4, SW1/4, W1/2NW1/4SE1/4, SE1/4NW1/4SE1/4, SW1/4SE1/4, W1/2SE1/4SE1/4, SE1/4SE1/4SE1/4
Section 5: E1/2, N1/2NW1/4, SE1/4NE1/4SW1/4, E1/2SE1/4SW1/4
Section 6: N1/2N1/2NE1/4, NE1/4NW1/4, S1/2NW1/4NW1/4, N1/2SW1/4NW1/4, NW1/4SE1/4NW1/4
Section 8: except SW1/4SW1/4 and S1/2SE1/4SW1/4
Section 9
Section 10: S1/2S1/2NE1/4, SW1/4NE1/4NW1/4, NW1/4NW1/4, S1/2NW1/4, S1/2
Section 11: S1/2NE1/4, S1/2S1/2NW1/4, NE1/4SW1/4NW1/4, N1/2SE1/4NW1/4, S1/2
Sections 12  14
Section 15: N1/2, N1/2N1/2SW1/4, E1/2SE1/4, NW1/4SE1/4, E1/2SW1/4SE1/4
Section 16: E1/2NE1/4, E1/2W1/2NE1/4, W1/2NW1/4NE1/4, NW1/4SW1/4NE1/4, N1/2N1/2NW1/4, SE1/4NE1/4NW1/4, NE1/4SE1/4NW1/4
Section 17: N1/2NE1/4NE1/4
Section 22: N1/2NE1/4NE1/4, NE1/4NW1/4NE1/4
Section 23: that portion of the N1/2NW1/4 lying west of Chilkat Lake;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-611__subsec_b__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 29 South, Range 57 East, Copper River Meridian
Section 4: NW1/4NW1/4SW1/4, S1/2NW1/4SW1/4, SW1/4SW1/4, NW1/4SE1/4SW1/4, S1/2SE1/4SW1/4
Section 5: except Lots 2  4, N1/2NE1/4, NE1/4SE1/4NE1/4
Section 6: except Lots 1 and 9
Sections 7 and 8
USS 907
Section 9: W1/2W1/2NE1/4, SE1/4SW1/4NE1/4, SW1/4SE1/4NE1/4, NW1/4, S1/2
Section 10: Lots 1  4, W1/2NE1/4SW1/4, NW1/4SE1/4SW1/4, E1/2SW1/4SE1/4SW1/4
Section 14: that portion west of the Haines Highway
Section 15: except NE1/4NE1/4 and Lots 7  10, 13  14
Sections 16  18
USS 786
Section 19: NE1/4NE1/4NE1/4
Section 20: NE1/4, E1/2NW1/4, NW1/4NW1/4, E1/2SW1/4NW1/4, NE1/4SE1/4, N1/2NW1/4SE1/4, SE1/4NW1/4SE1/4, NE1/4SE1/4SE1/4
Sections 21 and 22
Section 23: that portion west of the Haines Highway
Section 25: that portion west of the Haines Highway
Section 26: that portion west of the Haines Highway
Section 28: NE1/4, NE1/4NW1/4, N1/2NW1/4NW1/4, N1/2SE1/4NW1/4, NE1/4SE1/4, N1/2NW1/4SE1/4, SE1/4NW1/4SE1/4, NE1/4SE1/4SE1/4
Section 34: NE1/4, NE1/4NW1/4, NE1/4SE1/4NW1/4, NE1/4SE1/4, NE1/4NW1/4SE1/4, E1/2SE1/4SE1/4
Section 36: that portion west of the Haines Highway;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-611__subsec_b__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 29 South, Range 58 East, Copper River Meridian
Section 3: S1/2SW1/4NW1/4, SW1/4NE1/4SW1/4, W1/2SW1/4, SE1/4SW1/4, S1/2SW1/4SE1/4
Section 4: SW1/4NE1/4NE1/4, W1/2NE1/4, SE1/4NE1/4, NW1/4, NE1/4SW1/4, SE1/4
Section 9: NE1/4NE1/4
Section 10: N1/2, E1/2SW1/4, E1/2W1/2SW1/4, NW1/4NW1/4SW1/4, SE1/4
Section 31: that portion south of the Haines Highway;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-611__subsec_b__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 30 South, Range 57 East, Copper River Meridian
Section 1
Section 2: NE1/4, NE1/4NW1/4, N1/2NW1/4NW1/4, SE1/4NW1/4NW1/4, N1/2SE1/4NW1/4, SE1/4SE1/4NW1/4, N1/2SE1/4, N1/2SE1/4SE1/4
Section 3: NE1/4NE1/4NE1/4
Section 12: NE1/4, NE1/4NW1/4, NE1/4NW1/4NW1/4, NE1/4SE1/4NW1/4, W1/2NE1/4SE1/4, NE1/4NW1/4SE1/4, E1/2E1/2SE1/4, NW1/4SE1/4SE1/4;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-611__subsec_b__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Township 30 South, Range 58 East, Copper River Meridian
Section 6: that portion west of the Haines Highway
Section 7: that portion west of the Haines Highway
Section 8: that portion west of the Haines Highway
Section 16: that portion west of the Haines Highway
Section 17: that portion west of the Haines Highway
Section 18: Lots 1  3 and 5, SW1/4NE1/4, N1/2SE1/4NW1/4, SE1/4SE1/4NW1/4, SE1/4.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-612">
            <num>41.21.612</num>
            <heading>Land excluded.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-612__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Private land, approved or pending Native allotments, pending and approved land selections made by the Haines Borough under state law on July 1, 1982, University of Alaska grant land not located within the Chilkat River Critical Habitat Area established by
AS 16.20.585
, and existing transportation and utility corridors located partially or completely within the Alaska Chilkat Bald Eagle Preserve are excluded from the Alaska Chilkat Bald Eagle Preserve.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-612__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>University of Alaska grant land located within the boundary of the Chilkat River Critical Habitat Area established under
AS 16.20.585
is excluded from the Alaska Chilkat Bald Eagle Preserve.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-613">
            <num>41.21.613</num>
            <heading>Eminent domain prohibited.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.613.   Eminent domain prohibited.
The commissioner may not acquire private land or University of Alaska grant land located partially or completely within the Alaska Chilkat Bald Eagle Preserve by eminent domain for any purpose.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-614">
            <num>41.21.614</num>
            <heading>Native allotments.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.614.   Native allotments.
Approved or pending Native allotments located partially or completely within the Alaska Chilkat Bald Eagle Preserve are not adversely affected by the establishment of the Alaska Chilkat Bald Eagle Preserve and all approved allotments and all pending allotments located partially or completely within the preserve shall be treated as private land.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-615">
            <num>41.21.615</num>
            <heading>Fish and game management.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.615.   Fish and game management.
The Department of Fish and Game is responsible for the management of fish and game resources in the Alaska Chilkat Bald Eagle Preserve
(1) under applicable law and consistent with the purposes of
AS 41.21.610
 41.21.630;
(2) subject to the authority of the Secretary of the Interior to permit the taking of bald eagles for the religious purposes of an Indian tribe under 16 U.S.C. 668a (§ 2, Bald Eagle Protection Act).</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-616">
            <num>41.21.616</num>
            <heading>Regulations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.616.   Regulations.
The department shall consult with the Department of Fish and Game, the United States Fish and Wildlife Service, a local governing body of a municipality, any local fish and game advisory committees, and the Alaska Chilkat Bald Eagle Preserve Advisory Council established by
AS 41.21.625
before adoption of reasonable regulations governing public use and protection of the Alaska Chilkat Bald Eagle Preserve. The Department of Fish and Game shall consult with the department and the Alaska Chilkat Bald Eagle Preserve Advisory Council in proposing regulations governing fish and game management in the Alaska Chilkat Bald Eagle Preserve for adoption by the Board of Fisheries or the Board of Game.  The Department of Fish and Game and the department shall cooperate with the United States Fish and Wildlife Service in its administration of federal law governing the conservation of bald eagles.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-617">
            <num>41.21.617</num>
            <heading>Other uses generally.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-617__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>is closed to mineral entry under
AS 38.05.135
 38.05.275 and 38.05.700  38.05.795, to commercial harvest of timber, and to sale under state land disposal laws. The commissioner may lease the land described in
AS 41.21.611</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-617__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>under
AS 38.05.070
 38.05.105 for a purpose consistent with
AS 41.21.610</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-617__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and (b). A municipality may select land within the Alaska Chilkat Bald Eagle Preserve under law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-618">
            <num>41.21.618</num>
            <heading>Traditional uses.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-618__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and (b).  The director of the division of parks shall hold a public hearing in Haines and Klukwan before restricting a traditional use permitted under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-619">
            <num>41.21.619</num>
            <heading>Access and rights-of-way.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-619__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>does not have reasonable, timely, and economically feasible access and egress by means other than crossing land designated as Alaska Chilkat Bald Eagle Preserve land in
AS 41.21.611
(b), the director of the division of parks shall grant a private landowner, the University of Alaska, a holder of a valid existing right to land, or a state agency, municipality, or federal agency the rights necessary to assure reasonable, timely, and economically feasible access and egress. A permittee or licensee of an owner of land or the holder of a valid existing right to land may use access and egress granted under this section.  The rights of access and egress granted under this section are subject to reasonable regulation and stipulations established by the director of the division of parks after consulting with the Alaska Chilkat Bald Eagle Preserve Advisory Council to protect the purposes and values of the Alaska Chilkat Bald Eagle Preserve and to minimize adverse environmental impacts in the preserve.  As used in this section, valid existing right includes but is not limited to a valid mining right, an existing mineral right, and a subsurface right.  The director of the division of parks shall give favorable consideration to applications for utility rights-of-way that are compatible with
AS 41.21.610</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-619__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and (b).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-620">
            <num>41.21.620</num>
            <heading>Management plan.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-620__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The director of the division of parks and the Alaska Chilkat Bald Eagle Advisory Council established under
AS 41.21.625
, in written consultation with the United States Fish and Wildlife Service, the Department of Fish and Game, the Chilkat Indian Village, the Chilkoot Indian Association, and other appropriate groups, may use information gained through cooperative resource studies in the development of the management plan for the Alaska Chilkat Bald Eagle Preserve and in decisions affecting the management and administration of the preserve.  The director of the division of parks and the advisory council shall investigate the need for additional research to increase the knowledge and understanding of the natural and cultural resources of the area and to enhance the effective management of the Alaska Chilkat Bald Eagle Preserve.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-620__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The director of the division of parks and the director of the division of forestry and fire protection shall consult in the preparation of the management plan prepared under (a) of this section to promote effective, efficient, and coordinated administration of the Haines State Forest Resource Management Area and the Alaska Chilkat Bald Eagle Preserve for the purposes and values for which each is established.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-621">
            <num>41.21.621</num>
            <heading>Additions or deletions to preserve.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.621.   Additions or deletions to preserve.
An agency of the state may not participate or cooperate with a federal or private study considering additions to or deletions from the area of the Alaska Chilkat Bald Eagle Preserve without giving 90 days' prior notice to the Alaska Chilkat Bald Eagle Preserve Advisory Council.  The director of the division of parks may waive the notice required by this subsection on the director's determination in writing to the advisory council that an emergency necessitates immediate study or a shorter period of notice to the advisory council.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-622">
            <num>41.21.622</num>
            <heading>Historical, cultural and burial sites.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.622.   Historical, cultural and burial sites.
Historical, cultural, and burial sites identified in the Alaska Chilkat Bald Eagle Preserve management plan are not available for surface disposal under
AS 41.21.617
and shall be managed by the director of the division of parks to prevent vandalism, destruction, and desecration.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-625">
            <num>41.21.625</num>
            <heading>Alaska Chilkat Bald Eagle Preserve Advisory Council.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-625__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A 12-member Alaska Chilkat Bald Eagle Preserve Advisory Council is established.  The members of the advisory council shall be selected under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-625__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The governor shall appoint individuals to the Alaska Chilkat Bald Eagle Preserve Advisory Council representing the following interests for a two-year term:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-625__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a resident of the Haines Borough representing a conservation organization;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-625__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a representative of the United States Fish and Wildlife Service; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-625__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a member of the Upper Lynn Canal fish and game advisory committee.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-625__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The mayor of the Haines Borough, the president of Klukwan, Inc., the chair of the Council of the Chilkat Indian Village, and the chair of the Chilkoot Indian Association are ex officio members of the Alaska Chilkat Bald Eagle Preserve Advisory Council. A member of the Haines Borough Assembly who has been selected by the Haines Borough Assembly is also an ex officio member of the advisory council. For this selection, preference shall be given to those members of the Haines Borough Assembly who do not also sit on boards that are already represented on the advisory council. The mayor of the Haines Borough may recommend to the governor for appointment to the advisory council the name of a resident of the Haines Borough for the representation of commercial or industrial interests.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-625__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner of fish and game, the director of the division of parks, and the director of the division of forestry and fire protection, or their designees, serve ex officio as members of the Alaska Chilkat Bald Eagle Preserve Advisory Council.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-625__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Alaska Chilkat Bald Eagle Preserve Advisory Council shall assist the department in the development and monitoring of a management plan for the Alaska Chilkat Bald Eagle Preserve. The management plan shall be presented at public hearings in Haines and Klukwan before approval and implementation by the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-625__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Members of the Alaska Chilkat Bald Eagle Preserve Advisory Council selected under (b)  (d) of this section may select alternates to act as members of the advisory council in their absence.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-630">
            <num>41.21.630</num>
            <heading>Existing rights.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.630.   Existing rights.
The establishment of the Alaska Chilkat Bald Eagle Preserve under
AS 41.21.610
 41.21.630 does not enlarge, diminish, add to, or waive a requirement of law otherwise applicable to the management or use of the state land of the Haines State Forest Resource Management Area (
AS 41.15.300
 41.15.330) or private land.  An activity allowed under law on land not described in
AS 41.21.611
(b), including but not limited to an activity described in
AS 41.21.618
, timber harvest, mining, resource development, and recreation, is permitted so long as the activity is conducted in compliance with law.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-800">
            <num>41.21.800</num>
            <heading>Selection of sites.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.800.   Selection of sites.
The department and the Department of Transportation and Public Facilities shall jointly select sites of 10 acres or less for their historic or scenic value, or for recreation beaches along waterways, roadside rests for travelers resting, camping, or parking, and determine what facilities are necessary or desirable at these sites.  Selection of the sites for roadside rests and recreation beaches shall be based upon the flow of traffic and distances to and between facilities otherwise provided.  Insofar as possible, sites shall be located on, or adjacent to, highway rights-of-way and small boat waterways. The department may acquire the sites jointly selected by grant, gift, purchase, lease, dedication, or prescription and hold them in the name of the state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-805">
            <num>41.21.805</num>
            <heading>Construction and maintenance of facilities.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.805.   Construction and maintenance of facilities.
The Department of Transportation and Public Facilities may construct and maintain facilities at scenic sites, recreation beaches or roadside rests as are determined to be necessary and desirable. Facilities may include, but are not limited to, access roads, camp facilities, including picnic tables, fireplaces and toilets, camping areas or other facilities that are considered necessary and desirable for the convenience and benefit of travelers and small boat operators.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-850">
            <num>41.21.850</num>
            <heading>Wilderness trails and campsites.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.850.   Wilderness trails and campsites.
There is established in the state a system of wilderness trails and campsites.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-852">
            <num>41.21.852</num>
            <heading>Selection.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.852.   Selection.
The department, in consultation with the Departments of Fish and Game and Transportation and Public Facilities, shall designate a system of wilderness trails and campsites throughout the state.  Significant in the selection shall be the scenic, historic, natural, or cultural qualities of the areas through which the trails may pass.  The department may acquire the trail sites jointly selected by grant, gift, purchase, lease, dedication, or prescription and hold them in the name of the state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-854">
            <num>41.21.854</num>
            <heading>Uniform marker.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.854.   Uniform marker.
The commissioner shall establish a uniform marker for the wilderness trails system.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-856">
            <num>41.21.856</num>
            <heading>Regulations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.856.   Regulations.
The commissioner shall adopt regulations concerning the use, management, development, and administration of the trails.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-858">
            <num>41.21.858</num>
            <heading>Campsites; work by prisoners.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-858__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Transportation and Public Facilities may construct and maintain campsites throughout the wilderness trails system. Campsites may include any type of shelter or camp facility considered necessary and desirable for the benefit and convenience of travelers.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-858__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>As an aid to the construction and maintenance of trails and campsites under (a) of this section, the commissioner of corrections is authorized to establish a program that would allow prisoners to volunteer for work on the trails and campsites.  The commissioner is authorized to grant remuneration for the work, either in money or reduction of sentence, which the commissioner considers sufficient.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-860">
            <num>41.21.860</num>
            <heading>Federal financial assistance.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.860.   Federal financial assistance.
The commissioner is authorized to consider the feasibility of any form of financial assistance available to the state for the planning, acquisition, or development of trails under 16 U.S.C. 460d, 460l-4 to 460l-11 and 23 U.S.C. 120 (note) (P.L. 88-578, Land and Water Conservation Fund Act of 1965).</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-864">
            <num>41.21.864</num>
            <heading>Grants for the establishment of trails and footpaths.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-864__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Within the limits of available appropriations, a city or borough of any class is entitled to state grants for the purpose of acquiring land or rights-of-way over land and establishing and maintaining trails and footpaths on that land or those rights-of-way.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-864__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Within the limits of available appropriations, the Department of Transportation and Public Facilities is entitled to state grants for the establishment and maintenance of footpaths and trails along certain designated existing highways or when a highway, road or street is being constructed, reconstructed or relocated after June 7, 1972.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-864__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before a grant is awarded under this section, application shall be submitted to the commissioner of natural resources, accompanied by a comprehensive plan for the establishment of trails and paths.  The plan may provide for ski trails, dog sled trails, motorized vehicle trails, bicycle paths, bridle paths, footpaths and other trails and paths, and designate separate and incompatible uses of these trails and paths.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-864__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon approval of the plan, funds shall be utilized and disbursed to cities and boroughs and to the Department of Transportation and Public Facilities according to regulations adopted by the commissioner of natural resources.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-864__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before the distribution of funds by the commissioner, consideration shall be given to the extent of funding available under other federal, local and state aid programs.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-864__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing in
AS 41.21.864
 41.21.872 prohibits a city or borough for which a grant is authorized from entering into an agreement with the Department of Natural Resources for the establishment and maintenance of trails and footpaths outside cities and boroughs.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-866">
            <num>41.21.866</num>
            <heading>Paths and trails along highways.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.866.   Paths and trails along highways.
The commissioner of transportation and public facilities shall administer the plan and program providing for the establishment and maintenance of footpaths, bridle paths, bicycle paths, ski trails, dog sled trails, motorized vehicle trails, and other paths and trails along certain designated existing highways, or when a highway, road, or street is being constructed, reconstructed, or relocated after June 7, 1972. Trails established under an approved plan submitted by the Department of Transportation and Public Facilities may be used for those types of uses written into the plan.  A uniform system of marking the paths and trails established under this section shall be established by the commissioner of transportation and public facilities.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-868">
            <num>41.21.868</num>
            <heading>Authorization of funds.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-868__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An amount of not less than three-eighths of one percent nor more than one percent of the total yearly state and federal matching sum combined, under the federal-aid highways program (23 U.S.C.), shall be appropriated annually from the general fund to the department for the purposes of providing grants to eligible cities and boroughs for trails, footpaths, and shelter construction and maintenance in appropriate areas, including but not limited to existing park and recreation areas and for the purpose of providing grants to the Department of Transportation and Public Facilities for developing the program specified in
AS 41.21.864</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-868__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and 41.21.866.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-868__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (c) of this section, the sums appropriated under this section shall continue to be available for expenditure by the departments or by eligible cities and boroughs for a period of three years after the close of the fiscal year for which the sums are authorized, unless they are obligated for expenditure, in which case they shall remain available until spent.  Any amounts not obligated remaining unexpended at the end of the three-year period lapse.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-868__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The amount expended by a city or borough under
AS 41.21.864</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-868__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or by the Department of Transportation and Public Facilities under
AS 41.21.864</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-868__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and 41.21.866, may not in any one fiscal year be less than 10 percent of the total amount of the funds it receives in that year for the purposes authorized in
AS 41.21.864
 41.21.872.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-870">
            <num>41.21.870</num>
            <heading>Use and marking of trails and footpaths.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-870__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>may be used for more than one type of transportation, motorized or nonmotorized, as considered appropriate by the commissioner.  Except along highways within the jurisdiction of the Department of Transportation and Public Facilities, the department shall provide a uniform system of marking trails and footpaths.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-872">
            <num>41.21.872</num>
            <heading>Reports.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.872.   Reports.
Cities and boroughs receiving grants under
AS 41.21.864
 41.21.872 shall submit to the commissioner complete reports covering their expenditures relating to the establishment of trails and footpaths.  Reports shall be submitted annually on projects extending over 12 months. Reports on shorter projects shall be submitted at the completion of the project.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-900">
            <num>41.21.900</num>
            <heading>Purpose ofAS 41.21.900 41.21.908.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.900.   Purpose of
AS 41.21.900
 41.21.908.
The purpose of
AS 41.21.900
 41.21.908 is to provide avenues of action for youth in the state interested in the preservation of a healthy environment by establishing a volunteer corps to teach and practice conservation on all levels of activities which are environment related.  The aim is to foster and supplement programs on the local and state level and provide some of the manpower needed to successfully accomplish the goal of a healthy and pleasant environment in which to live.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-902">
            <num>41.21.902</num>
            <heading>Alaska Conservation Action Corps created.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.902.   Alaska Conservation Action Corps created.
There is created in the division of parks of the department the Alaska Conservation Action Corps.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-904">
            <num>41.21.904</num>
            <heading>Activities of corps.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.904.   Activities of corps.
The corps may be assigned
(1) to provide staff services for public agencies involved in planning for the future of our environment;
(2) tasks of cleaning litter from city streets, highways, local parks, neighborhoods, beaches, natural forests, rivers, creeks, state and national parks on a continuing basis;
(3) to participate in neighborhood improvement programs including the creation of neighborhood parks and playgrounds, supplementing local government efforts on a voluntary basis on request;
(4) to fire prevention activities in forest land, including the cleaning of brush and deadfalls and the construction and maintenance of fire trails and firebreaks and firefighting in time of need;
(5) the task of building and maintaining hiking and riding trails and campsites, improving wildlife habitats and protection of wildlife refuges and wilderness areas under supervision of the Department of Fish and Game;
(6) to participate in drainage and erosion control improvements on public land and the reforestation of fire-devastated areas;
(7) the task of conducting conservation summer camp programs for youths to learn and practice conservation skills;
(8) monitoring duties in areas of environmental concern where control and enforcement are maintained such as the monitoring of air and water pollution levels or checking on how well developers are meeting subdivision regulations.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-906">
            <num>41.21.906</num>
            <heading>Compensation.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-906__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Part-time corps members shall be paid on an hourly basis, to be determined by the commissioner.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-906__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Compensation for corps members who are involved in continuous service in an away-from-home situation shall be set on a weekly or monthly basis to be determined by the commissioner.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-908">
            <num>41.21.908</num>
            <heading>Nonapplicability of child labor laws.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.908.   Nonapplicability of child labor laws.
AS 23.10.325
 23.10.370 do not apply to
AS 41.21.900
 41.21.908.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-910">
            <num>41.21.910</num>
            <heading>Alaska Youth Hostel System established.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.910.   Alaska Youth Hostel System established.
There is established the Alaska youth hostel system administered by the division of parks of the department.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-912">
            <num>41.21.912</num>
            <heading>Duties of division.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.912.   Duties of division.
The division shall
(1) after consultation with community organizations or individuals and after maximum utilization of existing local effort, plan and facilitate the implementation of a statewide system of youth hostel facilities;
(2) administer a program of grants to eligible nonprofit corporations, municipalities, and organizations for construction, maintenance, and operation of youth hostels;
(3) cooperate and consult with national or international organizations established for the purpose of establishing or regulating youth hostel facilities and follow, where appropriate, the specific guidelines established by the American Youth Hostel Association and the International Youth Hostel Association;
(4) adopt, in accordance with
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act), regulations governing the establishment and administration of youth hostel facilities.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-914">
            <num>41.21.914</num>
            <heading>Hostel locations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.914.   Hostel locations.
In developing the statewide system of Alaska youth hostels, the division shall, within the limits of available funding, and after receiving the recommendations of the coordinator of the Alaska youth hostel program, establish at least one youth hostel in each of the five following major regions of the state: arctic, southcentral, interior, southwestern, and southeastern.  Hostel facilities shall be located, when possible, within major population areas within those regions. Other hostels may be established within the five regions as funding permits.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-916">
            <num>41.21.916</num>
            <heading>Hostel facility.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.916.   Hostel facility.
Each youth hostel facility shall be equipped with suitable toilet and kitchen facilities. Each facility shall be supervised under regulations adopted by the division of parks.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-918">
            <num>41.21.918</num>
            <heading>Duties of coordinator.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.918.   Duties of coordinator.
The director of the division of parks shall designate a member of the division staff as coordinator of the Alaska youth hostel program.  The coordinator shall
(1) recommend to the division of parks locations for the construction of youth hostels;
(2) advise the division on use policy for the Alaska youth hostel system;
(3) render other assistance considered necessary and appropriate by the division;
(4) establish criteria for the grant programs authorized under
AS 41.21.912
(2) and have approval authority for grants made under
AS 41.21.912
(2).
Article 10. General Provisions.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-950">
            <num>41.21.950</num>
            <heading>Penalty.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.950.   Penalty.
A person who violates a provision of this chapter or a regulation adopted under this chapter is guilty of a misdemeanor and upon conviction is punishable by a fine of not more than $1,000, or by imprisonment for not more than six months, or by both.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-955">
            <num>41.21.955</num>
            <heading>Enforcement authority.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-955__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For offenses committed within parks and recreational facilities subject to the department's supervision, the following persons are peace officers of the state and they shall enforce the provisions of this chapter and the regulations adopted under this chapter:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-955__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an employee of the department authorized by the commissioner;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-955__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a police officer in the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-955__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>any other person authorized by the commissioner.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-955__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each person designated in (a) of this section may, when enforcing the provisions of this chapter or a regulation adopted under this chapter,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-955__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>execute a warrant or other process issued by an officer or court of competent jurisdiction;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-955__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>administer or take an oath, affirmation, or affidavit; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-955__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>arrest or issue a citation to a person who violates a provision of this chapter or a regulation adopted under this chapter.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-960">
            <num>41.21.960</num>
            <heading>Form and issuance of citation.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-21-960__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When a peace officer stops or contacts a person concerning the commission of a misdemeanor offense committed within a park or recreational facility subject to the department's supervision, the officer may issue a citation to the person, subject to the provisions of
AS 12.25.175
 12.25.230. The person receiving the citation may not be required to endorse the citation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-960__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The state supreme court shall identify those offenses that are amenable to disposition without court appearance and shall establish by rule or order a schedule of bail amounts, not to exceed fines prescribed by law, for those offenses.  Before establishing or amending the schedule of bail amounts required by this subsection, the supreme court shall appoint and consult with an advisory committee consisting of two persons from the department, two district court judges, one member of the House Resources Committee, and one member of the Senate Resources Committee of the legislature.  If the offense for which the citation is issued is one that may be disposed of without court appearance, the citing officer shall write on the citation the amount of bail applicable to the cited offense.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-960__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a person cited for an offense for which a bail amount has been established under (b) of this section does not contest the citation, the person may, on or before the 30th day after the date of the citation, mail or personally deliver to the clerk of the court having jurisdiction over the place where the offense occurred</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-960__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the amount of bail indicated on the citation for that offense; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-21-960__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a copy of the citation indicating the offender's waiver of appearance, plea of no contest, and direction to forfeit the bail and any items seized from the offender.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-960__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When bail has been forfeited under this section, a judgment of conviction shall be entered. Forfeiture under this section of bail and items seized from the offender is a complete satisfaction for the offense, and the clerk of the court shall provide the offender with a receipt stating that fact if requested.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-960__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person cited under this section is guilty of failure to obey a citation under
AS 12.25.230
if the person fails to pay the bail amount established under (b) of this section or fails to appear in court as required.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-21-960__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding other provisions of law, if a person cited for a misdemeanor for which a bail amount has been established under (b) of this section appears in court and is found guilty, the penalty that is imposed for the offense may not exceed the bail amount for that offense established under (b) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-21-990">
            <num>41.21.990</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.21.990.   Definitions.
In this chapter,
(1) scenic park means relatively spacious areas of outstanding natural significance, where major values are in their natural geological, faunal, or floral characteristics, the purpose of which is directed primarily toward the preservation of its outstanding natural features and where development is minimal and only for the purpose of making the areas available for public enjoyment in a manner consistent with the preservation of the natural values such as camping, picnicking, sightseeing, nature study, hiking, riding, and related activities which involve no major modification of the land, forests, or waters, and without extensive introduction of artificial features or forms of recreational development that are primarily of urban character;
(2) wilderness park means an area whose predominant character is the result of the interplay of natural processes, large enough and so situated as to be unaffected, except in minor ways, by what takes place in the nonwilderness around it, a physical condition which activates the innermost emotions of the observer and where development of man-made objects will be strictly limited and depend entirely on good taste and judgment so that the wilderness values are not lost.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>