<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-18/chapter-50"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-18/chapter-50"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="18.50"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-18/chapter-50/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-18/chapter-50/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-18/chapter-50/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-18/chapter-50/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_18">
        <num>18</num>
        <heading>Health, Safety, Housing, Human Rights, and Public Defender</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_18__chp_50">
          <num>50</num>
          <heading>Vital Statistics Act</heading>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-010">
            <num>18.50.010</num>
            <heading>Bureau of Vital Statistics.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.50.010.   Bureau of Vital Statistics.
There is established within the department a section to be called the Bureau of Vital Statistics which shall install, maintain, and operate the state system of vital statistics.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-020">
            <num>18.50.020</num>
            <heading>Department to adopt regulations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.50.020.   Department to adopt regulations.
The department may, in compliance with
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act), adopt, amend, and repeal regulations for the purpose of carrying out this chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-030">
            <num>18.50.030</num>
            <heading>Appointment of state registrar of vital statistics.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.50.030.   Appointment of state registrar of vital statistics.
The commissioner shall select the state registrar of vital statistics in accordance with state personnel laws and regulations.  The registrar shall carry out the provisions of this chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-040">
            <num>18.50.040</num>
            <heading>Duties of state registrar.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.50.040.   Duties of state registrar.
The state registrar shall
(1) administer and enforce this chapter and the regulations adopted under it, and issue instructions for the efficient administration of the statewide system of vital statistics;
(2) direct and supervise the statewide system of vital statistics and the bureau, and keep its records;
(3) direct, supervise, and control the activities of local registrars related to the operation of the vital statistics system;
(4) prescribe and furnish the forms required by this chapter and the regulations issued under it;
(5) prepare and publish reports of vital statistics and other required statistical reports.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-050">
            <num>18.50.050</num>
            <heading>Delegation of duties.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.50.050.   Delegation of duties.
The state registrar may delegate the functions and duties vested in the state registrar to employees of the bureau and to local registrars as the state registrar considers necessary or expedient.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-060">
            <num>18.50.060</num>
            <heading>Seal.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.50.060.   Seal.
The state registrar shall have a seal, which shall bear within the perimeter of the seal the words Seal of the State Registrar of Vital Statistics of Alaska, and within the circle, at the top of the seal, a star representing the north star, beneath it the Dipper of seven stars, and beneath this a quill.  The seal shall be used in the certification of copies of records under custody of the state registrar, and to authenticate other copies, documents, records, and reports the state registrar considers necessary.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-070">
            <num>18.50.070</num>
            <heading>Registration districts.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.50.070.   Registration districts.
The state registrar shall establish registration districts throughout the state. The state registrar may consolidate or subdivide a district to facilitate registration. Registration districts shall take into account the boundary lines of local governmental units, house districts, judicial districts, and other local boundary lines in general use, where feasible.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-080">
            <num>18.50.080</num>
            <heading>Appointment of local registrars.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-50-080__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Where feasible, the state registrar shall use the services of a local recording official located within a registration district as local registrar of vital statistics.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-080__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Where utilization under (a) of this section is not feasible, the state registrar shall appoint a local registrar and may appoint one or more deputy local registrars of vital statistics for each registration district, to be compensated on a fee basis as specified in
AS 18.50.120
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-080__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The state registrar may remove a local registrar or a deputy local registrar appointed under (b) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-090">
            <num>18.50.090</num>
            <heading>Duties of local registrars.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.50.090.   Duties of local registrars.
Within the local registration district, the local registrar shall
(1) administer and enforce this chapter, and the instructions issued and regulations adopted under it;
(2) require that certificates be completed and filed in accordance with this chapter, and the instructions issued and regulations adopted under it;
(3) transmit monthly, or more frequently when directed to do so by the state registrar, the certificates, reports, or other returns filed with the local registrar, to the local recording official or to the bureau in accordance with the regulations adopted and instructions issued under this chapter;
(4) maintain the records, make reports, and perform the other duties required by the state registrar.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-100">
            <num>18.50.100</num>
            <heading>Keeping of permanent records.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.50.100.   Keeping of permanent records.
The state registrar may, where feasible, require permanent local records to be kept in the form of copies of the original vital statistics records. The state registrar shall designate in each case how this is to be done by the local recording official, in connection with other local registrars of vital statistics in the recording area.  The state registrar shall issue instructions concerning the keeping of these records, their disclosure, corrections, issuance of copies, and fees to be charged.  In matters pertaining to the system of vital statistics, the local recording officials and local registrars shall be directly supervised in this work by the state registrar.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-110">
            <num>18.50.110</num>
            <heading>Duties of deputy local registrar.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.50.110.   Duties of deputy local registrar.
In accordance with regulations adopted under this chapter, the deputy local registrar shall perform the duties of the local registrar in the absence or incapacity of the local registrar and shall perform other duties required by the state registrar.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-120">
            <num>18.50.120</num>
            <heading>Compensation of local registrars.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.50.120.   Compensation of local registrars.
When a local recording official receiving a salary or other regular compensation for general recording duties serves as local registrar of vital statistics, the local registrar is not entitled to fees under this section. Otherwise, local registrars of vital statistics shall be paid, from funds appropriated for this purpose, as follows:
(1) for a certificate of birth, death, fetal death, or marriage occurring in the registration district, properly completed and transmitted by the local registrar in accordance with the regulations adopted and instructions issued under this chapter, $2;
(2) for each monthly report indicating the number of the various vital events that occurred in the registration district, properly made in accordance with the regulations adopted and instructions issued under this chapter, $1.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-130">
            <num>18.50.130</num>
            <heading>Subregistrars.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-50-130__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In registration districts containing scattered villages, the local registrar may, with the approval of the state registrar, designate one person in each village as subregistrar for a designated area.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-130__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The subregistrar is responsible for preparing, signing, and filing with the local registrar, in accordance with instructions of the bureau, a certificate for each birth, death, and fetal death occurring in the area designated and not attended by a physician or nurse.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-130__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For each certificate filed in accordance with instructions of the bureau the subregistrar is entitled to a fee of $1.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-140">
            <num>18.50.140</num>
            <heading>Payment of fees to local registrars and others.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.50.140.   Payment of fees to local registrars and others.
The state registrar shall certify monthly, or at least quarterly, the number and type of records filed by, and the amount due to each local registrar and deputy registrar, and the amount due to each subregistrar. Upon certification, the amounts due shall be paid from the proper state appropriations by the Department of Administration.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-150">
            <num>18.50.150</num>
            <heading>Form of certificate.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.50.150.   Form of certificate.
The form of certificates, reports, and other returns required by this chapter, or by regulations adopted under it, must include as a minimum the items recommended by the federal agency responsible for national vital statistics subject to approval of any modification by the state registrar.  The bureau shall prescribe and furnish forms.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-160">
            <num>18.50.160</num>
            <heading>Birth registration.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-50-160__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A certificate of birth for each live birth that occurs in the state shall be filed with the bureau, as provided in this section, within five days after the birth. When a birth occurs on a moving conveyance within the United States and the child is first removed from the conveyance in this state, the birth shall be registered in this state and the place where the child is first removed shall be considered the place of birth. When a birth occurs on a moving conveyance in international waters, international air space, a foreign country, or a foreign country's air space and the child is first removed from the conveyance in this state, the birth shall be registered in this state but the certificate shall show the actual place of birth if the place can be determined.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-160__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When a birth occurs in or en route to an institution, the person in charge of the institution or a designated representative of the person in charge of the institution shall obtain the personal data, prepare the certificate, certify that the child was born alive at the place and time and on the date stated either by signature on the certificate or another certification process, including an electronic process, approved by the bureau, and file the certificate as directed in (a) of this section. The physician or other person in attendance shall provide the medical information required by the certificate within 72 hours after the birth.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-160__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When a birth occurs outside an institution, the certificate shall be prepared and filed by one of the following in the indicated order of priority:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-160__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the physician in attendance at or immediately after the birth; or, in the absence of a physician,</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-160__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a person other than a parent in attendance at or immediately after the birth; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-160__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a parent; or, if a parent is unable,</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-160__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the person in charge of the premises where the birth occurs.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-160__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the mother was married at conception, during the pregnancy, or at birth, the name of the husband shall be entered on the certificate as the father of the child unless</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-160__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>paternity has been lawfully determined otherwise by a tribunal, in which case the name of the father, if determined by a tribunal, shall be entered; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-160__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>both the mother and the mother's husband execute affidavits attesting that the husband is not the father and that another man is the father, and the mother and the other man execute affidavits attesting that the other man is the father, so long as the affidavits meet the requirements of (g) of this section.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-160__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the mother was not married at conception, during the pregnancy, or at birth, the name of the father may not be entered on the certificate of birth unless</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-160__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>paternity has been lawfully determined by a tribunal, in which case the name of the father, if determined by the tribunal, shall be entered;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-160__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>both the mother and the man to be named as the father have executed affidavits attesting that that man is the father, so long as the affidavits meet the requirements of (g) of this section and
AS 18.50.165
; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-160__subsec_e__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>otherwise specified by statute.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-160__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In the case of a child born out of wedlock, the certificate of birth shall be filed in accordance with (a), (b), and (c) of this section unless the state registrar directs another procedure.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-160__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An affidavit under (d) or (e) of this section must meet the following requirements:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-160__subsec_g__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the affidavit must be executed by all required individuals; an affidavit may be executed jointly, individually, or in combination of jointly and individually; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-160__subsec_g__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if an affidavit is executed by more than one individual, the signature of each individual must be individually notarized.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-160__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, unless the context requires otherwise, tribunal means a court, administrative agency, or quasi-judicial entity authorized by law to determine parentage.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-162">
            <num>18.50.162</num>
            <heading>Notification about hearing screening.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.50.162.   Notification about hearing screening.
When the bureau receives a certificate of live birth under
AS 18.50.160
for a newborn who was delivered outside of a hospital, the bureau shall forward the names and addresses of the parents to the department employees who administer the screening program set out in
AS 47.20.310
 47.20.390. Those department employees shall notify the child's parents of the merits of having the child screened for hearing ability.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-165">
            <num>18.50.165</num>
            <heading>Acknowledgement of paternity; forms.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-50-165__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The state registrar shall prepare a form for use in acknowledging paternity under
AS 25.20.055
. The form must comply with the minimum requirements of 42 U.S.C. 652(a)(7). The form must include</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-165__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a statement that the man who signs the form is acknowledging that the man is the natural father of the child named in the form and that the man assumes the parental duty of support of that child;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-165__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the address and social security number of both parents of the child named in the form;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-165__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>signature lines for both parents;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-165__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a signature line for either a witness or notary public; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-165__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a statement that
(A) sets out the legal consequences to and the rights and responsibilities of the mother and the man acknowledging paternity of signing the form, including</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-165__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>if one of the parents is a minor, any rights given due to minority status;
(ii) legal alternatives to signing the form; and
(iii) the legal responsibility that arises from signing the form;
(B) the mother and the man acknowledging paternity have been notified that, unless fraud, duress, or material mistake of fact is shown in accordance with
AS 25.20.050
, the acknowledgment may only be rescinded by the earlier of the following dates:</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-165__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>60 days after the date of the person's signature; or
(ii) the date of initiation of an administrative or judicial procedure to establish support of the child in which the person is a party; and
(C) the mother and the man acknowledging paternity have read and understand the contents of the form.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-165__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The registrar shall distribute copies of the form prepared under (a) of this section to each hospital in the state, to each physician in the state whose practice includes attendance at births, to each certified nurse midwife and certified direct-entry midwife in the state, and to each other interested person in the state who requests copies of the form.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-165__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 148 ch 87 SLA 1997.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-165__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The state registrar shall keep on file all forms acknowledging paternity that are submitted to the registrar under
AS 25.20.055
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-165__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An acknowledgment of paternity that met the requirements of state law at the time that the acknowledgment was made in this state is not ineffective due to changes in the form for acknowledgment occurring after the date that the acknowledgment was made.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-165__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An acknowledgment of paternity affidavit or form executed in another state meeting that state's legal requirements shall be considered in this state as if the affidavit or form was executed in compliance with this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-165__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The registrar shall offer voluntary acknowledgment of paternity services by making available technical assistance about the form described in this section. Upon request, the registrar shall provide oral assistance to parents wishing to complete the form.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-170">
            <num>18.50.170</num>
            <heading>Foundling registration.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-50-170__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The person who assumes the custody of a living infant of unknown parentage shall within seven days report the information prescribed by the state registrar on a form and in the manner prescribed by the state registrar to the local registrar of the registration district in which the child was found.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-170__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The place where the child was found shall be entered as the place of birth and the date of birth shall be determined by approximation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-170__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A report registered under this section constitutes the certificate of birth for the infant.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-170__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the child is identified and a certificate of birth is found or obtained, a report registered under this section shall be sealed and filed in accordance with instructions of the state registrar, and may be opened only by order of a superior court or as provided by regulation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-180">
            <num>18.50.180</num>
            <heading>Delayed registration of birth.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-50-180__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the birth of a person born in the state has not been registered, a certificate may be filed in accordance with regulations adopted under this chapter. The certificate shall be registered subject to the evidentiary requirements the department prescribes by regulation to substantiate the alleged facts of birth.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-180__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the birth occurred more than seven days but less than one year before the application for registration, the birth may be filed with the proper local registrar in accordance with regulations adopted under this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-180__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the birth occurred one year or more before the application for registration, the birth shall be filed on a form prescribed by the bureau, and shall be submitted to the bureau for registration.  The state registrar may accept the certificate for registration when the evidence required by regulation is submitted to substantiate the facts of birth.  A certificate registered under this subsection shall be marked delayed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-180__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the birth occurred 12 years or more before the application for registration, the certificate of birth shall be prepared on a form entitled delayed certificate of birth. The information provided on this form shall be subscribed and sworn to by the person whose birth is to be registered before an official authorized to administer oaths. When a person is not competent to swear to this information it shall be subscribed and sworn to by a parent, legal guardian, or the person's representative.  The form must provide for the name and sex of the person whose birth is to be registered; the place and date of birth; and other information required by the bureau. When the certificate is submitted, the state registrar shall add a description and an abstract of each document submitted in support of the delayed registration. The original delayed certificate of birth shall be filed with the bureau.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-180__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The state registrar shall accept the registration if the applicant was born in the state and if the applicant's sworn statements are established to the satisfaction of the state registrar by the necessary evidence established by regulation. The items necessary to be substantiated, the type of documents acceptable as evidence, the number of necessary documents, and the form and content of the description and abstract of each document to be added to the certificate shall be prescribed by regulation. In general they shall follow the national standards recommended by the agencies responsible for national vital statistics and for the use of records in the interest of national security.  The state registrar may make exceptions when necessary by reducing the number of documents required for delayed filings by Indians, Eskimos and Aleuts, natives of the state, if the state registrar is otherwise satisfied with the validity of the application.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-180__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the applicant does not submit documentation required in support of the applicant's statements or when the state registrar finds reason to question the validity or adequacy of the certificate or the supporting evidence, the state registrar may not accept the delayed certificate of birth and shall advise the applicant of the reasons for this action, and of the applicant's right of appeal to the superior court. The bureau may provide for the dismissal of an application that is not actively prosecuted.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-190">
            <num>18.50.190</num>
            <heading>Delayed registration of death or marriage.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.50.190.   Delayed registration of death or marriage.
When a death or marriage occurring in the state has not been registered, a certificate may be filed in accordance with regulations adopted under this chapter. The certificate shall be registered subject to evidentiary requirements prescribed by the department by regulation to substantiate the alleged facts of death or marriage.  Certificates of death and marriage registered one year or more after the date of occurrence shall be marked delayed.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-200">
            <num>18.50.200</num>
            <heading>Judicial procedure to establish facts of birth.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-50-200__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a delayed certificate of birth is not accepted under
AS 18.50.180
, a petition may be filed with the superior court for an order establishing a record of the date and place of birth of the person.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-200__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The petition shall be made on a form prescribed and furnished by the bureau, and must contain the following statements, sworn to by the petitioner:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-200__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>that the person for whom a delayed certificate of birth is sought was born in the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-200__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>that no record of birth of the person can be found in the bureau or in the files of the local custodian of birth records;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-200__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>that diligent efforts by the petitioner have failed to obtain the necessary evidence to file a delayed certificate with the bureau;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-200__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>that the state registrar has refused to register a delayed certificate of birth;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-200__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>other statements and information as may be required.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-200__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The petition shall be accompanied by a statement of the state registrar made in accordance with
AS 18.50.180</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-200__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and all documentary evidence that was submitted to the bureau in support of the registration.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-200__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The court shall fix a time and place for hearing the petition, and the state registrar shall be given 15 days' notice of the hearing.  The state registrar or an authorized representative may appear and testify in the proceeding.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-200__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the court from the evidence presented finds that the person for whom a delayed certificate of birth is sought was born in the state, it shall make findings as to the place and date of birth, and other findings the petition requires and shall issue an order on a form prescribed and furnished by the bureau to establish a record of birth.  This order must include the birth data to be registered, a description of the evidence presented in the manner prescribed under
AS 18.50.180
, and the date of the court's action, and shall be marked as a court order.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-200__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The clerk of the superior court shall forward each order to the bureau before the 11th day of the calendar month following the month in which it was entered.  The bureau shall register the order and the order constitutes the record of birth. Copies of the record of birth may be issued in accordance with the provisions of this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-210">
            <num>18.50.210</num>
            <heading>Court reports of adoption.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-50-210__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For each adoption decreed by a court in the state, the court shall require the preparation of a report of adoption on a form prescribed and furnished by the bureau. The report must include the facts necessary to locate and identify the original certificate of birth, if any, of the person adopted. If the person being adopted was born in the state, the report must provide information necessary to establish a new certificate of birth. If the person being adopted was born outside the United States, the report must provide findings, if requested by the adoptive parents, or other information necessary to establish a certificate of birth.  The report must identify the order of adoption, and be certified by the court or the clerk.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-210__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The petitioner or the attorney for the petitioner shall furnish with the petition for adoption information in the possession of the petitioner necessary to prepare the adoption report. The social welfare agency or other person concerned shall supply the court with additional information necessary to complete the report if the information is in the possession of the agency or the person. The furnishing of the information is a prerequisite to the issuance of a final decree in the matter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-210__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Whenever an adoption decree is amended or vacated, the court shall prepare a report on a form prescribed and furnished by the bureau.  The report must include the facts necessary to identify the original adoption report and the facts amended in the adoption decree necessary to properly amend the original report, or the new certificate of birth if already established.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-210__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before the 11th day of each calendar month, the court shall forward to the bureau reports of decrees of adoption, including those vacated or amended, that were entered in the preceding month, together with the related reports the bureau requires.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-210__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the bureau receives a report of an adoption, or vacation or amendment of an adoption from a court for a person born in the United States but outside the state, a copy shall be made for the bureau's files and the original shall be forwarded to the appropriate registration authority in the state of birth.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-211">
            <num>18.50.211</num>
            <heading>Certificate of birth for foreign-born adopted person.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-50-211__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The state registrar shall issue a certificate of birth for a person born outside the United States whose adoptive parents are residents of the state at the time of the adoption, upon request by the adopted person, or by the adopted person's adoptive parent or guardian that the certificate be made, and upon receipt of an adoption report as provided in
AS 18.50.210
together with</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-211__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the information necessary to identify the original certificate of birth; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-211__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if there is no original certificate of birth, the findings of the court under
AS 25.23.175
, unless the adoption proceeding is commenced before August 31, 1982, in which case an affidavit of an adoptive parent setting out the true or probable date and place of birth and parentage of the adopted person must accompany the adoption report.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-211__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 2 ch 14 SLA 1995.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-211__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A certificate of birth issued under this section shall be in a form prescribed by the state registrar and shall state that it is not evidence of United States citizenship.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-211__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon proof of naturalization an amended certificate of birth shall be issued under this section that deletes the statement that the certificate is not evidence of United States citizenship.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-220">
            <num>18.50.220</num>
            <heading>New certificate of birth.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-50-220__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The state registrar shall establish a new certificate of birth for a person born in the state, upon proper request that the certificate be made, and upon receipt of</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-220__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an adoption report as provided in
AS 18.50.210
, or a certified copy of the decree of adoption from a court of competent jurisdiction in another state, together with the information necessary to identify the original certificate of birth and to establish the new certificate of birth; however, a new certificate of birth may not be established if so requested by the court decreeing the adoption, the adoptive parents, or the adopted person if the adopted person is of legal age; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-220__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the evidence required by law and regulation proving that the person has been legitimated.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-220__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When a new certificate of birth is established, the actual place and date of birth shall be shown.  The new certificate shall be substituted for the original certificate of birth, and</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-220__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>thereafter, in the case of an adoption, the original certificate and the evidence of adoption are not subject to inspection except as provided in
AS 18.50.500
 18.50.510 or by order of the superior court under
AS 25.23.150
, but the state registrar shall allow inspection by an agent of the state or federal government acting in the performance of the agent's official duties; in the case of a legitimation, the original certificate and the evidence of legitimation are not subject to inspection except upon order of the superior court or as provided by regulation; however, the regulation shall allow inspection by an agent of the state or federal government acting in the performance of the agent's official duties;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-220__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>upon receipt of a report that an adoption has been vacated, the original certificate of birth shall be restored to its place in the files and the new certificate and evidence are not subject to inspection except upon order of a superior court.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-220__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If no certificate of birth is on file for the person for whom a new certificate is to be established under this section, a delayed certificate of birth shall be filed with the bureau as provided in this chapter before a new certificate of birth may be established.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-220__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When a new certificate of birth is established by the state registrar, the state registrar shall direct the disposition of and substitution for all copies of the original certificate of birth in the custody of a local registrar of vital statistics or other local custodian of the records.  When an adoption has been vacated, the state registrar shall instruct the local officials as to a necessary action.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-225">
            <num>18.50.225</num>
            <heading>Birth certificates suitable for display.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-50-225__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to another birth certificate issued under this chapter, the state registrar shall issue, on request and payment of a fee of $25, a birth certificate representing that the birth of the person named on the certificate is recorded in the office of the registrar. The fee required under this subsection is in addition to a fee required under
AS 18.50.330
for a copy of a birth certificate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-225__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The certificate issued under (a) of this section must be in a form consistent with the need to protect the integrity of vital records and must be suitable for display.  It may bear the seal of the state and may be signed by the governor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-225__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A certificate issued under (a) of this section has the same status as evidence as an original birth certificate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-225__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The estimated amount by which the fees received under this section exceed the cost of issuing birth certificates under (a) of this section may be appropriated annually by the legislature to the Alaska children's trust grant account (
AS 37.14.205
).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-230">
            <num>18.50.230</num>
            <heading>Death registration; disclosure for child support purposes.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-50-230__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A death certificate for each death that occurs in the state shall be filed with the local registrar of the registration district in which the death occurred within three days after death and before final disposition of the body or removal of the body from the state, except as provided by regulation in special problem cases. For the purpose of this section, if the place of death is unknown, a death certificate shall be filed in the registration district in which the dead body is found. When a death occurs on a moving conveyance a death certificate shall be filed in the registration district in which the dead body is first removed from the conveyance.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-230__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The funeral director or person acting as the funeral director who first assumes custody of a dead body shall file the death certificate.  The funeral director or the person acting as the funeral director shall obtain the personal data from the next of kin or the best qualified person or source available and the medical certification of cause of death from the person responsible for this information.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-230__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The medical certification shall be completed and signed within 24 hours after death by the physician, the advanced practice registered nurse, or the physician assistant in charge of the patient's care for the illness or condition that resulted in death except when an official inquiry or inquest is required and except as provided by regulation in special problem cases.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-230__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When a death occurs without medical attendance, or when official inquiry is required, the department shall provide by regulation, in accordance with law, the responsibility for completing and signing the medical certification. This subsection is intended to include, among others, cases involving a medical examiner and cases involving presumption of death.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-230__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To assist the Alaska Court System to remove the names of deceased persons from jury lists under
AS 09.20.050
(c), the state registrar of vital statistics shall forward to the administrative director of the Alaska Court System the names of persons for whom certificates of death were issued and reported to the registrar.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-230__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A death certificate issued under this section must include the decedent's social security number, if ascertainable. Upon request, the registrar shall provide a decedent's social security number to the child support services agency created in
AS 25.27.010
, or the child support agency of another state, for child support purposes authorized under law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-235">
            <num>18.50.235</num>
            <heading>Certificate of birth resulting in stillbirth.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-50-235__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After a stillbirth occurs in the state, the person required to file a fetal death registration under
AS 18.50.240</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-235__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>shall advise the mother and, if the father is present, the father</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-235__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>that the parent may request the preparation of a certificate of birth resulting in stillbirth;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-235__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>that the parent may obtain a certificate of birth resulting in stillbirth by contacting the bureau; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-235__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>of the contact information for the bureau.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-235__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A parent who requests a certificate of birth resulting in stillbirth may provide a name for placement on the certificate. If a name is not provided, the bureau shall cause the certificate to show either baby boy or baby girl, as appropriate, and the last name of the parent who requested the certificate. The name provided on the certificate of birth resulting in stillbirth must be the same name as the name on the fetal death certificate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-235__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A certificate of birth resulting in stillbirth must include the state file number of the corresponding fetal death certificate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-235__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall prescribe the form and content of a certificate of birth resulting in stillbirth to record the birth and specify the information required to prepare the certificate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-235__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A certificate issued under this section is not proof of a live birth, and the certificate must contain the phrase not proof of live birth. The bureau may not use a certificate of birth resulting in stillbirth to calculate live birth statistics.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-235__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A parent may request that the bureau issue a certificate of birth resulting in stillbirth regardless of the date on which the certificate of fetal death was issued.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-235__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may adopt regulations needed to implement this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-235__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-235__subsec_h__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>fetal death has the meaning given in
AS 18.50.950
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-235__subsec_h__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>stillbirth means a fetal death that resulted in the issuance of a fetal death certificate under
AS 18.50.240
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-240">
            <num>18.50.240</num>
            <heading>Fetal death registration.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-50-240__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A fetal death certificate for each fetal death that occurs in the state shall be filed with the local registrar of the registration district in which the delivery occurred within three days after the delivery and before final disposition of the fetus or removal of the fetus from the state, except as provided by regulation in special problem cases. However, the filing of a certificate for a product of a pregnancy of less than 20 weeks may be determined by regulation. For the purposes of this section, if the place of fetal death is unknown, a fetal death certificate shall be filed in the registration district in which the dead fetus is found. When a fetal death occurs on a moving conveyance a fetal death certificate shall be filed in the registration district in which the fetus is first removed from the conveyance.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-240__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The funeral director or person acting as the funeral director who first assumes custody of a fetus shall file the fetal death certificate.  In the absence of a funeral director or a person acting as a funeral director, the physician or other person in attendance at or after the delivery shall file the certificate of fetal death.  The person who files the certificate shall obtain the personal data from the next of kin or the best qualified person or source available and the medical certification of cause of death from the person responsible for this information.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-240__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The medical certification shall be completed and signed within 24 hours after delivery by the physician in attendance at or after delivery except when an official inquiry or inquest is required and except as provided by regulation in special problem cases.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-240__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When a fetal death occurs without medical attendance upon the mother at or after the delivery, or when official inquiry is required, the department shall provide by regulation, in accordance with law, the responsibility for completing and signing the medical certification.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-245">
            <num>18.50.245</num>
            <heading>Report of induced termination of pregnancy.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-50-245__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A hospital, clinic, or other institution where an induced termination of pregnancy is performed in the state shall submit a report directly to the state registrar within 30 days after the induced termination is completed. The report may not contain the name of the patient whose pregnancy was terminated but must contain the information required by the state registrar in regulations adopted under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-245__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When an induced termination of pregnancy is performed by a physician outside of a hospital, clinic, or other institution, the physician shall submit the report required under this section within 30 days after the induced termination of pregnancy is completed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-245__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-245__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an induced termination of pregnancy is considered to be performed where the act interrupting the pregnancy is performed even if the resultant expulsion of the product of conception occurs elsewhere;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-245__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>prescription of a medicine by a physician who knows that the medicine will be taken with the intention of inducing termination of a pregnancy is considered to be the act that interrupts the pregnancy even if the medicine is taken outside of the physician's presence; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-245__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an induced termination of pregnancy is considered to be completed when the product of conception is extracted or expulsed.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-245__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The state registrar shall annually prepare a statistical report based on the reports received under this section. The report must include the types of information required under (e) of this section, except that the statistical report may not identify or give information that can be used to identify the name of any physician who performed an induced termination of pregnancy, the name of any facility in which an induced termination of pregnancy occurred, or the name of the municipality or community in which the induced termination of pregnancy occurred. The data gathered from the reports received under this section may only be presented in aggregate statistics, not individually, so that specific individuals may not be identified. After preparation of the annual report, the state registrar shall destroy the reports received under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-245__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The state registrar shall adopt regulations to implement this section. The regulations that establish the information that will be required in a report of an induced termination of pregnancy</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-245__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>must require information substantially similar to the information required under the United States Standard Report of Induced Termination of Pregnancy, as published by the National Center for Health Statistics, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, United States Department of Health and Human Services, in April 1998, as part of DHHS Publication No. (PHS) 98-1117;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-245__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>must require, if known, whether the unidentified patient requested and received a written copy of the information required to be maintained on the Internet under
AS 18.05.032
; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-245__subsec_e__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>may not include provisions that would violate a woman's privacy by requiring the woman's name or any identifying information in the report.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-250">
            <num>18.50.250</num>
            <heading>Permits.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-50-250__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (e) of this section, the funeral director or person acting as the funeral director who first assumes custody of a dead body or fetus shall obtain a burial-transit permit before final disposition or removal from the state of the body or fetus and within 72 hours after death, except as otherwise authorized by regulation for special problem cases.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-250__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The local registrar of the registration district where the death occurred shall issue a burial-transit permit when a certificate of death or fetal death has been filed in accordance with this chapter, except as otherwise authorized by regulation in special problem cases.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-250__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A burial-transit permit that accompanies a dead body or fetus brought into the state is authority for final disposition of the body or fetus in the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-250__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A permit for disinterment and reinterment is required before disinterment of a dead body or fetus except as authorized by regulation or otherwise provided by law.  Upon proper application the permit shall be issued by the local registrar of vital statistics in accordance with instructions of the state registrar.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-250__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The state medical examiner shall obtain the burial-transit permit before a body is transported under
AS 12.65.025
(a)(2).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-260">
            <num>18.50.260</num>
            <heading>Extension of time.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-50-260__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>By regulation and upon the conditions it prescribes to assure compliance with the purposes of this chapter, the department may provide for the extension of the periods prescribed in
AS 18.50.160
and 18.50.230  18.50.250 for the filing of birth certificates, death certificates, fetal death certificates, medical certifications or causes of death, and for the obtaining of permits, in cases in which compliance with the applicable prescribed period would result in undue hardship.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-260__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Regulations may provide for the issuance of a burial-transit permit under
AS 18.50.250
before the filing of a certificate of death or fetal death upon conditions designed to assure compliance with the purposes of this chapter in a case in which compliance with the requirement that the certificate be filed before the issuance of the permit would result in undue hardship.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-270">
            <num>18.50.270</num>
            <heading>Marriage registration.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-50-270__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A certificate of marriage for each marriage performed in the state shall be filed with the local registrar of vital statistics of the registration district in which the marriage was performed within seven days of the marriage.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-270__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The official who issues the marriage license shall prepare the certificate of marriage on forms prescribed and furnished by the bureau, as specified elsewhere in the statutes and in regulations adopted under this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-270__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who performs a marriage shall complete the forms as specified elsewhere in the statutes or in regulations adopted under this chapter, and shall file the original certificate of marriage with the local registrar.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-270__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An official issuing a marriage license shall report to the state registrar before the 11th day of each calendar month, on forms prescribed and furnished by the bureau, the information required concerning each marriage license issued during the preceding month.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-272">
            <num>18.50.272</num>
            <heading>Heirloom certificates of marriage suitable for display.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-50-272__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to a certificate of marriage issued under this chapter, the state registrar shall issue, on request and payment of a fee established by regulation, an heirloom certificate of marriage representing the marriage of the persons named on the certificate of marriage that is recorded in the office of the registrar.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-272__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall adopt regulations that establish the amount of the fee for each design of an heirloom certificate of marriage. Notwithstanding
AS 37.10.050
(a), each fee shall be set at an amount that is more than the estimated actual costs to the department, not to exceed the estimated fair market value of a comparable artistic rendition. The fee required under this subsection is in addition to any fee established under
AS 18.50.330
for a copy of a certificate of marriage.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-272__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The certificate issued under (a) of this section must be in a form consistent with the need to protect the integrity of vital records and must be suitable for display. It may bear the seal of the state and may be signed by the governor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-272__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An heirloom certificate of marriage issued under (a) of this section has the same status as evidence as an original certificate of marriage filed under
AS 18.50.270
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-272__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The estimated amount by which the fees received under this section exceed the cost of issuing heirloom certificates of marriage under (a) of this section may be appropriated annually by the legislature to the Alaska children's trust grant account (
AS 37.14.205
).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-280">
            <num>18.50.280</num>
            <heading>Court reports of divorce, dissolution, and annulment.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-50-280__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For each dissolution, divorce, and annulment of marriage granted by a court in the state, the clerk of the court shall prepare and file a certificate of dissolution, divorce, or annulment with the bureau, on forms prescribed and furnished by the bureau. The forms must require the reporting of the social security numbers of the petitioner or plaintiff and, if ascertainable, the other party to the dissolution, divorce, or annulment of marriage. The petitioner or plaintiff shall furnish the court with the information necessary to complete the certificate, and the furnishing of this information is prerequisite to the issuance of a decree.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-280__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before the 11th day of each month the clerk of the court shall forward to the bureau the certificate of each dissolution, divorce, and annulment granted during the preceding calendar month and the related reports required by regulation adopted under this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-280__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon request, the bureau shall provide a social security number supplied under (a) of this section to the child support services agency created in
AS 25.27.010
, or the child support enforcement agency of another state, for child support purposes authorized under law.
Article 4. Records.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-290">
            <num>18.50.290</num>
            <heading>Corrections and amendments.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-50-290__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A certificate or record registered by the bureau may be amended only in accordance with this chapter and the regulations the department adopts to protect the integrity and accuracy of vital statistics records.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-290__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A certificate that is amended under this section shall be marked amended, with the date of amendment.  A summary description of the evidence submitted in support of the amendment shall be endorsed on or made a part of the record. The department shall prescribe by regulation the conditions under which additions or minor corrections may be made to vital statistics records without the certificate being considered amended.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-290__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon receipt of a certified copy of a court order changing the name of a person born in the state or a person born outside the United States whose adoptive parents are residents of the state at the time of the adoption and upon request of the person or the person's parent, guardian, or legal representative, the state registrar shall amend the certificate of birth to reflect the new name.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-290__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When a certificate is corrected or amended under this section, the state registrar shall instruct the local custodian of the copy of the certificate to make the changes in the copy.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-300">
            <num>18.50.300</num>
            <heading>Reproduction of records.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.50.300.   Reproduction of records.
To preserve original documents the state registrar may prepare typewritten, photographic, or other reproductions of original records and files in the state registrar's office.  When certified by the state registrar, the reproduction shall be accepted as the original record.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-310">
            <num>18.50.310</num>
            <heading>Disclosure of records.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-50-310__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To protect the integrity of vital statistics records, to ensure their proper use, and to ensure the efficient and proper administration of the vital statistics system, it is unlawful for a person to permit inspection of or to disclose information contained in vital statistics records, or to copy or issue a copy of all or part of a record, except as provided by this section or as authorized by regulations issued under this chapter. Regulations issued under this chapter may not authorize inspection, disclosure, or copying of all or part of any report or record received under
AS 18.50.245
, except that the statistical report prepared under
AS 18.50.245</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-310__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>may be copied and distributed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-310__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The bureau may permit the use of data contained in vital statistics records, other than reports of induced terminations of pregnancy, for research purposes.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-310__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Information in vital statistics records indicating that a birth occurred out of wedlock may not be disclosed except upon order of a superior court or as provided by regulations.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-310__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Appeals from decisions of the custodians of local records refusing disclosure under (a) and (b) of this section shall be made to the state registrar, whose decision is binding upon the custodian of local records.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-310__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may by regulation provide for the release of information, other than information in reports of induced terminations of pregnancy, to authorized representatives of organizations or foundations that counsel the next of kin of victims of sudden infant death syndrome.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-310__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding the provisions of
AS 40.25.120
, when 100 years have elapsed after the date of a birth, or 50 years have elapsed after the date of a death, marriage, divorce, dissolution of marriage, or annulment, the records of these events in the custody of the state registrar become public records subject to inspection and copying as provided in
AS 40.25.110
 40.25.140.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-310__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The principal health officer of a municipality, or a municipal health officer designated by the principal health officer, may inspect vital statistics records pertinent to the functions of the principal health officer. The state registrar may enter into an agreement with a municipality governing the conditions and purposes of those inspections.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-310__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Marriage license applications shall be open for public inspection or examination during normal business hours. The bureau may, in response to a request under
AS 25.27.300
, disclose to the child support services agency whether the bureau has a record indicating that a person has remarried after the date specified by the agency.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-310__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, principal health officer means the municipal official who is exercising health powers and who is primarily responsible for public health in the municipality.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-315">
            <num>18.50.315</num>
            <heading>Records of missing children.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-50-315__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon receiving notification by the Department of Public Safety or another law enforcement agency that a child born in this state is missing, the bureau shall flag the birth certificate record of the missing child in a manner that alerts the bureau to the fact that the record is that of a missing child when a copy of that birth certificate or information regarding that birth certificate is requested. Upon notification by the department that the person who was listed as a missing child has been found, the bureau shall remove the flag from the person's birth certificate record.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-315__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The bureau may not provide a copy of a birth certificate or information concerning the birth record of a person whose record is flagged under (a) of this section except as provided in this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-315__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When a copy of a flagged birth certificate is requested, the bureau shall immediately notify the Department of Public Safety. If a flagged record is requested in person, the bureau shall record the name, address, and telephone number of the person making the request. The bureau may only provide a copy of the requested birth certificate by mail.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-315__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-315__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>child means a person under 18 years of age;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-315__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>law enforcement agency has the meaning given in
AS 12.36.090
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-320">
            <num>18.50.320</num>
            <heading>Copies of data from vital records.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-50-320__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>a personal representative of the veteran's estate;
(ii) a trustee of a revocable trust of which the veteran was the settlor; or
(iii) a person who needs a certified copy of the veteran's death certificate for the purpose of satisfying an eligibility requirement for a benefit related to the death of the veteran;
(B) veteran means an individual who was</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-320__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>on active duty at the time of the veteran's death or had received an honorable or general discharge from a branch of the armed services of the United States, the National Guard, a reserve unit of the United States armed services, the Alaska Scouts, the Alaska Territorial Guard, or the Alaska Naval Militia; and
(ii) a resident of the state at the time of the individual's death.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-330">
            <num>18.50.330</num>
            <heading>Fees for services.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-50-330__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The state registrar shall prescribe the fees to be paid for certified copies of certificates, for issuing marriage licenses, for searches of the files or records, for the filing of delayed or substitute certificates, for making amendments, for supplying documentary evidence for these purposes, and for special services rendered by the bureau.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-330__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 28 ch 90 SLA 1991.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-340">
            <num>18.50.340</num>
            <heading>Persons required to keep records.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-50-340__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person in charge of an institution shall keep a record of personal particulars and data concerning each person admitted or confined to the institution.  This record must include the information required by the certificates of birth, death, and fetal death issued under the provisions of this chapter, and other information required by the bureau.  The record shall be made at the time of admission from information provided by the person, but when it cannot be obtained from the person it shall be obtained from relatives or other sources acquainted with the facts.  The name and address of the person providing the information must be a part of the record.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-340__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When a dead human body or fetus is released or disposed of by an institution, the person in charge of the institution shall keep a record showing the name of the deceased, date of death, name and address of the person to whom the body is released, date of removal from the institution, or if finally disposed of by the institution, the date, place, and manner of disposition.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-340__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A funeral director, embalmer, or other person who removes from the place of death or transports or finally disposes of a dead body or fetus, in addition to filing a certificate or form required by this chapter, shall keep a record identifying the body, and the information pertaining to the receipt, removal, and delivery of the body required by the bureau.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-340__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Records maintained under this section shall be retained for a period of not less than five years and shall be made available for inspection by the state registrar or a representative of the state registrar upon demand.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-350">
            <num>18.50.350</num>
            <heading>Duty to furnish information.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.50.350.   Duty to furnish information.
A person having knowledge of the facts shall furnish the information the person possesses regarding a birth, death, fetal death, induced termination of pregnancy, marriage, or divorce, upon demand of the state registrar.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-500">
            <num>18.50.500</num>
            <heading>Identity of biological parents.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-50-500__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After receiving a request by an adopted person 18 years of age or older for the identity of a biological parent of the person, the state registrar shall provide the person with an uncertified copy of the person's original birth certificate and any change in the biological parent's name or address attached to the certificate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-500__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The state registrar may not disclose the name and address of a biological parent, except as required under (a) of this section or by the court under
AS 25.23.150
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-500__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An adopted person 18 years of age or older, or a biological parent, may submit to the state registrar a notice of change of name or address.  The state registrar shall attach the information to the original birth certificate of the adopted person.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-500__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The state registrar shall disclose to a biological parent, at that parent's request, the most current name and address of an adopted child that appear in the state registrar's adoption files if the child is 18 years of age or older and has requested in writing that the information be disclosed if ever requested by the biological parent.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-510">
            <num>18.50.510</num>
            <heading>Descriptive information regarding biological parents.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-50-510__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The state registrar shall, at the request of an adoptive parent or of an adopted person 18 years of age or older, release the following information regarding a biological parent named on the original birth certificate of the adopted person if available from the registrar's adoption records:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-510__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the age of the biological parent on the day the adopted person was born;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-510__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the heritage of the biological parent, to include
(A) national origin;
(B) ethnic background; and
(C) tribal membership;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-510__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the medical history of the biological parent and of blood relatives of the biological parent;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-510__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the number of years of school completed by the biological parent by the day the adopted person was born;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-510__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a physical description of the biological parent on the day the adopted person was born, including height, weight, and color of hair, eyes, and skin;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-510__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the existence of other children of the biological parent;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-510__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>whether the biological parent was alive at the time of adoption;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-510__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the religion of the biological parent; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-510__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>other information provided by the biological parent for disclosure to the child, which may include such items as photographs, letters, and a statement explaining the reasons for the adoption.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-510__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Information released under (a) of this section shall be on a standard form prepared by the commissioner. The information may not include the name of a biological parent or other information not listed in (a) of this section.
Article 6. General Provisions.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-900">
            <num>18.50.900</num>
            <heading>Prohibited acts and penalties.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-50-900__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person is guilty of a misdemeanor, and upon conviction is punishable by a fine of not more than $1,000, or by imprisonment for not more than one year, or by both, who</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-900__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>without lawful authority and with the intent to deceive, makes, alters, amends, or mutilates a certificate of birth or certified copy of a certificate of birth with the intent that it may be used;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-900__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>wilfully and knowingly uses or attempts to use, or furnishes to another for use, for the purpose of deception, a certificate of birth or certified copy of a record of birth so made, altered, amended, or mutilated;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-900__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>with the intention to deceive wilfully uses or attempts to use a certificate of birth or certified copy of a record of birth knowing that the certificate or certified copy was issued upon a record that is false in whole or in part or that relates to the birth of another person; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-900__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>wilfully and knowingly furnishes a certificate of birth or certified copy of a record of birth with the intention that it be used by a person other than the person to whom the record of birth relates.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-900__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person is guilty of a misdemeanor, and upon conviction is punishable by a fine of not more than $300, or by imprisonment for not more than three months, or by both, except when a more severe penalty is provided for in this chapter, who</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-900__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>wilfully and knowingly makes a false statement in a report or certificate of birth required to be filed under this chapter or regulations adopted under it, or in an application for amendment of it, or in an affidavit or paper submitted in support of such a certificate or application, with intent to induce or secure the registration of a birth, or the acceptance of a certificate of birth as evidence of the date and place of birth, identity, or citizenship, or the amendment of a birth certificate for a purpose of deception; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-900__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>wilfully and knowingly falsifies, makes or alters a certificate or certified copy of a vital statistics record except as provided in this chapter or regulations adopted under it.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-50-900__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person is guilty of a misdemeanor, and upon conviction is punishable by a fine of not more than $100, except when a different penalty is provided for in this chapter, who</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-900__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>knowingly transports or accepts for transportation, interment, or other final disposition a dead body without the required permit issued in accordance with this chapter or regulations adopted under it;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-900__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>refuses to provide information, or who knowingly furnishes false information, required by this chapter or regulations adopted under it; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-50-900__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>violates the provisions of this chapter or neglects or refuses to perform a duty imposed upon the person by this chapter or the regulations adopted under it.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-950">
            <num>18.50.950</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.50.950.   Definitions.
In this chapter,
(1) adoptive parent means a person who has adopted another person under
AS 25.23
;
(2) biological parent means a parent named on the original certificate of birth of an adopted person;
(3) bureau means the Bureau of Vital Statistics;
(4) commissioner means the commissioner of health;
(5) dead body means a lifeless human body or parts or bones of it from the state of which it reasonably may be concluded that death recently occurred;
(6) department means the Department of Health;
(7) fetal death means death before the complete expulsion or extraction from its mother of a product of human conception, irrespective of the duration of pregnancy, where
(A) the death is indicated by the fact that, after expulsion or extraction, the fetus does not breathe or show evidence of life such as beating of the heart, pulsation of the umbilical cord, or definite movement of voluntary muscles; and
(B) the expulsion or extraction is not caused by an induced termination of pregnancy;
(8) filing means the presentation of a certificate, report, or other record provided for in this chapter, of a birth, death, fetal death, adoption, marriage, or divorce for registration by the bureau;
(9) final disposition means the burial, interment, cremation, or other disposition of a dead body or fetus;
(10) induced termination of pregnancy means the purposeful interruption of an intrauterine pregnancy with the intention other than to produce a live-born infant, and that does not result in a live birth, except that induced termination of pregnancy does not include management of prolonged retention of products of conception following fetal death;
(11) institution means a public or private establishment that provides in-patient medical, surgical, or diagnostic care or treatment, or nursing, custodial, or domiciliary care to two or more unrelated individuals, or to which persons are committed by law;
(12) live birth means the complete expulsion or extraction from its mother of a product of human conception, irrespective of the duration of pregnancy, that, after expulsion or extraction, breathes or shows evidence of life such as beating of the heart, pulsation of the umbilical cord, or definite movement of voluntary muscles, whether or not the umbilical cord has been cut or the placenta is attached;
(13) medical history includes information relating to a person's medical conditions and treatment, immunization records, and other medical information about the person that could be important to the health care of the adopted person;
(14) physician means a person authorized or licensed to practice medicine under the laws of the state;
(15) registration means the acceptance by the bureau and the incorporation in its official records of certificates, reports, or other records provided for in this chapter, of births, deaths, fetal deaths, adoptions, marriages, or divorces;
(16) state registrar means the state registrar of vital statistics;
(17) system of vital statistics includes the registration, collection, preservation, amendment, and certification of vital statistics records, and related activities including the tabulation, analysis, and publication of statistical data derived from them;
(18) vital statistics means records of birth, death, fetal death, induced termination of pregnancy, marriage, divorce, adoption, and related data.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-50-990">
            <num>18.50.990</num>
            <heading>Short title.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.50.990.   Short title.
This chapter may be cited as the Vital Statistics Act.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>