<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-44/chapter-17"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-44/chapter-17"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="44.17"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-44/chapter-17/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-44/chapter-17/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-44/chapter-17/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-44/chapter-17/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_44">
        <num>44</num>
        <heading>State Government</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_44__chp_17">
          <num>17</num>
          <heading>Organization and Administration of Departments</heading>
          <section eId="sec_44-17-005">
            <num>44.17.005</num>
            <heading>Offices and departments.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.17.005.   Offices and departments.
There are in the state government the following principal offices and departments:
(1) Office of the Governor;
(2) Department of Administration;
(3) Department of Law;
(4) Department of Revenue;
(5) Department of Education and Early Development;
(6) Department of Health;
(7) Department of Labor and Workforce Development;
(8) Department of Commerce, Community, and Economic Development;
(9) Department of Military and Veterans' Affairs;
(10) Department of Natural Resources;
(11) Department of Fish and Game;
(12) Department of Public Safety;
(13) Department of Transportation and Public Facilities;
(14) Department of Environmental Conservation;
(15) Department of Corrections;
(16) Department of Family and Community Services.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-17-010">
            <num>44.17.010</num>
            <heading>Delegation of functions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.17.010.   Delegation of functions.
The principal executive officer of each state department may assign the functions vested in the department to subordinate officers and employees.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-17-020">
            <num>44.17.020</num>
            <heading>Divisions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.17.020.   Divisions.
The principal executive officer of each department may, with the approval of the governor, establish divisions or other administrative or organization units within the department in the interests of economy and efficiency and in accord with sound administrative principles and practices.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-17-030">
            <num>44.17.030</num>
            <heading>Regulations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.17.030.   Regulations.
The principal executive officer of each department may adopt regulations, consistent with law or regulations established by the governor, for
(1) the administration of the department;
(2) the conduct of employees;
(3) the distribution and performance of business; and
(4) the custody, use, and preservation of the records, documents, and property pertaining to department business.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-17-040">
            <num>44.17.040</num>
            <heading>Department staffs.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.17.040.   Department staffs.
The principal executive officer of each department may establish necessary subordinate positions, make appointments to these positions, and remove persons appointed within the limitations of appropriations and subject to state personnel laws.  Each person appointed to a subordinate position established by the principal executive officer is under the supervision, direction, and control of the officer.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-17-050">
            <num>44.17.050</num>
            <heading>Continuation of functions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.17.050.   Continuation of functions.
Each department exercising the functions, powers, and duties of a former department or agency is, for the purpose of succession to all rights, powers, duties, and obligations of the former department or agency, considered a continuation of the former department or agency.  If a former agency is referred to by law, contract, or document, the reference is considered to apply to the department now exercising the functions of the former agency.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-17-060">
            <num>44.17.060</num>
            <heading>Unassigned functions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.17.060.   Unassigned functions.
Administrative functions established by law that are not assigned by law to any department shall be assigned by the governor to that department which, in accordance with the organization of state government, can most appropriately and effectively perform the activity.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-17-070">
            <num>44.17.070</num>
            <heading>Reorganization by department heads.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.17.070.   Reorganization by department heads.
Subject to state personnel laws and the approval of the commissioner of administration, the principal executive officer of each department may, in the interest of improved management, abolish unnecessary offices and positions, transfer officers and employees between positions, and change the duties, titles, and compensation of existing offices and positions.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-17-080">
            <num>44.17.080</num>
            <heading>Appearance before the legislature.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.17.080.   Appearance before the legislature.
The principal executive officer of each department and each employee of a department of the state government may not appear before the legislature to present requests or information pertaining to appropriations or revenue bills unless called upon to do so by the legislature or by a committee of the legislature.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>