<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-43"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-43"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="14.43"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-43/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-43/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-43/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-43/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_14">
        <num>14</num>
        <heading>Education, Libraries, and Museums</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_14__chp_43">
          <num>43</num>
          <heading>Financial Aid Programs for Postsecondary Students</heading>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-010">
            <num>14.43.010</num>
            <heading>Scholarships for dormitory rent.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.43.010.   Scholarships for dormitory rent.
The high school student in each graduating class in each high school in the state who, upon the completion of four years of high school work in a high school in the state, obtains the highest average standing for all the credits earned, and who is graduated at an annual commencement is entitled to receive, during dormitory residence at the University of Alaska, a scholarship covering dormitory rent for a period of two years following the year of graduation upon presenting to the registrar of the university a certificate signed by the superintendent or principal of the high school from which the student graduated stating that the graduate named is entitled to receive the benefits of the scholarship. Dormitory residence is governed by the rules and regulations established by the Board of Regents.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-015">
            <num>14.43.015</num>
            <heading>Alternate upon refusal or failure to accept.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.43.015.   Alternate upon refusal or failure to accept.
If a person entitled to receive the benefit of
AS 14.43.010
declines or fails to accept it, the graduate next in line in class standing is entitled to receive the benefit.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-020">
            <num>14.43.020</num>
            <heading>Applications for and issuance and report of certificates.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.43.020.   Applications for and issuance and report of certificates.
A certificate shall be applied for and issued to a graduate before August 2 of each year and shall be reported immediately to the registrar of the University of Alaska by the superintendent or principal issuing it.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-025">
            <num>14.43.025</num>
            <heading>Forfeiture of scholarship benefits.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.43.025.   Forfeiture of scholarship benefits.
Failure to do passing work in more than one subject during a semester, or withdrawal or expulsion from the University of Alaska, constitutes a forfeiture during the following semester or semesters of the benefits of
AS 14.43.010
and 14.43.015.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-030">
            <num>14.43.030</num>
            <heading>Payment of scholarships.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.43.030.   Payment of scholarships.
Payment of the scholarships shall be made monthly to the University of Alaska upon vouchers drawn upon the Department of Administration and duly certified by the treasurer and the president of the Board of Regents.  Payments may not be made in excess of amounts specifically appropriated for this purpose.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-050">
            <num>14.43.050</num>
            <heading>Purpose of scholarships.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.43.050.   Purpose of scholarships.
Because of the language difficulty and economic conditions of the Native peoples of the state, and the necessity for integrating the Native cultures with the state economy, it is the purpose of the legislature to provide assistance to Natives who wish to pursue a higher education beyond the attainments possible in the free public schools system.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-055">
            <num>14.43.055</num>
            <heading>Scholarships.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.43.055.   Scholarships.
The Board of Regents of the University of Alaska shall offer not more than 15 new scholarships for each academic year to Alaska Natives desiring to attend the University of Alaska. The board shall give preference to Natives residing in the rural areas of the state who desire to receive training in the field of education.  If there are more than 15 applications the board shall award 15 scholarships to those applicants who have the highest scholastic record or who the board determines are the most qualified among the applicants and who are financially unable to obtain a higher education without assistance.  The University of Alaska shall provide such minimum financial assistance to these students as is necessary in each individual case, but not exceeding fees, board, and room.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-060">
            <num>14.43.060</num>
            <heading>Continuation of scholarships.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.43.060.   Continuation of scholarships.
The award of free room and board shall be made from any funds available to the University of Alaska. Each Native who receives a scholarship under
AS 14.43.050
 14.43.075 is entitled to retain the scholarship and to receive free room and board during attendance at the University of Alaska as long as the student maintains a grade average equivalent to a C or better.  However, no Native is entitled to the scholarship for more than four years, or for more than the number of years necessary to receive a bachelor's degree.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-065">
            <num>14.43.065</num>
            <heading>Scholarships in addition to other scholarships.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.43.065.   Scholarships in addition to other scholarships.
The scholarships under
AS 14.43.050
 14.43.075 are supplemental and in addition to any other scholarship to which an applicant is entitled or may receive.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-075">
            <num>14.43.075</num>
            <heading>Definition of Native.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.43.075.   Definition of Native.
In
AS 14.43.050
 14.43.075, Native means a person between the ages of 17 and 25 who is a descendant of a member of the aboriginal races inhabiting the state when annexed to the United States, or who is a descendant of an Indian or Eskimo who, since the year 1867 and prior to June 30, 1952, migrated into the state from Canada, and who is a descendant having at least one-quarter blood derived from these ancestors.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-085">
            <num>14.43.085</num>
            <heading>Free tuition and fees for a spouse or dependent of a peace officer or members of the armed services or a fire department.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-085__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person enrolled as a student in good standing in a state supported educational institution in this state is entitled to a waiver of undergraduate tuition and fees if the person was the spouse or dependent child of a bona fide resident of the state who was</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-085__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a member of the armed services and who died in the line of duty or who died as a result of injuries sustained while in the line of duty for the state or federal government or who was listed by the United States Department of Defense as a prisoner of war or as missing in action; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-085__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a peace officer or a member of a fire department who died from an act arising out of and in the course of
(A) employment as a peace officer or a firefighter; or
(B) duties as a volunteer firefighter.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-085__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-085__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>armed services means the Alaska National Guard, Alaska Naval Militia, and the armed services of the United States;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-085__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>dependent child means a person who was a dependent of a peace officer or of a member of the armed services or a fire department at the time of the peace officer's or member's death, and who is
(A) the peace officer's or member's natural or adopted child;
(B) a child in relation to whom the deceased armed services member, firefighter, or peace officer stood in loco parentis for at least three years before the peace officer's or member's death;
(C) the peace officer's or member's stepchild; or
(D) the peace officer's or member's acknowledged illegitimate child;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-085__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>fire department means a federal, state, or municipal fire department or a regularly organized volunteer fire department registered with the state fire marshal;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-085__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>line of duty has the meaning given under federal law;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-085__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>peace officer has the meaning given in
AS 01.10.060
and includes a correctional officer;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-085__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>resident means a person who resided in the state for at least one year before serving in the armed services and who lists Alaska as the home state for purposes of military records, or a person who was employed as a peace officer in this state or was a member of a fire department located in this state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-085__subsec_b__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>spouse means a person who was married to a peace officer or to a member of the armed services or a fire department at the time of the peace officer's or member's death.
Article 4. Education Loan Program.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-091">
            <num>14.43.091</num>
            <heading>Education loan program.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-091__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>There is created the education loan program to provide loans to individuals who are students to assist in paying the costs of postsecondary education. The provisions of this section,
AS 14.43.100
 14.43.160, 14.43.910, 14.43.920, and 14.43.990 apply to the loans.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-091__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon approval by the commission of an education loan, the corporation shall finance a loan disbursement, subject to any limit that the corporation sets on the total amount of loans that the corporation will finance in a school year. A loan financed under this section becomes an asset of the corporation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-091__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Repayments of principal and interest on a loan are paid into the education loan fund established in
AS 14.42.210
. If money made available by the corporation is inadequate to fully finance eligible loan applications, additional financing from the general fund may be requested and appropriated for that year.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-100">
            <num>14.43.100</num>
            <heading>Applications.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-100__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Applications shall be submitted to the executive director of the commission.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-100__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person whose loan application is not approved by the executive director of the commission may appeal to the commission and the commission shall consider the application.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-105">
            <num>14.43.105</num>
            <heading>Administration of program.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.43.105.   Administration of program.
The executive director shall administer the programs subject to review by the commission and in accordance with the regulations adopted by the commission. The adoption of these regulations is subject to
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act). A summary of the regulations shall be distributed to each applicant.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-110">
            <num>14.43.110</num>
            <heading>Education loans.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-110__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In a school year, the commission may make a loan not to exceed</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-110__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>$8,500 to a full-time undergraduate student or $5,000 to a half-time undergraduate student attending a college or university if the full- or half-time student is otherwise eligible under
AS 14.43.125
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-110__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>$9,500 to a full-time graduate student or $4,500 to a half-time graduate student attending a college or university if the full- or half-time graduate student is otherwise eligible under
AS 14.43.125
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-110__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>$5,500 to a full-time student or $2,000 to a half-time student if the full- or half-time student is attending a career education program that is at least six weeks in length and is otherwise eligible under
AS 14.43.125
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-110__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission may make a loan for a summer term, even if the total loan for the school year exceeds the limit imposed under (a) of this section if the loan for the summer term is counted against the limit imposed under (a) of this section for the following school year.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-110__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall adopt regulations establishing a minimum amount for which a loan may be made.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-120">
            <num>14.43.120</num>
            <heading>Conditions of loans.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-120__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Proceeds from an education loan to a full-time student may only be used for books and supplies, tuition and required fees, loan origination fees, and room and board. Proceeds from an education loan to a half-time student may only be used for books and supplies, tuition and required fees, and loan origination fees.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-120__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Education loans may only be used to attend a</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-120__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>career education program operating on a sound fiscal basis that has
(A) operated for two years before the borrower attends; and
(B) submitted an executed program participation agreement as required by the commission; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-120__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>college or university that
(A) has operated for at least two years before the borrower attends;
(B) is accredited by a national or regional accreditation association recognized by the Council for Higher Education Accreditation or is approved by the commission;
(C) if the loans are federally insured, is approved by the United States Secretary of Education;
(D) is a degree granting institution; and
(E) has submitted an executed program participation agreement as required by the commission.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-120__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To maintain a loan awarded to a full-time student the student must continue to be enrolled as a full-time student in good standing in a career education program, college, or university that meets the requirements under (b) of this section. To maintain a loan awarded to a half-time student, the student must continue to be enrolled as a half-time student in good standing in (1) a career education program, college, or university in the state that meets the requirements under (b) of this section, or (2) a career education program, college, or university that meets the requirements under (b) of this section, and be physically present in the state while attending the career education program, college, or university. The commission shall adopt regulations defining good standing for purposes of this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-120__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Education loans may not be made to a student</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-120__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for more than a total of $42,500 for undergraduate study;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-120__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for more than a total of $47,500 for graduate study;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-120__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for more than a combined total of $60,000 for undergraduate and graduate study;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-120__subsec_d__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to attend an institution if the total amount of education loans made to students to attend that institution exceeds $100,000 and the default rate on those loans is (A) greater than 20 percent but less than 25 percent, and the institution is unable to reduce its default rate within 24 months after the rate determination; or (B) equal to or greater than 25 percent for two consecutive calendar years; for purposes of this paragraph, the default rate shall be determined by the commission for each annual group of loans required to be repaid under (g) of this section on or after July 1, 1996; if an education loan is refused based on the provisions of this paragraph and, under a subsequent default rate determination, an institution's default rate does not exceed the limits established under this paragraph, the commission may not refuse to issue an education loan to attend that institution based on the provisions of this paragraph.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-120__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Interest on an education loan accrues from the time the loan is disbursed; however, the state shall pay the interest while the borrower continues to be enrolled under (c) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-120__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 45 ch 89 SLA 2014.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-120__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A borrower's obligation to commence repayment of the principal and interest on the loan begins six months after the borrower is no longer enrolled under (c) of this section. The borrower shall repay the total amount owed in periodic installments of at least $50 a month over a period of not more than 15 years from the commencement of the repayment obligation. If the commission and the borrower agree to a different repayment schedule, the borrower shall repay the loan in accordance with the agreement. A borrower may make payments earlier than required by this subsection or the agreement.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-120__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Security may not be required for a loan; however, a loan origination fee, as specified in (u) of this section, shall be deducted at the time that the loan is disbursed. Additionally, the borrower shall pay all fees and costs incurred in collection on the loan if it becomes delinquent or in default.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-120__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 18 ch 54 SLA 1997.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-120__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 19 ch 92 SLA 1987.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-120__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A borrower's obligation to make periodic payments of principal shall be deferred, but the borrower's obligation to pay interest shall continue, unless the state pays the interest by appropriation under (t) of this section, during any of the following periods:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-120__subsec_k__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>return to full-time student status in good standing in a career education program, college, or university that meets the requirements under (b) of this section;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-120__subsec_k__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if the borrower received a loan to attend as a half-time student, return to
(A) half-time student status in good standing in a career education program, college, or university in the state that meets the requirements under (b) of this section;
(B) at least half-time student status in good standing in a career education program, college, or university that meets the requirements under (b) of this section, and the borrower is physically present in the state while attending the career education program, college, or university; a borrower is not eligible for deferral under this paragraph for a period longer than eight years; or
(C) full-time student status in good standing in a career education program, college, or university that meets the requirements under (b) of this section;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-120__subsec_k__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>serving an initial period of up to three years on active duty as a member of the armed forces of the United States;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-120__subsec_k__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>serving, for up to three years, as a full-time volunteer under the Peace Corps Act;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-120__subsec_k__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>serving, for up to three years, as a full-time volunteer under the Domestic Volunteer Service Act of 1973;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-120__subsec_k__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>serving, for up to two years, as a full-time volunteer under the National and Community Service Trust Act of 1993 (AmeriCorps);</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-120__subsec_k__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for a one-time period up to 12 months in which the borrower is seeking and unable to find employment in the United States; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-120__subsec_k__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>during the period of disability if, after the loan is disbursed, the borrower becomes totally disabled as certified by competent medical authority.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-120__subsec_l">
              <num>(l)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The state shall pay the interest on that portion of a loan that is not federally insured during</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-120__subsec_l__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the period while the borrower continues to be enrolled under (c) of this section; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-120__subsec_l__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>deferments under (k) of this section.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-120__subsec_m">
              <num>(m)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In case of hardship, the commission may extend repayment of a loan for an additional period of up to five years.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-120__subsec_n">
              <num>(n)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 11 ch 89 SLA 1981.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-120__subsec_o">
              <num>(o)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 19 ch 92 SLA 1987.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-120__subsec_p">
              <num>(p)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 102 ch 21 SLA 2000.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-120__subsec_q">
              <num>(q)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 18 ch 54 SLA 1997.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-120__subsec_r">
              <num>(r)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The rate of interest, time of payment of an installment of principal or interest, or other terms of an education loan may be modified if required to establish or maintain tax-exempt status under 26 U.S.C. 103 (Internal Revenue Code of 1986), as amended, for the interest on bonds issued by the Alaska Student Loan Corporation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-120__subsec_s">
              <num>(s)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A portion of a loan shall be forgiven by the state if, after being enrolled in the course of study for which the loan was granted, the borrower is a student who is unable to complete the school term as a result of serving on active duty as a member of the armed forces of the United States. The portion of the loan that shall be forgiven by the state is equal to the amount borrowed by the student for the school term in which the borrower's studies are terminated.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-120__subsec_t">
              <num>(t)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Payment of interest under (l) of this section and forgiveness under (s) of this section are subject to appropriation by the legislature. Money obtained from the sale of bonds by the Student Loan Corporation under
AS 14.42.220
may not be appropriated for the payment of interest or the forgiveness of loans.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-120__subsec_u">
              <num>(u)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The corporation by regulation shall set a loan origination fee, not to exceed five percent of the total education loan amount, to be assessed upon an education loan that is funded from the education loan fund of the corporation. The loan origination fee shall be deducted by the commission at the time the loan is disbursed. The loan origination fees shall be deposited into an origination fee account within the education loan fund of the corporation, and subsequently used by the corporation to offset losses incurred as a result of death, disability, default, or bankruptcy of the borrower.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-120__subsec_v">
              <num>(v)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 45 ch 89 SLA 2014.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-122">
            <num>14.43.122</num>
            <heading>Consolidation of loans.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-122__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The corporation may offer a borrower who has received more than one education loan the option of consolidating the multiple loans into a single loan as provided in this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-122__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For a borrower to be eligible for consolidation of a loan under this section, the borrower must apply on a form approved by the corporation and must</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-122__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>physically reside in the state and have maintained a domicile in the state for not less than 12 consecutive months before submitting an application for consolidation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-122__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>be a previous borrower, cosigner, or beneficiary of an education loan made under
AS 14.43
or
AS 14.44
; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-122__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>be a graduate of a high school or postsecondary institution physically located in the state.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-122__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, education loan means a loan to finance the cost of attendance at a postsecondary institution in or outside the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-125">
            <num>14.43.125</num>
            <heading>Eligibility of students.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-125__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person is eligible for a loan if the person</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-125__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is
(A) enrolled as a full-time student in a career education, associate, baccalaureate, or graduate degree program;
(B) enrolled as a half-time student in a career education, associate, baccalaureate, or graduate degree program</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-125__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>in the state; or
(ii) out of the state and is physically present in this state while attending that program; or
(C) a graduate of a high school or the equivalent, or scheduled for graduation from a high school within six months, who, at the time of loan disbursement, will be enrolled in compliance with (A) or (B) of this paragraph;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-125__subsec_i__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is not delinquent and has never been in default on a loan previously awarded by the commission;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-125__subsec_i__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is a resident of the state at the time of application for the loan; for purposes of this section, a person qualifies as a resident of the state if at the time of application for the loan the person
(A) has been physically present in the state for at least one year immediately before the time of application for the loan with the intent to remain indefinitely;
(B) is dependent on a parent or guardian for care, the parent or guardian has been present in the state for at least one year immediately before the time of application for the loan with the intent to remain indefinitely, and the person has been present in the state for at least one year of the immediately preceding five years except that the commission may by a two-thirds vote, acting upon a written appeal by the person, grant an exemption to the requirement that the person has been present in the state for one year of the immediately preceding five years;
(C) has been physically present in the state for at least one year immediately before the applicant was absent from the state, the person intends to return permanently to the state, and the absence is due solely to</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-125__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>serving an initial period of up to three years on active duty as a member of the armed forces of the United States;
(ii) serving for up to three years as a full-time volunteer under the Peace Corps Act;
(iii) serving for up to three years as a full-time volunteer under the Domestic Volunteer Service Act of 1973;
(iv) required medical care for the applicant or the applicant's immediate family;</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-125__subsec_v">
              <num>(v)</num>
              <content>
                <p>being a person who otherwise qualifies as a resident and is accompanying a spouse who qualifies as a resident under (i)  (iv) of this paragraph;
(vi) an absence allowed under (D)(i)  (iv) of this paragraph; or
(D) is a dependent of a parent or guardian who has been physically present in the state for at least one year immediately before the parent or guardian was absent from the state, the parent or guardian intends to return permanently to the state, and the absence is due solely to</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-125__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>participating in a foreign exchange student program recognized by the commission;
(ii) attending a school as a full-time student;
(iii) full-time employment by the state;
(iv) being a member of or employed full-time by the state's congressional delegation;</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-125__subsec_v">
              <num>(v)</num>
              <content>
                <p>being a person who otherwise qualifies as a resident and is accompanying a spouse who qualifies as a resident under (i)  (iv) of this paragraph;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-125__subsec_v__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>does not have a past due child support obligation established by court order or by the child support services agency under
AS 25.27.160
 25.27.220 at the time of application or loan disbursement;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-125__subsec_v__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has not, within the previous five years, had a loan discharged or written off by the commission for any reason;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-125__subsec_v__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>does not have a status, at the time of the application for a loan or disbursement of loan funds, that would prevent the person from repaying the loan as it becomes due;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-125__subsec_v__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has not within the previous seven years defaulted on another loan made to the person by a lending entity unless the person can show good faith efforts to repay the loan and extraordinary circumstances that led to the default;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-125__subsec_v__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>does not have a credit history, at the time of application for a loan, that demonstrates chronic inability or unwillingness to pay an extension of credit or loan as it becomes due; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-125__subsec_v__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has complied with the military selective service registration requirements imposed under 50 U.S.C. App. 453 (Military Selective Service Act), if those requirements were applicable to the person.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-125__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person does not qualify as a resident of the state under this section if the person declares or establishes residence in another state during an absence from Alaska.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-125__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not be awarded an education loan under
AS 14.43.091
 14.43.160 if that person receives a teacher education loan under
AS 14.43.600
 14.43.700 for the same period of attendance.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-125__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (a)(6)  (8) of this section, the commission may issue a loan to a person if another person who satisfies the requirements of (a)(2) and (a)(4)  (8) of this section cosigns the loan.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-125__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission may withhold disbursement of a loan if the borrower becomes ineligible under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-135">
            <num>14.43.135</num>
            <heading>Discrimination prohibited.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.43.135.   Discrimination prohibited.
The programs established under this chapter shall be carried out without regard to the applicant's or participant's race, creed, sex, color, ancestry, national origin, or membership in fraternal or political organizations.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-140">
            <num>14.43.140</num>
            <heading>Enforceability of certain contracts with minors.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.43.140.   Enforceability of certain contracts with minors.
A written obligation entered into by a minor at least 16 years of age, evidencing a loan or other assistance received by the minor from any person for the purpose of furthering the minor's education in a career education program or an institution of higher learning, is enforceable against the minor with the same effect as if the minor were, at the time of its execution, 18 years of age, if the person making the loan has before making the loan a certification from the institution that the minor is enrolled in the institution or has been accepted for enrollment.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-145">
            <num>14.43.145</num>
            <heading>Default.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-145__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For the purposes of this chapter, a loan is in default after a loan payment has become 180 or more days past due or, for a loan under
AS 14.43.161
 14.43.168 or 14.43.170  14.43.175, the default requirements established by the commission have been met. Upon default,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-145__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>repayment of the remaining balance is accelerated and due;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-145__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the commission may take the borrower's permanent fund dividend under
AS 43.23.160
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-145__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the commission may issue an order to withhold and deliver under
AS 14.43.147
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-145__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>[Repealed, § 34 ch 23 SLA 2018.]</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-145__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the commission may record the lien created under
AS 14.43.149
; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-145__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the commission may establish an administrative collection order under
AS 14.43.151
 14.43.155.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-145__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall notify the borrower of the default, and the consequences of default imposed under (a) of this section, by mailing a notice to the borrower's most recent address provided to the commission by the borrower or obtained by the commission.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-145__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A borrower may appeal a notice of default by filing a statement with the executive director, within 30 days after the date of the notice, requesting that the loan status be reviewed.
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act) does not apply to the review of default under this section. The borrower has the burden to show that, at the time of the notice of default, (1) no loan payment was more than 180 days past due or, for a loan under
AS 14.43.161
 14.43.168 or 14.43.170  14.43.175, the default requirements established by the commission had not yet been met; or (2) that the borrower entered into, and was in compliance with, a default forbearance agreement with the commission. Within 40 days after receiving a written request for review, the director shall inform the borrower in writing of the executive director's decision. The decision of the executive director is a final decision that may be appealed to the superior court under the Alaska Rules of Appellate Procedure.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-147">
            <num>14.43.147</num>
            <heading>Order to withhold and deliver.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-147__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Thirty days after the date a notice of default under
AS 14.43.145</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-147__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>is mailed or the date of the decision of the executive director under
AS 14.43.145
(c), whichever is later, the commission may issue an order to withhold and deliver property to a person, or agency or political subdivision of the state, who the commission has reason to believe possesses property due, owing, or belonging to the borrower.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-147__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The order to withhold and deliver shall be served personally or by certified mail, return receipt requested, upon the person, or agency or political subdivision of the state, possessing the property. The order must state the amount of the borrower's liability and include notice of the terms of this section. All real and personal property, including earnings, that are due, owing, or belonging to the borrower are subject to an order to withhold and deliver.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-147__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person, or agency or political subdivision of the state, served with an order to withhold and deliver, is required to make true answers under oath and in writing to inquiries contained in the order within three weeks after service of the order and to all inquiries subsequently made.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-147__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon receipt of the order, the person, or agency or political subdivision of the state, shall immediately withhold property due, owing, or belonging to the borrower and shall deliver the property to the commission after three weeks have expired from the date of the service of the order. Money shall be delivered by remittance payable to the order of the commission.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-147__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An employer shall withhold the earnings of a borrower subject to an order at each succeeding interval of payment until the entire amount of the debt stated in the order has been withheld. An employer may, for each payment made under an order to withhold and deliver, deduct $5 from other wages or salary owed to the borrower.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-147__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a borrower who is subject to an order terminates employment, the employer shall promptly notify the commission and provide the borrower's last known home address and the name and address of the borrower's new employer, if known. The employer shall keep a record of the order for two years after the borrower terminates employment. If the employer reemploys the borrower within that two-year period, the employer shall immediately reimplement the order unless the employer has received notice of satisfaction under (j) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-147__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An employer may not discharge, discipline, or refuse to employ a borrower on the basis of an order issued under this section. A person who violates this subsection or a regulation adopted to implement it is liable for a civil penalty of not more than $10,000. The employee may seek restitution or reinstatement from the employer.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-147__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person, or agency or political subdivision of the state, who complies with an order to withhold and deliver that is regular on its face is not subject to civil liability to an individual or agency for conduct in compliance with the notice. A state agency that complies with an order to withhold and deliver that is regular on its face is not required to pay interest under
AS 37.05.285
for failure to make timely payment to the borrower.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-147__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An order to withhold and deliver under this section is subject to the exemptions under
AS 09.38
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-147__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon satisfaction of a loan obligation, the commission shall, within 15 working days, notify all persons served with an order under this section that the order is no longer in force. If the commission receives money under an order after satisfaction of the loan, the commission shall within 15 working days return the overpayment to the borrower. If the commission fails to return an overpayment as required under this subsection, the commission is liable to the borrower for the amount of the overpayment, plus legal interest under
AS 45.45.010
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-147__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a person, or agency or political subdivision of the state, knowingly fails to make an answer to an order under this section within the time prescribed, or knowingly fails to honor an order under this section, the person, or agency or political subdivision of the state, is liable to the commission in an amount equal to 100 percent of the amount that is the basis of the order, together with costs, interest, and reasonable attorney fees. In this subsection, knowingly has the meaning given in
AS 11.81.900
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-147__subsec_l">
              <num>(l)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A borrower against whom an order has been served under this section may apply for relief to the superior court.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-148">
            <num>14.43.148</num>
            <heading>Nonrenewal of license.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.43.148.   Nonrenewal of license.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-148">
            <num>14.43.148</num>
            <heading>Nonrenewal of license.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.43.148.   Nonrenewal of license.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-149">
            <num>14.43.149</num>
            <heading>Lien.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-149__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The amount owing on a loan that is in default under this chapter, including principal, interest, and collection costs, is a lien upon all property and right to property, real or personal, belonging to the borrower. The lien arises at the time that the commission mails or otherwise delivers a notice of default under
AS 14.43.145</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-149__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and continues until the balance of the loan, including principal, interest, and collection costs, is paid in full.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-149__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A lien created under (a) of this section is</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-149__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>not valid against a mortgagee or other lienholder, pledgee, purchaser, or judgment creditor until notice of the lien is recorded in the records of the recording district where the property subject to the lien is situated; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-149__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>subject to
AS 40.19.040</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-150">
            <num>14.43.150</num>
            <heading>Order to assign wages for defaulted loan.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-150__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In a court proceeding regarding a defaulted loan under this chapter in which the court has entered judgment in favor of the commission, the court may, on its own motion or motion of the commission, after notice and an opportunity for hearing, order the loan recipient to assign to the commission that portion of salary or wages due the loan recipient currently and in the future in an amount sufficient to pay the amount ordered by the court to be repaid to the commission.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-150__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The order of assignment is binding upon an employer upon service of a copy of the order upon the employer and until further order of the court or until the employment of the obligee is terminated. The employer may, for each payment made under the order, deduct $1 from other wages or salary owed to the employee.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-150__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An employer may not terminate an employee's employment because wages of the employee are subject to an order under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-150__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An assignment of wages authorized under this section that is made under court order has priority as against an attachment, execution, or other assignment, except for an assignment for payment of child support under
AS 25.27.070
, restitution to a crime victim authorized under
AS 12.55.045
, or as otherwise ordered by the court.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-151">
            <num>14.43.151</num>
            <heading>Authority and procedure to administratively establish and enforce a collection order.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.43.151.   Authority and procedure to administratively establish and enforce a collection order.
If a judgment in favor of the commission has not been entered by the court regarding a defaulted loan awarded under this chapter, the commission may establish a duty to repay the defaulted loan through a collection order using the procedures prescribed in
AS 14.43.152
 14.43.155 and may enforce the collection order. Action under this section may be undertaken at the commission's discretion if the borrower is in default under
AS 14.43.145
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-152">
            <num>14.43.152</num>
            <heading>Initiation of administrative action to establish a collection order; required notice.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-152__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An action to establish a collection order authorized under
AS 14.43.151
is initiated by the commission's serving on the borrower a notice of establishment of collection order. The notice shall be served by mailing the notice to the borrower at</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-152__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the borrower's most recent address provided to the commission by the borrower; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-152__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>another address known to the commission.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-152__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The notice served under (a) of this section must state</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-152__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the amount of the liability for default under
AS 14.43.145
for which the borrower is found to be responsible; the amount stated under this paragraph shall include all principal, interest, and collection fees;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-152__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>that a lien may be recorded against the borrower's property as authorized under
AS 14.43.145</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-152__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>that the borrower may appear at a hearing held by the commission and show cause that a collection order should not be entered because, at the time of the notice,
(A) no loan payment was more than 180 days past due or, for a loan under
AS 14.43.161
 14.43.168 or 14.43.170  14.43.175, the default requirements established by the commission had not yet been met; or
(B) the borrower had entered into, or was in compliance with, an agreement to forbear default with the commission; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-152__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>that, if the borrower served with the notice does not request a hearing within 30 days after the date of mailing of the notice, a collection order will be entered and the property of the borrower will be subject to a lien under
AS 14.43.149
in the amount stated in the collection order without further notice or hearing.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-153">
            <num>14.43.153</num>
            <heading>Hearings in administrative action to establish a collection order; burden of proof.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-153__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A borrower served with a notice of establishment of collection order under
AS 14.43.152
is entitled to a hearing before the commission if the request for a hearing is served on the commission by registered mail, return receipt requested, within 30 days after the date the notice is mailed to the borrower.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-153__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a request for a hearing in accordance with (a) of this section is made, the issuance of a collection order is automatically stayed pending the decision of the hearing officer for the commission. If a request for a hearing is not made, the collection order is final at the expiration of the 30-day period specified in (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-153__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A borrower claiming that the notice is incorrect has the burden at hearing to document the existence of one of the conditions described in
AS 14.43.152
(b)(3)(A) and (B).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-153__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Within 60 days after the date of the hearing, the hearing officer shall enter a decision determining whether default has occurred and, if default has occurred, specifying the amount of the collection order and declaring that the property of the borrower is subject to a lien under
AS 14.43.149
in the amount of the collection order.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-153__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the borrower who requested the hearing fails to appear at the hearing, the hearing officer shall enter a decision</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-153__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>confirming that a default has occurred;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-153__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>confirming the amount of the collection order;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-153__subsec_e__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>declaring that the property of the borrower is subject to a lien under
AS 14.43.149
in the amount stated under (2) of this subsection.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-153__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The decision of the hearing officer is a final decision that may be appealed to the superior court under the Alaska Rules of Appellate Procedure.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-154">
            <num>14.43.154</num>
            <heading>Collection orders as judgments.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-154__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>if a hearing is not requested; or</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-154__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>on the date the hearing officer enters a decision in favor of the commission if a hearing was requested by the borrower.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-155">
            <num>14.43.155</num>
            <heading>Nature of remedies.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.43.155.   Nature of remedies.
AS 14.43.154
provides a remedy in addition to and not as a substitute for any other remedies available to the commission.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-160">
            <num>14.43.160</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.43.160.   Definitions.
In
AS 14.43.091
 14.43.160, unless the context otherwise requires,
(1) career education means a course or program in vocational-technical training or education approved by the commission;
(2) federally insured means a loan covered by the provisions of 20 U.S.C. 1001  1155, as amended;
(3) full-time student means an undergraduate or career education student who is enrolled and is in regular attendance at classes for at least 12 semester hours of credit or the equivalent during the semester or a graduate student who is enrolled and is in regular attendance at classes for at least nine semester hours of credit or the equivalent; any combination of semester hours of credit, or the equivalent, aggregating to the requisite number of semester hours and undertaken during a semester at two or more public or private institutions of higher education constitutes full-time student status;
(4) half-time student means an undergraduate, graduate, or career education student who, during the semester, is enrolled and is in regular attendance at classes at one or more public or private institutions of higher education for six to 11 semester credit hours or an equivalent of six to 11 semester credit hours, and includes a career education student enrolled and in regular attendance in classes for 15 hours a week or a graduate student who is enrolled and is in regular attendance at classes for the equivalent of six to eight semester hours of credit or the equivalent;
(5) school year means an academic period that is a minimum of 30 weeks of instructional time that begins between July 1 of one year and June 30 of the following year;
(6) summer term means the period from June 1 through August 31.
Article 5. AlaskAdvantage Loan Program.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-161">
            <num>14.43.161</num>
            <heading>Purpose; creation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.43.161.   Purpose; creation.
There is established the AlaskAdvantage loan program to provide postsecondary educational financial assistance through the federal guaranteed student loan program. The AlaskAdvantage loan program is the primary source for financial aid to eligible borrowers under this chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-162">
            <num>14.43.162</num>
            <heading>Eligibility.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-162__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For a borrower to be eligible for a loan under
AS 14.43.161
 14.43.168, the borrower must meet the eligibility requirements established by the federal guaranteed student loan program and must be</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-162__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a resident of the state as determined under (b) of this section; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-162__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>physically present in this state and attending an institution that is physically located in this state.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-162__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To meet the residency requirement of (a) of this section, the borrower</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-162__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>must physically reside in this state and maintain a domicile in this state during the 12 consecutive months before the date of application for the program, except that the borrower may be absent from this state for not more than a total of 60 days during that 12-month period; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-162__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>may not have
(A) declared or established residency in another state; or
(B) received residency or a benefit based on residency from another state.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-162__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To continue to meet the residency requirement of (a) of this section for each year that a loan is received or subsequently applied for, the borrower must meet the requirements of (b) of this section, except for</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-162__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>full-time attendance at an educational or training institution;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-162__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>military service; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-162__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>demonstrated good cause as determined by the commission.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-163">
            <num>14.43.163</num>
            <heading>Restrictions on award.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.43.163.   Restrictions on award.
Under
AS 14.43.161
 14.43.168, the commission may make loans subject to the following restrictions:
(1) a loan amount awarded may not exceed the maximum amount for the school year as established by the federal guaranteed student loan program;
(2) a borrower may not be awarded a loan amount that would, when aggregated with other loans awarded to the student under the federal guaranteed student loan program, exceed the maximum total amount allowable for each borrower that is established by the federal guaranteed student loan program;
(3) the loan award may not exceed the total cost of attendance at the postsecondary institution less other forms of financial aid awarded to the borrower to pay for those costs.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-164">
            <num>14.43.164</num>
            <heading>Use of loan.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.43.164.   Use of loan.
A borrower may use a loan under
AS 14.43.161
 14.43.168 only for postsecondary education and reasonably related purposes as authorized by the federal guaranteed student loan program.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-165">
            <num>14.43.165</num>
            <heading>Interest.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-165__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The corporation shall set the rate of interest on a loan made under
AS 14.43.161
 14.43.168 in accordance with federal and state law. Interest on a loan made under
AS 14.43
.l61  14.43.168 may not exceed the rate specified by the applicable provisions of the federal guaranteed student loan program. Interest on a loan made under
AS 14.43.161
 14.43.168 accrues from the time that the loan is disbursed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-165__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A borrower may elect to make payments of interest that is payable during the borrower's term of attendance at the postsecondary institution or during certain deferment periods authorized by the commission; however, the commission shall capitalize any unpaid interest as part of the principal to be repaid as agreed, or upon graduation, withdrawal, or completion of the deferment period.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-165__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding the provisions of (b) of this section, if a borrower qualifies for a subsidized loan under the federal guaranteed student loan program, the interest on the loan is paid by the federal government during the borrower's term of attendance and any qualifying deferment and grace periods authorized under the loan.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-166">
            <num>14.43.166</num>
            <heading>Repayment of loans.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.43.166.   Repayment of loans.
A borrower's obligation to commence repayment of the principal and interest on a loan under
AS 14.43.161
 14.43.166 and 14.43.168 begins six months after the borrower's completion or other termination of the postsecondary education program. The commission may accelerate the repayment of any loan made in error or in reliance upon a false statement made by the borrower. The commission shall determine the period over which loans are repaid; however, the maximum period of repayment of loans may not exceed the maximum period permitted under applicable provisions of the federal guaranteed student loan program.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-167">
            <num>14.43.167</num>
            <heading>Consolidation of loans.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.43.167.   Consolidation of loans.
The commission may offer
(1) an eligible borrower who has received more than one loan under the federal guaranteed student loan program the option of consolidating the multiple loans into a single loan; or
(2) to consolidate loans made to married borrowers if the married borrowers agree to be jointly and severally liable for repayment of the consolidated loan, regardless of the borrowers' future marital status or the death of one of the borrowers.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-168">
            <num>14.43.168</num>
            <heading>Default.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-168__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall establish the default requirements for loans made under
AS 14.43.161
 14.43.168; however, the requirements may not be less restrictive than those established by the federal guaranteed student loan program.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-168__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The provisions of
AS 14.43.145
 14.43.155 apply to loans under
AS 14.43.161
 14.43.168 that are in default.
Article 6. Alaska Supplemental Education Loan Program.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-170">
            <num>14.43.170</num>
            <heading>Creation; purpose.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.43.170.   Creation; purpose.
There is created the Alaska supplemental education loan program to provide postsecondary educational supplemental financial assistance. Supplemental financial assistance is available to qualified borrowers to assist with unmet costs of attendance at a postsecondary institution approved by the commission. The commission shall make the public aware of the Alaska supplemental education loan program to facilitate providing loans to as many eligible borrowers as possible.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-171">
            <num>14.43.171</num>
            <heading>Applicability of other laws.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.43.171.   Applicability of other laws.
The provisions of
AS 14.43.120
(b), 14.43.120(d)(4), 14.43.135, 14.43.140, and 14.43.145  14.43.160 apply to the loans made under
AS 14.43.170
 14.43.175 as if the loans were made under those applicable provisions.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-172">
            <num>14.43.172</num>
            <heading>Eligibility.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-172__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For a borrower to be eligible for a loan under
AS 14.43.170
 14.43.175, the borrower must be, or be about to be, enrolled in a postsecondary institution on at least a half-time basis and must be</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-172__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a resident of this state
(A) attending or about to attend a postsecondary institution that has been approved by and has executed a program participation agreement with the commission; or
(B) attending or about to attend an approved federal guaranteed student loan institution; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-172__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>physically present in this state and attending or about to attend a federal guaranteed student loan institution located in this state.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-172__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To meet the residency requirement of (a) of this section, the borrower must meet the standards set out in
AS 14.43.162
(b).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-172__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to the provisions of (a) of this section, a borrower is eligible for a loan under
AS 14.43.170
 14.43.175 if the borrower</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-172__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is not delinquent in payment on a loan previously awarded by the commission;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-172__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>at the time of application or loan disbursement, does not have a past due child support obligation established by court order or by the child support services agency under
AS 25.27.160
 25.27.220;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-172__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has not, within the previous five years, had a loan discharged or written off by the commission for any reason;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-172__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>does not have a status, at the time of application for a loan or disbursement of loan money, that would prevent the borrower from repaying the loan as it becomes due;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-172__subsec_c__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has not, within the previous five years, defaulted on another loan made to the borrower by a lending entity unless the borrower can show good faith efforts to repay the loan and extraordinary circumstances that led to the default;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-172__subsec_c__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has a credit history, at the time of application for a loan, that demonstrates an ability and willingness to pay an extension of credit or loan as it becomes due; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-172__subsec_c__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has complied with the military selective service registration requirements imposed under 50 U.S.C. App. 453 (Military Selective Service Act), if those requirements were applicable to the person.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-172__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission may not make a loan to a borrower who has been in default on a loan previously awarded by the commission unless the previously awarded loan has been paid in full.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-172__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (c)(4)  (6) of this section, the commission may make a loan to a borrower if another individual who satisfies the requirements of (c) of this section cosigns the loan.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-172__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission may withhold disbursement of a loan if the borrower no longer meets the eligibility standards set out in this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-172__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A borrower who is attending a postsecondary institution in this state that has been approved by the commission but is not an approved federal guaranteed student loan institution must also comply with and meet any other requirements established by the commission.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-173">
            <num>14.43.173</num>
            <heading>Loan award maximums; use of loan award.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-173__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In a school year, the corporation may finance a loan under
AS 14.43.170
 14.43.175 in a maximum amount to be determined by the corporation to an eligible</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-173__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>undergraduate student attending an eligible college or university;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-173__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>graduate student attending an eligible college or university; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-173__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>student attending an eligible career education program.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-173__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The corporation may finance loans made under
AS 14.43.170
 14.43.175 to an eligible borrower in a maximum total amount to be determined by the corporation for</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-173__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an undergraduate study program;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-173__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a graduate study program; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-173__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a combined undergraduate and graduate study program.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-173__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To maintain a loan award under
AS 14.43.170
 14.43.175, the borrower must continue to be in good standing as determined by the institution and approved by the commission.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-173__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall determine a borrower's loan award amount for a specific school year, which may not exceed the limits established by the corporation or the borrower's costs of attendance.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-175">
            <num>14.43.175</num>
            <heading>Repayment of loans.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.43.175.   Repayment of loans.
A borrower's obligation to repay the principal of and interest on a loan made under
AS 14.43.170
 14.43.175 begins not later than six months following the borrower's completion or other termination of the postsecondary program or on the date the borrower ceases to be enrolled in the program at least half time. The commission and borrower may agree to a repayment schedule that begins immediately upon disbursement of a loan.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-250">
            <num>14.43.250</num>
            <heading>Declaration of purpose.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-250__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The legislature may pay tribute to the memory of Alaskans who, by the example of their lives, or by their distinguished contribution and service to this state, their community or their profession, exemplified the best that is the challenge of The Great Land by the creation of memorial education loans as a part of a general memorial education revolving loan fund, setting out the purpose for which each is created, and the conditions applicable to each loan.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-250__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The purposes of the several memorial education loan accounts in the memorial education revolving loan fund are as follows:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-250__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Michael Murphy memorial education loan perpetuates the memory of Michael Murphy, a member of the Alaska State Troopers, who, while on leave from that division, gave his life for his adopted country in Vietnam on May 22, 1968;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-250__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Carroll L. Butch Swartz memorial education loan perpetuates the memory of Carroll L. Butch Swartz, of Juneau, who was a student intern with the Criminal Justice Planning Agency and the Governor's Commission on the Administration of Justice during the summer months of 1972 and 1973 and whose accidental and untimely death in November 1973 occurred while completing his undergraduate education at Yale University, thus never realizing his educational goals or career objective;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-250__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Harvey Golub memorial education loan perpetuates the memory of Harvey Golub, of Juneau, who was chief engineer of the bridge design section of the Department of Highways of the State of Alaska and whose accidental and untimely death September 13, 1971, cut short a widely-respected career in civil engineering;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-250__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Robert L. Thomas memorial education loan perpetuates the memory of Robert L. Thomas, of Juneau, who as Deputy Commissioner of Education, and for 13 years as a member of the professional staff of that department contributed significantly to the creation, operation, and administration of a sound system of public education in Alaska and whose tragic and untimely death March 12, 1974, terminated a distinguished career in education and public administration that long will be exemplary for those who aspire to service in that profession;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-250__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the A.W. (Winn) Brindle memorial education loan perpetuates the memory of A.W. (Winn) Brindle, who was the president of the Wards Cove Packing Company and Columbia-Wards Fisheries and whose death July 4, 1977, terminated a distinguished career dedicated to the development of the Alaska seafood industry; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-250__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Nick Begich memorial education loan perpetuates the memory of Nick Begich, teacher and school superintendent at Fort Richardson, father of the Alaska kindergarten program, state senator, and member of the United States House of Representatives, whose accidental and untimely death in October of 1972 cut short a productive and distinguished career in education and public service.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-255">
            <num>14.43.255</num>
            <heading>Fund created.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-255__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>There is created a memorial education revolving loan fund. The fund shall be used to provide education loans to students selected under
AS 14.43.250
 14.43.325. Repayments of a loan shall be deposited into the memorial education revolving loan fund and shall be used to make new loans.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-255__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each memorial education loan, the purpose of which is set out in
AS 14.43.250
(b), is a separate account in the memorial education revolving loan fund created under (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-255__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 42 ch 85 SLA 2001.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-300">
            <num>14.43.300</num>
            <heading>Limits and conditions of loans.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-300__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An education loan to a recipient under
AS 14.43.250
(b)(1)  (4) or (6) may not exceed $2,500 a school year for an undergraduate student or $5,000 a school year for a graduate student and may not be made to a student for more than six years. An education loan to a recipient under
AS 14.43.250
(b)(5) may not exceed the cost of tuition and required fees, books and educational supplies, room and board, and transportation for two round trips between the recipient's home and school each year. A loan under
AS 14.43.250
(b)(5) may not be made for more than five years of undergraduate study, five years of graduate study, or a combined maximum of eight years of study.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-300__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A loan made under
AS 14.43.250
 14.43.325 may be used only as follows:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-300__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a Michael Murphy memorial education loan may be used only to pursue a certificate or degree program in an accredited college or university in law enforcement, law, probation and parole, or penology, or closely related fields;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-300__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a Carroll L. Butch Swartz memorial education loan may be used only to pursue a degree program in an accredited college or university in criminal law, criminology, corrections, police science and administration, juvenile justice, or other fields closely related to criminal justice;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-300__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a Harvey Golub memorial education loan may be used only to pursue a degree program in an accredited college or university in civil, mechanical, electrical, electronic, petroleum, mining, traffic and transportation, sanitary, chemical, or other recognized field of engineering;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-300__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a Robert L. Thomas memorial education loan may be used only to pursue a degree program in an accredited college or university that will lead to a career in education or public administration, or other closely related field;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-300__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an A.W. (Winn) Brindle memorial education loan may be used only to pursue a certificate or degree program in an accredited school, college, or university in fisheries, fishery science, fishery management, seafood processing, food technology, or other closely related field; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-300__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a Nick Begich memorial education loan may be used only to pursue a degree program in an accredited college or university that will lead to a career in education, public administration, government, or other closely related field.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-300__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The recipient of a memorial education loan must be a resident of Alaska and enrolled or eligible for enrollment as a full-time student in a certificate or degree program in a field listed in (b) of this section that is appropriate to the memorial education loan received.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-300__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The recipient must at all times continue to be enrolled as a full-time student in good standing at an accredited postsecondary institution that is appropriate to the memorial education loan received.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-300__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In any year in which the memorial education revolving loan fund created under
AS 14.43.255
has inadequate receipts to fund a loan in one of the loan categories listed in
AS 14.43.250
(b), no loan in that loan category may be offered and the receipts shall be added to the amount available for that category in the succeeding year.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-300__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The administering authority may provide conditions in the note signed by the recipient or in a separate document or communication that will help it carry out the provisions of
AS 14.43.250
 14.43.325.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-300__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 31 ch 63 SLA 2004.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-305">
            <num>14.43.305</num>
            <heading>Repayment of loans.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-305__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Memorial education loans under
AS 14.43.250
(b)(1)  (4) or (6) shall be noninterest-bearing and security for the loan may not be required. However, the note signed by the recipient shall provide for the payment of attorney fees, costs of court, and skip-tracing fees if any are incurred in collection of the unpaid amount owed on the loan.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-305__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>No part of a loan made under
AS 14.43.250
 14.43.325 need be repaid during an academic year in which the student is attending an accredited college or university as a full-time student.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-305__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Loans may be repaid at an accelerated rate at the option of the recipient.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-305__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a loan is in default, the administering authority shall notify the recipient that repayment of the remaining balance is accelerated and due by sending the recipient a notice of registered or certified mail.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-305__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A recipient of a memorial education loan under
AS 14.43.250
(b)(1)  (4) or (6) who graduates from a degree program, or for a loan under
AS 14.43.250
(b)(1) from a certificate program, shall receive forgiveness of one-fifth of loan principal for each one-year period the recipient is employed full time in Alaska in</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-305__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>law-enforcement or related fields, if a recipient of a Michael Murphy memorial education loan;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-305__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>criminal law, criminal justice, or other closely related fields, if a recipient of a Carroll L. Butch Swartz memorial education loan;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-305__subsec_e__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a recognized branch of the engineering profession or other closely related fields, if a recipient of a Harvey Golub memorial education loan;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-305__subsec_e__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>education or public administration, or other closely related field, if a recipient of a Robert L. Thomas memorial education loan; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-305__subsec_e__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>education, public administration, government, or other closely related field, if a recipient of a Nick Begich memorial education loan.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-305__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>That portion of the loan that is forgiven under (e) or (j) of this section shall be considered a grant to the recipient.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-305__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A recipient who does not qualify for forgiveness of all or a part of the loan made under
AS 14.43.250
(b)(1)  (4) or (6) shall begin repayment of the unforgiven portion within six months after leaving employment or terminating studies in</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-305__subsec_g__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>law enforcement or related fields, if a recipient of a Michael Murphy memorial education loan;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-305__subsec_g__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>criminal law, criminal justice, or other closely related fields, if a recipient of a Carroll L. Butch Swartz memorial education loan;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-305__subsec_g__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a recognized branch of the engineering profession or other closely related fields, if a recipient of a Harvey Golub memorial education loan;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-305__subsec_g__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>education or public administration, or other closely related field, if a recipient of a Robert L. Thomas memorial education loan; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-305__subsec_g__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>education, public administration, government, or other closely related field, if a recipient of a Nick Begich memorial education loan.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-305__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The unforgiven portion of a loan under (g) of this section shall be repaid in an amount, and at a monthly rate, to be determined by the administering authority after consultation with the recipient, but in any event not less than $50 a month.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-305__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To the extent they are not in conflict with terms and conditions under
AS 14.43.250
 14.43.325, the terms and conditions of a memorial education loan made under
AS 14.43.250
(b)(5) are the same as the terms and conditions for an education loan under
AS 14.43.091
 14.43.160, except that the interest on the loan is equal to five percent.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-305__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A recipient of a memorial education loan under
AS 14.43.250
(b)(5) who graduates from a certificate or degree program shall receive forgiveness of 10 percent of loan principal, up to a maximum of 50 percent of loan principal, for each one-year period during the first five years following graduation that the recipient is employed full time in the state in fisheries, fishery science, fishery management, seafood processing, food technology, or other closely related field.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-310">
            <num>14.43.310</num>
            <heading>Selection.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-310__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In selecting from among eligible applicants a person who will be granted a loan under
AS 14.43.250
 14.43.325, the administering authority shall consider the following:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-310__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the applicant's career goals and aspirations;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-310__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the applicant's prior academic record;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-310__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the financial need of the applicant; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-310__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>other items that may be considered relevant by the administering authority to determine whether an applicant will receive a loan.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-310__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To assist the administering authority in selecting eligible applicants for award of each of the memorial education loans under
AS 14.43.250
 14.43.325 and in reviewing the memorial education loan program, the following advisory committees are established:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-310__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>three Alaska state troopers, each one to be selected from and to represent a state trooper region of the state by the regional commander to serve for three years, for the Michael Murphy memorial education loan;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-310__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>[Repealed, § 24 ch 22 SLA 2001.]</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-310__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>three members of the state Board of Registration for Architects, Engineers, and Land Surveyors selected annually by the board from among its engineer members, for the Harvey Golub memorial education loan; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-310__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>three members of the state Board of Education and Early Development, or of the staff of the Department of Education and Early Development, or any combination of these, selected annually by the board, for the Robert L. Thomas memorial education loan.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-310__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In selecting from among eligible applicants for award of a memorial education loan under
AS 14.43.250
(b)(5), the administering authority shall give preference to applicants nominated by private donors to the A.W. (Winn) Brindle memorial education loan account in the memorial education revolving loan fund.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-310__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In selecting from among eligible applicants for award of a memorial education loan under
AS 14.43.250
(b)(6), the administering authority shall give preference to applicants nominated by the board members of the Nick Begich Scholarship Intern Fund, Inc.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-320">
            <num>14.43.320</num>
            <heading>Administering authority.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-320__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The memorial education loans provided for under
AS 14.43.250
 14.43.325 shall be administered by the executive director of the commission, subject to review by the commission and to those regulations the commission may prescribe to carry out the purposes of
AS 14.43.250
 14.43.325.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-320__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To the extent that they are not in conflict with the provisions of
AS 14.43.250
 14.43.325, the provisions of
AS 14.43.091
 14.43.160 relating to education loans are applicable to loans made under
AS 14.43.250
 14.43.325.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-325">
            <num>14.43.325</num>
            <heading>Funding.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-325__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The memorial education revolving loan fund created under
AS 14.43.255
shall be funded by voluntary contributions by state employees who may contribute the value of one or more days of annual leave a year to the memorial education revolving loan fund to be credited to any one or more of the education loan accounts listed in
AS 14.43.250</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-325__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>at the discretion of the donor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-325__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Administration shall pay to the account of the memorial education revolving loan fund established under
AS 14.43.255
an amount equal to the value of the total number of days of annual leave contributed by state employees under (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-325__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The administering authority may accept contributions from private sources for the memorial education revolving loan fund created under
AS 14.43.255
.  These contributions shall be deposited in the memorial education revolving loan fund created under
AS 14.43.255
to be credited to any one or more of the education loan accounts listed in
AS 14.43.250</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-325__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>at the discretion of the donor.  For the purpose of this subsection, private sources means private individuals, corporations, foundations, or other philanthropic or charitable organizations.
Article 8. Alaska Education Grant Program.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-400">
            <num>14.43.400</num>
            <heading>Purpose; creation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.43.400.   Purpose; creation.
There is created the Alaska education grant program to provide financial assistance to eligible students to enable them to attend, or continue their attendance at, postsecondary educational institutions. Funds designated by the corporation or appropriated for this program may be used as matching funds for the state's participation in the federal grant program under 20 U.S.C. 1070c  1070c-4.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-405">
            <num>14.43.405</num>
            <heading>Administration.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-405__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Alaska education grant program created under
AS 14.43.400
 14.43.420 shall be administered by the executive director of the commission.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-405__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 31 ch 63 SLA 2004.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-406">
            <num>14.43.406</num>
            <heading>Applicability of other laws.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-406__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To the extent they are not in conflict with the provisions of
AS 14.43.400
 14.43.420, the provisions of
AS 14.43.162
(b), 14.43.910, and 14.43.920 apply to a grant made under
AS 14.43.400
 14.43.420.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-406__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In determining a student's eligibility for a grant under
AS 14.43.400
 14.43.420, the executive director of the commission shall apply the standards contained in the definitions of full-time student, half-time student, and school year in
AS 14.43.160
as if those provisions were applicable to application for the grant.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-415">
            <num>14.43.415</num>
            <heading>Eligibility; priority.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-415__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For an applicant to be eligible for a grant under
AS 14.43.400
 14.43.420, the applicant must be</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-415__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a resident of this state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-415__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>enrolled or about to be enrolled
(A) at an institution located in the state that is</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-415__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>accredited by an institutional accrediting body recognized by the United States Secretary of Education; or
(ii) approved to participate in the Alaska performance scholarship program as a qualified postsecondary institution under
AS 14.43.830
; and
(B) on at least a half-time basis; and</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-415__subsec_i__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>able to demonstrate financial need in accordance with standards for determining financial need established by the commission.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-415__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 45 ch 89 SLA 2014.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-415__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall adopt regulations to establish terms and conditions for awarding grants under
AS 14.43.400
 14.43.420 and to establish the amounts to be awarded for on-time, full-time, and half-time student status.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-420">
            <num>14.43.420</num>
            <heading>Limitation on grants.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-420__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A grant made under
AS 14.43.400
 14.43.420 may not be in an amount that exceeds $4,000 for each school year.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-420__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 31 ch 63 SLA 2004.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-420__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A student may receive not more than a total of $16,000 in grants awarded under
AS 14.43.400
 14.43.420.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-420__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission may apply the amounts awarded under
AS 14.43.400
 14.43.420 to a state match required by federal grant programs under 20 U.S.C. 1070c-2.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-510">
            <num>14.43.510</num>
            <heading>Repayment condition for medical education program participants.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-510__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided under (b) and (c) of this section, as a condition of participating in a medical education program under
AS 14.42.033
, a program participant shall agree to either return to the state and actively engage in professional medical practice or repay financial support provided by the state on behalf of the program participant. The financial support to be repaid is equal to 50 percent of the amount paid for each program participant by the state to the contracting postsecondary institution, plus interest. The rate of interest is equal to the 12th Federal Reserve District discount rate in effect on March 1 of the year in which the financial support is provided plus two percentage points. Interest imposed under this subsection begins to accrue when the person terminates studies under the medical education program. Accrued interest shall be added to the principal balance of the repayment obligation at the time the borrower is obligated to commence repayment and at the end of a deferment period.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-510__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a program participant under (a) of this section has graduated from the medical education program for which the financial support was received and is employed in the state in the field for which the person received the financial support, including employment in the state in a medical residency program, the repayment obligation shall be forgiven and considered a grant in an amount equal to the following percentages plus accrued interest:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-510__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for employment in rural areas of the state,
(A) one year employment, 33 1/3 percent;
(B) two years employment, an additional 33 1/3 percent;
(C) three years employment, an additional 33 1/3 percent;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-510__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for employment in areas of the state that are not rural,
(A) one year employment, 20 percent;
(B) two years employment, an additional 20 percent;
(C) three years employment, an additional 20 percent;
(D) four years employment, an additional 20 percent;
(E) five years employment, an additional 20 percent.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-510__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Repayment under (a) of this section is required to begin not later than six months after the person terminates studies under the medical education program except that repayment shall be deferred for a person who (1) qualifies for forgiveness under (b) of this section for as long as the person remains qualified for forgiveness under (b) of this section; (2) is employed in a medical residency program for as long as the person remains in the medical residency program; or (3) is performing a service obligation imposed by the National Health Service Corps, the Indian Health Service, or the Uniformed Service Scholarship Program for as long as the person is performing the service. Forgiveness under (b) of this section only applies to that portion of the repayment obligation that has not been repaid to the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-510__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a person meets the qualifying conditions under this section for forgiveness after beginning repayment, the repayment requirement is deferred in the month following qualification for forgiveness. Repayment shall be deferred as long as the person remains qualified or until the balance of the repayment obligation has been fully forgiven. If the person is delinquent or in default on the person's regular repayment schedule, repayment shall continue until the person is current in payments. A period of time during which the person is making past due payments may not be considered as a qualifying period for the purpose of calculating forgiveness benefits.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-510__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of qualifying for forgiveness under this section, a person must be a full-time employee for a period of at least six months in order to qualify for a prorated forgiveness benefit. In this subsection, full-time employee does not include seasonal or temporary employment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-510__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person's obligation to repay under this section ends if the person dies and is deferred during any period in which a physician certifies that the person is totally disabled.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-510__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This section does not apply to loans received by a person under
AS 14.43.010
 14.43.160 or 14.43.710  14.43.750.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-510__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission may adopt regulations to implement this section. Except as provided in this section, regulations adopted under this subsection may not exempt or defer a repayment required under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-510__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, rural means a community with a population of 7,500 or less that is not connected by road or rail to Anchorage or Fairbanks or with a population of 3,500 or less that is connected by road or rail to Anchorage or Fairbanks.
Article 10. Teacher Education Loan Program.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-600">
            <num>14.43.600</num>
            <heading>Findings and intent.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-600__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The legislature finds that there is a wide and unacceptable disparity between the distribution of Native teachers and Native students in rural elementary and secondary schools in the state.  Many rural schools have virtually no Native teachers and no non-Native students. The undesirable effects of this disparity include the following:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-600__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>there is a serious weakness in the ability of teaching staffs in rural schools to foster a sense of Native traditions and cultures in the Native students;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-600__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>many rural students are forced to exist in two entirely separate situations: the essentially traditional atmosphere of many Native homes, and the essentially modern atmosphere of the classroom;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-600__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>almost no Native students return to rural schools to teach, continuing the imbalance and exacerbating its effects; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-600__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>there is an annual turnover of 40 percent among teachers in regional educational attendance areas in the state.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-600__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The legislature further finds that existing programs have failed to increase the proportion of Natives teaching in rural schools.  Therefore, it is the intent of the legislature to establish the teacher education loan program to encourage rural high school graduates to return to rural schools as teachers and relieve the conditions described in this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-610">
            <num>14.43.610</num>
            <heading>Program established.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.43.610.   Program established.
There is established the teacher education loan program to provide an incentive for rural high school graduates to pursue teaching careers in rural elementary and secondary schools in the state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-620">
            <num>14.43.620</num>
            <heading>Teacher education revolving loan fund.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-620__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The teacher education revolving loan fund is created for the purpose of making education loans to students selected under
AS 14.43.600
 14.43.700. The fund consists of money or assets appropriated or transferred to the commission for deposit into the fund, money or assets deposited into the fund by the commission, and earnings on investments of money held in the fund.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-620__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 45 ch 89 SLA 2014.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-620__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission may make a new loan under this section only if sufficient money or assets are available in the fund established under (a) of this section. If no new loans are issued in a fiscal year under this subsection, the commission shall use deposits for the year in the succeeding year.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-630">
            <num>14.43.630</num>
            <heading>Administration.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-630__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The teacher education loan program shall be administered by the commission in accordance with regulations adopted by the commission. The commission shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-630__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>allocate the loan awards available for teacher education loans annually to local school boards giving a preference to rural school districts; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-630__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>develop and distribute to the local school boards an application form for teacher education loans; the form must include a requirement that the applicant supply a high school academic transcript and a statement of intent to enter a teaching career at the elementary or secondary school level in the state.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-630__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The local school boards shall select the recipients of the teacher education loans according to the criteria in
AS 14.43.650
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-640">
            <num>14.43.640</num>
            <heading>Conditions of and limitations on loans.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-640__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To the extent that they are not in conflict with the provisions of
AS 14.43.600
 14.43.700, the provisions of
AS 14.43.100
 14.43.160 are applicable to loans made under
AS 14.43.600
 14.43.700.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-640__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a borrower meets the conditions provided in (a) of this section and is employed as a teacher in a rural elementary or secondary school, the portion of the loan that shall be paid by the state is the following percentages of the total loan received plus interest up to a total of 100 percent of the total loan:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-640__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>one year employment, 15 percent;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-640__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>two years employment, an additional 15 percent;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-640__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>three years employment, an additional 15 percent;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-640__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>four years employment, an additional 25 percent;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-640__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>over four years employment, an additional 30 percent.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-640__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A loan may not exceed $7,500 in a school year, exclusive of loan guarantee fees.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-640__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Proceeds from a teacher education loan may be used only for undergraduate expenses of books, tuition, required fees, loan guarantee fees, room and board, and the transportation expense for two round trips between the loan recipient's home and school.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-640__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Teacher education loans made to a student may not exceed a total of $37,500.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-640__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (b) of this section, a borrower who fails to qualify for loan payment by the state because the borrower is required to reside in an urban area of the state in order to receive medical treatment is still entitled to receive loan payments by the state under (b) of this section if the medical condition for which the borrower is receiving treatment did not exist before the borrower received the teacher education loan and the borrower is employed as a teacher in an urban elementary or secondary school.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-640__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall set the interest rate on a teacher education loan made from the teacher education revolving loan fund established under
AS 14.43.620
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-650">
            <num>14.43.650</num>
            <heading>Selection criteria.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-650__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To be eligible for a teacher education loan, a student must</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-650__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>be a graduate of a public or private high school in the state, with sufficient credits to be admitted to an accredited college or university;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-650__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>be enrolled in or show evidence of intent to enroll in a degree program directed at a teaching career at the elementary or secondary school level;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-650__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>meet the conditions set by the student's local school board with respect to the district's requirements for teachers in particular subject areas;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-650__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>submit to the local school board an application provided by the commission under
AS 14.43.630</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-650__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>not have a past due child support obligation established by court order or by the child support services agency under
AS 25.27.160
 25.27.220 at the time of application.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-650__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A local school board shall award teacher education loans giving a preference to applicants from rural schools who meet the qualifications for a loan and taking into account the applicants' academic records.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-650__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A student may not be awarded a teacher education loan under
AS 14.43.600
 14.43.700 if the student receives a loan under
AS 14.43.170
 14.43.175 for the same period of attendance.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-700">
            <num>14.43.700</num>
            <heading>Definition.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.43.700.   Definition.
In
AS 14.43.600
 14.43.700, rural means a community with a population of 7,500 or less that is not connected by road or rail to Anchorage or Fairbanks or a community with a population of 1,500 or less that is connected by road or rail to Anchorage or Fairbanks.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-710">
            <num>14.43.710</num>
            <heading>Program established.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.43.710.   Program established.
The Alaska family education loan program is established to provide low interest loans to families to assist in paying the costs of postsecondary education for family members.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-720">
            <num>14.43.720</num>
            <heading>Family education loan account.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-720__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The family education loan account is created within the education loan fund (
AS 14.42.210
). The account shall be used to make family education loans to families selected under
AS 14.43.710
 14.43.750, to pay the costs of collecting family education loans that are in default if those costs are not recovered from the family, and to pay the costs of administering the account. Unless the instrument evidencing the family education loan has been sold or assigned to the Alaska Student Loan Corporation, repayments of principal and interest on family education loans shall be paid into the family education loan account. If estimated funds available from family education loan repayments are inadequate to fully fund estimated family education loans in a fiscal year, additional funding from the general fund may be requested and appropriated for that year.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-720__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission may sell or assign notes and other instruments evidencing family education loans to the Alaska Student Loan Corporation and enter into agreements with the corporation relating to loans, the administration of the education loan fund created under
AS 14.42.210
, and the payment of and security for bonds of the corporation. Proceeds from the sale or assignment of notes and other instruments shall be deposited in the family education loan account.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-740">
            <num>14.43.740</num>
            <heading>Loan terms, limits, and conditions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-740__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The provisions of
AS 14.43.100
, 14.43.120(a)  (c), (m), and (r)  (u), 14.43.122, 14.43.135, 14.43.145  14.43.155, 14.43.173, and 14.43.910  14.43.990 apply to a loan made under
AS 14.43.710
 14.43.750.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-740__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 18 ch 54 SLA 1997.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-740__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The corporation shall set the interest rate on a loan made under
AS 14.43.710
 14.43.750, but the annual rate may not exceed 8.25 percent.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-740__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Repayment of the principal and interest on a loan made under
AS 14.43.710
 14.43.750 begins on the first of the month immediately following loan disbursement. The loan may be cancelled without prejudice at any time before actual disbursement. The loan shall provide for repayment of the total amount owed in periodic installments in not more than 10 years from the commencement of repayment. If the commission and the borrower agree to a different repayment schedule, the borrower shall repay the loan in accordance with the agreement.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-740__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Provision shall be made for payment by the borrower of fees and costs incurred in collection of delinquent or defaulted loans.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-740__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission may withhold disbursement of a loan if the borrower or family member is no longer eligible under
AS 14.43.750
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-740__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 45 ch 89 SLA 2014.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-750">
            <num>14.43.750</num>
            <heading>Eligibility.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-750__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may apply for and obtain a family education loan on behalf of a family member if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-750__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the borrower and the family member
(A) are residents of the state at the time of application for the loan; for purposes of this paragraph, a borrower and family member qualify as residents of the state if the borrower and the family member have been physically present in the state for at least one year immediately before the time of application for the loan with the intent to remain indefinitely or, if not physically present in the state, the borrower and family member have not declared or established residency in another state, intend to return permanently to the state, and the absence meets the requirements imposed under
AS 14.43.125</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-750__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the family member
(A) is enrolled as a full-time student in a career education, associate, baccalaureate, or graduate degree program; or
(B) is a graduate of a high school or the equivalent, or scheduled for graduation from a high school within six months, who, at the time of loan disbursement, will be enrolled in compliance with (A) of this paragraph; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-750__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>neither the borrower nor the family member
(A) is delinquent or has ever been in default on a loan previously awarded by the commission unless the defaulted loan has been voluntarily paid in full;
(B) is past due on a child support obligation established by court order or by the child support services agency under
AS 25.27.160
 25.27.220 at the time of application or loan disbursement;
(C) has, within the previous five years, had a loan discharged or written off by the commission for any reason.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-750__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 26 ch 5 SLA 1996.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-810">
            <num>14.43.810</num>
            <heading>Alaska performance scholarship program established; regulations.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-810__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Alaska performance scholarship program is established to provide scholarships for high school graduates who are Alaska residents to attend a qualified postsecondary institution in the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-810__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall, in consultation with the commission, adopt regulations necessary to implement the Alaska performance scholarship program. The commission shall administer the daily operations of the Alaska performance scholarship program and financing of the Alaska performance scholarship program, including the procedures for applying for the scholarships, establishing standards for and ensuring continuing compliance with programmatic standards, and requiring students to apply for other nonloan financial aid, consistent with federal law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-820">
            <num>14.43.820</num>
            <heading>Alaska performance scholarship program; eligibility.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-820__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subject to appropriation, the commission shall award an Alaska performance scholarship to an applicant who</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-820__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is a resident of the state as defined in
AS 01.10.055
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-820__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>graduated or will graduate within 18 months from a high school in the state; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-820__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>except as provided in (c) of this section, has completed, is enrolled in, or plans to enroll in a core academic curriculum of high school level coursework that includes
(A) four years of mathematics, four years of language arts, four years of science, and four years of social studies, one year of which may include a foreign language, an Alaska Native language, fine arts, cultural heritage, or career and technical education;
(B) three years of mathematics, four years of language arts, three years of science, four years of social studies, and two years of</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-820__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>a foreign language, an Alaska Native language, fine arts, or cultural heritage; or
(ii)  career and technical education, one year of which includes two semesters of sequentially more rigorous content within a career cluster; or
(C)  three years of mathematics, four years of language arts, three years of science, four years of social studies, one year of which may be career and technical education, and two years of a foreign language, an Alaska Native language, fine arts, or cultural heritage.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-820__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall establish in regulation standards for continuing and regaining eligibility for a scholarship.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-820__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall waive a portion of the core academic requirements specified under (a)(3) of this section for not more than 24 additional months after a student graduates from a high school in the state to provide an eligible applicant the opportunity to complete the academic requirements at a qualified postsecondary institution using a scholarship awarded under
AS 14.43.825</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-820__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or at a public high school in the state with a district sponsorship under (f) of this section if the applicant submits a timely application on a form approved by the commissioner and provides satisfactory proof that the applicant was unable to complete the academic requirements under (a)(3) of this section as a result of circumstances beyond the applicant's control, including</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-820__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>illness or disability;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-820__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a lack of reasonable access to the required coursework at a small or remote high school attended by the applicant in the state; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-820__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>other circumstances prescribed by regulation adopted by the board.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-820__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall approve or deny an application for a waiver submitted under (c) of this section within 30 days after receiving the application.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-820__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An applicant who receives a waiver under (c) of this section, shall, within the time granted for the waiver, provide satisfactory proof to the commissioner of completion of the core academic requirements specified under (a)(3) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-820__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding a contrary provision in this title, a school district that agrees to sponsor a student for a waiver under (c) of this section may include a student who has been approved for a waiver under (c) of this section in the student count conducted under
AS 14.17.600
as a full-time or part-time student if the student attends a school in the district for the purpose of completing the core academic requirements under (a)(3) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-820__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-820__subsec_g__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>career cluster means a group of jobs and industries that are related by skills or products;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-820__subsec_g__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>district has the meaning given in
AS 14.17.990
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-820__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Not later than January 15 of each year, a district shall provide to each student in the district who is enrolled in grade nine or grade 10 information about the Alaska performance scholarship.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-820__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Not later than December 31 of each year, a district shall notify each student in the district who is enrolled in grade 11 of the remaining academic requirements the student must meet to be awarded an Alaska performance scholarship at each level described in
AS 14.43.825
(a).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-820__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Not later than August 15 of each year, the commission shall notify each applicant awarded a scholarship under (a) of this section that the applicant has been awarded an Alaska performance scholarship. The notice must</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-820__subsec_j__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>identify the Alaska performance scholarship level awarded as described in
AS 14.43.825</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-820__subsec_j__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>inform the applicant that
(A) the commission may disburse the award only if the applicant meets the requirements described in (l) of this section; and
(B) the commission will adjust the applicant's award under the circumstances described in (k) of this section.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-820__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a district provides information to or otherwise communicates with a student regarding the Alaska performance scholarship, the district shall also provide information about the requirements to increase an award level under
AS 14.43.825</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-820__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p> (j).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-820__subsec_l">
              <num>(l)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If, at the time an applicant awarded an Alaska performance scholarship graduates from high school, the applicant's grade-point average differs from the grade-point average on which the commission based the applicant's award, the commission shall adjust the applicant's award in accordance with the applicable Alaska performance scholarship level described in
AS 14.43.825
(a).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-820__subsec_m">
              <num>(m)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (a) of this section, and except as provided in (c) of this section, the commission may disburse an Alaska performance scholarship awarded to an applicant under this section only if the applicant</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-820__subsec_m__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has, at the time of the applicant's graduation from high school,
(A) completed the core academic curriculum of high school level coursework described in (a)(3) of this section; and
(B) met the minimum</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-820__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>grade-point average in high school described in
AS 14.43.825
(a); or
(ii) score on a college entrance examination described in
AS 14.43.825
(a); and</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-820__subsec_i__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is enrolled in good standing in a course of study at a qualified postsecondary institution in this state that is intended to result in the award of a certificate or degree.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-825">
            <num>14.43.825</num>
            <heading>Maximum annual awards.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-825__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The maximum annual awards for the Alaska performance scholarships are as follows:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-825__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the first award level is $7,000 and requires a (A) 3.5 grade-point average or above, or the equivalent established under (g) of this section; or
(A) 3.5 grade-point average or above, or the equivalent established under (g) of this section; or
(B) very high minimum score on a college entrance examination;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-825__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the second award level is $5,250 and requires a
(A) 3.0 grade-point average or above, or the equivalent established under (g) of this section; or
(B) high minimum score on a college entrance examination;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-825__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the third award level is $3,500 and requires a
(A) 2.5 grade-point average or above, or the equivalent established under (g) of this section; or
(B) moderately high minimum score on a college entrance examination.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-825__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A student's eligibility for a scholarship terminates eight years after the date the student graduates from high school unless the student qualifies for an extension of time allowed by the department by regulation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-825__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (b) of this section, a student receiving a scholarship may remain eligible for up to eight semesters of enrollment in good standing at a qualified university or college, which may include graduate courses. A student's eligibility under this subsection is extended by one semester for each semester the student is enrolled part time in good standing at a qualified university or college.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-825__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Scholarships may be awarded to a full-time student or, if a student is enrolled part time, prorated based on the number of credits. In this subsection, full time means enrollment in a course of study that is not less than 12 credits, and part time means enrollment in a course of study that is not less than six credits but less than 12 credits.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-825__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The amount of a scholarship award may not exceed the amount of the student's costs of attendance as certified by the postsecondary institution for the purposes of federal financial aid, less any other scholarships or nonloan financial aid awarded to the student.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-825__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Payment of a scholarship is subject to appropriation and the availability of funds for expenditure under
AS 37.14.750
. If insufficient funds are appropriated or available in a fiscal year to pay all eligible scholarships, the commission may not award a scholarship to a new applicant, and the commission shall pay existing awards on a pro rata basis for that fiscal year.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-825__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For high schools that do not award grades on a four-point scale, or five-point scale for advanced placement classes, the department shall establish by regulation the equivalent rating required for a scholarship awarded under (a)(1)(A), (2)(A), and (3)(A) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-825__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each time a student who is an award recipient completes two semesters of full-time enrollment at a qualified postsecondary institution in this state, the postsecondary institution shall review and notify the commission of the student's postsecondary institution grade-point average. If the student's grades qualify under (i) of this section, the commission shall increase the award level for the student as described in (i) of this section and notify the student of the increase. In this subsection, full-time enrollment means enrollment in a course of study that is not less than 15 credits.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-825__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If an award recipient's postsecondary institution grade-point average is</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-825__subsec_i__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>3.5 or above, or the equivalent established under (j) of this section, the commission shall increase the student's award level to the amount described in (a)(1) of this section;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-825__subsec_i__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>3.0 or above, or the equivalent established under (j) of this section, the commission shall increase the student's award level to the amount described in (a)(2) of this section.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-825__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For qualified postsecondary institutions that do not award grades on a four-point scale, the commission shall establish by regulation the equivalent rating required to increase an award under (i) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-825__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-825__subsec_k__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>award recipient means a student who has received an Alaska performance scholarship at the second or third award level;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-825__subsec_k__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>postsecondary institution grade-point average means the weighted or unweighted average of all grades on a four-point scale, or the equivalent as established by the commission by regulation, obtained by a student at a qualified postsecondary institution in this state.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-830">
            <num>14.43.830</num>
            <heading>Qualified postsecondary institutions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-830__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The following institutions are qualified postsecondary institutions for purposes of awarding an Alaska performance scholarship:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-830__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a university or college physically located in the state that
(A) is authorized to operate in the state under
AS 14.48.020
or is exempt from authorization under
AS 14.48.030</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-830__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a career and technical school program physically located in the state that meets the standards established in (a)(1)(C) and (D) of this section and that has been included on a list of certified career and technical school programs received from the Department of Labor and Workforce Development; the commission shall publish the list on or before June 30 of the year preceding enrollment.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-830__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Labor and Workforce Development shall, in consultation with the Department of Education and Early Development, adopt regulations under
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act) establishing criteria under which the Department of Labor and Workforce Development shall certify career and technical school programs in the state as eligible to participate in the Alaska performance scholarship program.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-840">
            <num>14.43.840</num>
            <heading>Report to the legislature.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-840__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To the extent permitted under law, the department, the commission, the University of Alaska, and the Department of Labor and Workforce Development shall share data necessary to prepare public reports regarding the program.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-840__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Not more than 10 days after the convening of each regular legislative session, the department, the commission, the University of Alaska, and the Department of Labor and Workforce Development shall present an annual report to the public, the governor, and the legislature containing information of public interest regarding the program, including</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-840__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the number of applicants and number and types of scholarships awarded;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-840__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the dollar amount of scholarships awarded in past years and the dollar amount expected to be awarded for the next year; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-840__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>data and trends in the data regarding high school and postsecondary student performance, programmatic changes, and retention and graduation rates over time.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-849">
            <num>14.43.849</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.43.849.   Definitions.
In
AS 14.43.810
 14.43.849, unless the context requires otherwise,
(1) department means the Department of Education and Early Development;
(2) grade-point average means the weighted or unweighted average of all grades on a four-point scale, or five-point scale for advanced placement classes, or the equivalent as established by the department by regulation, obtained by the student in high school;
(3) high school means a public or accredited secondary school in the state and a home school program that is approved by the department;
(4) program means the Alaska performance scholarship program established under
AS 14.43.810
 14.43.849;
(5) school district means a borough school district, a city school district, a regional educational attendance area, and a state boarding school.
Article 13. General Provisions.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-910">
            <num>14.43.910</num>
            <heading>Confidentiality of financial need information.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.43.910.   Confidentiality of financial need information.
All information submitted in support of a determination of financial need as provided in this chapter is confidential. However, an applicant may inspect or copy information from the applicants' application, or records relating to the applicant's own application, or authorize release of the application or records to designated individuals or organizations.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-915">
            <num>14.43.915</num>
            <heading>Alaska education grant account and Alaska performance scholarship award account.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-915__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Alaska education grant account is created as an account in the general fund. Money may be appropriated to the account from the Alaska higher education investment fund under
AS 37.14.750
and from other sources. The commission may use the money in the account to pay grants awarded under
AS 14.43.400
 14.43.420 and to pay the cost of administration of the Alaska education grant program created under
AS 14.43.400
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-915__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Alaska performance scholarship award account is created as an account in the general fund. Money may be appropriated to the account from the Alaska higher education investment fund under
AS 37.14.750
and from other sources. The commission may use the money in the account to pay scholarships awarded to students under
AS 14.43.810
 14.43.849.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-915__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Of the total amount available annually to the commission for payment of grants under
AS 14.43.400
 14.43.420 and for payment of scholarships under
AS 14.43.810
 14.43.849, one-third of the combined amount in the accounts established under (a) and (b) of this section shall be available solely for payment of grants awarded under
AS 14.43.400
 14.43.420. The commission shall annually allocate to all qualified applicants for scholarships awarded under
AS 14.43.810
 14.43.849 two-thirds of the combined amount in the accounts. If an insufficient number of qualified applicants are awarded grants under
AS 14.43.400
 14.43.420 or scholarships under
AS 14.43.810
 14.43.849, or both, before the end of that fiscal year, the commissioner shall redeposit the remaining funds into the Alaska higher education investment fund established under
AS 37.14.750
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-915__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall reserve a percentage calculated under this subsection of the total amount available for awards in the accounts established under (a) and (b) of this section each year for award to students who graduate from a school district with an ADM of less than 800 or from a school that was operated by the Alaska State-Operated School System established under former
AS 14.08.020
. The percentage reserved under this subsection shall be calculated by adding the ADMs of districts with an ADM of less than 800 and the number of students enrolled in a school that was operated by the Alaska State-Operated School System established under former
AS 14.08.020
that is located in a district with an ADM of 800 or more and then dividing that number by the sum of the ADMs of all districts in the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-915__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If an insufficient number of applicants apply for the available amount reserved under (d) of this section, the commission shall redeposit the remaining amount in the account from which the funds originated.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-915__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-915__subsec_f__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>ADM has the meaning given in
AS 14.17.990
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-915__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>district has the meaning given in
AS 14.17.990
, but also includes a state boarding school under
AS 14.16
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-920">
            <num>14.43.920</num>
            <heading>Repayment by ineligible recipient.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.43.920.   Repayment by ineligible recipient.
If a person receives a scholarship, loan, or grant under this title for which the person is not eligible under the provisions of this title, the scholarship, loan, or grant is void and the entire balance of money paid is immediately due to the scholarship, loan, or grant fund. This section is in addition to any penalty that may be imposed according to another provision of law.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-930">
            <num>14.43.930</num>
            <heading>Scholarship program information.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-43-930__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board shall make information about scholarship programs available in each school district in the state and at each campus of the University of Alaska.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-930__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>By September 15 before each annual graduation, a qualified high school in the state with a high school graduating class shall provide</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-930__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to the board a list of the names and addresses of students in the graduating class who meet scholarship eligibility requirements for each scholarship program; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-930__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a notice of eligibility for the scholarship program to those students on the list prepared under (1) of this subsection.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-930__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A school district shall amend its policies, including those applying to student directory information, as necessary to comply with this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-930__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A qualified high school may not provide to the board the name of a student if the parent of the student objects to the disclosure.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-43-930__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-930__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>board means the Board of Regents of the University of Alaska;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-43-930__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>qualified high school means a public high school, a high school accredited by the Northwest Association of Accredited Schools, or a high school registered with the department.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-43-990">
            <num>14.43.990</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.43.990.   Definitions.
In this chapter,
(1) AlaskAdvantage means the service mark registered by the commission under 15 U.S.C. 1051 (Trademark Act) that is used to describe financial aid and higher education outreach programs and services provided by the commission;
(2) approved federal family education loan institution means a postsecondary education institution in this state or outside of this state that is approved for participation in the federal guaranteed student loan program;
(3) commission means the Alaska Commission on Postsecondary Education;
(4) corporation means the Alaska Student Loan Corporation created in
AS 14.42.100
;
(5) education loan means a loan made to finance the cost of attendance in a postsecondary education program that is made by the commission or is a loan received through the federal guaranteed student loan program;
(6) federal guaranteed student loan program means the programs of the United States government making postsecondary educational financial aid available under 20 U.S.C. 1070  1099c-2, as amended;
(7) on-time student means an undergraduate who is enrolled and is in regular attendance at classes for 15 or more semester hours of credit or the equivalent during the semester; any combination of semester hours of credit or the equivalent aggregating to the requisite number of semester hours and undertaken during a semester at two or more public or private institutions of higher education constitutes on-time student status.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>