<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-28/chapter-37"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-28/chapter-37"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="28.37"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-28/chapter-37/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-28/chapter-37/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-28/chapter-37/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-28/chapter-37/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_28">
        <num>28</num>
        <heading>Motor Vehicles</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_28__chp_37">
          <num>37</num>
          <heading>Driver License Compact</heading>
          <section eId="sec_28-37-010">
            <num>28.37.010</num>
            <heading>Compact enacted.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.37.010.   Compact enacted.
The Driver License Compact is enacted into law and entered into with all other jurisdictions legally joining in it in the form substantially contained in
AS 28.37.110
 28.37.190.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-37-020">
            <num>28.37.020</num>
            <heading>Licensing authority.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.37.020.   Licensing authority.
In this chapter the term licensing authority with reference to this state means the entity in the Department of Administration that administers
AS 28.15.011
 28.15.151. The department shall furnish to the appropriate authority of another party state the information or documents reasonably necessary to facilitate the administration of
AS 28.37.130
 28.37.150.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-37-030">
            <num>28.37.030</num>
            <heading>Expenses of administrator.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.37.030.   Expenses of administrator.
The compact administrator provided for in
AS 28.37.170
is not entitled to additional compensation on account of service as the administrator, but is entitled to expenses incurred in connection with the duties and responsibilities as the administrator, in the same manner as for expenses incurred in connection with other duties or responsibilities of the office or employment.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-37-040">
            <num>28.37.040</num>
            <heading>Executive head.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.37.040.   Executive head.
In this chapter, with reference to this state, the term executive head means the governor.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-37-110">
            <num>28.37.110</num>
            <heading>Findings and policy statement.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-37-110__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The party states find that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-37-110__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the safety of their streets and highways is materially affected by the degree of compliance with state laws and local ordinances relating to the operation of motor vehicles;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-37-110__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>violation of a law or ordinance is evidence that the violator engages in conduct that is likely to endanger the safety of persons and property;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-37-110__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the continuance in force of a license to drive is predicated upon compliance with laws and ordinances relating to the operation of motor vehicles, in whichever jurisdiction the vehicle is operated.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-37-110__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>It is the policy of the party states to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-37-110__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>promote compliance with the laws, ordinances, and administrative regulations relating to the operation of motor vehicles by their drivers in each of the jurisdictions where those drivers operate motor vehicles;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-37-110__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>make the reciprocal recognition of licenses to drive and eligibility for them more just and equitable by considering the overall compliance with motor vehicle laws, ordinances, and administrative regulations as a condition precedent to the continuance or issuance of a license by reason of which the licensee is authorized or permitted to operate a motor vehicle in the party states.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-37-130">
            <num>28.37.130</num>
            <heading>Reports of convictions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.37.130.   Reports of convictions.
The licensing authority of a party state shall report each conviction of a person from another party state occurring within its jurisdiction to the licensing authority of the home state of the licensee.  The report shall clearly identify the person convicted; describe the violation specifying the section of the statute, code, or ordinance violated; identify the court in which action was taken; indicate whether a plea of guilty or not guilty was entered, or the conviction was a result of the forfeiture of bail, bond or other security; and shall include any special findings made in connection with the conviction.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-37-140">
            <num>28.37.140</num>
            <heading>Effect of conviction in party state.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-37-140__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The licensing authority in the home state, for the purposes of suspending, revoking, or limiting the license to operate a motor vehicle, shall give the same effect to the conduct reported under
AS 28.37.130
as it would if the conduct had occurred in the home state, in the case of a conviction for</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-37-140__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>manslaughter or negligent homicide resulting from the operation of a motor vehicle;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-37-140__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>driving a motor vehicle while under the influence of intoxicating liquor or a narcotic drug, or under the influence of any other drug to a degree that renders the driver incapable of safely driving a motor vehicle;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-37-140__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>any felony in the commission of which a motor vehicle is used;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-37-140__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>failure to stop and render aid in the event of a motor vehicle accident resulting in the death or personal injury of another.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-37-140__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>As to another conviction, reported under
AS 28.37.130
, the licensing authority in the home state shall give the effect to the conduct that is provided by the laws of the home state if the offense constituting the conduct report under
AS 28.37.130
has elements similar to those of the home state as defined in the home state at the time the offense constituting the conduct report under
AS 28.37.130
was committed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-37-140__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the laws of a party state do not provide for offenses or violations denominated or described in precisely the words employed in (a) of this section, the party state shall construe the denominations and descriptions appearing in (a) of this section as being applicable to and identifying the offenses or violations of a substantially similar nature, and the laws of the party state shall contain the provisions necessary to ensure that full force and effect is given to this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-37-150">
            <num>28.37.150</num>
            <heading>Grounds requiring refusal to issue license.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.37.150.   Grounds requiring refusal to issue license.
Upon application for a license to drive, the licensing authority in a party state shall ascertain whether the applicant has ever held, or is the holder of a license to drive issued by another party state. The licensing authority in the state where application is made may not issue a license to drive to the applicant if
(1) the applicant has held a license, but the license has been suspended, revoked, or canceled, or the applicant has been disqualified from operating a commercial motor vehicle by reason, in whole or in part, of a violation, and the suspension period has not terminated;
(2) the applicant has held a license, but the license has been revoked by reason, in whole or in part, of a violation, and the revocation has not terminated; except that after the expiration of one year from the date the license was revoked, the person may make application for a new license if permitted by law; the licensing authority may refuse to issue a license to an applicant if, after investigation, the licensing authority determines that it will not be safe to grant to the person the privilege of driving a motor vehicle on the public highways;
(3) the applicant is the holder of a license to drive issued by another party state and currently in force, unless the applicant surrenders the license;
(4) the applicant has held a license, but has been disqualified from operating a commercial motor vehicle by reason, in whole or in part, of a violation, and the disqualification has not terminated; however, a person may make an application for a noncommercial driver's license if permitted by other law.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-37-160">
            <num>28.37.160</num>
            <heading>Application of other state laws.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.37.160.   Application of other state laws.
Except as expressly required by provisions of this chapter, nothing in this chapter shall be construed to affect the right of a party state to apply any of its other laws relating to licenses to drive to any person or circumstance, nor to invalidate or prevent any driver license agreement or other cooperative arrangement between a party state and a nonparty state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-37-170">
            <num>28.37.170</num>
            <heading>Administrator of compact.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-37-170__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The head of the licensing authority of each party state shall be the administrator of the compact for that state.  The administrators of all party states, acting jointly, shall have the power to formulate all necessary and proper procedures for the exchange of information under this compact.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-37-170__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The administrator of each party state shall furnish to the administrator of each other party state the information or documents reasonably necessary to facilitate the administration of the compact.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-37-180">
            <num>28.37.180</num>
            <heading>Compact as law; withdrawal procedure.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-37-180__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The compact shall become effective as to any state in which the compact becomes effective as the law of that state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-37-180__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A party state may withdraw from the compact by enacting a statute repealing the compact as the law of the state, but a withdrawal may not take effect until six months after the executive head of the withdrawing state has given notice of the withdrawal to the executive heads of all other party states.  Withdrawal does not affect the validity or applicability by the licensing authorities of states remaining party to the compact of any report of conviction occurring before the withdrawal.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-37-190">
            <num>28.37.190</num>
            <heading>Construction and validity; severability.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.37.190.   Construction and validity; severability.
The compact shall be liberally construed so as to effectuate its purposes. The provisions of the compact are severable and if any phrase, clause, sentence, or provision of the compact is declared to be contrary to the constitution of any party state or of the United States or the applicability of it to a government, agency, person or circumstance is held invalid, the validity of the remainder of the compact and the applicability of it to any government, agency, person or circumstance shall not be affected by it.  If the compact is held contrary to the constitution of any party state, the compact shall remain in full force and effect as to the remaining states and in full force and effect as to the state affected as to all severable matters.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-37-199">
            <num>28.37.199</num>
            <heading>Compact definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.37.199.   Compact definitions.
In this chapter,
(1) conviction means a conviction of an offense related to the use or operation of a motor vehicle that is prohibited by state law, municipal ordinance, or administrative regulation, or a forfeiture of bail, bond or other security deposited to secure appearance by a person charged with having committed an offense described in this paragraph, and that is required to be reported to the licensing authority under
AS 28.37.130
;
(2) home state means the state that has issued and has the power to suspend or revoke the use of the license or permit to operate a motor vehicle;
(3) state means a state, territory, or possession of the United States, the District of Columbia, or the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>