<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-40/chapter-15"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-40/chapter-15"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="40.15"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-40/chapter-15/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-40/chapter-15/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-40/chapter-15/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-40/chapter-15/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_40">
        <num>40</num>
        <heading>Public Records and Recorders</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_40__chp_15">
          <num>15</num>
          <heading>Subdivisions and Dedications</heading>
          <section eId="sec_40-15-010">
            <num>40.15.010</num>
            <heading>Approval, filing, and recording of subdivisions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 40.15.010.   Approval, filing, and recording of subdivisions.
Before the lots or tracts of any subdivision or dedication may be sold or offered for sale, the subdivision or dedication shall be approved by the authority having jurisdiction, as prescribed in this chapter and shall be filed and recorded in the office of the recorder. The recorder may not accept a subdivision or dedication for filing and recording unless it shows this approval. However, the recorder may accept for filing and recording a division of a tract or parcel of land approved under
AS 29.40.080
(c).</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_40-15-020">
            <num>40.15.020</num>
            <heading>Plats to be acknowledged and contain certificate that taxes and assessments are paid.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 40.15.020.   Plats to be acknowledged and contain certificate that taxes and assessments are paid.
Every plat shall be acknowledged before an officer authorized to take acknowledgment of deeds.  A certificate of acknowledgment shall be endorsed on or annexed to the plat and recorded with it. A person filing and recording a plat, map, subdivision, or replat of property, or vacating the whole or any portion of an existing plat, map, subdivision, or replat shall file and record with it a certificate from the tax-collecting official or officials of the area in which the land is located that all taxes levied against the property at that date are paid.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_40-15-030">
            <num>40.15.030</num>
            <heading>Dedication of streets, alleys, and thoroughfares.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 40.15.030.   Dedication of streets, alleys, and thoroughfares.
When an area is subdivided and a plat of the subdivision is approved, filed, and recorded, all streets, alleys, thoroughfares, parks and other public areas shown on the plat are considered to be dedicated to public use.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_40-15-040">
            <num>40.15.040</num>
            <heading>Certified copy of plat as evidence.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 40.15.040.   Certified copy of plat as evidence.
A copy of a plat certified by the recorder of the recording district in which it is filed or recorded as a true and complete copy of the original filed or recorded in the recording office for the district is admissible in evidence in all courts in the state with the same effect as the original.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_40-15-050">
            <num>40.15.050</num>
            <heading>Plats legalized.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 40.15.050.   Plats legalized.
All plats filed or recorded with the recorder before March 30, 1953, whether executed and acknowledged in accordance with this chapter or not, are validated and all streets, alleys, or public thoroughfares shown on these plats are considered to be dedicated to public use. The last plat of the area of record on March 30, 1953, is the official plat of the area as of that date, and the streets, alleys, or thoroughfares shown on it are considered to be dedicated to public use. The streets, alleys, or thoroughfares shown on an earlier plat of the same area, or any part of it, that are in conflict with those shown on the official plat are considered to be abandoned and vacated.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_40-15-060">
            <num>40.15.060</num>
            <heading>Missing plats.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 40.15.060.   Missing plats.
When a filed or recorded plat is missing and a present record is not available except by reference to the missing plat, a counterpart copy approved by the platting authority may be filed and recorded as of the original date of the missing plat and after filing and recording has the same legal effect and notice as the original missing plat.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_40-15-070">
            <num>40.15.070</num>
            <heading>Platting authority.</heading>
            <subsection eId="40-15-070__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If land proposed to be subdivided or dedicated is situated within a municipality that has the power of land use regulation and that is exercising platting authority, the proposed subdivision or dedication shall be submitted to the municipal platting authority for approval. A subdivision may not be filed and recorded until it is approved by the platting authority.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="40-15-070__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Natural Resources is the platting authority in the areas of the state not described in (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_40-15-200">
            <num>40.15.200</num>
            <heading>Application to state and political subdivisions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 40.15.200.   Application to state and political subdivisions.
All subdivisions of land made by the state, its agencies, instrumentalities, and political subdivisions are subject to the provisions of
AS 40.15.010
 40.15.200 and
AS 29.40.070
 29.40.160, or home rule ordinances or regulations governing subdivisions, and shall comply with ordinances and other local regulations adopted under
AS 40.15.010
 40.15.200 and
AS 29.40.070
 29.40.160 or former
AS 29.33.150
 29.33.240, or under home rule authority, in the same manner and to the same extent as subdivisions made by other landowners.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_40-15-300">
            <num>40.15.300</num>
            <heading>Purposes ofAS 40.15.300 40.15.380.</heading>
            <subsection eId="40-15-300__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and to ensure that provision has been made for access to those subdivisions.
AS 40.15.300
 40.15.380 are not intended to provide the state with any authority to establish engineering or other standards for subdivisions beyond those expressly set out in
AS 40.15.300
 40.15.380.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_40-15-305">
            <num>40.15.305</num>
            <heading>Examination of plats before recording.</heading>
            <subsection eId="40-15-305__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall exercise the platting authority for the state except within a municipality that has the power of land use regulation and that is exercising platting authority.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="40-15-305__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall review and approve each plat under
AS 40.15.300
  40.15.380 before the plat is recorded under
AS 40.17
. The approval by the commissioner shall be affixed to the plat in the form of the following statement:
PLAT APPROVAL
This plat is approved by the commissioner of natural resources, or the commissioner's designee, in accordance with
AS 40.15
.
Commissioner  Date</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="40-15-305__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The recorder may not accept for filing and recording a plat for which the commissioner's approval is required under this section without the approval of the commissioner endorsed on the plat.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="40-15-305__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Within 45 days after a plat is filed, the commissioner shall approve the plat or return it to the applicant for modification or correction. Unless the applicant for plat approval consents to an extension of time, the plat is approved and a certificate of approval shall be issued by the commissioner if the commissioner fails to act within that period. The commissioner shall state in writing reasons for disapproval of a plat.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="40-15-305__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A recorded plat may not be altered or replatted except on petition of the state, a municipality, a public utility, or the owner of a majority of the land affected by the proposed alteration or replat. The petition shall be filed with the commissioner and shall be accompanied by a copy of the existing plat showing the proposed alteration or replat. The provisions of
AS 29.40.130
and  29.40.140(a) apply to an alteration or replat submitted under this subsection. The provisions of (d) of this section do not apply to an alteration or replat petition, but the commissioner shall state in writing reasons for disapproval of the petition.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="40-15-305__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In the case of a vacation of a street, right-of-way, or other public area, the provisions of
AS 29.40.140</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="40-15-305__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and  29.40.160(a) and (b) apply. When applying these provisions to land outside a municipality, the word municipality should be read as state when the context requires.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="40-15-305__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding another provision of
AS 40.15.300
  40.15.380, the commissioner shall approve, without review under
AS 40.15.300
  40.15.380, a plat under
AS 38.04.045
that consists solely of land owned by the state. The commissioner may not charge a fee for the approval under this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_40-15-310">
            <num>40.15.310</num>
            <heading>Requirements for plat approval.</heading>
            <subsection eId="40-15-310__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each plat must show on its face a certificate of ownership, with the names and addresses of each owner listed. Each owner of record shall sign the certificate, and the signatures shall be acknowledged.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="40-15-310__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The surveyor preparing the plat shall sign and affix the seal of the surveyor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_40-15-320">
            <num>40.15.320</num>
            <heading>Monuments.</heading>
            <subsection eId="40-15-320__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In a subdivision with five or fewer lots, the existence of at least a 5/8 inch by 24 inch rebar and cap monument at controlling exterior corners of the subdivision shall be established by the surveyor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="40-15-320__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In a subdivision of more than five lots, each interior corner shall be monumented with at least a 5/8 inch by 24 inch rebar and cap.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="40-15-320__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a monument of record does not lie on the parcel or tract boundary, the plat shall reflect a boundary survey and tie to a monument of record.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_40-15-330">
            <num>40.15.330</num>
            <heading>Plat standards.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 40.15.330.   Plat standards.
The commissioner shall establish plat standards by regulation.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_40-15-340">
            <num>40.15.340</num>
            <heading>Engineering standards.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 40.15.340.   Engineering standards.
Except for subdivisions of state land, the commissioner may not establish engineering standards for subdivisions.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_40-15-350">
            <num>40.15.350</num>
            <heading>Certified copy of plat as evidence.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 40.15.350.   Certified copy of plat as evidence.
A copy of a plat certified by the recorder of the recording district in which it is filed or recorded as a true and complete copy of the original filed or recorded in the recording office for the district is admissible in evidence in all courts in the state with the same effect as the original.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_40-15-360">
            <num>40.15.360</num>
            <heading>Applicability.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 40.15.360.   Applicability.
The provisions of
AS 40.15.300
 40.15.380 do not apply to maps, site plans, or other graphic representations prepared for
(1) the purpose of transferring a leasehold interest; the extraction of natural resources; or solely for the issuance of licenses or permits; or
(2) disposing of land by aliquot part descriptions of 40 acres or more within surveyed sections provided that the least aliquot part unit shall be not less than a 1/4 1/4 section.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_40-15-370">
            <num>40.15.370</num>
            <heading>Regulations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 40.15.370.   Regulations.
The commissioner may adopt regulations to implement the provisions of
AS 40.15.300
 40.15.380, but only those that are necessary and that are in accordance with the purposes stated in
AS 40.15.300
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_40-15-380">
            <num>40.15.380</num>
            <heading>Applicability to governmental bodies; right-of-way acquisition plats.</heading>
            <subsection eId="40-15-380__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in this section and
AS 40.15.305
(g),
AS 40.15.300
 40.15.380 apply to the state, its agencies, instrumentalities, and political subdivisions in the same manner and to the same extent that they apply to other landowners.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="40-15-380__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A plat for a subdivision created by the acquisition by the state, its agencies, instrumentalities, or political subdivisions, of a right-of-way, airport parcel, or land for a similar public purpose in an area outside a municipality that has the power of land use regulation and that is exercising platting authority, is subject only to the approval provisions of this section and any provision of
AS 40.15.300
 40.15.380 not in conflict with this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="40-15-380__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A right-of-way acquisition plat must contain the</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="40-15-380__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>location and name of the acquisition project;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="40-15-380__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>approximate timetable for the acquisition and construction;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="40-15-380__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>dimensions and area of the proposed tract, parcel, or parcels to be acquired and the remainder of the parcel or parcels;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="40-15-380__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>name of the record owner or owners of the subject parcels;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="40-15-380__subsec_c__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>signature and seal of the surveyor preparing the plat.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="40-15-380__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall review each right-of-way acquisition plat for compliance with this section. If the plat does not meet the requirements of this section, it shall be returned to the submitting agency with an explanation of the deficiencies. A plat for which the commissioner's approval is required under
AS 40.15.305
may not be recorded under
AS 40.17
without the commissioner's approval endorsed on the plat.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="40-15-380__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After approval by the commissioner, the original plat shall be filed with the appropriate district recorder within 30 days by the submitting agency.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="40-15-380__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The minimum monumentation requirements for</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="40-15-380__subsec_f__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>right-of-way acquisition subdivisions are a 5/8 inch by 24 inch reinforcement bar with appropriate identification cap set points from which the right-of-way may be defined, not exceeding 1,320 feet or, when line of sight permits, 2,640 feet; all recovered monumented property corners of records, the lines of which are intersected by a right-of-way acquisition, shall be monumented as part of the right-of-way plat, either on the right-of-way line or at the original monument position;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="40-15-380__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an airport parcel and land for a similar public purpose subdivision not defined by centerline shall be as provided in
AS 40.15.320
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="40-15-380__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If construction of improvements is scheduled to follow the right-of-way acquisition, the placement of the centerline monuments may be delayed until the improvements have been completed, in which case a statement designating the schedule for placing the monuments must be included on the plat.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="40-15-380__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The state, its agencies, instrumentalities, or political subdivisions may acquire or obtain conveyances, including dedication of lots or tracts of a right-of-way acquisition plat, before submittal of a right-of-way acquisition plat for approval by the commissioner. A right-of-way acquisition conveyance may be recorded before approval and recording of the right-of-way acquisition plat.
Article 5. General Provisions.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_40-15-900">
            <num>40.15.900</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 40.15.900.   Definitions.
In this chapter,
(1) commissioner means the commissioner of natural resources;
(2) monument means a fixed physical object marking a point on the surface of the earth used to commence or control a survey or to establish a lot corner;
(3) plat means a map or delineated representation of a tract or parcel of land showing the subdivision of land into lots, blocks, streets, or other divisions;
(4) street means an access way in common use including all of the land lying within a dedicated right-of-way as delineated on a plat showing streets, whether improved or unimproved;
(5) subdivision
(A) means the division of a tract or parcel of land into two or more lots by the landowner or by the creation of public access, excluding common carrier and public utility access;
(B) does not include cadastral plats or cadastral control plats created by or on behalf of the United States Department of the Interior, Bureau of Land Management, regardless of whether these plats include easements or other public dedications;
(6) surveyor means an individual licensed to practice land surveying in the state under
AS 08.48
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>