<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-18/chapter-15"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-18/chapter-15"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="18.15"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-18/chapter-15/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-18/chapter-15/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-18/chapter-15/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-18/chapter-15/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_18">
        <num>18</num>
        <heading>Health, Safety, Housing, Human Rights, and Public Defender</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_18__chp_15">
          <num>15</num>
          <heading>Disease Control and Threats to Public Health</heading>
          <section eId="sec_18-15-150">
            <num>18.15.150</num>
            <heading>Taking of blood sample.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.15.150.   Taking of blood sample.
Each licensed physician and in the absence of a licensed physician each licensed graduate nurse who attends a pregnant woman for conditions relating to the pregnancy during the period of gestation or at delivery shall take, or have taken, a sample of the blood of the woman at the time of the woman's first professional visit or within 10 days after the visit, unless the serological test is contrary to the tenets or practice of the religious creed of which the woman is an adherent.  The blood specimen shall be submitted to an approved laboratory or clinic for a standard serological test of syphilis. Any other person permitted by law to attend pregnant women but not permitted by law to take blood samples shall have a sample of blood taken by a licensed physician, or on order of a licensed physician, and shall submit the sample to an approved laboratory or clinic for a standard serological test for syphilis.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-15-160">
            <num>18.15.160</num>
            <heading>Test for syphilis.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.15.160.   Test for syphilis.
For the purposes of
AS 18.15.150
 18.15.180 a standard serological test is a test for syphilis approved by the department and shall be performed in a laboratory or clinic approved by the department.  On request the laboratory test required by
AS 18.15.150
 18.15.180 shall be performed without charge at the laboratories of the department.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-15-170">
            <num>18.15.170</num>
            <heading>Report of birth.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.15.170.   Report of birth.
In reporting a birth and stillbirth, the physician and other person required to make the report shall state on the certificate whether a serological test for syphilis has been made upon a specimen of blood taken from the woman who bore the child and the approximate date when the specimen was taken.  A birth certificate may not state the result of the test.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-15-180">
            <num>18.15.180</num>
            <heading>Penalty.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.15.180.   Penalty.
A licensed physician or licensed nurse attending a pregnant woman during the period of gestation or at delivery, or a representative of a laboratory or clinic who violates
AS 18.15.150
 18.15.180 is guilty of a misdemeanor and, upon conviction, is punishable by a fine of not more than $500. However, a person attending a pregnant woman during the period of gestation or at delivery, who requests the specimen in accordance with
AS 18.15.150
, and whose request is refused, is not guilty of a misdemeanor.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-15-200">
            <num>18.15.200</num>
            <heading>Screening for phenylketonuria.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-15-200__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A physician who attends a newborn child shall cause this child to be tested for phenylketonuria (PKU).  If the mother is delivered in the absence of a physician, the nurse who first visits the child shall cause this test to be performed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-200__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall adopt regulations regarding the method used and the time or times of testing as accepted medical practice indicates.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-200__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The necessary laboratory tests and the test materials, reporting forms, and mailing cartons shall be provided by the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-200__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>All tests considered positive by the screening method shall be reported by the screening laboratory to the physician and to the department.  The department shall provide services for the performance of a quantitative blood phenylalanine test or its equivalent for diagnostic purposes.  A confirmed diagnosis of phenylketonuria shall be reported to the physician and to the department.  The department shall provide services for treatment and clinical follow-up of any diagnosed case.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-200__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When presumptive positive screening tests have been reported to the department, it shall provide, on request, either the true blood phenylalanine test or subsidize the performance of this test at an approved laboratory.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-200__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A licensed physician or licensed nurse attending a newborn or infant who violates this section is guilty of a misdemeanor and, upon conviction, is punishable by a fine of not more than $500. However, a person attending a newborn or infant whose request for appropriate specimens from the newborn or infant is denied by the parent or guardian is not guilty of a misdemeanor.  The fact that a child has not been subjected to the test because a request for appropriate specimens has been denied by the parents or guardian shall be reported to the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-200__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, physician means a doctor of medicine licensed to practice medicine in this state, or an officer in the regular medical service of the armed forces of the United States or the United States Public Health Service assigned to duty in this state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-15-205">
            <num>18.15.205</num>
            <heading>Screening for congenital heart disease.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-15-205__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A provider of birthing services who attends a birth in the state shall ensure that, as close to 24 hours after the birth as feasible, screening for congenital heart defects through pulse oximetry equipment and methods appropriate for use on a newborn is performed on the newborn, unless screening is refused under (d) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-205__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A provider of birthing services who attends a birth in the state shall, as soon as possible after screening conducted under (a) of this section, make a referral for confirmatory testing on a newborn whose pulse oximetry results are abnormal and provide advice to the parent or legal guardian regarding the need for appropriate interventions.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-205__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The provider who performs pulse oximetry screening under (a) of this section shall report to the parents and attending physicians of the newborn and to the department the results of screening.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-205__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before performing screening for congenital heart disease under (a) of this section, a provider of birthing services shall provide to a parent or legal guardian of a newborn information on the screening and the option to refuse the screening.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-205__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall establish procedures for submitting reports of newborn screening results to the department and for summarizing reported data.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-205__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, provider of birthing services means a physician, midwife, nurse, or other qualified professional who attends the delivery of a newborn in the course of the provider's practice.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-15-210">
            <num>18.15.210</num>
            <heading>Testing for certain other heritable diseases.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.15.210.   Testing for certain other heritable diseases.
The department shall administer and provide services for testing for other heritable diseases that lead to intellectual disabilities, developmental disabilities, or both, and physical disabilities as screening programs accepted by current medical practice and as developed.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-15-250">
            <num>18.15.250</num>
            <heading>Hepatitis B testing and vaccination program for volunteer emergency personnel.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-15-250__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall establish a program under which hepatitis B testing and vaccination is reasonably accessible at no charge to all volunteer emergency medical and rescue personnel in the state who provide an emergency medical or rescue service primarily within an unincorporated community or within a municipality that does not provide funding for the service.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-250__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality that has the power to do so shall establish a program under which hepatitis B testing and vaccination is reasonably accessible at no charge to all law enforcement officers and all volunteer or employed emergency medical and rescue personnel who provide service to the public within the municipality. The department shall, upon request, assist a municipality in establishing a program required under this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-250__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Public Safety shall establish a program under which hepatitis B testing and vaccination is reasonably accessible at no charge to all officers of the state troopers. The Department of Health shall, upon request, assist the Department of Public Safety in establishing a program required under this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-250__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-250__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>emergency medical and rescue personnel means a trauma technician, emergency medical technician, rescuer, or mobile intensive care paramedic;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-250__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>employed means that the person is a paid employee of a first responder service, a rescue service, an ambulance service, or a fire department that provides emergency medical or rescue services as part of its duties;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-250__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>law enforcement officer means a member of the police force of a municipality;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-250__subsec_d__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>volunteer means that the person is an active volunteer of a first responder service, a rescue service, an ambulance service, or a fire department that provides emergency medical or rescue services as part of its duties.
Article 4. Chlamydia and Gonorrhea.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-15-270">
            <num>18.15.270</num>
            <heading>Testing procedures.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-15-270__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall make available on a statewide basis the best current testing method available to detect gonorrhea and chlamydia.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-270__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall use the best current testing method available for diagnosis of gonorrhea and chlamydia.
Article 5. Blood Tests of Persons Charged with Sex Offenses.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-15-300">
            <num>18.15.300</num>
            <heading>Order for blood test; disclosure of results.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-15-300__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A defendant charged in a criminal complaint, indictment, presentment, or information filed with a magistrate or court with a violation of
AS 11.41.410
 11.41.450 that includes sexual penetration as an element of the offense, or a minor with respect to whom a petition has been filed in a juvenile court alleging a violation of
AS 11.41.410
 11.41.450 that includes sexual penetration as an element of the offense, may be ordered by a court having jurisdiction of the complaint, indictment, information, presentment, or juvenile petition to submit to testing as provided in
AS 18.15.300
 18.15.320.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-300__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An alleged victim listed in the complaint, indictment, information, presentment, or juvenile petition, the parent or guardian of an alleged victim who is a minor or incompetent, or the prosecuting attorney on the behalf of an alleged victim, may petition the court for an order authorized under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-300__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon receipt of a petition filed under (b) of this section, the court shall determine if (1) probable cause exists to believe that a crime for which a test may be ordered under (a) of this section has been committed, and (2) probable cause exists to believe that sexual penetration took place between the defendant or minor and the alleged victim in an act for which the defendant or minor is charged under (a) of this section. In making the determination, the court may rely exclusively on the evidence presented at a grand jury proceeding or preliminary hearing.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-300__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the court finds probable cause exists to believe that (1) a crime for which a test may be ordered under (a) of this section has been committed, and (2) sexual penetration described in (c)(2) of this section took place, the court shall order that the defendant or minor provide two specimens of blood for testing as provided in
AS 18.15.300
 18.15.320.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-300__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Copies of the blood test results shall be provided to the defendant or minor, each requesting victim, the victim's designee or, if the victim is a minor or incompetent, the victim's parents or legal guardian. If the defendant or minor is being incarcerated or detained at the time of the blood test or thereafter, the blood test results shall be provided to the officer in charge and the chief medical officer of the facility in which the defendant or minor is incarcerated or detained, including an incarceration or detention ordered as a result of conviction or judgment of delinquency or child in need of aid for an act for which the defendant or minor is charged under (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-300__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A court may not order a test under this section</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-300__subsec_f__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>before seven days after the defendant or minor's arrest;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-300__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>after the entry of a disposition favorable to a defendant; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-300__subsec_f__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if the defendant is convicted or adjudicated delinquent or in need of aid, after 90 days after the issuance of the judgment and sentence or of the judgment in a juvenile action.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-300__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-300__subsec_g__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>disposition favorable to the defendant means an adjudication by a court other than a conviction, or if the defendant is a minor not being prosecuted as an adult, that the minor is not adjudicated delinquent or a child in need of aid, for an offense for which a blood test could be ordered under this section;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-300__subsec_g__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>sexual penetration has the meaning given in
AS 11.81.900</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-15-310">
            <num>18.15.310</num>
            <heading>Testing; test results.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-15-310__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The withdrawal of blood for a test under
AS 18.15.300
- 18.15.320 shall be performed in a medically approved manner. Only a physician or physician assistant licensed under
AS 08.64
, registered or advanced practice registered nurse, licensed practical nurse, or certified emergency medical technician may withdraw blood specimens for the purposes of
AS 18.15.300
- 18.15.320.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-310__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The court shall order that the blood specimens withdrawn under
AS 18.15.300
 18.15.320 be transmitted to a licensed medical laboratory and that tests be conducted on them for medically accepted indications of exposure to or infection by the human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) and other sexually transmitted diseases for which medically approved testing is readily and economically available as determined by the court.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-310__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Copies of test results that indicate exposure to or infection by HIV or other sexually transmitted diseases shall also be transmitted to the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-310__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The test results shall be provided to the designated recipients with the following disclaimer:
The tests were conducted in a medically approved manner but tests cannot determine exposure to or infection by HIV or other sexually transmitted diseases with absolute accuracy. Persons receiving this test result should continue to monitor their own health and should consult a physician as appropriate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-310__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The court shall order all persons, other than the test subject, who receive test results under
AS 18.15.300
 18.15.320 to maintain the confidentiality of personal identifying data relating to the test results except for disclosures by the victim, or if the victim is a minor or incompetent by the victim's parents or legal guardian, as</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-310__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is necessary to obtain medical or psychological care or advice or to ensure the health of the victim's spouse, immediate family, persons occupying the same household as the victim, or a person in a dating, courtship, or engagement relationship with the victim;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-310__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is necessary to pursue civil remedies against the test subject; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-310__subsec_e__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>otherwise permitted by the court.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-310__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The specimens and the results of tests ordered under
AS 18.15.300
 18.15.320 are not admissible evidence in a criminal or juvenile proceeding.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-310__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person performing testing, transmitting test results, or disclosing information under
AS 18.15.300
 18.15.320 is immune from civil liability for an act or omission under authority of
AS 18.15.300
 18.15.320. However, this subsection does not preclude liability for a grossly negligent or intentional violation of a provision of
AS 18.15.300
 18.15.320.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-310__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the results of a blood test conducted under
AS 18.15.300
indicate exposure to or infection by HIV or other sexually transmitted diseases for which testing was conducted, the department shall provide (1) free counseling and free testing to a victim for HIV and other sexually transmitted diseases reasonably communicable through the offense; and (2) counseling to the alleged perpetrator or defendant upon request of the alleged perpetrator or defendant. The department shall provide referral to appropriate health care facilities and support services at the request of the victim.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-310__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-310__subsec_i__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>AIDS means acquired immunodeficiency syndrome or HIV symptomatic disease;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-310__subsec_i__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>counseling means providing a person with information and explanations relating to AIDS and HIV that are medically appropriate for that person, including all or part of the following:
(A) accurate information regarding AIDS and HIV;
(B) an explanation of behaviors that reduce the risk of transmitting AIDS and HIV;
(C) an explanation of the confidentiality of information relating to AIDS diagnoses and HIV tests;
(D) an explanation of information regarding both social and medical implications of HIV tests;
(E) disclosure of commonly recognized treatment or treatments of AIDS and HIV;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-310__subsec_i__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>HIV means the human immunodeficiency virus.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-15-320">
            <num>18.15.320</num>
            <heading>Cost of performing test; reimbursement.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-15-320__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The cost of performing a blood test under
AS 18.15.300
shall be paid by the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-320__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a defendant for whom a blood test has been ordered under
AS 18.15.300
is convicted of an offense for which the defendant was charged, and for which a blood test could be ordered under
AS 18.15.300
, the court shall order the defendant to reimburse the department for the cost of the test and may order the Department of Corrections to deduct the amount of the test from any pay the inmate receives under
AS 33.30.201
.
Article 6. Public Health Authority and Powers.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-15-355">
            <num>18.15.355</num>
            <heading>Prevention and control of conditions of public health importance.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-15-355__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may use the powers and provisions set out in
AS 18.15.355
 18.15.395 to prevent, control, or ameliorate conditions of public health importance or accomplish other essential public health services and functions.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-355__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In performing its duties under
AS 18.15.355
 18.15.395, the department may</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-355__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establish standards
(A) for the prevention, control, or amelioration of conditions of public health importance;
(B) to accomplish other essential public health services and functions; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-355__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>adopt regulations to implement and interpret
AS 18.15.355
 18.15.395.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-15-360">
            <num>18.15.360</num>
            <heading>Data collection.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-15-360__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department is authorized to collect, analyze, and maintain databases of information related to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-360__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>risk factors identified for conditions of public health importance;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-360__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>morbidity and mortality rates for conditions of public health importance;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-360__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>community indicators relevant to conditions of public health importance;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-360__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>longitudinal data on traumatic or acquired brain injury from the registry established under
AS 47.80.500</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-360__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>health care services and price information collected under
AS 18.23.400
; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-360__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>any other data needed to accomplish or further the mission or goals of public health or provide essential public health services and functions.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-360__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department is authorized to obtain information from federal, state, and local governmental agencies, Alaska Native organizations, health care providers, pre-hospital emergency medical services, or other private and public organizations operating in the state. The department may also use information available from other governmental and private sources, reports of hospital discharge data, information included in death certificates, other vital statistics, environmental data, and public information. The department may request information from and inspect health care records maintained by health care providers that identify individuals or characteristics of individuals with reportable diseases or other conditions of public health importance.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-360__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may collect information to establish and maintain a comprehensive vaccination registry to aid, coordinate, and promote effective and cost-efficient disease prevention and control efforts in the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-360__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may not acquire identifiable health information under this section without complying with the provisions of
AS 18.15.355
 18.15.395 and regulations adopted under those statutes.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-15-362">
            <num>18.15.362</num>
            <heading>Acquisition and use of identifiable health information; public health purpose.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.15.362.   Acquisition and use of identifiable health information; public health purpose.
The department may acquire and use identifiable health information collected under
AS 18.15.355
 18.15.395 only if the
(1) acquisition and use of the information relates directly to a public health purpose;
(2) acquisition and use of the information is reasonably likely to contribute to the achievement of a public health purpose; and
(3) public health purpose cannot otherwise be achieved at least as well with nonidentifiable health information.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-15-365">
            <num>18.15.365</num>
            <heading>Information security safeguards.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-15-365__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall acquire, use, disclose, and store identifiable health information collected under
AS 18.15.355
 18.15.395 in a confidential manner that safeguards the security of the information, and maintain the information in a physically and technologically secure environment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-365__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall expunge, in a confidential manner, identifiable health information collected under
AS 18.15.355
 18.15.395 when the use of the information by the department no longer furthers the public health purpose for which it is required.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-365__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who knowingly discloses identifiable health information in violation of this section or a regulation adopted under this section is guilty of a class B misdemeanor. In this subsection, knowingly has the meaning given in
AS 11.81.900
(a).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-365__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who intentionally discloses identifiable health information in violation of this section or a regulation adopted under this section is guilty of a class A misdemeanor. In this subsection, intentionally has the meaning given in
AS 11.81.900
(a).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-15-370">
            <num>18.15.370</num>
            <heading>Reportable disease list.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.15.370.   Reportable disease list.
The department shall maintain a list of reportable diseases or other conditions of public health importance that must be reported to the department. The list may include birth defects, cancers, injuries, and diseases or other conditions caused by exposure to microorganisms; pathogens; or environmental, toxic, or other hazardous substances. The department shall regularly maintain and may revise the list. The department may also establish registries for diseases and conditions that must be reported to the department.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-15-375">
            <num>18.15.375</num>
            <heading>Epidemiological investigation.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-15-375__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may investigate conditions of public health importance in the state through methods of epidemiological investigation. The department may also ascertain the existence of cases of illness or other conditions of public health importance, investigate potential sources of exposure or infection and ensure that they are subject to proper control measures, and determine the extent of the disease outbreak, epidemic, risk to health and safety, or disaster.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-375__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Investigations under this section may include identification of individuals who have been or may have been exposed to or affected by a condition of public health importance, interviewing and testing those individuals, examining facilities or materials that may pose a threat to the public health, and interviewing other individuals. In conducting the investigations the department may</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-375__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>identify all individuals thought to have been exposed to any agent that may be a potential cause of the disease outbreak, epidemic, or disaster;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-375__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>interview, test, examine, or screen an individual where needed to assist in the positive identification of those exposed or affected or to develop information relating to the source or spread of the disease or other condition of public health importance; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-375__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>inspect health care records maintained by a health care provider.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-375__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When testing, screening, or examining an individual under this section, the department shall adhere to the following requirements:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-375__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the department may not require the testing, examination, or screening of an individual without the consent of the individual or the individual's legal guardian, except as otherwise provided in this section or other law;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-375__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the department may require testing, examination, or screening of a nonconsenting individual only upon an order of a state medical officer, and only upon a finding that the individual has or may have been exposed to a contagious disease that poses a significant risk to the public health; the order must be personally served on the person to be tested, examined, or screened within a reasonable period of time before the testing, examination, or screening is to take place;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-375__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the department shall obtain an ex parte order in accordance with (d) of this section if the individual to be tested, examined, or screened objects to the state medical officer's order;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-375__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a health care practitioner shall perform an examination under this section; the individual to be examined may, under conditions specified by the state medical officer, choose the health care practitioner who will perform the examination;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-375__subsec_c__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a testing, examination, or screening program shall be conducted for the sole purpose of identifying a condition of public health importance that poses a threat to the public health and may be avoided, cured, alleviated, or made less contagious through safe and effective treatment, modifications in individual behavior, or public health intervention;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-375__subsec_c__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>before testing, examination, or screening, the department shall explain to the individual or individual's legal representative the nature, scope, purposes, benefits, risks, and possible results of the testing, examination, or screening;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-375__subsec_c__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in conjunction with or directly after the dissemination of the results of the testing, examination, or screening, the department shall fully inform the individual or individual's legal representative of the results of the testing, examination, or screening.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-375__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A judicial officer may issue an ex parte order for testing, examination, or screening upon a showing of probable cause, supported by oath or affirmation, that the individual has or may have been exposed to a contagious disease that poses a significant risk to the public health. The court shall specify the duration of the ex parte order for a period not to exceed five days. To conduct the testing, examination, or screening of an individual who is not being detained under an order of isolation or quarantine, the court may order a peace officer to take the individual into protective custody until a hearing is held on the ex parte petition if a hearing is requested.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-375__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The individual subject to the ex parte order must be given, with the petition and order, a form to request a hearing to vacate the ex parte order. If a hearing is requested to vacate the ex parte order, the court shall hold the hearing within three working days after the date the request is filed with the court. The public shall be excluded from a hearing under this subsection unless the individual subject to the ex parte order elects to have the hearing open.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-15-380">
            <num>18.15.380</num>
            <heading>Medical treatment.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-15-380__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A health care practitioner or public health agent who examines or treats an individual who has or may have been exposed to a contagious disease shall instruct the individual about the measures for preventing transmission of the disease and the need for treatment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-380__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may administer medication or other medical treatment, including the use of directly observed therapy where appropriate, to a consenting individual who has or may have been exposed to a contagious disease.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-380__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An individual has the right to refuse treatment and may not be required to submit to involuntary treatment as long as the individual is willing to take steps outlined by the state medical officer to prevent the spread of a communicable disease to others. However, an individual who exercises the right to refuse treatment under this subsection may be responsible for paying all costs incurred by the state in seeking and implementing a quarantine or isolation order made necessary by a refusal of treatment by the individual. The department shall notify an individual who refuses treatment under this subsection that the refusal may result in an indefinite period of quarantine or isolation and that the individual may be responsible for payment of the costs of the quarantine or isolation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-15-385">
            <num>18.15.385</num>
            <heading>Isolation and quarantine.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-15-385__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may isolate or quarantine an individual or group of individuals if isolation or quarantine is the least restrictive alternative necessary to prevent the spread of a contagious or possibly contagious disease to others in accordance with regulations adopted by the department consistent with the provisions of this section and other law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-385__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall adhere to the following conditions and standards when isolating or quarantining an individual or group of individuals:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-385__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>isolation and quarantine shall be by the least restrictive means necessary to prevent the spread of a contagious or possibly contagious disease that poses a significant risk to public health; isolation and quarantine may include confinement to private homes or other private and public premises; absent exceptional circumstances that would jeopardize public health, a person shall be allowed to choose confinement in the person's home;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-385__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>isolated individuals shall be confined separately from quarantined individuals;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-385__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the health status of an isolated or quarantined individual shall be monitored regularly to determine whether the individual continues to require isolation or quarantine;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-385__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if a quarantined individual subsequently becomes infected or is reasonably believed to have become infected with a contagious or possibly contagious disease, the individual shall promptly be removed to isolation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-385__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the department shall immediately terminate an isolation and quarantine order when an individual poses no substantial risk of transmitting a contagious or possibly contagious disease to others.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-385__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may authorize a health care practitioner, public health agent, or another person access to an individual in isolation or quarantine as necessary to meet the needs of the isolated or quarantined individual. An individual who enters isolation or quarantine premises with or without authorization of the department may be isolated or quarantined if needed to protect the public health.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-385__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before quarantining or isolating an individual, the department shall obtain a written order from the superior court authorizing the isolation or quarantine, unless the individual consents to the quarantine or isolation. The department shall file a petition for a written order under this subsection. The petition must</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-385__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>allege
(A) the identity of each individual proposed to be quarantined or isolated;
(B) the premises subject to isolation or quarantine;
(C) the date and time the isolation or quarantine is to begin;
(D) the suspected contagious disease;
(E) that the individual poses a significant risk to public health;
(F) whether testing, screening, examination, treatment, or related procedures are necessary;
(G) that the individual is unable or unwilling to behave so as not to expose other individuals to danger of infection; and
(H) that the department is complying or will comply with (b) of this section; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-385__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>be accompanied by an affidavit signed by a state medical officer attesting to the facts asserted in the petition, including specific facts supporting the allegations required by (1)(D) and (G) of this subsection; the petition shall be personally served according to court rules, along with notice of the time and place of the hearing under (f) of this section.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-385__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (d) of this section, when the department has probable cause to believe that the delay involved in seeking a court order imposing isolation or quarantine would pose a clear and immediate threat to the public health and isolation or quarantine is the least restrictive alternative and is necessary to prevent the spread of a contagious or possibly contagious disease, a state medical officer in the department may issue an emergency administrative order to temporarily isolate or quarantine an individual or group of individuals. An emergency administrative order of temporary quarantine or isolation by a state medical officer is enforceable by any peace officer in the state. Within 24 hours after implementation of the emergency administrative order, the department shall notify the superior court by filing a petition under (d) of this section that also alleges that the emergency action was necessary to prevent or limit the transmission of a contagious or possibly contagious disease to others that would pose an immediate threat to the public health. The petition must be signed by a state medical officer.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-385__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An individual served with a petition under (d) of this section or an emergency administrative order to temporarily isolate or quarantine under (e) of this section has the right to a court hearing. The court shall hold a hearing within 48 hours after a petition is filed. The department may request a continuance of the hearing for up to five days. The court may grant the continuance for good cause shown and in extraordinary circumstances, giving due regard to the rights of the affected individuals, the protection of the public health, the severity of the need for isolation or quarantine, and other evidence. During a continuance, an isolated or quarantined individual shall remain in isolation or quarantine. The court may order the consolidation of individual claims into group claims if the number of individuals affected is so large as to render individual participation impractical, there are questions of law or fact common to the individual claims or rights to be determined, the group claims or rights are typical of the affected individuals' claims or rights, and the entire group can be adequately represented. The public shall be excluded from a hearing under this section unless the individual elects to have the hearing open under (g)(2) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-385__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>During the hearing, the individual has the right to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-385__subsec_g__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>view and copy all petitions and reports in the court file of the individual's case;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-385__subsec_g__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>elect to have the hearing open to the public;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-385__subsec_g__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>have the rules of evidence and civil procedure applied so as to provide for the informal but efficient presentation of evidence;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-385__subsec_g__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>have an interpreter if the individual does not understand English;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-385__subsec_g__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>present evidence on the individual's behalf;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-385__subsec_g__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>cross-examine witnesses who testify against the individual;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-385__subsec_g__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>call experts and other witnesses to testify on the individual's behalf; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-385__subsec_g__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>participate in the hearing; under this paragraph, participation may be by telephone if the individual presents a substantial risk of transmitting a contagious or possibly contagious disease to others.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-385__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>At the conclusion of the hearing, the court may commit the individual to isolation or quarantine for not more than 30 days if the court finds, by clear and convincing evidence, that the isolation or quarantine is necessary to prevent or limit the transmission to others of a disease that poses a significant risk to the public health. The court may issue other orders as necessary. Orders are enforceable by a peace officer of this state. The order must</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-385__subsec_h__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>identify the isolated or quarantined individual or group of individuals by name or shared or similar characteristics or circumstances;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-385__subsec_h__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>specify factual findings warranting isolation or quarantine under this section;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-385__subsec_h__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>include any conditions necessary to ensure that isolation or quarantine is carried out within the stated purposes and restrictions of this section; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-385__subsec_h__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>be served on the affected individual or group of individuals in accordance with existing court rules.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-385__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before the expiration of an order issued under (h) of this section, the court may continue isolation or quarantine for additional periods not to exceed 30 days upon a showing by the department by clear and convincing evidence that the action is necessary to prevent or limit the transmission to others of a disease that poses a significant risk to the public health.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-385__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An isolated or quarantined individual or group of individuals may apply to the court for an order to show cause why isolation or quarantine should not be terminated. The court shall rule on the application to show cause within 48 hours after filing. An isolated or quarantined individual or group of individuals may request a hearing in the court for remedies regarding breaches of the conditions of isolation or quarantine. A request for a hearing may not stay or enjoin an isolation or quarantine order. Where extraordinary circumstances justify the immediate granting of relief, the court shall fix a date for hearing on the alleged matters within 24 hours after receipt of the request. Otherwise, the court shall fix a date for hearing on the alleged matters within five days after receipt of a request.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-385__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The provisions of this section apply to minors. All notices required to be served on an individual shall also be served on the parents or guardians of an individual who is an unemancipated minor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-385__subsec_l">
              <num>(l)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall adopt regulations to protect, as much as possible, the privacy rights of individuals subject to isolation or quarantine under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-385__subsec_m">
              <num>(m)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may quarantine or isolate individuals who have been exposed to hazardous materials that can cause serious illness or injury by transmission of the hazardous material to others. The provisions of this section concerning isolation and quarantine of individuals to prevent the spread of contagious or possibly contagious diseases shall apply to isolation or quarantine of individuals who have been exposed to hazardous materials.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-385__subsec_n">
              <num>(n)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who knowingly violates this section or a regulation adopted under this section is guilty of a class B misdemeanor. In this subsection, knowingly has the meaning given in
AS 11.81.900
(a).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-385__subsec_o">
              <num>(o)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who intentionally violates this section or a regulation adopted under this section is guilty of a class A misdemeanor. In this subsection, intentionally has the meaning given in
AS 11.81.900
(a).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-15-390">
            <num>18.15.390</num>
            <heading>Powers of the department in a public health disaster.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-15-390__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>due to an outbreak of disease or a credible threat of an imminent outbreak of disease, the department, in coordination with the Department of Military and Veterans' Affairs, may</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-390__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>close, direct, and compel the evacuation of, or decontaminate or cause to be decontaminated, any facility if there is reasonable cause to believe that the facility may endanger the public health;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-390__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>decontaminate or cause to be decontaminated or destroy any material if there is reasonable cause to believe that the material may endanger the public health;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-390__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>inspect, control, restrict, and regulate, by rationing and using quotas, prohibitions on shipments, allocation, or other means, the use, sale, dispensing, distribution, or transportation of food, fuel, clothing, medicines, and other commodities, as may be reasonable and necessary to respond to the disaster;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-390__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>adopt and enforce measures to provide for the safe disposal of infectious waste or contaminated material as may be reasonable and necessary to respond to the disaster; these measures may include the collection, storage, handling, destruction, treatment, transportation, or disposal of infectious waste or contaminated material;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-390__subsec_c__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>require all bags, boxes, or other containers of infectious waste or contaminated material to be clearly identified as containing infectious waste or contaminated material and, if known, the type of infectious waste or contaminated material;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-390__subsec_c__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>adopt and enforce measures to provide for the safe disposal of human remains as may be reasonable and necessary to respond to the disaster; these measures may include the embalming, burial, cremation, interment, disinterment, transportation, or disposal of human remains;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-390__subsec_c__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>take possession or control of any human remains, require clear labeling of human remains before disposal with all available information to identify the decedent and the circumstances of death, and require that the human remains of a deceased individual with a contagious disease or transmissible agent have an external, clearly visible tag indicating that the human remains are infected and, if known, the contagious disease or transmissible agent;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-390__subsec_c__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>require persons in charge of disposing of any human remains to maintain and promptly deliver to the department a written or electronic record of each set of human remains, the disposal of the remains, and all available information to identify the decedent, including fingerprints, photographs, dental information, and a deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) specimen of the human remains;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-390__subsec_c__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>order the disposal of the human remains of an individual who has died of a contagious disease or transmissible agent through burial or cremation within 24 hours after death, taking into account the religious, cultural, family, and individual beliefs of the deceased individual and the individual's family;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-390__subsec_c__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>require any business or facility holding a funeral establishment permit issued under
AS 08.42.100
to accept human remains, to provide the use of the business or facility as is reasonable and necessary to respond to the disaster, and, if necessary, to transfer the management and supervision of the business or facility to the state during the course of the disaster;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-390__subsec_c__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>procure, by condemnation or otherwise, a business or facility authorized to embalm, bury, cremate, inter, disinter, transport, and dispose of human remains under the laws of this state as may be reasonable and necessary to respond to the disaster, with the right to take immediate possession of the facilities;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-390__subsec_c__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>appoint and prescribe the duties of emergency assistant medical examiners as may be required for the proper performance of the duties of the office; the appointment of emergency assistant medical examiners may not exceed the termination of the declaration of a state of disaster; the department may terminate an emergency appointment made under this paragraph for any reason.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-15-392">
            <num>18.15.392</num>
            <heading>Representation; guardian ad litem.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-15-392__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or 18.15.385 has the right to be represented by counsel in the proceedings. If the individual cannot afford an attorney, the court shall direct the Public Defender Agency to provide an attorney. The court may, on its own motion or upon request of the individual's attorney or a party, direct the office of public advocacy to provide a guardian ad litem for the individual.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-15-393">
            <num>18.15.393</num>
            <heading>Report to legislature.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.15.393.   Report to legislature.
The department shall annually report to the legislature the activities conducted by the department under
AS 18.15.355
 18.15.395, including information pertaining to the number of individuals quarantined, the purpose for the quarantine, and the length of the quarantine.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-15-395">
            <num>18.15.395</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-15-395__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>etiologic agents and associated biologicals;
(ii) specimen cultures and dishes and devices used to transfer, inoculate, and mix cultures;
(iii) wastes from production of biologicals and serums; and
(iv) discarded, killed, or attenuated vaccines;
(C) except for teeth or formaldehyde or other preservative agents, pathological waste, including</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-395__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>biopsy materials and all human tissues;
(ii) anatomical parts that emanate from surgery, obstetrical procedures, necropsy or autopsy, and laboratory procedures; and
(iii) animal carcasses exposed to pathogens in research and the bedding and other waste from those animals; and
(D) sharps, including needles, intravenous tubing with needles attached, scalpel blades, lancets, breakable glass tubes, and syringes that have been removed from their original sterile containers;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-395__subsec_i__subsec_16">
                <num>(16)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>isolation means the physical separation and confinement of an individual who is, or group of individuals who are, infected or reasonably believed to be infected with a contagious or possibly contagious disease from nonisolated individuals, to prevent or limit the transmission of the disease to nonisolated individuals;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-395__subsec_i__subsec_17">
                <num>(17)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>least restrictive means the policy or practice that least infringes on the rights or interests of others;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-395__subsec_i__subsec_18">
                <num>(18)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>public health agent means an official or employee of the department who is authorized to carry out provisions of
AS 18.15.355
 18.15.395;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-395__subsec_i__subsec_19">
                <num>(19)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>public health purpose means the prevention, control, or amelioration of a condition of public health importance, including an analysis or evaluation of a condition of public health importance and an evaluation of a public health program;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-395__subsec_i__subsec_20">
                <num>(20)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>public information means information that is generally open to inspection or review by the public;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-395__subsec_i__subsec_21">
                <num>(21)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>quarantine means the physical separation and confinement of an individual or group of individuals who are or may have been exposed to a contagious or possibly contagious disease and who do not show signs or symptoms of a contagious disease from nonquarantined individuals to prevent or limit the transmission of the disease to nonquarantined individuals;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-395__subsec_i__subsec_22">
                <num>(22)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>screening means the systematic application of a testing or examination to a defined population;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-395__subsec_i__subsec_23">
                <num>(23)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>specimen means blood; sputum; urine; stool; or other bodily fluids, wastes, tissues, and cultures necessary to perform required tests;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-395__subsec_i__subsec_24">
                <num>(24)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>state medical officer means a physician licensed to practice medicine by this state and employed by the department, with responsibilities for public health matters;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-395__subsec_i__subsec_25">
                <num>(25)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>testing means any diagnostic or investigative analysis or medical procedure that determines the presence or absence of or exposure to a condition of public health importance, or its precursor, in an individual;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-395__subsec_i__subsec_26">
                <num>(26)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>transmissible agent means a biological substance capable of causing disease or infection through individual to individual, animal to individual, or other modes of transmission;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-395__subsec_i__subsec_27">
                <num>(27)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>vaccination means a suspension of attenuated or noninfectious microorganisms or derivative antigens administered to stimulate antibody production or cellular immunity against a pathogen for the purpose of preventing, ameliorating, or treating an infectious disease.
Article 7. Blood Testing of Prisoners and Others for Bloodborne Pathogens.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-15-400">
            <num>18.15.400</num>
            <heading>Bloodborne pathogen testing of prisoners, certain adult or juvenile offenders, and public safety officers; required disclosures and consent.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-15-400__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When requested by a public safety officer who may have received a significant exposure from an adult or juvenile offender or a prisoner, the employing agency shall follow the testing procedures of
AS 18.15.400
 18.15.450 if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-400__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a physician licensed under
AS 08
determines that a significant exposure to the public safety officer has occurred;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-400__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the physician for the public safety officer needs the adult or juvenile offender's or prisoner's bloodborne pathogens test results to begin, continue, modify, or discontinue treatment in accordance with the most current guidelines of the United States Public Health Service, because of possible exposure to a bloodborne pathogen; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-400__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the public safety officer consents to providing a blood sample for testing for a bloodborne pathogen.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-400__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before employing the testing procedures of
AS 18.15.400
 18.15.450 or disclosing any information about the adult or juvenile offender or prisoner or public safety officer, the employing agency shall inform the</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-400__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>adult or juvenile offender or prisoner that
(A) the adult or juvenile offender's or prisoner's bloodborne pathogens test results, without the adult or juvenile offender's or prisoner's name or other uniquely identifying information, shall be reported to the public safety officer if requested and that test results collected are for medical purposes and may not be used as evidence in any criminal proceedings or civil proceedings;
(B) the adult or juvenile offender or prisoner may refuse to provide a blood sample and that the adult or juvenile offender's or prisoner's refusal may result in a request for a court order to require the adult or juvenile offender or prisoner to provide a blood sample; and
(C) the employing agency will advise the public safety officer of the confidentiality requirements and penalties before the officer's health care provider discloses any test results;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-400__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>public safety officer of the confidentiality requirements of
AS 18.15.440
and that the public safety officer may be subject to penalties for unauthorized release of test results about the adult or juvenile offender or prisoner.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-400__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the disclosures have been made, the employing agency shall ask the adult or juvenile offender or prisoner if the adult or juvenile offender or prisoner has ever had a positive test for a bloodborne pathogen. The employing agency shall disclose the adult or juvenile offender's or prisoner's existing bloodborne pathogens test results to the public safety officer without the adult or juvenile offender's or prisoner's name or other uniquely identifying information.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-15-410">
            <num>18.15.410</num>
            <heading>Consent for testing; court order for testing; exception.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-15-410__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When a public safety officer has made a request under
AS 18.15.400
, except as provided in (b) or (c) of this section or in
AS 18.15.420
, before collecting and testing the blood of an adult or juvenile offender or a prisoner, the employing agency shall first obtain the consent of the adult offender or prisoner or the adult or juvenile offender's or prisoner's representative if the adult or juvenile offender or prisoner is unable to provide the consent.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-410__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Consent of an adult or juvenile offender's or a prisoner's representative is not required if the employing agency has made reasonable efforts to locate the adult or juvenile offender's or prisoner's representative and the representative cannot be found within 24 hours after a significant exposure. If testing of available blood occurs without consent because the adult or juvenile offender or prisoner is unconscious or unable to provide consent, and a representative cannot be located, the employing agency shall provide the information required in
AS 18.15.400
to the adult or juvenile offender, prisoner, or representative whenever it is possible to do so.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-410__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If an adult or juvenile offender or a prisoner dies before an opportunity to consent to blood collection or testing, consent is not required, and the adult or juvenile offender's or prisoner's blood may be collected and tested.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-410__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the adult or juvenile offender or prisoner or the adult or juvenile offender's or prisoner's representative, if appropriate, consents and a sample of the adult or juvenile offender's or prisoner's blood</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-410__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is available, the employing agency shall have the blood tested for bloodborne pathogens;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-410__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is not available, the employing agency shall collect a sample and have the blood sample tested for bloodborne pathogens.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-410__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The employing agency may not withhold care or treatment on the requirement that the adult or juvenile offender or prisoner consent to testing for bloodborne pathogens.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-15-420">
            <num>18.15.420</num>
            <heading>Testing without consent.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-15-420__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When a public safety officer has made a request under
AS 18.15.400
, the employing agency shall file a petition in the superior court for a court order requiring the adult or juvenile offender or prisoner to provide a blood sample for testing for bloodborne pathogens. The employing agency shall serve the petition on the adult or juvenile offender or prisoner at least 48 hours before a hearing on the petition. The petition must include the following information supported by affidavit:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-420__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a statement that the employing agency followed the procedures in
AS 18.15.400
 18.15.450 and attempted to obtain bloodborne pathogens test results according to those sections;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-420__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a statement that
(A) the public safety officer and employing agency have documented the officer's exposure to blood or body fluids during performance of the officer's work duties;
(B) the employing agency has asked the adult or juvenile offender or prisoner to consent under
AS 18.15.410
, and the adult or juvenile offender or prisoner does not consent;
(C) the employing agency has provided the public safety officer and the adult or juvenile offender or prisoner with the disclosures required under
AS 18.15.400
; and
(D) the employing agency has informed the public safety officer of the confidentiality requirements of
AS 18.15.440
and the penalties for unauthorized release of adult or juvenile offender or prisoner information;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-420__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a statement that a physician licensed under
AS 08
and knowledgeable about the most current recommendations of the United States Public Health Service has determined that a significant exposure has occurred to the public safety officer; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-420__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a statement that a physician has documented that the public safety officer has provided a blood sample and consented to testing for bloodborne pathogens, and bloodborne pathogens test results are needed for beginning, continuing, modifying, or discontinuing medical treatment for the public safety officer.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-420__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A court shall order an adult or juvenile offender or a prisoner to provide a blood sample for bloodborne pathogen testing if the court finds that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-420__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>there is probable cause to believe that a significant exposure to the public safety officer from the adult or juvenile offender or prisoner has occurred;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-420__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a licensed physician for the public safety officer needs the test results for beginning, continuing, modifying, or discontinuing medical treatment for the public safety officer; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-15-420__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a compelling need for the testing and test results exists; in making this finding, the court shall consider the need for the test against the privacy or other interests of the adult or juvenile offender or prisoner.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-420__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The court may impose appropriate safeguards against unauthorized disclosure by specifically identifying the persons to have access to the test results and the uses of the test results when ordering a test under (b) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-420__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After testing is completed under this section, the employing agency shall inform the adult or juvenile offender or prisoner whose blood was tested of the results. The employing agency shall inform the public safety officer's physician of the adult or juvenile offender's or prisoner's test results without the adult or juvenile offender's or prisoner's name or other uniquely identifying information.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-15-440">
            <num>18.15.440</num>
            <heading>Confidentiality; penalties for unauthorized disclosure; immunity.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-15-440__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Bloodborne pathogens test results of an adult or juvenile offender or a prisoner are confidential and may not be disclosed except as provided in
AS 18.15.400
 18.15.450 and as needed for the treatment or medical care of an adult or juvenile offender or a prisoner specific to a bloodborne pathogen-related illness.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-440__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An adult or juvenile offender or a prisoner may bring a civil action against a person who knowingly, in violation of
AS 18.15.400
 18.15.450, releases the adult or juvenile offender's or prisoner's name or other uniquely identifying information with the test results or otherwise releases the test results.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-15-440__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The employing agency, a physician, and designated health care personnel are immune from liability in any civil, administrative, or criminal action relating to the disclosure of test results of an adult or juvenile offender or a prisoner to a public safety officer and the testing of a blood sample from an adult or juvenile offender or a prisoner for bloodborne pathogens if a good faith effort has been made to comply with
AS 18.15.400
 18.15.450.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-15-445">
            <num>18.15.445</num>
            <heading>Assistance by departments and municipalities.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.15.445.   Assistance by departments and municipalities.
The department, the Department of Public Safety, the Department of Corrections, and each municipality shall assist public safety officers and employing agencies in complying with the requirements of
AS 18.15.400
 18.15.450.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-15-450">
            <num>18.15.450</num>
            <heading>Definitions forAS 18.15.400 18.15.450.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.15.450.   Definitions for
AS 18.15.400
 18.15.450.
In
AS 18.15.400
 18.15.450,
(1) adult or juvenile offender means a person in custody, arrested, or charged under a criminal complaint or a minor being held or subject to a petition under
AS 47.12
;
(2) bloodborne pathogens means pathogenic microorganisms that are present in human blood and can cause disease in humans; these pathogens include hepatitis B virus (HBV), hepatitis C virus (HCV), and human immunodeficiency virus (HIV);
(3) employing agency means the
(A) department that employs a state employee who is, or contracts with another person who is or employs, a public safety officer;
(B) municipality that employs a municipal employee who is, or contracts with another person who is or employs, a public safety officer or that contracts with, sponsors, or accepts the services of a public safety officer who volunteers for a volunteer fire department or emergency medical services agency;
(C) Department of Public Safety for a public safety officer who volunteers for a volunteer fire department or emergency medical services agency that provides services in the unorganized borough outside of a municipality;
(4) prisoner has the meaning given in
AS 33.30.901
;
(5) public safety officer means a state or municipal juvenile or adult correctional, probation, or parole officer, a contractor or employee of a contractor in a correctional facility, a juvenile detention or treatment facility staff member, or a peace officer or firefighter, emergency medical technician, or mobile intensive care paramedic employed by or volunteering for the state or a municipality or volunteer fire department or emergency medical services provider;
(6) significant exposure means contact likely to transmit a bloodborne pathogen, in a manner supported by the most current guidelines and recommendations of the United States Public Health Service at the time an evaluation takes place, that includes
(A) percutaneous injury, contact of mucous membrane or nonintact skin, or prolonged contact of intact skin; and
(B) contact, in a manner that may transmit a bloodborne pathogen, with blood, tissue, or potentially infectious body fluids.
Article 8. General Provisions.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-15-900">
            <num>18.15.900</num>
            <heading>Definition.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.15.900.   Definition.
In this chapter, department means the Department of Health.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>