<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-36/chapter-15"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-36/chapter-15"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="36.15"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-36/chapter-15/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-36/chapter-15/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-36/chapter-15/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-36/chapter-15/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_36">
        <num>36</num>
        <heading>Public Contracts</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_36__chp_15">
          <num>15</num>
          <heading>Alaska Product Preferences</heading>
          <section eId="sec_36-15-010">
            <num>36.15.010</num>
            <heading>Use of local forest products required in projects financed by public money.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 36.15.010.   Use of local forest products required in projects financed by public money.
In a project financed by state money in which the use of timber, lumber, and manufactured lumber products is required, only timber, lumber, and manufactured lumber products originating in this state from local forests shall be used wherever practicable.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_36-15-020">
            <num>36.15.020</num>
            <heading>Insertion of clause in calls for bids and in contracts.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 36.15.020.   Insertion of clause in calls for bids and in contracts.
A clause containing the substance of
AS 36.15.010
shall be inserted in all calls for bids and in all contracts awarded.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_36-15-050">
            <num>36.15.050</num>
            <heading>Use of local agricultural and fisheries products required in purchases with state money.</heading>
            <subsection eId="36-15-050__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When agricultural products are purchased by the state or by a school district that receives state money, a  preference  not less than seven percent  nor more than 15 percent shall be applied to the price of  products harvested in the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="36-15-050__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When fisheries products are purchased by the state or by a school district that receives state money, a  preference  not less than seven percent  nor more than 15 percent shall be applied to the price of  products harvested or processed within the jurisdiction of the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="36-15-050__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A solicitation for the purchase of agricultural or fisheries products  must include written notice of the preferences under (a) and (b) of this section and specify  that  agricultural products harvested in the state  and fisheries products harvested or processed within the jurisdiction of the state will be used where possible. If the state or a school district that receives state money purchases agricultural  products harvested outside the state or fisheries products harvested  or processed outside the  jurisdiction of the state, the officer responsible for the purchase shall certify in writing the reasons that  agricultural products harvested in the state  or fisheries products harvested or processed within the jurisdiction of the state were not purchased.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="36-15-050__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a contractor fails to comply with this section, the purchasing agency shall withhold payment until the contractor complies. If a school district fails to comply with this section, the department responsible for disbursing state money to the school district shall withhold the money until the school district complies.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="36-15-050__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An interested party, as defined in
AS 36.30.699
, may seek administrative or judicial review of the award of a contract in violation of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="36-15-050__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Compliance with this section is not required if an exception to this section is mandated for participation in a federal program.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="36-15-050__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A bidder receiving a preference under this section may not receive a preference under
AS 36.30.322
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="36-15-050__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="36-15-050__subsec_h__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>agricultural products includes dairy products, timber and lumber, and products manufactured in the state from timber and lumber;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="36-15-050__subsec_h__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>school district includes a regional educational attendance area established under
AS 14.08
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="36-15-050__subsec_h__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>state money includes state reimbursement to school districts for school or related construction, foundation funding for education, municipal assistance, community assistance, revenue sharing, and state funds for capital projects.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_36-15-060">
            <num>36.15.060</num>
            <heading>Insertion of clause in calls for bids and in contracts.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 36.15.060.   Insertion of clause in calls for bids and in contracts.
A clause containing the substance of the relevant subsection of
AS 36.15.050
shall be inserted in all calls for bids and in all contracts awarded that involve agricultural or fisheries products.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>