<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-35/chapter-10"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-35/chapter-10"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="35.10"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-35/chapter-10/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-35/chapter-10/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-35/chapter-10/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-35/chapter-10/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_35">
        <num>35</num>
        <heading>Public Buildings, Works, and Improvements</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_35__chp_10">
          <num>10</num>
          <heading>Public Works</heading>
          <section eId="sec_35-10-010">
            <num>35.10.010</num>
            <heading>Standard plans and specifications and limitation on cost.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 35.10.010.   Standard plans and specifications and limitation on cost.
The department shall prepare and adopt plans and specifications and determine standards for the construction of each public work. Each public work shall be limited in cost to the amount of the appropriation made for that purpose. The plans and specifications may be amended from time to time as the department considers advisable. This section does not apply to the construction of school buildings.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-10-015">
            <num>35.10.015</num>
            <heading>Accessibility of public buildings and facilities.</heading>
            <subsection eId="35-10-015__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall prepare, adopt, and enforce regulations governing the construction of public buildings and facilities by or for the state, including the University of Alaska, and its political subdivisions, whether financed in whole or in part by federal funds, to ensure that public buildings and facilities are accessible to and usable by persons with disabilities and by the aged or infirm. The regulations of the department must conform to a standard comparable to applicable provisions of federal law, regulations, and standards.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="35-10-015__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall develop and maintain an inventory of all public buildings and facilities with respect to their compliance with the regulations adopted under (a) of this section. In addition, the department shall develop cost estimates and recommended priorities for the upgrading of public buildings and facilities that do not conform with the regulations adopted under (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="35-10-015__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>All ferries owned or operated by the state shall be equipped with elevators or other passenger lifting equipment, ramps, or other facilities and devices to ensure that these vessels are accessible to and usable by persons with disabilities and by aged or infirm passengers. In this subsection, accessible to and usable by means that a person with a disability or an aged or infirm passenger can board, disembark, and move between decks and about the public areas aboard a state ferry with personal comfort and safety and with safety to other passengers and members of the crew.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="35-10-015__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After June 25, 1976, a ferry may not be constructed, lengthened, completely renovated, or purchased for use or entered into service by the division of marine transportation of the department as a part of the Alaska marine highway system that does not include adequate facilities and devices to ensure that the vessel is accessible to and usable by persons with disabilities and by aged or infirm passengers. Some staterooms and all restrooms, indoor passageways, outdoor weather decks, and other public areas aboard the vessel shall be so designed and constructed as to permit access and use by persons with disabilities and by aged or infirm passengers, including those persons occupying a wheelchair.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="35-10-015__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After June 25, 1976, a public building or facility in the state may not be planned, designed, financed, constructed, opened to public use, or otherwise placed in operation unless it meets the standards established under this section. If the standards for a public building or facility are not provided for in federal statute, regulation, or standards, the department shall determine the extent of, and adopt regulations setting the standards for, access to and use of the public building or facility by persons with disabilities and by the aged or infirm.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="35-10-015__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may establish by regulation and collect reasonable fees for services provided in the course of determining compliance with regulations adopted under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="35-10-015__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, public facilities includes vessels owned by the state and operated by the division of marine transportation of the department as a part of the Alaska marine highway system.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-10-025">
            <num>35.10.025</num>
            <heading>Compliance with local building codes.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 35.10.025.   Compliance with local building codes.
A public building shall be built in accordance with applicable local building codes, including the obtaining of required permits. This section applies to all buildings of the state and corporate authorities of the state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-10-030">
            <num>35.10.030</num>
            <heading>Inspecting and supervising public works construction.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 35.10.030.   Inspecting and supervising public works construction.
The department shall supervise and inspect the construction of public works and shall see that the work performed in constructing, repairing, altering, or improving public works is in accordance with the drawings and specifications for them, that the interests of the state are fully protected, and that no person, firm, or corporation employed on any work performs the work in any other or different manner than is provided by the contract and the plans and specifications.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-10-040">
            <num>35.10.040</num>
            <heading>Failure of contractor to perform work.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 35.10.040.   Failure of contractor to perform work.
If a contractor or person in charge of the construction of a public building in the state fails to perform the work in a good and workmanlike manner and does not perform the work in accordance with the plans and specifications of the contract, the department shall direct what legal action, if any, shall be taken.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-10-050">
            <num>35.10.050</num>
            <heading>Duty of department to examine and report on existing public buildings.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 35.10.050.   Duty of department to examine and report on existing public buildings.
The department shall, from time to time, examine all existing public buildings and report the condition of each and any necessary additional construction that is needed on them.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-10-060">
            <num>35.10.060</num>
            <heading>Inspection and testing of materials.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 35.10.060.   Inspection and testing of materials.
The department may inspect and test materials, supplies, equipment, and machinery used by a contractor constructing or maintaining public works, and may develop methods and procedures for inspection and testing.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-10-070">
            <num>35.10.070</num>
            <heading>Research on public works.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 35.10.070.   Research on public works.
The department may gather, investigate, and compile information concerning the use, construction, and maintenance of public works, the practices and methods of efficient organization, financing and such other information, data and statistics of the state, and the extent of natural resources of building materials in the state.  The department shall disseminate this information, together with recommendations it considers advisable.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-10-080">
            <num>35.10.080</num>
            <heading>Statement of work authorized, completion schedule, and recommendations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 35.10.080.   Statement of work authorized, completion schedule, and recommendations.
Not later than February 1 of each year, the department shall prepare a statement showing the public works authorized within the past six-year period and the completion schedule as of that date, together with recommendations regarding the need for additional public works construction, if any.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-10-090">
            <num>35.10.090</num>
            <heading>Application for federal funds.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 35.10.090.   Application for federal funds.
The department shall apply in the name of the state, as applicant, to the appropriate federal agency for the construction or assistance in the construction of boat harbor, dike, jetty, or breakwater harbor facilities where the facilities are necessary, feasible, and appropriate to the local economy.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-10-100">
            <num>35.10.100</num>
            <heading>Determining need and priority of projects.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 35.10.100.   Determining need and priority of projects.
The department shall prepare the preliminary determination of need for each project of the type described in
AS 35.10.090
and its feasibility and appropriateness through representations and data submitted to it by the residents of each community desiring a project, and from other information available to it.  The department shall approve and make the final determination of those projects, and their order or priority for which application is made.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-10-110">
            <num>35.10.110</num>
            <heading>Contracting with communities for local participation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 35.10.110.   Contracting with communities for local participation.
The department may contract with a community for the participation of the community either in the financing of projects or, instead of local financial participation, to contract with the community for its installing necessary piling, floats, and related equipment and facilities whether at the community's direct expense or through local volunteer labor, after completion of the basic boat harbor, dike, jetty, or breakwater facilities.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-10-120">
            <num>35.10.120</num>
            <heading>Lease or sale of marine or harbor facilities.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 35.10.120.   Lease or sale of marine or harbor facilities.
The department may lease for a period up to 50 years or may sell for a nominal sum to an incorporated city, public utility district, or other incorporated area marine or harbor facilities constructed or rebuilt with territorial funds or state funds or with territorial or state and federal matching funds.  The intent of this section is to allow cities, public utility districts, and other incorporated areas to lease or purchase marine or harbor facilities so that they may enforce municipal ordinances on them and legally assess fees to meet maintenance costs.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-10-130">
            <num>35.10.130</num>
            <heading>Construction within appropriations and limits imposed by the legislature.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 35.10.130.   Construction within appropriations and limits imposed by the legislature.
Each public work shall be constructed in a completed manner within the appropriation and limits imposed by the legislature.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-10-135">
            <num>35.10.135</num>
            <heading>Public facility planning fund.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 35.10.135.   Public facility planning fund.
There is established within the Office of the Governor, office of management and budget a public facility planning fund.  The fund is a capital fund and consists of (1) money appropriated by the legislature, (2) money reimbursed to it from the proceeds of the sales of general obligation bonds and revenue bonds issued for projects and (3) money reimbursed to it from appropriations for any projects for which money from the fund has been spent.  The fund is available for expenditure, on a reimbursable basis, only for the purposes of providing working capital for facility program planning and for facility procurement planning as specified in this chapter.  All expenditures from the fund are subject to an independent audit which shall be made annually and reported to the governor and the legislature.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-10-160">
            <num>35.10.160</num>
            <heading>Findings and purpose.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 35.10.160.   Findings and purpose.
The legislature finds that since the needs of the state for physical facilities of all kinds are diverse, the planning, design, and procurement of public facilities through lease or construction should be executed in accordance with facility procurement policies developed by the department and reviewed annually by the legislature.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-10-170">
            <num>35.10.170</num>
            <heading>Duties of department.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 35.10.170.   Duties of department.
In addition to other duties prescribed by statute, the department shall
(1) develop facility procurement policies for the planning, design, lease, construction, maintenance, and operation of public facilities of the state;
(2) develop and maintain an inventory of physical facilities currently owned or occupied by the state;
(3) make projections of future public facility needs of the state, analyze facilities needed, and establish methodology for program planning and facilities project planning, design, and construction, based upon
(A) a justification of the level of service anticipated by the program agency, utilizing population projections and estimates approved by the governor;
(B) consideration of the geographical area to be served by the facility and relevant data concerning the agency's existing public facilities in that area;
(C) the date by which the services are to be provided;
(D) alternative program methods for providing the services; and
(E) pertinent data requested by the department in accordance with procedures developed under
AS 35.10.180
;
(4) engage in experimental projects as necessary relating to any available or future method of facility procurement, design, lease, or construction and any method of improving existing design, planning, and construction techniques;
(5) develop life cycle costs of public facilities of the state;
(6) develop life cycle costing methodologies for the following special purposes:
(A) budget forecasting to support facility program planning and analysis;
(B) systematic cost estimating to forecast planning, design, leasing, and construction;
(C) budget forecasting to support development of annual maintenance and operating strategies and life cycle cost plans;
(D) alternative methods of space acquisition and space equalization that will maximize the effectiveness of public funds;
(7) apply for and accept, on behalf of the state, grants from the federal government or an agency of it or from another state foundation, corporation, association, or individual for any of the functions or purposes of the department and may expend any of the money received under this section for any of the functions or purposes.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-10-180">
            <num>35.10.180</num>
            <heading>Physical facility procurement and planning policies.</heading>
            <subsection eId="35-10-180__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall develop and keep current by periodic revision physical facility procurement and planning policies for public buildings and other state facilities and shall develop regulations and guidelines for the implementation of these policies.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="35-10-180__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In developing and revising these policies the department shall seek public review and evaluation by any reasonable means and shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="35-10-180__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>consult and cooperate with officials of the federal government, local governments, other political subdivisions of the state, and other interested persons regarding physical facility procurement planning;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="35-10-180__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>request and receive from an agency or other unit of the state government the assistance and data needed to carry out the requirements of this section.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="35-10-180__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall submit copies of proposed policies and plans annually, within 10 days after the legislature convenes, to the legislature.  The legislature may approve, reject, or modify the policies and plans by concurrent resolution. If the legislature fails to act during the legislative session, the policies and plans are approved.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-10-190">
            <num>35.10.190</num>
            <heading>Coordination by department.</heading>
            <subsection eId="35-10-190__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall coordinate the procurement of physical facilities through lease or construction for the state to insure the greatest cost savings of planning, design, and contractual techniques.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="35-10-190__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the state or an agency of the state determines that a public facility is to be constructed or renovated, it shall, unless exempted by regulations of the department, submit to the department an application for a certificate that the proposed facility complies with adopted facility procurement policies. The department may reject the application but if it does so it shall state in writing the reasons for the rejection. If a written statement that the application is rejected does not issue within 30 days after receipt of the application by the department, unless the department and the applicant have agreed upon an extension of time for consideration, the certificate of compliance is not required. Except as provided otherwise by regulation or by this section, a public facility of the state may not be constructed or renovated by the state unless a certificate that the facility complies with adopted facility procurement policies has been issued.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-10-195">
            <num>35.10.195</num>
            <heading>Conformance withAS 36.30.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 35.10.195.   Conformance with
AS 36.30
.
The contractual techniques for the procurement of labor, materials, and contractual services, including facility procurement through lease or construction, under this chapter must conform to the requirements of
AS 36.30
(State Procurement Code).</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-10-200">
            <num>35.10.200</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 35.10.200.   Definitions.
In
AS 35.10.160
 35.10.200,
(1) life cycle costs means analytic techniques that provide data to describe the first cost of procurement of public facilities through lease or construction, and the maintenance cost, operation cost, and occupancy cost of the facilities;
(2) policies includes but is not limited to budget accounting and cost planning techniques, facility design techniques, and contractual techniques for the procurement of labor, materials, and contractual services.
Article 5. Utilities and Encroachments in Public Facilities.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-10-210">
            <num>35.10.210</num>
            <heading>Use of public facilities for utilities.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 35.10.210.   Use of public facilities for utilities.
A utility facility may be constructed, placed, or maintained across, along, over, under, or within a state public facility only in accordance with regulations adopted or procedures prescribed by the department and only if authorized by a written permit issued by the department.  The department may charge a fee for a permit issued under this section.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-10-220">
            <num>35.10.220</num>
            <heading>Relocation of utility facilities incident to public facility projects.</heading>
            <subsection eId="35-10-220__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If, incident to the construction of a public facility project, the department determines and orders that a utility facility located across, along, over, under, or within a state public facility must be changed, relocated, or removed, the utility owning or maintaining the facility shall change, relocate, or remove it in accordance with the order, within a reasonable time set by the department in the order.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="35-10-220__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the utility facility is not changed, relocated, or removed in accordance with the order, a permit authorizing the utility issued by the department under
AS 35.10.210
becomes invalid and the facility will be considered an unauthorized encroachment subject to the provisions of
AS 35.10.270
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="35-10-220__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The cost of change, relocation, or removal, as defined in
AS 35.95.100
, ordered under (a) of this section is to be paid as follows:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="35-10-220__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>by the department as a cost of public facility construction, if the utility facility is installed or authorized after June 11, 1986 under a utility permit or a regulation and is installed in the location specified in the permit;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="35-10-220__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>by the department as a cost of public facility construction, if the facility was installed before June 11, 1986 under a utility permit and is in the location specified in the permit;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="35-10-220__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>by the department as a cost of public facility construction, if the utility facility was installed before the location became a state public facility or before permits were required;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="35-10-220__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>by the department as a cost of public facility construction, if the utility permit that requires the utility to pay the relocation cost was issued more than five years before the contract for the public facility construction project was first advertised;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="35-10-220__subsec_c__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>by the utility in all other cases unless the commissioner finds it is in the public interest for the cost to be paid by the department.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-10-230">
            <num>35.10.230</num>
            <heading>Encroachment permits.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 35.10.230.   Encroachment permits.
An encroachment may be constructed, placed, changed, or maintained across or within a public facility, but only in accordance with regulations or procedures adopted by the department.  An encroachment may not be constructed, placed, maintained, or changed until it is authorized by a written permit issued by the department, unless the department provides otherwise by regulation.  The department may charge a fee for a permit issued under this section.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-10-240">
            <num>35.10.240</num>
            <heading>Relocation or removal of encroachment.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 35.10.240.   Relocation or removal of encroachment.
If, incidental to the construction or maintenance of a state public facility, the department determines and orders that an encroachment previously authorized by written permit must be changed, relocated, or removed, the owner of the encroachment shall change, relocate, or remove it within a reasonable time set by the department in the order.  The cost of the change, relocation, or removal shall be paid as provided in
AS 35.10.220
(c).  If the owner does not change, relocate, or remove an encroachment within the time set by the department, the encroachment is considered an unauthorized encroachment and subject to the provisions of
AS 35.10.270
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-10-250">
            <num>35.10.250</num>
            <heading>Unauthorized encroachments.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 35.10.250.   Unauthorized encroachments.
If an unauthorized encroachment exists in, on, under, or over a state public facility, the department may require the removal of the encroachment, at the expense of the owner, in the manner provided in
AS 35.10.260
 35.10.270.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-10-260">
            <num>35.10.260</num>
            <heading>Notice of removal of unauthorized encroachment.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 35.10.260.   Notice of removal of unauthorized encroachment.
Notice shall be given the owner, occupant, or person in possession of an unauthorized encroachment, or to another person causing or permitting the encroachment to exist, by serving upon any of them a notice demanding the removal of the encroachment within a time limit set by the department.  The notice must describe the encroachment with reasonable certainty as to its character and location. Service of the notice may be made by certified mail.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_35-10-270">
            <num>35.10.270</num>
            <heading>Removal after noncompliance; removal expense.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 35.10.270.   Removal after noncompliance; removal expense.
After a failure of the owner of an unauthorized encroachment to comply with the notice or order of the department under
AS 35.10.220
, 35.10.240, or 35.10.260, the department may remove the encroachment, or cause it to be removed.  The owner of the unauthorized encroachment shall pay to the department
(1) the expense of the removal of the encroachment;
(2) all costs and expenses paid by the state as a result of a claim or claims filed against the state by third parties for damages due to delays because the encroachment was not changed, removed, or relocated according to the order of the department; and
(3) costs and expense of suit.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>