<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-28/chapter-35"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-28/chapter-35"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="28.35"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-28/chapter-35/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-28/chapter-35/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-28/chapter-35/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-28/chapter-35/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_28">
        <num>28</num>
        <heading>Motor Vehicles</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_28__chp_35">
          <num>35</num>
          <heading>Offenses and Accidents</heading>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-028">
            <num>28.35.028</num>
            <heading>Court-ordered treatment.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-35-028__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding another provision of law, with the consent of the state and the defendant, the court may elect to proceed in a criminal case under
AS 04.16.200</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-028__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or (e),
AS 28.35.030
, or 28.35.032, including the case of a defendant charged with violating the terms of probation, under the procedure provided in this section and order the defendant to complete a court-ordered treatment program. The state may not consent to a referral under this subsection unless the state has consulted with the victim and explained the process and consequences of the referral to the victim. A court may not elect to proceed under this section if the defendant has previously participated in a court-ordered treatment program under this section two or more times.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-028__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Once the court elects to proceed under this section, the defendant shall enter a no contest or guilty plea to the offense or shall admit to a probation violation, as appropriate. The state and the defendant may enter into a plea agreement to determine the offense or offenses to which the defendant is required to plead. If the court accepts the agreement, the court shall enforce the terms of the agreement. The court shall enter a judgment of conviction for the offense or offenses for which the defendant has pleaded or an order finding that the defendant has violated probation, as appropriate. A judgment of conviction or an order finding a probation violation must set a schedule for payment of restitution owed by the defendant. In a judgment of conviction and on probation conditions that the court considers appropriate, the court may withhold pronouncement of a period of imprisonment or a fine to provide an incentive for the defendant to complete recommended treatment successfully. Imprisonment or a fine imposed by a court shall comply with
AS 12.55
or any mandatory minimum or other sentencing provision applicable to the offense. However, notwithstanding Rule 35, Alaska Rules of Criminal Procedure, and any other provision of law, the court, at any time after the period when a reduction of sentence is normally available, may consider and reduce the defendant's sentence, including imprisonment, fine, or license revocation, based on the defendant's compliance with the treatment plan; when reducing a sentence, the court (1) may not reduce the sentence below the mandatory minimum sentence for the offense unless the court finds that the defendant has successfully complied with and completed the treatment plan and that the treatment plan approximated the severity of the minimum period of imprisonment, and (2) may consider the defendant's compliance with the treatment plan as a mitigating factor allowing a reduction of a sentence under
AS 12.55.155
(a). A court entering an or</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-028__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the defendant does not successfully complete the treatment plan imposed by the court under this section, the defendant's no contest or guilty plea or admission to a probation violation to the court shall stand, and the sentence previously imposed shall be executed or, if sentence has not yet been imposed, sentence shall be imposed by the court.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-028__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding any other provision of law to the contrary, the judge, the state, the defendant, and the agencies involved in the defendant's treatment plan are entitled to information and reports bearing on the defendant's assessment, treatment, and progress. The victim is entitled to periodic reports on the defendant's progress and participation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-028__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to other conditions authorized under
AS 12.30
or
AS 12.55
, a court may impose the following conditions of bail or probation:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-028__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>require the defendant to submit to electronic monitoring;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-028__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>require the defendant to submit to house arrest.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-028__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A court shall refer a defendant who is ordered to participate in a treatment program under this section to an alcohol safety action program developed and implemented or designated under
AS 47.37.040</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-028__subsec_f__subsec_21">
                <num>(21)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for screening, referral, and monitoring.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-028__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to other conditions authorized under
AS 12.30
, a court may require the defendant to take a drug or combination of drugs intended to prevent substance abuse.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-028__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-028__subsec_h__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>court-ordered treatment program or treatment plan means a treatment program for a person who consumes alcohol or drugs and that
(A) requires participation for at least 18 consecutive months;
(B) includes planning and treatment for alcohol or drug addiction;
(C) includes emphasis on personal responsibility;
(D) provides in-court recognition of progress and sanctions for relapses;
(E) requires payment of restitution to victims and completion of community work service;
(F) includes physician-approved treatment of physical addiction and treatment of the psychological causes of addiction;
(G) includes a monitoring program and physical placement or housing; and
(H) requires adherence to conditions of probation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-028__subsec_h__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>sentence or sentencing includes a suspended imposition of sentence as authorized under
AS 12.55.085
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-029">
            <num>28.35.029</num>
            <heading>Open container.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-35-029__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not drive a motor vehicle on a highway or vehicular way or area, when there is an open bottle, can, or other receptacle containing an alcoholic beverage in the passenger compartment of the vehicle, except as provided in (b) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-029__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in
AS 28.33.130
, a person may transport an open bottle, can, or other receptacle containing an alcoholic beverage</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-029__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in the trunk of a motor vehicle;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-029__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>on a motor driven cycle, or behind the last upright seat in a motor home, station wagon, hatchback, or similar trunkless vehicle, if the open bottle, can, or other receptacle is enclosed within another container;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-029__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>behind a solid partition that separates the vehicle driver from the area normally occupied by passengers; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-029__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if the open bottle, can, or other receptacle is in the possession of a passenger in a motor vehicle for which the owner receives direct monetary compensation and that has a capacity of 12 or more persons.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-029__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-029__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>alcoholic beverage has the meaning given in
AS 04.21.080</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-029__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>[Repealed, § 29 ch 3 SLA 1992.]</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-029__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>motor vehicle means a vehicle for which a driver's license is required;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-029__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>open includes having a broken seal;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-029__subsec_c__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>passenger compartment means the area normally occupied by the driver and passengers and includes a utility or glove compartment accessible to the driver or a passenger while the motor vehicle is being operated.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-029__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who violates (a) of this section is guilty of an infraction.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-030">
            <num>28.35.030</num>
            <heading>Operating a vehicle, aircraft, or watercraft while under the influence of an alcoholic beverage, inhalant, or controlled substance.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-35-030__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person commits the crime of driving while under the influence of an alcoholic beverage, inhalant, or controlled substance if the person operates or drives a motor vehicle or operates an aircraft or a watercraft</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-030__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>while under the influence of an alcoholic beverage, intoxicating liquor, inhalant, or any controlled substance, singly or in combination; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-030__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>and if, as determined by a chemical test taken within four hours after the alleged operating or driving, there is 0.08 percent or more by weight of alcohol in the person's blood or 80 milligrams or more of alcohol per 100 milliliters of blood, or if there is 0.08 grams or more of alcohol per 210 liters of the person's breath.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-030__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided under (n) of this section, driving while under the influence of an alcoholic beverage, inhalant, or controlled substance is a class A misdemeanor. Upon conviction,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-030__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the court shall impose a minimum sentence of imprisonment of
(A) not less than 72 consecutive hours, require the person to use an ignition interlock device after the person regains the privilege, including any limited privilege, to operate a motor vehicle for a minimum of six months, and impose a fine of not less than $1,500 if the person has not been previously convicted;
(B) not less than 20 days, require the person to use an ignition interlock device after the person regains the privilege, including any limited privilege, to operate a motor vehicle for a minimum of 12 months, and impose a fine of not less than $3,000 if the person has been previously convicted once;
(C) not less than 60 days, require the person to use an ignition interlock device after the person regains the privilege, including any limited privilege, to operate a motor vehicle for a minimum of 18 months, and impose a fine of not less than $4,000 if the person has been previously convicted twice and is not subject to punishment under (n) of this section;
(D) not less than 120 days, require the person to use an ignition interlock device after the person regains the privilege, including any limited privilege, to operate a motor vehicle for a minimum of 24 months, and impose a fine of not less than $5,000 if the person has been previously convicted three times and is not subject to punishment under (n) of this section;
(E) not less than 240 days, require the person to use an ignition interlock device after the person regains the privilege, including any limited privilege, to operate a motor vehicle for a minimum of 30 months, and impose a fine of not less than $6,000 if the person has been previously convicted four times and is not subject to punishment under (n) of this section;
(F) not less than 360 days, require the person to use an ignition interlock device after the person regains the privilege, including any limited privilege, to operate a motor vehicle for a minimum of 36 months, and impose a</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-030__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the court may not
(A) suspend execution of sentence or grant probation except on condition that the person</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-030__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>serve the minimum imprisonment under (1) of this subsection;
(ii) pay the minimum fine required under (1) of this subsection;
(B) suspend imposition of sentence; or
(C) suspend the requirement for an ignition interlock device for a violation of (a)(1) of this section involving an alcoholic beverage or intoxicating liquor, singly or in combination, or a violation of (a)(2) of this section;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-030__subsec_i__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the court shall revoke the person's driver's license, privilege to drive, or privilege to obtain a license under
AS 28.15.181
, and may order that the motor vehicle, aircraft, or watercraft that was used in commission of the offense be forfeited under
AS 28.35.036
; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-030__subsec_i__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the court may order that the person, while incarcerated or as a condition of probation or parole, take a drug or combination of drugs intended to prevent the consumption of an alcoholic beverage; a condition of probation or parole imposed under this paragraph is in addition to any other condition authorized under another provision of law.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-030__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 34 ch 119 SLA 1990.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-030__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as prohibited by federal law or regulation, every provider of treatment programs to which persons are ordered under this section shall supply the judge, prosecutor, defendant, and an agency involved in the defendant's treatment with information and reports concerning the defendant's past and present assessment, treatment, and progress. Information compiled under this subsection is confidential and may only be used in connection with court proceedings involving the defendant's treatment, including use by a court in sentencing a person convicted under this section, or by an officer of the court in preparing a presentence report for the use of the court in sentencing a person convicted under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-030__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who is sentenced to imprisonment for 72 consecutive hours upon a first conviction under this section and who is not released from imprisonment after 72 hours may not bring an action against the state or a municipality or its agents, officers, or employees for damages resulting from the additional period of confinement if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-030__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the employee or employees who released the person exercised due care and, in releasing the person, followed the standard release procedures of the prison facility; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-030__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the additional period of confinement did not exceed 12 hours.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-030__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 34 ch 119 SLA 1990.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-030__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (b) of this section, the court may reduce the fine required to be imposed under (b) of this section by the cost of the ignition interlock device.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-030__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The court shall order a person convicted under this section to satisfy the screening, evaluation, referral, and program requirements of an alcohol safety action program if such a program is available in the community where the person resides, or a private or public treatment facility approved by the Department of Health, under
AS 47.37
to make referrals for rehabilitative treatment or to provide rehabilitative treatment. If a person is convicted under (n) of this section, the court shall order the person to be evaluated as required by this subsection before the court imposes sentence for the offense.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-030__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A program of inpatient treatment may be required by the authorized agency under (h) of this section only if authorized in the judgment, and may not exceed the maximum term of inpatient treatment specified in the judgment. A person who has been referred for inpatient treatment under this subsection may make a written request to the sentencing court asking the court to review the referral. The request for review shall be made within seven days of the agency's referral, and shall specifically set out the grounds upon which the request for review is based. The court may order a hearing on the request for review.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-030__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a person fails to satisfy the requirements of an authorized agency under (i) of this section, the court</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-030__subsec_j__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>may impose any portion of a suspended sentence; however, if the person was convicted under (n) of this section, the court shall impose a part or all of the remaining portion of any suspended sentence;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-030__subsec_j__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>may punish the failure as contempt of the authority of the court under
AS 09.50.010
or as a violation of a condition of probation; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-030__subsec_j__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall order the revocation or suspension of the person's driver's license, privilege to drive, and privilege to obtain a driver's license until the requirements are satisfied.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-030__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Imprisonment required under (b)(1)(A) of this section shall be served at a community residential center or by electronic monitoring at a private residence under
AS 33.30.065
. If a community residential center or electronic monitoring at a private residence is not available, imprisonment required under (b)(1)(A) of this section may be served at another appropriate place determined by the commissioner of corrections. Imprisonment required under (b)(1)(B)  (F) of this section may be served at a community residential center or at a private residence if approved by the commissioner of corrections. Imprisonment served at a private residence must include electronic monitoring under
AS 33.30.065
. The cost of imprisonment resulting from the sentence imposed under (b)(1) of this section shall be paid to the state by the person being sentenced. The cost of imprisonment required to be paid under this subsection may not exceed $2,000. Upon the person's conviction, the court shall include the costs of imprisonment as a part of the judgment of conviction. Except for reimbursement from a permanent fund dividend as provided in this subsection, payment of the cost of imprisonment is not required if the court determines the person is indigent. For costs of imprisonment that are not paid by the person as required by this subsection, the state shall seek reimbursement from the person's permanent fund dividend as provided under
AS 43.23.140
. A person sentenced under (b)(1)(B) of this section shall perform at least 160 hours of community service work, as required by the director of the community residential center or other appropriate place, or as required by the commissioner of corrections if the sentence is being served at a private residence. In this subsection, appropriate place means a facility with 24-hour on-site staff supervision that is specifically adapted to provide a residence, and includes a correctional center, residential treatment facility, hospital, halfway house, g</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-030__subsec_l">
              <num>(l)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner of corrections shall determine and prescribe by regulation a uniform average cost of imprisonment for the purpose of determining the cost of imprisonment required to be paid under (k) of this section by a convicted person. The regulations must include the costs associated with electronic monitoring under
AS 33.30.065
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-030__subsec_m">
              <num>(m)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the act for which a person is convicted under this section contributes to a motor vehicle accident, the court shall order the person to pay the reasonable cost of any emergency services that responded to the accident, if the convicted person or the convicted person's insurer has not already paid the cost of the emergency services. If payment is required under this subsection, the payment shall be made directly to the emergency service and shall be equal to the actual cost of responding to the accident or the previous year's annual average cost of responding to a motor vehicle accident, whichever is higher. In this subsection, emergency service includes a peace officer, fire department, ambulance service, emergency medical technician, or emergency trauma technician.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-030__subsec_n">
              <num>(n)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person is guilty of a class C felony if the person is convicted under (a) of this section and either has been previously convicted two or more times since January 1, 1996, and within the 10 years preceding the date of the present offense, or punishment under this subsection or under
AS 28.35.032</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-030__subsec_p">
              <num>(p)</num>
              <content>
                <p>was previously imposed within the last 10 years. For purposes of determining minimum sentences based on previous convictions, the provisions of (w)(4) of this section apply. Upon conviction, the court</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-030__subsec_p__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall impose a fine of not less than $10,000, require the person to use an ignition interlock device after the person regains the privilege to operate a motor vehicle for a minimum of 60 months, and impose a minimum sentence of imprisonment of not less than
(A) 120 days if the person has been previously convicted twice;
(B) 240 days if the person has been previously convicted three times;
(C) 360 days if the person has been previously convicted four or more times;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-030__subsec_p__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>may not
(A) suspend execution of sentence or grant probation except on condition that the person</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-030__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>serve the minimum imprisonment under (1) of this subsection;
(ii) pay the minimum fine required under (1) of this subsection;
(B) suspend imposition of sentence; or
(C) suspend the requirement for an ignition interlock device for a violation of (a)(1) of this section involving an alcoholic beverage or intoxicating liquor, singly or in combination, or a violation of (a)(2) of this section;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-030__subsec_i__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall permanently revoke the person's driver's license, privilege to drive, or privilege to obtain a license subject to restoration of the license under (o) of this section;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-030__subsec_i__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>may order that the person, while incarcerated or as a condition of probation or parole, take a drug or combination of drugs intended to prevent the consumption of an alcoholic beverage; a condition of probation or parole imposed under this paragraph is in addition to any other condition authorized under another provision of law;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-030__subsec_i__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall order forfeiture under
AS 28.35.036
of the vehicle, watercraft, or aircraft used in the commission of the offense, subject to remission under
AS 28.35.037
; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-030__subsec_i__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall order the department to revoke the registration for any vehicle registered by the department in the name of the person convicted under this subsection; if a person convicted under this subsection is a registered co-owner of a vehicle or is registered as a co-owner under a business name, the department shall reissue the vehicle registration and omit the name of the person convicted under this subsection.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-030__subsec_o">
              <num>(o)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon request, the department shall review a driver's license revocation imposed under (n)(3) of this section and, unless the revocation was ordered under (u) or (v) of this section or in a case in which the person was also convicted of a crime under
AS 11.41.100
 11.41.210, 11.41.280, 11.41.282, or a similar law in another jurisdiction,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-030__subsec_o__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>may restore the driver's license if
(A) the license has been revoked for a period of at least 10 years;
(B) the person has not been convicted of a driving-related criminal offense or a felony in the 10 years preceding the request for restoration of the license; and
(C) the person provides proof of financial responsibility;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-030__subsec_o__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall restore the driver's license if
(A) the person has been granted limited license privileges under
AS 28.15.201</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-030__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and has successfully driven under that limited license for three years without having the limited license privileges revoked;
(B) the person has successfully completed a court-ordered treatment program under
AS 28.35.028
or a rehabilitative treatment program under
AS 28.15.201
(h);
(C) the person has not been convicted of a violation of
AS 28.35.030
or 28.35.032 or a similar law or ordinance of this or another jurisdiction since the license was revoked;
(D) the person is otherwise eligible to have the person's driving privileges restored as provided in
AS 28.15.211
; in an application under this subsection, a person whose license was revoked for a violation of
AS 28.35.030</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-030__subsec_n">
              <num>(n)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or 28.35.032(p) is not required to submit compliance as required under
AS 28.35.030</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-030__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or 28.35.032(l); and
(E) the person provides proof of financial responsibility.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-030__subsec_p">
              <num>(p)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 7 ch 56 SLA 2006.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-030__subsec_q">
              <num>(q)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of this section, the director of the division within the department responsible for administration of this section or a person designated by the director may request and receive criminal justice information available under
AS 12.62
. In this subsection, criminal justice information has the meaning given in
AS 12.62.900
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-030__subsec_r">
              <num>(r)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 12 ch 85 SLA 2010.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-030__subsec_s">
              <num>(s)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In a prosecution under (a) of this section, a person may introduce evidence on the amount of alcohol consumed before or after operating or driving the motor vehicle, aircraft, or watercraft to rebut or explain the results of a chemical test, but the consumption of alcohol before operating or driving may not be used as a defense that the chemical test did not measure the blood alcohol at the time of the operating or driving. Consumption of alcohol after operating or driving the motor vehicle, aircraft, or watercraft may be used to raise such a defense.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-030__subsec_t">
              <num>(t)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (b) or (n) of this section, the court shall waive the requirement of the use of an ignition interlock device when a person operates a motor vehicle in a community included on the list published by the department under
AS 28.22.011
(b).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-030__subsec_u">
              <num>(u)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to the penalties imposed under (n) of this section, if a person is convicted under (n) of this section and has been convicted two or more times under (n) of this section or a similar law of another jurisdiction at any time preceding the date of the present offense, upon conviction, the court shall permanently revoke the person's driver's license, privilege to drive, or privilege to obtain a license.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-030__subsec_v">
              <num>(v)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to the penalties imposed under (b) of this section, if a person is convicted under (a) of this section and the person has previously had the person's driver's license restored under (o) of this section or under
AS 28.35.032
(q), upon conviction, the court shall permanently revoke the person's driver's license, privilege to drive, or privilege to obtain a license.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-030__subsec_w">
              <num>(w)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-030__subsec_w__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>inhalant has the meaning given to the phrase hazardous volatile material or substance in
AS 47.37.270
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-030__subsec_w__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>operate an aircraft means to navigate, pilot, or taxi an aircraft in the airspace over this state, or upon the land or water inside this state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-030__subsec_w__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>operate a watercraft means to navigate a vessel used or capable of being used as a means of transportation on water for recreational or commercial purposes on all waters, fresh or salt, inland or coastal, inside the territorial limits or under the jurisdiction of the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-030__subsec_w__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>previously convicted means having been convicted in this or another jurisdiction within the 15 years preceding the date of the present offense of any of the following offenses; however, convictions for any of these offenses, if arising out of a single transaction and a single arrest, are considered one previous conviction:
(A) operating a motor vehicle, aircraft, or watercraft in violation of this section or in violation of another law or ordinance with similar elements, except that the other law or ordinance may provide for a lower level of alcohol in the person's blood or breath than imposed under (a)(2) of this section;
(B) refusal to submit to a chemical test in violation of
AS 28.35.032
or in violation of another law or ordinance with similar elements; or
(C) operating a commercial motor vehicle in violation of
AS 28.33.030
or in violation of another law or ordinance with similar elements, except that the other law or ordinance may provide for a lower level of alcohol in the person's blood or breath than imposed under
AS 28.33.030</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-031">
            <num>28.35.031</num>
            <heading>Implied consent.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-35-031__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who operates or drives a motor vehicle in this state or who operates an aircraft as defined in
AS 28.35.030</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-031__subsec_w">
              <num>(w)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or who operates a watercraft as defined in
AS 28.35.030</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-031__subsec_w">
              <num>(w)</num>
              <content>
                <p>shall be considered to have given consent to a chemical test or tests of the person's breath for the purpose of determining the alcoholic content of the person's blood or breath if lawfully arrested for an offense arising out of acts alleged to have been committed while the person was operating or driving a motor vehicle or operating an aircraft or a watercraft while under the influence of an alcoholic beverage, inhalant, or controlled substance or if lawfully arrested under
AS 28.35.280
for the offense of minor operating a vehicle after consuming alcohol. The test or tests shall be administered at the direction of a law enforcement officer who has probable cause to believe that the person was operating or driving a motor vehicle or operating an aircraft or a watercraft in this state while under the influence of an alcoholic beverage, inhalant, or controlled substance or that the person was a minor operating a vehicle after consuming alcohol.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-031__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who operates or drives a motor vehicle in this state or who operates an aircraft or watercraft shall be considered to have given consent to a preliminary breath test for the purpose of determining the alcoholic content of the person's blood or breath. A law enforcement officer may administer a preliminary breath test at the scene of the incident if the officer has probable cause to believe that a person's ability to operate a motor vehicle, aircraft, or watercraft is impaired by the ingestion of alcoholic beverages and that the person</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-031__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>was operating or driving a motor vehicle, aircraft, or watercraft that is involved in an accident;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-031__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>committed a moving traffic violation or unlawfully operated an aircraft or watercraft; in this paragraph, unlawfully means in violation of any federal, state, or municipal statute, regulation, or ordinance, except for violations that do not provide reason to believe that the operator's ability to operate the aircraft or watercraft was impaired by the ingestion of alcoholic beverages; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-031__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>was operating or driving a motor vehicle in violation of
AS 28.35.029</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-031__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before administering a preliminary breath test under (b) of this section, the officer shall advise the person that refusal may be used against the person in a civil or criminal action arising out of the incident and that refusal is an infraction.  If the person refuses to submit to the test, the test shall not be administered.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-031__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The result of the test under (b) of this section may be used by the law enforcement officer to determine whether the driver or operator should be arrested.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-031__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Refusal to submit to a preliminary breath test at the request of a law enforcement officer is an infraction.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-031__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a driver or operator is arrested, the provisions of (a) of this section apply.  The preliminary breath test authorized in this section is in addition to any tests authorized under (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-031__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who operates or drives a motor vehicle in this state shall be considered to have given consent to a chemical test or tests of the person's breath and blood for the purpose of determining the alcoholic content of the person's breath and blood and shall be considered to have given consent to a chemical test or tests of the person's blood and urine for the purpose of determining the presence of controlled substances in the person's blood and urine if the person is involved in a motor vehicle accident that causes death or serious physical injury to another person. The test or tests may be administered at the direction of a law enforcement officer who has probable cause to believe that the person was operating or driving a motor vehicle in this state that was involved in an accident causing death or serious physical injury to another person.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-031__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing in this section shall be construed to restrict searches or seizures under a warrant issued by a judicial officer, in addition to a test permitted under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-032">
            <num>28.35.032</num>
            <heading>Refusal to submit to chemical test.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-35-032__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a person under arrest for operating a motor vehicle or aircraft while under the influence of an alcoholic beverage, inhalant, or controlled substance refuses the request of a law enforcement officer to submit to a chemical test authorized under
AS 28.33.031
(a)(1) or
AS 28.35.031
(a), or if a person involved in a motor vehicle accident that causes death or serious physical injury to another person refuses the request of a law enforcement officer to submit to a chemical test authorized under
AS 28.33.031
(a)(2) or
AS 28.35.031
(g), after being advised by the officer that the refusal will result in the denial or revocation of the driver's license, privilege to drive, or privilege to obtain a license, that the refusal may be used against the person in a civil or criminal action or proceeding arising out of an act alleged to have been committed by the person while operating a motor vehicle or aircraft while under the influence of an alcoholic beverage, inhalant, or controlled substance, and that the refusal is a crime, a chemical test may not be given, except as provided by
AS 28.35.035
. If a person under arrest for operating a watercraft while under the influence of an alcoholic beverage, inhalant, or controlled substance refuses the request of a law enforcement officer to submit to a chemical test authorized under
AS 28.35.031
(a), after being advised by the officer that the refusal may be used against the person in a civil or criminal action or proceeding arising out of an act alleged to have been committed by the person while operating a watercraft while under the influence of an alcoholic beverage, inhalant, or controlled substance, and that the refusal is a crime, a chemical test may not be given, except as provided by
AS 28.35.035
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-032__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 25 ch 77 SLA 1983.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-032__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 25 ch 77 SLA 1983.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-032__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 25 ch 77 SLA 1983.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-032__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The refusal of a person to submit to a chemical test authorized under
AS 28.33.031</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-032__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or
AS 28.35.031</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-032__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or (g) is admissible evidence in a civil or criminal action or proceeding arising out of an act alleged to have been committed by the person while operating or driving a motor vehicle or operating an aircraft or watercraft while under the influence of an alcoholic beverage, inhalant, or controlled substance.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-032__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided under (p) of this section, refusal to submit to a chemical test authorized by
AS 28.33.031</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-032__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or
AS 28.35.031</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-032__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or (g) is a class A misdemeanor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-032__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon conviction under this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-032__subsec_g__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the court shall impose a minimum sentence of imprisonment of
(A) not less than 72 consecutive hours, require the person to use an ignition interlock device after the person regains the privilege to operate a motor vehicle for a minimum of six months, and impose a fine of not less than $1,500 if the person has not been previously convicted;
(B) not less than 20 days, require the person to use an ignition interlock device after the person regains the privilege to operate a motor vehicle for a minimum of 12 months, and impose a fine of not less than $3,000 if the person has been previously convicted once;
(C) not less than 60 days, require the person to use an ignition interlock device after the person regains the privilege to operate a motor vehicle for a minimum of 18 months, and impose a fine of not less than $4,000 if the person has been previously convicted twice and is not subject to punishment under (p) of this section;
(D) not less than 120 days, require the person to use an ignition interlock device after the person regains the privilege to operate a motor vehicle for a minimum of 24 months, and impose a fine of not less than $5,000 if the person has been previously convicted three times and is not subject to punishment under (p) of this section;
(E) not less than 240 days, require the person to use an ignition interlock device after the person regains the privilege to operate a motor vehicle for a minimum of 30 months, and impose a fine of not less than $6,000 if the person has been previously convicted four times and is not subject to punishment under (p) of this section;
(F) not less than 360 days, require the person to use an ignition interlock device after the person regains the privilege to operate a motor vehicle for a minimum of 36 months, and impose a fine of not less than $7,000 if the person has been previously convicted more than four times and is not subject to punishment under (p) of this section;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-032__subsec_g__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the court may not
(A) suspend execution of the sentence required by (1) of this subsection or grant probation, except on condition that the person</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-032__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>serve the minimum imprisonment under (1) of this subsection;
(ii) pay the minimum fine required under (1) of this subsection;
(B) suspend imposition of sentence; or
(C) suspend the requirement for an ignition interlock device;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-032__subsec_i__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the court shall revoke the person's driver's license, privilege to drive, or privilege to obtain a license under
AS 28.15.181
, and may order that the motor vehicle, aircraft, or watercraft that was used in commission of the offense be forfeited under
AS 28.35.036
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-032__subsec_i__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the court may order that the person, while incarcerated or as a condition of probation or parole, take a drug or combination of drugs intended to prevent the consumption of an alcoholic beverage; a condition of probation or parole imposed under this paragraph is in addition to any other condition authorized under another provision of law; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-032__subsec_i__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the sentence imposed by the court under this subsection shall run consecutively with any other sentence of imprisonment imposed on the person.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-032__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as prohibited by federal law or regulation, every provider of treatment programs to which persons are ordered under this section shall supply the judge, prosecutor, defendant, and an agency involved in the defendant's treatment with information and reports concerning the defendant's past and present assessment, treatment, and progress. Information compiled under this subsection is confidential and may only be used in connection with court proceedings involving the defendant's treatment, including use by a court in sentencing a person convicted under this section, or by an officer of the court in preparing a pre-sentence report for the use of the court in sentencing a person convicted under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-032__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who is sentenced to imprisonment for 72 consecutive hours under (g) of this section and who is not released from imprisonment after 72 hours may not bring an action against the state or a municipality or its agents, officers, or employees for damages resulting from the additional period of confinement if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-032__subsec_i__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the employee or employees who released the person exercised due care and, in releasing the person, followed the standard release procedures of the prison facility; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-032__subsec_i__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the additional period of confinement did not exceed 12 hours.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-032__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of this section, convictions under
AS 28.33.030
or
AS 28.35.030
and for refusal to submit to a chemical test under this section, if arising out of a single transaction and a single arrest, are considered one previous conviction.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-032__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (g) of this section, the court may reduce the fine required to be imposed under (g) of this section by the cost of the ignition interlock device.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-032__subsec_l">
              <num>(l)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The court shall order a person convicted under this section to satisfy the screening, evaluation, referral, and program requirements of an alcohol safety action program if such a program is available in the community where the person resides, or a private or public treatment facility approved by the Department of Health under
AS 47.37
to make referrals for rehabilitative treatment or to provide rehabilitative treatment. If a person is convicted under (p) of this section, the court shall order the person to be evaluated as required by this subsection before the court imposes sentence for the offense.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-032__subsec_m">
              <num>(m)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A program of inpatient treatment may be required by the authorized agency under (l) of this section only if authorized in the judgment, and may not exceed the maximum term of inpatient treatment specified in the judgment. A person who has been referred for inpatient treatment under this subsection may make a written request to the sentencing court asking the court to review the referral. The request for review shall be made within seven days of the agency's referral, and shall specifically set out the grounds upon which the request for review is based. The court may order a hearing on the request for review.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-032__subsec_n">
              <num>(n)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a person fails to satisfy the requirements of an authorized agency under (m) of this section, the court</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-032__subsec_n__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>may impose any portion of a suspended sentence; however, if the person was convicted under (p) of this section, the court shall impose a part or all of the remaining portion of any suspended sentence;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-032__subsec_n__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>may punish the failure as contempt of the authority of the court under
AS 09.50.010
or as a violation of a condition of probation; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-032__subsec_n__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall order the revocation or suspension of the person's driver's license, privilege to drive, and privilege to obtain a driver's license until the requirements are satisfied.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-032__subsec_o">
              <num>(o)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Imprisonment required under (g)(1)(A) of this section shall be served at a community residential center or by electronic monitoring at a private residence under
AS 33.30.065
. If a community residential center or electronic monitoring at a private residence is not available, imprisonment required under (g)(1)(A) of this section may be served at another appropriate place determined by the commissioner of corrections. Imprisonment required under (g)(1)(B)  (F) of this section may be served at a community residential center or at a private residence if approved by the commissioner of corrections. Imprisonment served at a private residence must include electronic monitoring under
AS 33.30.065
. The cost of imprisonment resulting from the sentence imposed under (g)(1) of this section shall be paid to the state by the person being sentenced. The cost of imprisonment required to be paid under this subsection may not exceed $2,000. Upon the person's conviction, the court shall include the costs of imprisonment as a part of the judgment of conviction. Except for reimbursement from a permanent fund dividend as provided in this subsection, payment of the cost of imprisonment is not required if the court determines the person is indigent. For costs of imprisonment that are not paid by the person as required by this subsection, the state shall seek reimbursement from the person's permanent fund dividend as provided under
AS 43.23.140
. A person sentenced under (g)(1)(B) of this section shall perform at least 160 hours of community service work, as required by the director of the community residential center or other appropriate place, or as required by the commissioner of corrections if the sentence is being served at a private residence. In this subsection, appropriate place means a facility with 24-hour on-site staff supervision that is specifically adapted to provide a residence, and includes a correctional center, residential treatment facility, hospital, halfway house, g</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-032__subsec_p">
              <num>(p)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person is guilty of a class C felony if the person is convicted under this section and either has been previously convicted two or more times since January 1, 1996, and within the 10 years preceding the date of the present offense, or punishment under this subsection or under
AS 28.35.030</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-032__subsec_n">
              <num>(n)</num>
              <content>
                <p>was previously imposed within the last 10 years. For purposes of determining minimum sentences based on previous convictions, the provisions of
AS 28.35.030
(w)(4) apply. Upon conviction,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-032__subsec_n__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the court shall impose a fine of not less than $10,000, require the person to use an ignition interlock device after the person regains the privilege to operate a motor vehicle for a minimum of 60 months, and impose a minimum sentence of imprisonment of not less than
(A) 120 days if the person has been previously convicted twice;
(B) 240 days if the person has been previously convicted three times;
(C) 360 days if the person has been previously convicted four or more times;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-032__subsec_n__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the court may not
(A) suspend execution of the sentence required by (1) of this subsection or grant probation, except on condition that the person</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-032__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>serve the minimum imprisonment under (1) of this subsection;
(ii) pay the minimum fine required under (1) of this subsection;
(B) suspend imposition of sentence; or
(C) suspend the requirements for an ignition interlock device;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-032__subsec_i__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the court shall permanently revoke the person's driver's license, privilege to drive, or privilege to obtain a license subject to restoration under (q) of this section;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-032__subsec_i__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the court may order that the person, while incarcerated or as a condition of probation or parole, take a drug, or combination of drugs intended to prevent consumption of an alcoholic beverage; a condition of probation or parole imposed under this paragraph is in addition to any other condition authorized under another provision of law;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-032__subsec_i__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the sentence imposed by the court under this subsection shall run consecutively with any other sentence of imprisonment imposed on the person;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-032__subsec_i__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the court shall order forfeiture under
AS 28.35.036
, of the motor vehicle, aircraft, or watercraft used in the commission of the offense, subject to remission under
AS 28.35.037
; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-032__subsec_i__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the court shall order the department to revoke the registration for any vehicle registered by the department in the name of the person convicted under this subsection; if a person convicted under this subsection is a registered co-owner of a vehicle, the department shall reissue the vehicle registration and omit the name of the person convicted under this subsection.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-032__subsec_q">
              <num>(q)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon request, the department shall review a driver's license revocation imposed under (p)(3) of this section and, unless the revocation was ordered in a case in which the person was also convicted of a crime under
AS 11.41.100
 11.41.210, 11.41.280, 11.41.282, or a similar law in another jurisdiction or the revocation was ordered under
AS 28.35.030</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-032__subsec_u">
              <num>(u)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or (v), may restore the driver's license if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-032__subsec_u__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the license has been revoked for a period of at least 10 years;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-032__subsec_u__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the person has not been convicted of a driving-related criminal offense or a felony in the 10 years preceding the request for restoration of the license; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-032__subsec_u__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the person provides proof of financial responsibility.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-032__subsec_r">
              <num>(r)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 7 ch 56 SLA 2006.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-032__subsec_s">
              <num>(s)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of this section, the director of the division within the department responsible for administration of this section or a person designated by the director may request and receive criminal justice information available under
AS 12.62
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-032__subsec_t">
              <num>(t)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (g) or (p) of this section, the court shall waive the requirement of the use of an ignition interlock device when a person operates a motor vehicle in a community included on the list published by the department under
AS 28.22.011
(b).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-032__subsec_u">
              <num>(u)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-032__subsec_u__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>cost of imprisonment means the cost of imprisonment as determined under
AS 28.35.030</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-032__subsec_u__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>previously convicted has the meaning given in
AS 28.35.030
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-033">
            <num>28.35.033</num>
            <heading>Presumptions and chemical analysis of breath or blood.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-35-033__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon the trial of a civil or criminal action or proceeding arising out of acts alleged to have been committed by a person while operating or driving a motor vehicle or operating an aircraft or a watercraft while under the influence of an alcoholic beverage, inhalant, or controlled substance, the amount of alcohol in the person's blood or breath at the time alleged shall give rise to the following presumptions:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-033__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>If there was 0.04 percent or less by weight of alcohol in the person's blood, or 40 milligrams or less of alcohol per 100 milliliters of the person's blood, or 0.04 grams or less of alcohol per 210 liters of the person's breath, it shall be presumed that the person was not under the influence of an alcoholic beverage.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-033__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>If there was in excess of 0.04 percent but less than 0.08 percent by weight of alcohol in the person's blood, or in excess of 40 but less than 80 milligrams of alcohol per 100 milliliters of the person's blood, or in excess of 0.04 grams but less than 0.08 grams of alcohol per 210 liters of the person's breath, that fact does not give rise to any presumption that the person was or was not under the influence of an alcoholic beverage, but that fact may be considered with other competent evidence in determining whether the person was under the influence of an alcoholic beverage.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-033__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>If there was 0.08 percent or more by weight of alcohol in the person's blood, or 80 milligrams or more of alcohol per 100 milliliters of the person's blood, or 0.08 grams or more of alcohol per 210 liters of the person's breath, it shall be presumed that the person was under the influence of an alcoholic beverage.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-033__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of this chapter, percent by weight of alcohol in the blood shall be based upon milligrams of alcohol per 100 milliliters of blood.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-033__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in
AS 28.35.030
(s), the provisions of (a) of this section may not be construed to limit the introduction of any other competent evidence bearing upon the question of whether the person was or was not under the influence of intoxicating liquor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-033__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To be considered valid under the provisions of this section the chemical analysis of the person's breath or blood shall have been performed according to methods approved by the Department of Public Safety.  The Department of Public Safety is authorized to approve satisfactory techniques, methods, and standards of training necessary to ascertain the qualifications of individuals to conduct the analysis.  If it is established at trial that a chemical analysis of breath or blood was performed according to approved methods by a person trained according to techniques, methods, and standards of training approved by the Department of Public Safety, there is a presumption that the test results are valid and further foundation for introduction of the evidence is unnecessary.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-033__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The person tested may have a physician, or a qualified technician, chemist, registered or advanced practice registered nurse, or other qualified person of the person's own choosing administer a chemical test in addition to the test administered at the direction of a law enforcement officer. The failure or inability to obtain an additional test by a person does not preclude the admission of evidence relating to the test taken at the direction of a law enforcement officer; the fact that the person under arrest sought to obtain such an additional test, and failed or was unable to do so, is likewise admissible in evidence. The person who administers the chemical test shall clearly and expressly inform the person tested of that person's right to an independent test described under this subsection, and, if the person being tested requests an independent test, the department shall make reasonable and good-faith efforts to assist the person being tested in contacting a person qualified to perform an independent chemical test of the person's breath or blood.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-033__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon the request of the person who submits to a chemical test at the request of a law enforcement officer, full information concerning the test, including the results of it, shall be made available to the person or the person's attorney.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-034">
            <num>28.35.034</num>
            <heading>Surrender of license or permit.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.35.034.   Surrender of license or permit.
A person whose license or permit to operate or drive a motor vehicle has been revoked under
AS 28.15.165
or 28.15.181 shall surrender the license or permit to the department on receipt of notice of the revocation.  After the period of revocation has expired, the person may make application for a new license as provided by law.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-035">
            <num>28.35.035</num>
            <heading>Administration of chemical tests without consent.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-35-035__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a person is under arrest for an offense arising out of acts alleged to have been committed while the person was operating a motor vehicle, aircraft, or watercraft while under the influence of an alcoholic beverage, inhalant, or controlled substance, and that arrest results from an accident that causes death or physical injury to another person, a chemical test may be administered without the consent of the person arrested to determine the amount of alcohol in that person's breath or blood or to determine the presence of controlled substances in that person's blood and urine.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-035__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who is unconscious or otherwise in a condition rendering that person incapable of refusal is considered not to have withdrawn the consent provided under
AS 28.33.031</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-035__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or
AS 28.35.031</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-035__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or (g) and a chemical test may be administered to determine the amount of alcohol in that person's breath or blood or to determine the presence of controlled substances in that person's blood and urine. A person who is unconscious or otherwise incapable of refusal need not be placed under arrest before a chemical test may be administered.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-035__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a chemical test is administered to a person under (a) or (b) of this section, that person is not subject to the penalties for refusal to submit to a chemical test provided by
AS 28.35.032
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-036">
            <num>28.35.036</num>
            <heading>Forfeiture of vehicle, aircraft, or watercraft.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-35-036__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After conviction of an offense under
AS 28.15.291
(b),
AS 28.35.030
, or 28.35.032, a motor vehicle, aircraft, or watercraft involved in the commission of the offense is subject to forfeiture as provided under
AS 28.15.291
(b),
AS 28.35.030
, and 28.35.032.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-036__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before forfeiture of a motor vehicle, aircraft, or watercraft, the court shall schedule a hearing on the matter and shall notify the state and the convicted person of the time and place set for the hearing. Except for a motor vehicle, aircraft, or watercraft that is required to be forfeited under
AS 28.35.030
or 28.35.032, the court may order the forfeiture of the motor vehicle if the court, sitting without a jury, determines, by a preponderance of the evidence, that the forfeiture of the motor vehicle, aircraft, or watercraft will serve one or more of the following purposes:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-036__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>deterrence of the convicted person from the commission of future offenses under
AS 28.15.291</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-036__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>protection of the safety and welfare of the public;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-036__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>deterrence of other persons who are potential offenders under
AS 28.15.291</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-036__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>expression of public condemnation of the serious or aggravated nature of the convicted person's conduct.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-036__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon forfeiture of a motor vehicle, aircraft, or watercraft, the court shall require the</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-036__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>surrender of the registration and certificate of title of that motor vehicle; the registration and certificate of title shall be delivered to the department;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-036__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>convicted person to pay all administrative costs incurred by the state in forfeiting the motor vehicle, aircraft, or watercraft, including costs incurred by the department, law enforcement personnel, or the court system.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-036__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If not released under
AS 28.35.037
, a motor vehicle, aircraft, or watercraft forfeited under this section may be disposed of at the discretion of the Department of Public Safety.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-036__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Disposal under this subsection includes</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-036__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>sale, as a unit or in parts, including sale at an auction, and the proceeds deposited into the general fund;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-036__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>transfer to a state or municipal law enforcement agency;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-036__subsec_e__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>being declared surplus and transferred to the Department of Administration;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-036__subsec_e__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>being destroyed; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-036__subsec_e__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>transfer to a charitable organization; in this paragraph, charitable organization means a charity that is exempt from taxation under 26 U.S.C. 501(c)(3) (Internal Revenue Code).</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-037">
            <num>28.35.037</num>
            <heading>Remission of forfeitures.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-35-037__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon receiving notice from the court of the time and place set for a hearing under
AS 28.35.036
, the state shall provide to every person who has an ascertainable ownership or security interest in the motor vehicle, aircraft, or watercraft written notice that includes</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-037__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a description of the motor vehicle, aircraft, or watercraft;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-037__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the time and place of the forfeiture hearing;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-037__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the legal authority under which the motor vehicle, aircraft, or watercraft, may be forfeited;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-037__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>notice of the right to intervene to protect the interest in the motor vehicle, aircraft, or watercraft.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-037__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>At the hearing, a person who claims an ownership or security interest in the motor vehicle, aircraft, or watercraft, must establish by a preponderance of the evidence that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-037__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the petitioner has an interest in the motor vehicle, aircraft, or watercraft, acquired in good faith;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-037__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a person other than the petitioner was convicted of the offense that resulted in the forfeiture; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-037__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>before parting with the motor vehicle, aircraft, or watercraft, the petitioner did not know or have reasonable cause to believe that it would be used in the commission of an offense.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-037__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a person satisfies the requirements of (b) of this section, the court shall order that an amount equal to the value of the petitioner's interest in the motor vehicle, aircraft, or watercraft be paid to the petitioner, or the court shall order that the motor vehicle, aircraft, or watercraft be released to the petitioner together with title to the motor vehicle, aircraft or watercraft.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-037__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Forfeiture of a motor vehicle, aircraft, or watercraft under
AS 28.35.036
is without prejudice to the rights and does not extinguish the claims of a creditor with an interest in the motor vehicle, aircraft, or watercraft.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-039">
            <num>28.35.039</num>
            <heading>Definitions forAS 28.35.029 28.35.039.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.35.039.   Definitions for
AS 28.35.029
 28.35.039.
In
AS 28.35.029
 28.35.039,
(1) alcohol safety action program means a program for alcohol and substance abuse screening, referral, and monitoring developed and implemented or approved by the Department of Health under
AS 47.37
;
(2) controlled substance has the meaning given in
AS 28.33.190
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-050">
            <num>28.35.050</num>
            <heading>Action of operator immediately after accident.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-35-050__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An operator of a vehicle involved in an accident resulting in injury to or death of a person shall immediately stop the vehicle at the scene of the accident or as close to it as possible and return to, and remain at, the scene until the operator has fulfilled the requirements of
AS 28.35.060
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-050__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The operator of a vehicle involved in an accident resulting only in damage to a vehicle driven or attended by a person shall immediately stop the vehicle at the scene of the accident or as close to it as possible and return to, and remain at, the scene of the accident until the operator has fulfilled the requirements of
AS 28.35.060
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-050__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The operator of a vehicle involved in an accident resulting only in damage to a vehicle that is unattended shall immediately stop at the scene of the accident and undertake reasonable means and efforts to locate and notify the operator or owner of the damaged unattended vehicle of the name and address of the operator and owner of the vehicle striking the unattended vehicle.  If the operator or owner of the unattended vehicle cannot be located then the operator shall leave in a conspicuous place in or upon the unattended vehicle, a writing stating the name and address of the operator and of the owner of the vehicle that struck the unattended vehicle and setting forth a statement of the circumstances of the accident.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-060">
            <num>28.35.060</num>
            <heading>Duty of operator to give information and render assistance.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-35-060__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The operator of a vehicle involved in an accident resulting in injury to or death of a person or damage to a vehicle that is driven or attended by a person shall give the operator's name, address, and vehicle license number to the person struck or injured, or the operator or occupant, or the person attending, and the vehicle collided with and shall render to any person injured reasonable assistance, including making of arrangements for attendance upon the person by a physician and transportation, in a manner that will not cause further injury, to a hospital for medical treatment if it is apparent that treatment is desirable.  Under no circumstances is the giving of assistance or other compliance with the provisions of this paragraph evidence of the liability of an operator for the accident.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-060__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (c) of this section, a person who fails to comply with any of the requirements of this section is, upon conviction, punishable by imprisonment for not more than one year, or by a fine of not more than $500, or by both. This provision does not apply to a person incapacitated by the accident to the extent that the person is physically incapable of complying with the requirement.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-060__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who fails to comply with a requirement of this section regarding assisting an injured person is, upon conviction, punishable by imprisonment for not more than 10 years, or by a fine of not more than $10,000, or by both. This provision does not apply to a person incapacitated by the accident to the extent that the person is physically incapable of complying with the requirement.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-070">
            <num>28.35.070</num>
            <heading>Examination or impounding before repair.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.35.070.   Examination or impounding before repair.
A person may not make or have made repairs to damage or injury to a motor vehicle that could have been caused by collision with a person or property without first notifying the Department of Public Safety, chief of police, or in the absence of these, the nearest police officer or other peace officer, who shall immediately examine the vehicle and make a full report subscribed by the person in whose custody the vehicle then is.  A copy of the report shall be mailed or delivered to the Department of Public Safety.  If no official is within 10 miles of the place where the vehicle is brought for repair, then no notice or examination is required.  If there is ground for suspecting that the vehicle was involved in a collision with a person, the vehicle shall be impounded at the expense of the owner, for which the custodian shall have a lien, and shall be accessible only to officers detailed to the investigation of the case until released.  If, however, there is no reason to suspect that the damage to the motor vehicle was caused by collision with a person or property, the repair of the vehicle may be authorized by the officer in charge of the investigation at any time after the expiration of 24 hours thereafter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-080">
            <num>28.35.080</num>
            <heading>Immediate notice of accident.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-35-080__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The driver of a vehicle involved in an accident resulting in bodily injury to or death of a person or total property damage to an apparent extent of $2,000 or more shall immediately by the quickest means of communication give notice of the accident to the local police department if the accident occurs within a municipality, otherwise to the Department of Public Safety.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-080__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The driver of a vehicle involved in an accident resulting in bodily injury to or death of a person or total property damage to an apparent extent of $2,000 or more shall, within 10 days after the accident, forward a written or electronic report of the accident to the Department of Administration and to the local police department if the accident occurs within a municipality. A report is not required under this subsection if the accident is investigated by a peace officer.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-080__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The form of accident report required under (b) of this section can be obtained from the department's Internet website, any local police department, or the Department of Public Safety.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-080__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Administration may require the driver of a vehicle involved in an accident of which a report must be made to file supplemental reports whenever the original report is insufficient in the opinion of that department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-080__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Every law enforcement officer who, in the regular course of duty, investigates a motor vehicle accident for which a report must be made, either at the time of and at the scene of the accident or thereafter by interviewing the participants or witnesses, shall, within 24 hours after completing the investigation, forward an electronic report of the accident to the Department of Administration. However, the law enforcement officer may submit a written report if the law enforcement agency employing the officer has received an exemption from the Department of Public Safety because the law enforcement agency does not have the technological capacity to submit reports of motor vehicle accidents electronically. The commissioner of public safety shall notify the Department of Administration of the exemption and the period for which the exemption was granted under this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-080__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An accident report is not required under this section from a person who is physically incapable of making the report during the period of incapacity.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-080__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Administration shall consider accident reports under this section to satisfy any requirements for reporting of motor vehicle crashes in the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-090">
            <num>28.35.090</num>
            <heading>Rendering of report by others.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-35-090__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Whenever the driver of a vehicle is physically incapable of giving an immediate notice of an accident as required in
AS 28.35.080
and there was another occupant in the vehicle at the time of the accident capable of doing so, the occupant shall make or give the notice not given by the driver.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-090__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Whenever the driver is physically incapable of making a written report of an accident as required in
AS 28.35.080
and the driver is not the owner of the vehicle, then the owner of the vehicle involved in the accident shall within five days after learning of the accident make the report not made by the driver.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-100">
            <num>28.35.100</num>
            <heading>Form of reports.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-35-100__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Public Safety shall prepare and upon request supply to police departments, coroners, local peace officers, garages, and other suitable agencies or individuals, forms for accident reports. The written reports by persons involved in accidents and by investigating officers shall require sufficiently detailed information to disclose the cause of the accident, conditions existing at the time of the accident, and the persons and vehicles involved.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-100__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Every accident report required to be made in writing shall be made on the appropriate form approved by the Department of Public Safety and must contain all of the information required unless not available.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-110">
            <num>28.35.110</num>
            <heading>Penalty for giving false information in report or failing to report.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-35-110__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who gives information in reports as required in
AS 28.35.080
knowing or having reason to believe that the information is false is punishable by a fine of not more than $1,000, or by imprisonment for not more than one year, or by both.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-110__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall suspend the license or permit to drive and the nonresident operating privileges of a person failing to report an accident as provided in
AS 28.35.080
until the report is filed. The department may extend the suspension by not more than 30 days.  A person failing to make a report as required in
AS 28.35.080
is guilty of a misdemeanor and upon conviction is punishable by a fine of not more than $200, or by imprisonment for not more than 90 days, or by both.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-120">
            <num>28.35.120</num>
            <heading>Use of accident reports in evidence.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.35.120.   Use of accident reports in evidence.
A report made in accordance with this chapter may not be used in evidence in a criminal or civil action arising out of the accident that is the subject of the report.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-130">
            <num>28.35.130</num>
            <heading>False report or destruction of evidence involving a vehicle.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.35.130.   False report or destruction of evidence involving a vehicle.
An officer or person who knowingly makes or subscribes a false report concerning an investigation of a vehicle or damage or injury caused by a vehicle, as provided in this chapter, is guilty of unsworn falsification in the second degree. A person who destroys, obliterates, conceals, or removes, or who aids, abets, or assists in the destruction, obliteration, concealment, or removal from a vehicle, of evidence showing or tending to show that the vehicle collided with a person or property, is punishable by a fine of not more than $500, or by imprisonment for not more than six months, or by both.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-135">
            <num>28.35.135</num>
            <heading>Unlawful to knowingly make false statement, application, or certification.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-35-135__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not knowingly make a false affidavit, statement, or representation, or affirm falsely with respect to a matter or fact required to be set out under this title, nor may the person use a name other than the person's true name. A person convicted of violating this section is guilty of unsworn falsification in the second degree and is punishable as prescribed by law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-135__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who has a certification, registration, title, license, or other form issued under this title, or who has applied for a certification, registration, license, or other form, and who changes the person's name or moves from the address shown on the department's records or forms, shall notify the department of the change in name or address within 30 days</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-135__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>on a form or in a format specified by the department; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-135__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in a manner prescribed in regulations adopted by the department.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-140">
            <num>28.35.140</num>
            <heading>Unlawful obstruction or blocking of traffic; duty to yield to following traffic.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-35-140__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not purposely obstruct or block traffic on any roadway by any means.  However, a service vehicle such as a bus, garbage truck, tow truck, or ambulance may make brief stops on a roadway, which stops on the roadway are necessary in the performance of its services.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-140__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person operating a motor vehicle at any time on a two-lane roadway outside of an urban area shall pull the motor vehicle off the roadway at the first opportunity to pull over safely if there are five or more motor vehicles immediately following that motor vehicle. A person operating a motor vehicle who violates this subsection is guilty of an infraction as described in
AS 28.90.010</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-140__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and shall be punished by a fine of at least $100.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-145">
            <num>28.35.145</num>
            <heading>Overtaking and passing school bus.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-35-145__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The driver of a vehicle that approaches from any direction a school bus stopped on a highway or vehicular way or area shall stop not less than 30 feet from the school bus before reaching it when there are in operation on the school bus flashing red lights as required by regulation.  The driver may not proceed until the school bus proceeds and the flashing lights are no longer illuminated.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-145__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When a school bus is stopped on a highway or vehicular way or area, whether or not there are in operation on the school bus flashing red lights as required by regulation, the driver of a vehicle shall yield the right-of-way to a person crossing a highway, vehicular way, or area to embark on or disembark from the school bus, whether or not the person is crossing within a marked crosswalk.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-145__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The driver of a vehicle on a highway with separate roadways is not required to stop when meeting or passing a school bus that is on a different roadway or, if upon a controlled access highway, when a school bus is stopped off the highway in a loading zone that is part of, or adjacent to, the controlled access highway, and pedestrians are not permitted to cross the highway.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-145__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A driver convicted under this section is guilty of a class B misdemeanor and, in addition to other penalties as provided by law, is subject to a mandatory assessment of six demerit points under
AS 28.15.221
 28.15.261.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-145__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A vehicle owner, or in the case of a leased vehicle a lessee, is guilty of an infraction as described in
AS 28.90.010</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-145__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and may be punished by a fine not to exceed $100, if the vehicle owned or leased by the person is operated in violation of this section.  The owner or lessee may not be penalized if the vehicle was stolen, or the driver of the vehicle is convicted under (d) of this section.  This subsection does not apply to a lessor of a vehicle if the lessor keeps a record of the name and address of the lessee.  A violation of this subsection may not result in the loss of a driver's license or privilege to drive and does not constitute grounds for assessment of demerit points under
AS 28.15.221
 28.15.261.  This subsection does not prohibit or limit the prosecution of a vehicle driver for violating (a) or (b) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-155">
            <num>28.35.155</num>
            <heading>Operation of vehicle with certain tires prohibited.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-35-155__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>It is unlawful to operate a motor vehicle with studded tires or tires with chains attached on a paved highway or road from May 1 through September 15, inclusive, north of 60 North Latitude and from April 15 through September 30, inclusive, south of 60 North Latitude, except that at any latitude on a paved portion of the Sterling Highway a person may not operate a motor vehicle with studded tires or tires with chains attached from May 1 through September 15, inclusive. The commissioner of public safety shall by emergency order provide for additional lawful operating periods based on unusual seasonal or weather conditions. An emergency order adopted under this section is not subject to
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act). Upon application, a special individual traction permit may be issued by the Department of Administration allowing the operation of a motor vehicle with studded tires or chains at any time at the discretion of the vehicle owner. The fee for the special individual permit is one-third of the biennial registration fee applicable to that class of vehicle under
AS 28.10.421
. The department may provide an appropriate sticker or other device identifying the vehicle to which the permit applies.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-155__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, studded tire means a tire with metal studs or spikes imbedded in the periphery of the tire surface, and protruding not more than one-fourth inch from the tire surface.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-161">
            <num>28.35.161</num>
            <heading>Use of electronic devices while driving; unlawful installation of television, monitor, or similar device.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-35-161__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person commits the crime of driving while texting, while communicating on a computer, or while a screen device is operating if the person is driving a motor vehicle, and</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-161__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the vehicle has a television, video monitor, portable computer, or any other similar means capable of providing a visual display that is in full view of a driver in a normal driving position while the vehicle is in motion, and the monitor or visual display is operating while the person is driving; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-161__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the person is reading or typing a text message or other nonvoice message or communication on a cellular telephone, personal data assistant, computer, or any other similar means capable of providing a visual display that is in the view of the driver in a normal driving position while the vehicle is in motion and while the person is driving.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-161__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not install or alter equipment described in (a) of this section that allows the images to be viewed by the driver in a normal driving position while the vehicle is in motion.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-161__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subsections (a) and (b) of this section do not apply to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-161__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>portable cellular telephones or personal data assistants being used for voice communication or displaying caller identification information;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-161__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>equipment that is displaying only
(A) audio equipment information, functions, and controls;
(B) vehicle information or controls related to speed, fuel level, battery charge, and other vehicle safety or equipment information;
(C) navigation or global positioning;
(D) maps;
(E) visual information to</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-161__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>enhance or supplement the driver's view forward, behind, or to the sides of the motor vehicle for the purpose of maneuvering the vehicle; or
(ii) allow the driver to monitor vehicle occupants seated behind the driver;
(F) vehicle dispatching and response information for motor vehicles providing emergency road service or roadside assistance;
(G) vehicle dispatching information for passenger transport or freight or package delivery;
(H) information for use in performing highway construction, maintenance, or repair or data acquisition by the Department of Transportation and Public Facilities or a municipality; or
(I) information for use in performing utility construction, maintenance, repair, or data acquisition by a public utility; in this subparagraph, public utility has the meaning given in
AS 42.05.990
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-161__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subsections (a) and (b) of this section do not apply to devices and equipment installed in an emergency vehicle, whether removable or permanently installed, or to the viewing of authorized screen devices by police, fire, or emergency medical service personnel if the user of the equipment or device reasonably believes the information on the device is necessary to respond to a health, safety, or criminal matter. In this subsection, emergency vehicle means a police, fire, or emergency medical service vehicle.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-161__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>It is an affirmative defense to a prosecution under (b) of this section that the equipment installed or altered includes a device that, when the motor vehicle is being driven, disables the equipment for all uses except those described in (c) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-161__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who violates (a) of this section is guilty of</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-161__subsec_f__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a violation and shall be punished as provided in
AS 12.55
, unless any of the circumstances described in (2) - (4) of this subsection apply;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-161__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a class C felony if the person's driving causes physical injury to another person;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-161__subsec_f__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a class B felony if the person's driving causes serious physical injury to another person;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-161__subsec_f__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a class A felony if the person's driving causes the death of another person.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-161__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who violates (b) of this section is guilty of a class A misdemeanor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-175">
            <num>28.35.175</num>
            <heading>Propane gas detector required.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.35.175.   Propane gas detector required.
A person may not sell a recreational motor vehicle manufactured after 1990 or rent a recreational motor vehicle to another if the vehicle is equipped with a propane stove or propane heating device unless the vehicle is also equipped with a propane gas detector.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-180">
            <num>28.35.180</num>
            <heading>Disobedience to signals of officer regulating traffic prohibited.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.35.180.   Disobedience to signals of officer regulating traffic prohibited.
A driver of a vehicle may not refuse to obey a lawful order or direction of a peace officer, firefighter, or authorized flagman regulating and directing traffic.  A peace officer or firefighter regulating or directing traffic shall, upon request of a driver, produce evidence of authorization unless the officer or firefighter is wearing in view the badge or uniform of office.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-182">
            <num>28.35.182</num>
            <heading>Failure to stop at direction of peace officer.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-35-182__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person commits the offense of failure to stop at the direction of a peace officer in the first degree if the person violates (b) of this section, and, during the commission of that offense,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-182__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the person violates
AS 28.35.400
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-182__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the person is committing vehicle theft in the first or second degree; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-182__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>as a result of the person's operation or driving, an accident occurs or a person suffers serious physical injury; in this paragraph, serious physical injury has the meaning given in
AS 11.81.900
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-182__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person commits the offense of failure to stop at the direction of a peace officer in the second degree if the person, while driving or operating a vehicle or motor vehicle or while operating an aircraft or watercraft, knowingly fails to stop as soon as practical and in a reasonably safe manner under the circumstances when requested or signaled to do so by a peace officer.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-182__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In a prosecution under this section, it is an affirmative defense, if the peace officer, when requesting or signaling the defendant to stop,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-182__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>was operating a vehicle, motor vehicle, aircraft, or watercraft, and the vehicle, motor vehicle, aircraft, or watercraft
(A) did not meet lighting and audible signaling requirements of law for law enforcement vehicles; and
(B) was not marked appropriately so that a reasonable person would recognize it as a law enforcement vehicle; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-182__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>was not operating a vehicle, motor vehicle, aircraft, or watercraft, and the peace officer was not wearing the uniform of office or displaying a badge or other symbol of authority so as to be reasonably identifiable as a peace officer.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-182__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-182__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>knowingly has the meaning given in
AS 11.81.900
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-182__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>signal means a hand motion, audible mechanical or electronic noise device, visual light device, or combination of them, used in a manner that a reasonable person would understand to mean that the peace officer intends that the person stop.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-182__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Failure to stop at the direction of a peace officer in the first degree is a class C felony punishable as provided in
AS 12.55
. Failure to stop at the direction of a peace officer in the second degree is a class A misdemeanor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-185">
            <num>28.35.185</num>
            <heading>Overtaking and passing certain stationary vehicles.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-35-185__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The driver of a vehicle that approaches a stationary emergency vehicle, fire vehicle, law enforcement vehicle, tow truck in the act of picking up a vehicle, vehicle in the act of performing maintenance or road service work, or animal control vehicle being used to perform official duties, when the stationary vehicle is displaying flashing emergency lights on a highway or roadway</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-185__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>with two or more lanes traveling in the same direction, unless otherwise directed by law enforcement or emergency personnel, shall
(A) if possible in the existing safety and traffic conditions, vacate the lane closest to the emergency vehicle, fire vehicle, law enforcement vehicle, tow truck in the act of picking up a vehicle, vehicle in the act of performing maintenance or road service work, or animal control vehicle being used to perform official duties; or
(B) if a lane change under (A) of this paragraph would be impossible, prohibited by law, or unsafe, slow to a reasonable and prudent speed considering the traffic, roadway, and weather conditions;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-185__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>with fewer than two lanes traveling in the same direction, unless otherwise directed by law enforcement or emergency personnel, shall slow to a reasonable and prudent speed considering the traffic, roadway, and weather conditions.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-185__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who violates this section is guilty of</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-185__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a class A misdemeanor if personal injury results from the person's failure to vacate the lane or slow as required by this section;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-185__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an infraction, under circumstances other than in (1) of this subsection.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-191">
            <num>28.35.191</num>
            <heading>Failure to use headlights.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-35-191__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person commits the offense of failure to use headlights if the person operates a motor vehicle without the use of motor vehicle headlights</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-191__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>between one half-hour after sunset and one half-hour before sunrise;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-191__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>at any other time when, because of insufficient light or other atmospheric conditions, persons or motor vehicles are not clearly discernible at a distance of 1,000 feet; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-191__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>on a road that is a designated traffic safety corridor under
AS 19.10.075
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-191__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person operating a motor vehicle may not be required to use motor vehicle headlights except as required in (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-191__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Failure to use headlights is an infraction.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-225">
            <num>28.35.225</num>
            <heading>Enforcement.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.35.225.   Enforcement.
All law enforcement officers in this state and employees of the Department of Public Safety designated by that department's commissioner shall enforce this title and regulations adopted under this title. The state troopers shall advise and instruct all other law enforcement officers in the state concerning the requirements of this title and regulations adopted under this title.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-235">
            <num>28.35.235</num>
            <heading>Unauthorized use of parking reserved for persons with disabilities; penalties.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-35-235__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not park a motor vehicle in a parking place reserved for a person with a disability unless</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-235__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the person operating the vehicle has a special permit issued by the department under
AS 28.10.495
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-235__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the person operating the vehicle has parked the vehicle for the purpose of transporting a person who has a special permit issued by the department under
AS 28.10.495
and the person who has the special permit actually exits or enters the vehicle;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-235__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the motor vehicle displays a special license plate issued to a person with a disability under
AS 28.10.181</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-235__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and is operated by or used for the purpose of transporting a person with a disability; or</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-235__subsec_d__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the motor vehicle displays a special license plate or permit issued to persons with disabilities by another state, province, territory, or country and is being operated by or used for the purpose of transporting a person with a disability.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-235__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may enact ordinances necessary to enforce this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-235__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who violates this section is guilty of an infraction. Upon conviction, the court shall impose a fine of not less than $125, or, if the person has been previously convicted under this section, the court shall impose a fine of not less than $250. However, a person who violates this section and who was, at the time of the violation, operating a vehicle displaying a special license plate issued under
AS 28.10.181</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-235__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or a special permit issued under
AS 28.10.495</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-235__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>shall, upon conviction, pay a fine of $250 or, if the person has been previously convicted under this section, pay a fine of $500.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-245">
            <num>28.35.245</num>
            <heading>Motorcycle helmet.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-35-245__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A motorcycle helmet may not be manufactured or sold in the state unless the helmet conforms to standards established by regulation by the commissioner of public safety. The regulations must provide for helmets that allow normal peripheral vision and hearing and minimize neck injuries to the wearer potentially caused by the helmet. The regulations shall be adopted under the provisions of
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-245__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who is 18 years of age or older may not be required to wear a helmet while operating a motorcycle if the person is the holder of a license or endorsement to operate a motorcycle.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-251">
            <num>28.35.251</num>
            <heading>Failure to contain or confine a load.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-35-251__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person commits the crime of failure to contain or confine a load in the first degree if the person, with criminal negligence, violates (c) of this section and, as a result of that violation, causes serious physical injury to another person.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-251__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person commits the crime of failure to contain or confine a load in the second degree if the person, with criminal negligence, violates (c) of this section and damages the property of another person in an amount of $5,000 or more.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-251__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person commits the offense of failure to contain or confine a load in the third degree if the person drives or moves a motor vehicle loaded with any material on a highway unless</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-251__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the load is
(A) contained or confined to prevent the load from</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-251__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>dropping, leaking, or escaping; or
(ii) shifting on or within the vehicle to the extent that the motor vehicle's stability or maneuverability is adversely affected; and
(B) subjected to treatment by methods, approved by the commissioner of public safety by regulation, designed to settle the load or remove loose material before the vehicle is driven or moved on the highway; and</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-251__subsec_i__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>at least six inches of freeboard is maintained around the entire perimeter of a load consisting of sand, gravel, dirt, rock, or similar materials or the load is covered and securely fastened to prevent the cover from becoming loose or detached or from being a hazard to other users of the highway.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-251__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This section does not apply to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-251__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a vehicle that drops, sprinkles, or sprays sand, liquids, or other materials for the purpose of cleaning or maintaining the highway or providing or improving traction;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-251__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a commercial motor vehicle that is subject to the federal motor carrier cargo securement standards implemented through state or federal law;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-251__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the natural accumulation of snow, ice, mud, dirt, or similar materials on a motor vehicle;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-251__subsec_d__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a vehicle that is removing snow or hauling snow after removal; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-251__subsec_d__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>random litter; in this paragraph, litter includes plastic wrappers, empty plastic bags, leaves, paper, or similar soft materials.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-251__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Failure to contain or confine a load in the</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-251__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>first degree is a class A misdemeanor punishable as provided in
AS 12.55
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-251__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>second degree is a class B misdemeanor punishable as provided in
AS 12.55
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-251__subsec_e__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>third degree is an infraction punishable by a fine of not more than
(A) $2,500 if the person has been previously convicted three or more times of a violation of this section;
(B) $1,500 if the person has been previously convicted twice of a violation of this section;
(C) $750 if the person has been previously convicted one time of a violation of this section; or
(D) $300 if the person has not been previously convicted of a violation of this section.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-251__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, criminal negligence has the meaning given in
AS 11.81.900
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-253">
            <num>28.35.253</num>
            <heading>Anti-spray devices required.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-35-253__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not drive a motor vehicle on a highway unless the vehicle is equipped with fenders, mud flaps, or other anti-spray devices adequate to prevent the vehicle from being a hazard to other users of the highway.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-253__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Violation of this section is an infraction.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-255">
            <num>28.35.255</num>
            <heading>Penalty.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.35.255.   Penalty.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-255">
            <num>28.35.255</num>
            <heading>Penalty.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.35.255.   Penalty.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-261">
            <num>28.35.261</num>
            <heading>Operation of low-speed vehicles.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-35-261__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The operator of a low-speed vehicle is subject to all the traffic and other laws applicable to operators of passenger vehicles.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-261__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The operator of a low-speed vehicle may not operate that vehicle on a highway that has a maximum speed limit of more than 35 miles an hour. Notwithstanding this subsection, the operator of a low-speed vehicle may operate that vehicle</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-261__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>on a highway with a maximum speed limit of 45 miles an hour if the highway is
(A) within a municipality that</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-261__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>has a population of less than 35,000;
(ii) is not connected by road to Anchorage or Fairbanks; and
(iii) has passed an ordinance allowing for the operation of low-speed vehicles as provided for in this subparagraph; or
(B) within an area of the unorganized borough, outside of a city, that is not connected by road to Anchorage or Fairbanks;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-261__subsec_i__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>across an intersection with a highway that has a maximum speed limit greater than is permissible for low-speed vehicles under this subsection.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-261__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding
AS 28.01.010
, a municipality may, by ordinance, further restrict the operation of low-speed vehicles within its jurisdiction.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-280">
            <num>28.35.280</num>
            <heading>Minor operating a vehicle after consuming alcohol.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-35-280__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who is at least 14 years of age but not yet 21 years of age commits the offense of minor operating a vehicle after consuming alcohol if the person operates or drives a motor vehicle or operates an aircraft or a watercraft after having consumed any quantity of alcohol. A peace officer who has probable cause to believe that a person has committed the offense of minor operating a vehicle after consuming alcohol may</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-280__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>place the person under arrest;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-280__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>request that the person submit to a chemical test or tests of the person's breath for the purpose of determining the alcoholic content of the person's blood or breath; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-280__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>transport the person to a location at which a chemical or other test authorized under (2) of this subsection may be administered.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-280__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a chemical test under this section reveals any alcohol concentration within the person's blood or breath, the person shall be cited for violating this section and then released unless there is a lawful reason for further detention. A person who is 18 years of age or older shall be released on the person's own recognizance. A person who is under the age of 18 shall be released to a parent, guardian, or legal custodian.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-280__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who is cited for violating this section shall be advised by a peace officer that it is unlawful under
AS 28.35.290
for the person to operate a motor vehicle, aircraft, or watercraft during the 24 hours following the issuance of the citation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-280__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The offense of a minor operating a vehicle after consuming alcohol is an infraction, and, if the minor</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-280__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has not been previously convicted under this section,
AS 28.35.285
, or 28.35.290, upon conviction, the court shall impose a
(A) fine of $500; and
(B) period of community work service of not less than 20 hours nor more than 40 hours; the community work service under this subparagraph must be related to education about or prevention or treatment of misuse of alcohol if opportunities are available for that type of work service in the community; if such opportunities are not available, the court shall make other provisions for the work service;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-280__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has been previously convicted once under this section,
AS 28.35.285
, or 28.35.290, upon conviction, the court shall impose a
(A) fine of $1,000; and
(B) period of community work service of not less than 40 hours nor more than 60 hours; the community work service under this subparagraph must be related to education about or prevention or treatment of misuse of alcohol if opportunities are available for that type of work service in the community; if such opportunities are not available, the court shall make other provisions for the work service;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-280__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has been previously convicted two or more times under this section,
AS 28.35.285
, or 28.35.290, upon conviction, the court shall impose a
(A) fine of $1,500; and
(B) period of community work service of not less than 60 hours nor more than 80 hours; the community work service under this subparagraph must be related to education about or prevention or treatment of misuse of alcohol if opportunities are available for that type of work service in the community; if such opportunities are not available, the court shall make other provisions for the work service.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-280__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-280__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>operate an aircraft has the meaning given in
AS 28.35.030</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-280__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>operate a watercraft has the meaning given in
AS 28.35.030</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-285">
            <num>28.35.285</num>
            <heading>Minor's refusal to submit to chemical test.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-35-285__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a person under arrest for minor operating a vehicle after consuming alcohol refuses the request of a peace officer to submit to a chemical test or tests of the person's breath authorized under
AS 28.35.031</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-285__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and 28.35.280(a), after being advised by the officer that the refusal will result in the denial or revocation of the driver's license, privilege to drive, or privilege to obtain a license, that the refusal may be used against the person in a civil or criminal action or proceeding arising out of an act alleged to have been committed by the person while operating a vehicle after consuming alcohol, and that the refusal is a violation, a chemical test may not be given.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-285__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who is cited for violating this section shall be advised by a peace officer that it is unlawful under
AS 28.35.290
for the person to operate a motor vehicle, aircraft, or watercraft during the 24 hours following the issuance of the citation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-285__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The refusal of a minor to submit to a chemical test authorized under
AS 28.35.031</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-285__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and 28.35.280(a) is admissible evidence in a civil or criminal action or proceeding arising out of an act alleged to have been committed by the person while operating a vehicle after consuming alcohol.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-285__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Refusal to submit to a chemical test or tests of the person's breath requested under
AS 28.35.280
is an infraction, and, if the minor</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-285__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has not been previously convicted under this section,
AS 28.35.280
, or 28.35.290, upon conviction, the court shall impose a
(A) fine of $500; and
(B) period of community work service of not less than 20 hours nor more than 40 hours; the community work service under this subparagraph must be related to education about or prevention or treatment of misuse of alcohol if opportunities are available for that type of work service in the community; if such opportunities are not available, the court shall make other provisions for the work service;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-285__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has been previously convicted once under this section,
AS 28.35.280
, or 28.35.290, upon conviction, the court shall impose a
(A) fine of $1,000; and
(B) period of community work service of not less than 40 hours nor more than 60 hours; the community work service under this subparagraph must be related to education about or prevention or treatment of misuse of alcohol if opportunities are available for that type of work service in the community; if such opportunities are not available, the court shall make other provisions for the work service;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-285__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has been previously convicted two or more times under this section,
AS 28.35.280
, or 28.35.290, upon conviction, the court shall impose a
(A) fine of $1,500; and
(B) period of community work service of not less than 60 hours nor more than 80 hours; the community work service under this subparagraph must be related to education about or prevention or treatment of misuse of alcohol if opportunities are available for that type of work service in the community; if such opportunities are not available, the court shall make other provisions for the work service.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-290">
            <num>28.35.290</num>
            <heading>Driving during the 24 hours after being cited for alcohol or breath test offenses.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-35-290__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who has been cited for minor operating a vehicle after consuming alcohol under
AS 28.35.280
or for refusal to submit to a chemical test of breath under
AS 28.35.285
may not operate a motor vehicle, aircraft, or watercraft during the 24 hours following issuance of the citation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-290__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Operating a motor vehicle during the 24 hours after being cited for minor operating a vehicle after consuming alcohol or for minor's refusal to submit to a chemical test is an infraction, and, if the minor</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-290__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has not been previously convicted under this section,
AS 28.35.280
, or 28.35.285, upon conviction, the court shall impose a
(A) fine of $500; and
(B) period of community work service of not less than 20 hours nor more than 40 hours; the community work service under this subparagraph must be related to education about or prevention or treatment of misuse of alcohol if opportunities are available for that type of work service in the community; if such opportunities are not available, the court shall make other provisions for the work service;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-290__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has been previously convicted once under this section,
AS 28.35.280
, or 28.35.285, upon conviction, the court shall impose a
(A) fine of $1,000; and
(B) period of community work service of not less than 40 hours nor more than 60 hours; the community work service under this subparagraph must be related to education about or prevention or treatment of misuse of alcohol if opportunities are available for that type of work service in the community; if such opportunities are not available, the court shall make other provisions for the work service;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-290__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has been previously convicted two or more times under this section,
AS 28.35.280
, or 28.35.285, upon conviction, the court shall impose a
(A) fine of $1,500; and
(B) period of community work service of not less than 60 hours nor more than 80 hours; the community work service under this subparagraph must be related to education about or prevention or treatment of misuse of alcohol if opportunities are available for that type of work service in the community; if such opportunities are not available, the court shall make other provisions for the work service.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-290__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-290__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>operate an aircraft has the meaning given in
AS 28.35.030</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-290__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>operate a watercraft has the meaning given in
AS 28.35.030</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-300">
            <num>28.35.300</num>
            <heading>Tampering with or damaging a vehicle.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.35.300.   Tampering with or damaging a vehicle.
A person, without the right to do so, may not tamper with a vehicle, set or attempt to set a vehicle in motion, or damage a part or component of a vehicle.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-310">
            <num>28.35.310</num>
            <heading>Renting a motor vehicle.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-35-310__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not rent a motor vehicle to a person unless the person renting the vehicle is properly licensed under this title or, if a nonresident, the person is properly licensed under the laws of the jurisdiction of a person's residence.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-310__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not rent a motor vehicle until the person has inspected the license of the person to whom the vehicle is to be rented, and has verified the identification of the licensee.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-310__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Every person renting a motor vehicle shall keep a record of the registration number of the vehicle rented, the name, address and license number of the person to whom the vehicle is rented, and the date and place when and where the license of the intended driver was issued. The record shall be open to inspection by a peace officer or employee of the Department of Public Safety acting in an official capacity.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-310__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Every person renting a motor vehicle shall comply with the financial responsibility requirements of this title.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-310__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who rents motor vehicles to others shall provide child safety devices in sufficient quantity that all persons to whom the vehicles are to be rented can comply with the requirements of
AS 28.05.095
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-320">
            <num>28.35.320</num>
            <heading>Failure to return rental vehicle.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-35-320__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person in possession of a motor vehicle under an agreement in writing that requires the person to return the vehicle to a particular place or at a particular time who refuses or wilfully neglects to return it to the place and at the time specified in the agreement in writing with the intent to deprive the owner of the vehicle or to convert it to the person's own use, or who secretes, converts, sells, or attempts to sell the vehicle or any part of it is, upon conviction, punishable by imprisonment for not more than five years, or by a fine of not more than $1,000, or by both.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-320__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, wilfully neglects means omits, fails, or forbears, with a conscious purpose to injure, or without regard for the rights of the owner, or with indifference whether a wrong is done the owner or not.
Article 6. Reckless and Negligent Driving.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-400">
            <num>28.35.400</num>
            <heading>Reckless driving.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-35-400__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who drives a motor vehicle in the state in a manner that creates a substantial and unjustifiable risk of harm to a person or to property is guilty of reckless driving. A substantial and unjustifiable risk is a risk of such a nature and degree that the conscious disregard of it or a failure to perceive it constitutes a gross deviation from the standard of conduct that a reasonable person would observe in the situation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-400__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person convicted of reckless driving is guilty of a misdemeanor and is punishable by a fine of not more than $1,000 or by imprisonment for not more than one year or by both.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-400__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Lawfully conducted automobile, snowmobile, motorcycle, or other motor vehicle racing or exhibition events are not subject to the provisions of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-35-410">
            <num>28.35.410</num>
            <heading>Negligent driving.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-35-410__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who drives a motor vehicle in the state in a manner that creates an unjustifiable risk of harm to a person or to property and who, as a result of the creation of the risk, actually endangers a person or property is guilty of negligent driving.  An unjustifiable risk is a risk of such a nature and degree that a failure to avoid it constitutes a deviation from the standard of care that a reasonable person would observe in the situation.  Proof that a defendant actually endangered a person or property is established by showing that, as a result of the defendant's driving,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-410__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an accident occurred;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-410__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a person, including the defendant, took evasive action to avoid an accident;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-410__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a person, including the defendant, stopped or slowed down suddenly to avoid an accident; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-35-410__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a person or property, including the defendant or the defendant's property, was otherwise endangered.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-410__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The offense of negligent driving is a lesser offense than, and included in, the offense of reckless driving, and a person charged with reckless driving may be convicted of the lesser offense of negligent driving.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-410__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person convicted of negligent driving is guilty of an infraction as provided under
AS 28.90.010
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-35-410__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Lawfully conducted automobile, snowmobile, motorcycle or other motor vehicle racing or exhibition events are not subject to the provisions of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>