<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-44/chapter-46"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-44/chapter-46"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="44.46"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-44/chapter-46/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-44/chapter-46/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-44/chapter-46/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-44/chapter-46/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_44">
        <num>44</num>
        <heading>State Government</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_44__chp_46">
          <num>46</num>
          <heading>Department of Environmental Conservation</heading>
          <section eId="sec_44-46-010">
            <num>44.46.010</num>
            <heading>Commissioner of environmental conservation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.46.010.   Commissioner of environmental conservation.
The principal executive officer of the Department of Environmental Conservation is the commissioner of environmental conservation.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-46-020">
            <num>44.46.020</num>
            <heading>Duties of department.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-46-020__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Environmental Conservation shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-46-020__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>have primary responsibility for coordination and development of policies, programs, and planning related to the environment of the state and of the various regions of the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-46-020__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>have primary responsibility for the adoption and enforcement of regulations setting standards for the prevention and abatement of all water, land, subsurface land, and air pollution, and other sources or potential sources of pollution of the environment, including by way of example only, petroleum and natural gas pipelines;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-46-020__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>promote and develop programs for the protection and control of the environment of the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-46-020__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>take actions that are necessary and proper to further the policy declared in
AS 46.03.010
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-46-020__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>adopt regulations for
(A) the prevention and control of public health nuisances;
(B) the regulation of sanitation and sanitary practices in the interest of public health;
(C) standards of cleanliness and sanitation in connection with the construction, operation, and maintenance of a camp, cannery, food handling establishment, food manufacturing plant, mattress manufacturing establishment, industrial plant, school, barbershop, hairdressing, hair braiding, manicuring, esthetics, tattooing, permanent cosmetic coloring, body piercing, or ear piercing establishment, soft drink establishment, beer and wine dispensaries, and for other similar establishments in which lack of sanitation may create a condition that causes disease;
(D) the regulation of quality and purity of commercially compressed air sold for human respiration.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-46-020__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department's regulations for tattooing, permanent cosmetic coloring shops, and body piercing shops must include requirements that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-46-020__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the shop be equipped with appropriate sterilizing equipment, with availability of hot and cold running water, and with an appropriate waste receptacle;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-46-020__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the owner of the shop is responsible for ensuring that case history cards are kept for each client for a period of three years after the client's most recent tattooing, permanent cosmetic coloring, or body piercing;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-46-020__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a practitioner in the shop may use only instruments for tattooing, permanent cosmetic coloring, or body piercing that have been sterilized in accordance with methods approved by the department.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-46-025">
            <num>44.46.025</num>
            <heading>Fees for services.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-46-025__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as otherwise provided in
AS 37.10.050
 37.10.056, the Department of Environmental Conservation may adopt regulations that prescribe reasonable fees, and establish procedures for the collection of those fees, to cover the applicable direct costs, not including travel except in the case of a designated regulatory service, as that term is defined in
AS 37.10.058
, of inspections, permit preparation and administration, plan review and approval, and other services provided by the department relating to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-46-025__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>animals and animal products under
AS 03.05
; food, drugs, and cosmetics under
AS 17.20
; and public accommodations and facilities under
AS 18.35
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-46-025__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>certificates of inspection for motor vehicles under
AS 46.14.400
or 46.14.510;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-46-025__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>drinking water systems under
AS 46.03.720
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-46-025__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>water and wastewater operator training under
AS 46.30
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-46-025__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>waste management and disposal authorizations under
AS 46.03.100
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-46-025__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>certification of laboratories conducting environmental analyses of public drinking water systems or of oil or hazardous substances, or conducting other analyses required by the department;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-46-025__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>certification of federal permits or authorizations under 33 U.S.C. 1341 (sec. 401, Clean Water Act);</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-46-025__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>regulation of point source discharges of pollutants under the program authorized by
AS 46.03.020
(12);</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-46-025__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>regulation of pesticides and broadcast chemicals registered under
AS 46.03.320</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-46-025__subsec_a__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>licensing of pesticide applicators under
AS 46.03.320</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-46-025__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may not charge a fee for a service that is provided by a municipality under a delegation by the department to the municipality.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-46-025__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may adopt regulations that prescribe reasonable fees to cover the direct and indirect costs of air quality permit programs under
AS 46.14
and may establish procedures for the collection of those fees.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-46-025__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (a) of this section, the department may not charge a fee for inspection, permit preparation and administration, plan review and approval, or other services provided by the department under
AS 03.05
or
AS 44.46.020
(a)(5) to a school. In this subsection, school means a public school or private school for children of school age, as defined in
AS 14.03.070
, or a head start center that receives federal financial assistance under 42 U.S.C. 9835.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-46-025__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In (a)(9) and (10) of this section, reasonable fee means a fee that does not unduly interfere in the conduct of commerce in the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-46-028">
            <num>44.46.028</num>
            <heading>Flow-through hot springs.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-46-028__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A flow-through hot springs, whether natural or modified, when used for perceived medicinal or esthetic purposes, is exempt from further water quality regulation by the Department of Environmental Conservation while the fecal coliform count is maintained at 100 colonies or less per 100 milliliters and the body of water is free from dangerous levels of disease-causing pathogens or chemicals.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-46-028__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, flow-through hot springs means a body of water in which naturally occurring geothermal water enters the body of water to replace an equal amount of water constantly being drained from the body of water.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-46-029">
            <num>44.46.029</num>
            <heading>Dental radiological equipment.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.46.029.   Dental radiological equipment.
This chapter does not authorize the department to register, inspect, test, or otherwise regulate dental radiological equipment or records relating to dental radiological equipment regulated by the Department of Health under
AS 44.29.020
(d).</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>