<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-98"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-98"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="8.98"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-98/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-98/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-98/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-98/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_8">
        <num>8</num>
        <heading>Business and Professions</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_8__chp_98">
          <num>98</num>
          <heading>Veterinarians</heading>
          <section eId="sec_08-98-010">
            <num>08.98.010</num>
            <heading>Creation and membership of the board.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.98.010.   Creation and membership of the board.
There is created the Board of Veterinary Examiners composed of five members appointed by the governor and approved by the legislature.  Four members shall be licensed veterinarians who have been in active practice in the state for at least five years preceding appointment and one shall be a public member. A person may not serve on the board who is, or was during the two years immediately preceding appointment, a member of a faculty, board of trustees, or advisory board of a veterinary school.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-98-040">
            <num>08.98.040</num>
            <heading>Board meetings.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.98.040.   Board meetings.
The board shall hold at least three meetings each year.  The board may hold special meetings at the call of the chairman or of a majority of the members.  A majority of board members constitutes a quorum and a majority vote of those present is the decision of the board.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-98-050">
            <num>08.98.050</num>
            <heading>Powers and duties of the board.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-98-050__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-98-050__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establish examination requirements for eligible applicants for licensure to practice veterinary medicine;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-98-050__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>examine, or cause to be examined, eligible applicants for licensure or registration;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-98-050__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>approve the issuance of licenses and student permits to qualified applicants;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-98-050__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establish standards for the practice of veterinary medicine by regulation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-98-050__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>conduct disciplinary proceedings in accordance with this chapter;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-98-050__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>adopt regulations requiring proof of continued competency before a license is renewed;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-98-050__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>as requested by the department, monitor the standards and availability of veterinary services provided in the state and report its findings to the department;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-98-050__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>collect, or cause to be collected, data concerning the practice of veterinary technology by veterinary technicians in the state and submit the data to the department for maintenance;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-98-050__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establish, by regulation, educational and training requirements for
(A) the issuance of student permits; and
(B) the delegation of duties by veterinarians licensed under this chapter to veterinary technicians;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-98-050__subsec_a__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>identify resources and develop educational materials to assist licensees to identify an animal owner who may be at risk for abusing or misusing an opioid.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-98-050__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board may</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-98-050__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establish examination and registration requirements for veterinary technicians;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-98-050__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>adopt regulations or do any act necessary to carry out its duties under this chapter;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-98-050__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>adopt a certification process for licensure to practice veterinary medicine.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-98-070">
            <num>08.98.070</num>
            <heading>Duties of the department.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.98.070.   Duties of the department.
The department shall furnish the board with administrative services, including renting space for holding examinations, printing and mailing licenses and student permits, sending notices, before December 1 of each year, that licenses must be renewed, collecting fees and issuing receipts, keeping a current register of licensees, employing secretarial assistants, replying to routine requests for information, printing forms and informational bulletins, typing all matter to be reproduced, maintaining records and completed examinations, and keeping records of receipts and disbursements.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-98-080">
            <num>08.98.080</num>
            <heading>Department regulations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.98.080.   Department regulations.
The department shall adopt procedural regulations necessary to carry out the duties imposed on it by
AS 08.98.070
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-98-090">
            <num>08.98.090</num>
            <heading>Applicability of the Administrative Procedure Act.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.98.090.   Applicability of the Administrative Procedure Act.
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act) applies to regulations and proceedings under this chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-98-100">
            <num>08.98.100</num>
            <heading>Compensation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.98.100.   Compensation.
Members of the board are entitled to per diem allowances and transportation expenses allowed by law and paid members of other state examining boards.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-98-120">
            <num>08.98.120</num>
            <heading>License required; prohibitions; penalty.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-98-120__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not practice veterinary medicine, surgery, or dentistry unless the person is licensed as a veterinarian under this chapter or has a temporary permit issued under
AS 08.98.186
, except that a person may perform functions authorized by</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-98-120__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>regulation of the board if the person is licensed as a veterinary technician; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-98-120__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a permit issued under
AS 08.02.050
if the person is employed by an agency that has a permit issued under
AS 08.02.050
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-98-120__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-98-120__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>present or attempt to use a license or permit that was issued under this chapter to another person, either directly or by impersonation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-98-120__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>secure or attempt to secure a license or permit under this chapter through deceit, fraud, or intentional misrepresentation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-98-120__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>use or attempt to use an expired or revoked license or permit knowing of the license's or permit's status; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-98-120__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>falsely claim to be licensed or to hold a permit under this chapter.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-98-120__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Violation of this section is a misdemeanor punishable by a fine of not more than $10,000 or by imprisonment for not more than one year, or by both.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-98-125">
            <num>08.98.125</num>
            <heading>Exemptions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.98.125.   Exemptions.
This chapter does not apply to the following:
(1) a veterinary medical officer in the military service in the discharge of official duties or as an employee in the federal or state government performing veterinary medical services within the scope of the person's official duties;
(2) a veterinarian who is licensed in another state or country, or a person whose expertise a veterinarian licensed in this state believes would benefit an animal, and who provides only consultation to a veterinarian licensed in this state; in this paragraph, consultation means advice or assistance provided in person, telephonically, electronically, or by any other method of communication from a veterinarian or other person whose expertise, in the opinion of the veterinarian, would benefit the animal; and
(3) a veterinarian licensed and residing in another state who provides assistance, as requested by and under the supervision of a veterinarian licensed in this state, for the purpose of providing skills not otherwise available in this state in conducting research or other practice of veterinary medicine on captive or free-ranging wildlife; however, that assistance is limited to not more than three events in a calendar year for not more than a total of 60 days in the year and may not be on a regular or recurring basis, as defined by the board.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-98-150">
            <num>08.98.150</num>
            <heading>Administration of examination.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.98.150.   Administration of examination.
The board shall offer examinations at least once a year. Examinations shall be so administered that, whenever possible, one who grades a written examination does not know the identity of the examinee whose test is being graded.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-98-160">
            <num>08.98.160</num>
            <heading>Reexamination.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.98.160.   Reexamination.
A person who fails an examination may apply for a subsequent examination, but shall pay the examination fee each time the person applies.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-98-165">
            <num>08.98.165</num>
            <heading>Qualification for license.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-98-165__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An applicant is qualified to receive a license as a veterinarian who</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-98-165__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is a graduate of an accredited veterinary school or who has successfully completed the Educational Commission for Foreign Veterinary Graduates certification, the Program for the Assessment of Veterinary Education Equivalence certification, or another certification process approved by the board;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-98-165__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has, within the 60 months preceding application for the license, passed a national examination for veterinarians approved by the board;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-98-165__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has passed the written examination of the state on specific Alaska issues of veterinary practice;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-98-165__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is in good standing, as defined by the board in regulations; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-98-165__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has paid required fees.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-98-165__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 6 ch 5 SLA 1998.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-98-167">
            <num>08.98.167</num>
            <heading>Qualification for technician license.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.98.167.   Qualification for technician license.
The board shall adopt regulations under which a person may qualify to be licensed as a veterinary technician.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-98-180">
            <num>08.98.180</num>
            <heading>Temporary license.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.98.180.   Temporary license.
A person who meets the requirements of
AS 08.98.165
(a)(1), (4), and (5) is entitled to be temporarily licensed after applying for examination if the person works under the supervision of a licensed veterinarian. A license issued under this section is valid until the results of the examinations are published. A person may not receive more than one temporary license. An application for a temporary license must be signed by the supervising veterinarian and accompanied by the temporary license fee required under
AS 08.98.190
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-98-184">
            <num>08.98.184</num>
            <heading>Licensure by credentials.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.98.184.   Licensure by credentials.
The board shall approve the issuance of a license to an applicant who holds a valid license to practice veterinary medicine in another state, territory, or country if the applicant
(1) has graduated from an accredited school of veterinary medicine or has successfully completed the Educational Commission for Foreign Veterinary Graduates certification, the Program for the Assessment of Veterinary Education Equivalence certification, or another certification process approved by the board;
(2) has been engaged in the active practice of veterinary medicine for at least five of the seven years before filing the application;
(3) has passed the written examination of the state on specific Alaska issues of veterinary practice;
(4) is in good standing, as defined by the board in regulations; and
(5) has paid required fees.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-98-186">
            <num>08.98.186</num>
            <heading>Temporary permit.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.98.186.   Temporary permit.
A person licensed to practice veterinary medicine in another state who meets the requirements of
AS 08.98.165
(a)(1), (4), and (5) may be granted a temporary permit to conduct the practice of a person licensed in the state who is absent from practice. An application shall be signed by the person who is or will be absent from practice and by the applicant. A temporary permit is valid for no longer than 60 days after issuance but may be renewed.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-98-188">
            <num>08.98.188</num>
            <heading>Student permit.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-98-188__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board may approve the issuance of a student permit to a student enrolled in and in good standing at an accredited college of veterinary medicine who has completed three years of study and is participating in an externship program as part of the college's educational curriculum.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-98-188__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A student permit is valid for not longer than one year and may not extend beyond the student's graduation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-98-188__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A holder of a student permit is subject to the following limitations:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-98-188__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>assistance in diagnosis and surgery must be under the immediate supervision of a veterinarian licensed in this state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-98-188__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>assistance in treatment must be under the direct or indirect supervision of a veterinarian licensed in this state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-98-188__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>not more than one student permit holder at a time may be under the direct supervision of a veterinarian licensed in this state; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-98-188__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a veterinary practice may not retain more than two student permit holders at a time.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-98-188__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board shall establish requirements for student permits by regulation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-98-188__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person holding a permit under this section is not subject to provisions of this chapter other than this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-98-188__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-98-188__subsec_f__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>direct supervision means the supervising veterinarian is on the premises where the animal is being treated and is quickly and easily available;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-98-188__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>immediate supervision means the supervising veterinarian is in the immediate area and within audible and visual range of the animal patient and the person treating the patient;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-98-188__subsec_f__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>indirect supervision means the supervising veterinarian does not need to be on the premises but has given either written or oral instructions for the treatment of the animal;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-98-188__subsec_f__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>veterinary practice means a business that provides veterinary services.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-98-190">
            <num>08.98.190</num>
            <heading>Fees.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.98.190.   Fees.
The department shall set fees under
AS 08.01.065
for the following:
(1) application;
(2) examination;
(3) investigation of credentials;
(4) license;
(5) license renewal;
(6) temporary license;
(7) temporary permit.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-98-200">
            <num>08.98.200</num>
            <heading>Reinstatement of lapsed license.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.98.200.   Reinstatement of lapsed license.
A person whose license has lapsed is entitled to have the license reinstated without taking an examination unless the license has remained lapsed more than five years.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-98-235">
            <num>08.98.235</num>
            <heading>Grounds for imposition of disciplinary sanctions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.98.235.   Grounds for imposition of disciplinary sanctions.
After a hearing, the board may impose a disciplinary sanction on a person licensed under this chapter when the board finds that the person
(1) secured a license through deceit, fraud, or intentional misrepresentation;
(2) engaged in deceit, fraud, or intentional misrepresentation in the course of providing professional services or engaging in professional activities;
(3) advertised professional services in a false or misleading manner;
(4) has been convicted of a felony or other crime which affects the person's ability to continue to practice competently and safely;
(5) intentionally or negligently engaged in or permitted the performance of animal care by the person's supervisees which does not conform to minimum professional standards regardless of whether actual injury to the animal occurred;
(6) failed to comply with this chapter, with a regulation adopted under this chapter, or with an order of the board;
(7) continued to practice after becoming unfit due to
(A) professional incompetence;
(B) addiction or severe dependency on alcohol or other drugs which impairs the person's ability to practice safely;
(C) physical or mental disability;
(8) engaged in lewd or immoral conduct in connection with the delivery of professional service;
(9)  prescribed or dispensed an opioid in excess of the maximum dosage authorized under
AS 08.98.245
;
(10)  procured, sold, prescribed, or dispensed drugs in violation of a law, regardless of whether there has been a criminal action.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-98-245">
            <num>08.98.245</num>
            <heading>Maximum dosage for opioid prescriptions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-98-245__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A veterinarian may not issue an initial prescription for an opioid that exceeds a seven- day supply to the owner of an animal patient for outpatient use.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-98-245__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (a) of this section, a veterinarian may issue a prescription for an opioid that exceeds a seven-day supply to the owner of an animal if the veterinarian determines that more than a seven-day supply of an opioid is necessary</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-98-245__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to treat the animal's medical condition or for chronic pain management; the veterinarian may write a prescription for an opioid for the quantity needed to treat the animal's medical condition or chronic pain; the veterinarian shall document in the animal's medical record the condition triggering the prescription of an opioid in a quantity that exceeds a seven-day supply and indicate that a nonopioid alternative was not appropriate to address the medical condition; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-98-245__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for an owner who is unable to access a veterinarian or pharmacist within the time necessary for a refill of the seven-day supply because of a logistical or travel barrier; the veterinarian may write a prescription for an opioid for the quantity needed to treat the animal for the time that the owner is unable to access a veterinarian or pharmacist; the veterinarian shall document in the animal's medical record the reason for the prescription of an opioid in a quantity that exceeds a seven-day supply and indicate that a nonopioid alternative was not appropriate to address the medical condition.
Article 4. General Provisions.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-98-250">
            <num>08.98.250</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-98-250__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>diagnose, treat, correct, change, relieve, or prevent animal disease, deformity, defect, injury, or other physical or mental condition, including the prescription or administration of a drug, biologic apparatus, anesthetic, or other therapeutic or diagnostic substance;
(ii) use a manual or mechanical procedure for testing for pregnancy or correcting sterility or infertility; or
(iii) render advice or recommendation with regard to any matter listed in (i) or (ii) of this subparagraph;
(B) means to represent, directly or indirectly, publicly or privately, an ability or willingness to do any act in (A) of this paragraph for compensation;
(C) means to use a description, title, abbreviation, or letters in a manner or under circumstances tending to induce the belief that the person using it or them is qualified or licensed to do any act in (A) of this paragraph whether or not for compensation;
(D) does not include, whether or not for compensation,</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-98-250__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>practices related to artificial insemination and the use of a title, abbreviation, or letters in a manner which induces the belief that the person using them is qualified to perform artificial insemination;
(ii) the practices of a farrier done in the performance of the farrier's profession;
(iii) standard practices commonly performed on farm or domestic animals in the course of routine farming or animal husbandry, when performed by an owner or the owner's employee unless ownership of the animal is transferred for the purpose of avoiding application of this chapter or the primary purpose of hiring the employee is to avoid application of this chapter;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-98-250__subsec_i__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>veterinary technician means a person who performs functions delegated by a veterinarian licensed under this chapter.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>