<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-29/chapter-45"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-29/chapter-45"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="29.45"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-29/chapter-45/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-29/chapter-45/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-29/chapter-45/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-29/chapter-45/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_29">
        <num>29</num>
        <heading>Municipal Government</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_29__chp_45">
          <num>45</num>
          <heading>Municipal Taxation</heading>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-010">
            <num>29.45.010</num>
            <heading>Property tax.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-010__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A unified municipality may levy a property tax. A borough may levy</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-010__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an areawide property tax for areawide functions;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-010__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a nonareawide property tax for functions limited to the area outside cities;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-010__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a property tax in a service area for functions limited to the service area.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-010__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A home rule or first class city may levy a property tax subject to
AS 29.45.550
 29.45.560.  A second class city may levy a property tax subject to
AS 29.45.590
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-010__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a tax is levied on real property or on personal property, the tax must be assessed, levied, and collected as provided in this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-020">
            <num>29.45.020</num>
            <heading>Taxpayer notice.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-020__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a municipality levies and collects property taxes, the governing body shall provide the following notice:
NOTICE TO TAXPAYER
For the current fiscal year the (city)(borough) has been allocated the following amount of state aid for school and municipal purposes under the applicable financial assistance Acts:
PUBLIC SCHOOL FUNDING
PROGRAM (
AS 14.17
) $
STATE AID FOR RETIREMENT OF SCHOOL
CONSTRUCTION DEBT (
AS 14.11.100
)$
COMMUNITY ASSISTANCE PROGRAM
(
AS 29.60.850
 29.60.879)$
TOTAL AID$
The millage equivalent of this state aid, based on the dollar value of a mill in the municipality during the current assessment year and for the preceding assessment year, is:
MILLAGE EQUIVALENT
PREVIOUS YEARTHIS YEAR
PUBLIC SCHOOL FUNDING
PROGRAM ASSISTANCEMILLSMILLS
STATE AID FOR RETIREMENT OF
SCHOOL CONSTRUCTION DEBTMILLSMILLS
COMMUNITY ASSISTANCE
PROGRAMMILLSMILLS
TOTAL MILLAGE EQUIVALENTMILLSMILLS
Notice shall be provided by</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-020__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>furnishing a copy of the notice with tax statements mailed for the fiscal year for which aid is received; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-020__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>publishing in a newspaper of general circulation in the municipality a copy of the notice once each week for a period of three successive weeks, with publication to occur not later than 45 days after the final adoption of the municipality's budget.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-020__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Compliance with the provisions of this section is a prerequisite to receipt of community assistance under
AS 29.60.850
  29.60.879. The department shall withhold annual allocations under those sections until municipal officials demonstrate that the requirements of this section have been met.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-030">
            <num>29.45.030</num>
            <heading>Required exemptions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-030__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The following property is exempt from general taxation:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-030__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>municipal property, including property held by a public corporation of a municipality, state property, property of the University of Alaska, or land that is in the trust established by the Alaska Mental Health Enabling Act of 1956, P.L. 84-830, 70 Stat. 709, except that
(A) a private leasehold, contract, or other interest in the property is taxable to the extent of the interest; however, an interest created by an operating agreement or nonexclusive use agreement between the Alaska Industrial Development and Export Authority and a user of a shipyard or an integrated transportation and port facility, if the shipyard or integrated transportation and port facility is owned by the authority and initially placed in service before January 1, 1999, is taxable only to the extent of, and for the value associated with, those specific improvements used for lodging purposes;
(B) notwithstanding any other provision of law, property acquired by an agency, corporation, or other entity of the state through foreclosure or deed in lieu of foreclosure and retained as an investment of a state entity is taxable; this subparagraph does not apply to federal land granted to the University of Alaska under
AS 14.40.380
or 14.40.390, or to other land granted to the university by the state to replace land that had been granted under
AS 14.40.380
or 14.40.390, or to land conveyed by the state to the university under
AS 14.40.365
;
(C) an ownership interest of a municipality in real property located outside the municipality acquired after December 31, 1990, is taxable by another municipality; however, a borough may not tax an interest in real property located in the borough and owned by a city in that borough;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-030__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>household furniture and personal effects of members of a household;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-030__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>property used exclusively for nonprofit religious, charitable, cemetery, hospital, or educational purposes;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-030__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>property of a nonbusiness organization composed entirely of persons with 90 days or more of active service in the armed forces of the United States whose conditions of service and separation were other than dishonorable, or the property of an auxiliary of that organization;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-030__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>money on deposit;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-030__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the real property of certain residents of the state to the extent and subject to the conditions provided in (e) of this section;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-030__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>real property or an interest in real property that is
(A) exempt from taxation under 43 U.S.C. 1620(d), as amended or under 43 U.S.C. 1636(d), as amended; or
(B) acquired from a municipality in exchange for land that is exempt from taxation under (A) of this paragraph, and is not developed or made subject to a lease;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-030__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>property of a political subdivision, agency, corporation, or other entity of the United States to the extent required by federal law; except that a private leasehold, contract, or other interest in the property is taxable to the extent of that interest unless the property is located on a military base or installation and the property interest is created under 10 U.S.C. 2871  2885 (Military Housing Privatization Initiative), if the leaseholder enters into an agreement to make a payment in lieu of taxes to the political subdivision that has taxing authority;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-030__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>natural resources in place including coal, ore bodies, mineral deposits, and other proven and unproven deposits of valuable materials laid down by natural processes, unharvested aquatic plants and animals, and timber;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-030__subsec_a__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>property not exempt under (3) of this subsection that
(A) is owned by a private, nonprofit college or university that is accredited by a regional or national accrediting agency recognized by the Council for Higher Education Accreditation or the United States Department of Education, or both; and
(B) was subject to a private leasehold, contract, or other private interest on January 1, 2010, except that a holder of a private leasehold, contract, or other interest in the property shall be taxed to the extent of that interest.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-030__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In (a) of this section, property used exclusively for religious purposes includes the following property owned by a religious organization:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-030__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the residence of an educator in a private religious or parochial school or a bishop, pastor, priest, rabbi, minister, or religious order of a recognized religious organization; for purposes of this paragraph, minister means an individual who is
(A) ordained, commissioned, or licensed as a minister according to standards of the religious organization for its ministers; and
(B) employed by the religious organization to carry out a ministry of that religious organization;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-030__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a structure, its furniture, and its fixtures used solely for public worship, charitable purposes, religious administrative offices, religious education, or a nonprofit hospital;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-030__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>lots required by local ordinance for parking near a structure defined in (2) of this subsection.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-030__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Property described in (a)(3) or (4) of this section from which income is derived is exempt only if that income is solely from use of the property by nonprofit religious, charitable, hospital, or educational groups.  If used by nonprofit educational groups, the property is exempt only if used exclusively for classroom space.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-030__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Laws exempting certain property from execution under
AS 09
(Code of Civil Procedure) do not exempt the property from taxes levied and collected by municipalities.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-030__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The real property owned and occupied as the primary residence and permanent place of abode by a resident who is (1) 65 years of age or older; (2) a disabled veteran; or (3) at least 60 years of age and the widow or widower of a person who qualified for an exemption under (1) or (2) of this subsection is exempt from taxation on the first $150,000 of the assessed value of the real property. A municipality may by ordinance approved by the voters grant the exemption under this subsection to the widow or widower under 60 years of age of a person who qualified for an exemption under (2) of this subsection or to a resident who is the widow or widower of a person who dies from a service-connected cause sustained while serving as a member of the United States armed forces or as a member of the National Guard. A municipality may, in case of hardship, provide for exemption beyond the first $150,000 of assessed value in accordance with regulations of the department. Only one exemption may be granted for the same property, and, if two or more persons are eligible for an exemption for the same property, the parties shall decide between or among themselves who is to receive the benefit of the exemption. Real property may not be exempted under this subsection if the assessor determines, after notice and hearing to the parties, that the property was conveyed to the applicant primarily for the purpose of obtaining the exemption. The determination of the assessor may be appealed under
AS 44.62.560
 44.62.570. A municipality shall determine the eligibility requirements and application procedure for an optional exemption provided under this subsection. In this subsection, widow or widower means a person whose spouse has died and who has not remarried.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-030__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To be eligible for an exemption under (e) of this section for a year, a municipality may by ordinance require that an individual also meet requirements under one of the following paragraphs: (1) the individual shall be eligible for a permanent fund dividend under
AS 43.23.005
for that same year or for the immediately preceding year; or (2) if the individual has not applied or does not apply for one or both of the permanent fund dividends, the individual would have been eligible for one of the permanent fund dividends identified in (1) of this subsection had the individual applied. An exemption may not be granted under (e) of this section except upon written application for the exemption. Each municipality shall, by ordinance, establish procedures and deadlines for filing the application. The governing body of the municipality for good cause shown may waive the claimant's failure to make timely application for exemption and authorize the assessor to accept the application as if timely filed. If an application is filed within the required time and is approved by the assessor, the assessor shall allow an exemption in accordance with the provisions of (e) of this section. If the application for exemption is approved after taxes have been paid, the amount of tax that the claimant has already paid for the property exempted shall be refunded to the claimant. The assessor shall require proof in the form the assessor considers necessary of the right to and amount of an exemption claimed under (e) of this section, and shall require a disabled veteran claiming an exemption under (e) of this section to provide evidence of the disability rating. The assessor may require proof under this subsection at any time.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-030__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The state shall reimburse a borough or city, as appropriate, for the real property tax revenues lost to it by the operation of (e) of this section.  However, reimbursement may be made to a municipality for revenue lost to it only to the extent that the loss exceeds an exemption that was granted by the municipality, or that on proper application by an individual would have been granted under
AS 29.45.050
(a).  If appropriations are not sufficient to fully fund reimbursements under this subsection, the amount available shall be distributed pro rata among eligible municipalities.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-030__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (g) of this section, nothing in (e)  (j) of this section affects similar exemptions from property taxes granted by a municipality on September 10, 1972, or prevents a municipality from granting similar exemptions by ordinance as provided in
AS 29.45.050
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-030__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In (e)  (i) of this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-030__subsec_i__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>disabled veteran means a disabled person
(A) separated from the military service of the United States under a condition that is not dishonorable who is a resident of the state, whose disability was incurred or aggravated in the line of duty in the military service of the United States, and whose disability has been rated as 50 percent or more by the branch of service in which that person served or by the United States Department of Veterans Affairs; or
(B) who served in the Alaska Territorial Guard, who is a resident of the state, whose disability was incurred or aggravated in the line of duty while serving in the Alaska Territorial Guard, and whose disability has been rated as 50 percent or more;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-030__subsec_i__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>real property includes but is not limited to mobile homes, whether classified as real or personal property for municipal tax purposes.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-030__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>One motor vehicle per household owned by a resident 65 years of age or older on January 1 of the assessment year is exempt either from taxation on its assessed value or from the registration tax under
AS 28.10.431
. An exemption may be granted under this subsection only upon written application on a form prescribed by the Department of Administration.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-030__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall adopt regulations to implement the provisions of (g) and (j) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-030__subsec_l">
              <num>(l)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 8, ch. 9, SLA 2017.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-030__subsec_m">
              <num>(m)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For the purpose of determining property exempt under (a)(7)(A) of this section, the following definitions apply to terms used in 43 U.S.C. 1620(d) unless superseded by applicable federal law, and for the purpose of determining property exempt under (a)(7)(B) of this section, the following definitions apply:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-030__subsec_m__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>developed means a purposeful modification of the property from its original state that effectuates a condition of gainful and productive present use without further substantial modification; surveying, construction of roads, providing utilities or other similar actions normally considered to be component parts of the development process, but that do not create the condition described in this paragraph, do not constitute a developed state within the meaning of this paragraph; developed property, in order to remove the exemption, must be developed for purposes other than exploration, and be limited to the smallest practicable tract of the property actually used in the developed state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-030__subsec_m__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>exploration means the examination and investigation of undeveloped land to determine the existence of subsurface nonrenewable resources;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-030__subsec_m__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>lease means a grant of primary possession entered into for gainful purposes with a determinable fee remaining in the hands of the grantor; with respect to a lease that conveys rights of exploration and development, this exemption shall continue with respect to that portion of the leased tract that is used solely for the purpose of exploration.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-030__subsec_n">
              <num>(n)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If property or an interest in property that is determined not to be exempt under (a)(7) of this section reverts to an undeveloped state, or if the lease is terminated, the exemption shall be granted, subject to the provisions of (a)(7) and (m) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-040">
            <num>29.45.040</num>
            <heading>Property tax equivalency payments.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-040__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A resident of the state who rents a permanent place of abode is eligible for a tax equivalency payment from the state through the department if the resident is</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-040__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>at least 65 years old;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-040__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a disabled veteran; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-040__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>at least 60 years old and the widow or widower of a person who was eligible for payment under (1) or (2) of this subsection.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-040__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of determining the amount of a payment to an eligible person, the department shall calculate at the rate of one percent per mill a property tax equivalent percentage for each municipality that levies a property tax. The property tax equivalent percentage applied to the annual rent charged to the applicant equals the property tax equivalency payment payable under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-040__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To obtain a tax equivalency payment the eligible resident must apply to the department for payment for the preceding year by January 15 of each year on forms and in the manner prescribed by the department.  The department for good cause shown may waive an applicant's failure to make timely application for a tax equivalency payment and accept the application as if timely filed.  Each applicant shall submit with the application rental receipts or, if rental receipts are not available, other evidence satisfactory to the department for determination of the fact of payment of rent and the amount paid. A disabled veteran shall submit with the application evidence of the disability rating.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-040__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If two or more persons occupy a residence as tenants, not all of whom are eligible for a tax equivalency payment under this section, the assessor shall determine equitable partial payments to be made to the eligible tenants. However, a tax equivalency payment to an eligible applicant may not be reduced because the spouse is less than 65 years of age or is not a disabled veteran.  If all occupants in a residence are eligible for a tax equivalency payment under this section, the occupants shall decide between and among themselves which shall receive payment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-040__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If appropriations are not sufficient to fully fund tax equivalency payments under this section, the amount available shall be distributed pro rata among eligible residents.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-040__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, disabled veteran has the meaning given in
AS 29.45.030
(i).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-046">
            <num>29.45.046</num>
            <heading>River habitat protection tax credit.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-046__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless prohibited by municipal charter, a municipality may by ordinance provide for a river habitat protection credit to be applied to offset a portion of the property taxes due on land, or an interest in land taxable under this chapter, upon which an improvement has been constructed that aids in</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-046__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>protecting a river from degradation of fish habitat due to public or private use; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-046__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>restoring riparian fish habitat along or in a river that has been damaged by land use practices.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-046__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The amount of a river habitat protection credit shall be based upon a percentage of the verifiable costs of the improvement and may not exceed 50 percent of the total amount of taxes levied upon the land or upon the taxable interest in the land during a single tax year, but the credit may be granted for more than one year. If the credit is granted for more than one year and the land or taxable interest in the land is conveyed, the portion of the credit remaining is extinguished. The ordinance may limit the availability of a credit to some, but not all types of improvements for which a credit may be granted under this section and to some, but not all areas of the municipality. A credit may only be granted for an improvement that has been constructed in compliance with state and federal laws. A credit may not be granted for an improvement</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-046__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>required under state or federal law; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-046__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>located more than 150 feet from the mean high tide line or ordinary high water line; in this paragraph, ordinary high water line means that line on the shore of the nontidal portion of a river or stream that reflects the highest level of water during an ordinary year and is established by fluctuations of water and indicated by physical characteristics such as a clear, natural line impressed on the bank, shelving, changes in the character of soil, destruction of terrestrial vegetation, the presence of litter and debris, or other appropriate means that consider the characteristics of the surrounding area.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-046__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 3 ch 41 SLA 1995.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-046__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before an ordinance is adopted under (a) of this section, it must be approved by the commissioner of fish and game. The commissioner of fish and game shall approve a proposed ordinance if the improvements for which a credit is authorized aid in protecting or restoring habitat as required under this section without regard to the percentage of the total protection or restoration that could be achieved by ideal improvement measures. Within 60 days after receipt of a proposed ordinance, the commissioner of fish and game shall notify the municipality in writing as to whether the proposed ordinance is approved or disapproved and, if the proposed ordinance is disapproved, shall state the basis for that determination.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-047">
            <num>29.45.047</num>
            <heading>Air quality improvement tax credit.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 29.45.047.   Air quality improvement tax credit.
A municipality may by ordinance provide for a single or multiple year air quality improvement tax credit to offset a portion of the property taxes due on real property improvements made during the immediately preceding tax year before the municipality's initial approval of the tax credit, including new construction, refurbishments, remodels, and renovations that aid in improving the air quality in the municipality. The municipality shall establish eligibility criteria for the credit in the ordinance adopted under this section.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-049">
            <num>29.45.049</num>
            <heading>Energy efficient construction tax credit.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 29.45.049.   Energy efficient construction tax credit.
A municipality may by ordinance provide for a single or multiple year energy efficient construction tax credit to offset a portion of the property taxes due on real property improvements made during the immediately preceding tax year before the municipality's initial approval of the tax credit, including energy efficient new construction, refurbishments, remodels, and renovations. The municipality shall establish eligibility criteria for the credit in the ordinance adopted under this section.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-050">
            <num>29.45.050</num>
            <heading>Optional exemptions and exclusions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-050__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may exclude or exempt or partially exempt residential property from taxation by ordinance ratified by the voters at an election. An exclusion or exemption authorized by this subsection may be applied with respect to taxes levied in a service area to fund the special services. An exclusion or exemption authorized by this subsection may not exceed the assessed value of $75,000 for any one residence except that a municipality may, by ordinance, annually adjust the municipality's voter-authorized exemption by the amount calculated by the State Assessor to reflect the increase, if any, in the annual average cost of living, using the United States Department of Labor Consumer Price Index for Urban Alaska.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-050__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may by ordinance</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-050__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>classify and exempt from taxation
(A) the property of an organization not organized for business or profit-making purposes and used exclusively for community purposes if the income derived from rental of that property does not exceed the actual cost to the owner of the use by the renter;
(B) historic sites, buildings, and monuments;
(C) land of a nonprofit organization used for agricultural purposes if rights to subdivide the land are conveyed to the state and the conveyance includes a covenant restricting use of the land to agricultural purposes only; rights conveyed to the state under this subparagraph may be conveyed by the state only in accordance with
AS 38.05.069</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-050__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>classify as to type and exempt or partially exempt some or all types of personal property from ad valorem taxes.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-050__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The provisions of (a) of this section notwithstanding,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-050__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a borough may, by ordinance, adjust its property tax structure in whole or in part to the property tax structure of a city in the borough, including adjustments excluding personal property from taxation, establishing exemptions, and extending the redemption period;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-050__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a home rule or first class city has the same power to grant exemptions or exclude property from borough taxes that it has as to city taxes if
(A) the exemptions or exclusions have been adopted as to city taxes; and
(B) the city appropriates to the borough sufficient money to equal revenue lost by the borough because of the exemptions or exclusions, the amount to be determined annually by the assembly;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-050__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a city in a borough may, by ordinance, adjust its property tax structure in whole or in part to the property tax structure of the borough, including exempting or partially exempting property from taxation.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-050__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Exemptions or exclusions from property tax that have been granted by a home rule municipality in addition to exemptions authorized or required by law, and that are in effect on September 10, 1972, and not later withdrawn, are not affected by this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-050__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may by ordinance classify and exempt or partially exempt from taxation privately owned land, wet land and water areas for which a scenic, conservation, or public recreation use easement is granted to a governmental body. To be eligible for a tax exemption, or partial exemption, the easement must be in perpetuity. The easement is automatically terminated before an eminent domain taking of fee simple title or less than fee simple title to the property, so that the property owner is compensated at a rate that does not reflect the easement grant. The municipality may provide by ordinance that, if the area subject to the easement is sold, leased, or otherwise disposed of for uses incompatible with the easement or if the easement is conveyed to the owner of the property, the owner must pay to the municipality all or a portion of the amount of the tax exempted, with interest.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-050__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may by ordinance exempt from taxation all or part of the increase in assessed value of improvements to real property if an increase in assessed value is directly attributable to alteration of the natural features of the land, or new maintenance, repair, or renovation of an existing structure, and if the alteration, maintenance, repair, or renovation, when completed, enhances the exterior appearance or aesthetic quality of the land or structure. An exemption may not be allowed under this subsection for the construction of an improvement to a structure if the principal purpose of the improvement is to increase the amount of space for occupancy or nonresidential use in the structure or for the alteration of land as a consequence of construction activity. An exemption provided in this subsection may continue for up to four years from the date the improvement is completed, or from the date of approval for the exemption by the local assessor, whichever is later.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-050__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may by ordinance exempt from taxation all or part of the increase in assessed value of improvements to a single-family dwelling if the principal purpose of the improvement is to increase the amount of space for occupancy. An exemption provided in this subsection may continue for up to two years from the date the improvement is completed, or from the date of approval of an application for the exemption by the local assessor, whichever is later.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-050__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may by ordinance partially or wholly exempt land from a tax for fire protection service and fire protection facilities and may levy the tax only on improvements, including personal property affixed to the improvements.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-050__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may by ordinance approved by the voters exempt from taxation the assessed value that exceeds $150,000 of real property owned and occupied as a permanent place of abode by a resident who is</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-050__subsec_i__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>65 years of age or older;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-050__subsec_i__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a disabled veteran, including a person who was disabled in the line of duty while serving in the Alaska Territorial Guard; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-050__subsec_i__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>at least 60 years old and a widow or widower of a person who qualified for an exemption under (1) or (2) of this subsection.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-050__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may by ordinance approved by the voters exempt real or personal property in a taxing unit used in processing timber after it has been delivered to the processing site from up to 75 percent of the rate of taxes levied on other property in that taxing unit. An ordinance adopted under this subsection may not provide for an exemption that exceeds five years in duration. In this subsection, taxing unit means a municipality and includes</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-050__subsec_j__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a service area in a unified municipality or borough;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-050__subsec_j__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the entire area outside cities in a borough; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-050__subsec_j__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a differential tax zone in a city.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-050__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may by ordinance approved by the voters exempt from taxation pollution control facilities that meet requirements of the United States Environmental Protection Agency or the Department of Environmental Conservation. An ordinance adopted under this subsection may not provide for an exemption that exceeds five years in duration.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-050__subsec_l">
              <num>(l)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may by ordinance exempt from taxation an interest, other than record ownership, in real property of an individual residing in the property if the property has been developed, improved, or acquired with federal funds for low-income housing and is owned or managed as low-income housing by the Alaska Housing Finance Corporation under
AS 18.55.100
 18.55.960 or by a regional housing authority formed under
AS 18.55.996
. However, the corporation may make payments to the municipality or political subdivision for improvements, services, and facilities furnished by it for the benefit of a housing project, and this subsection does not prohibit a municipality from receiving those payments or any payments in lieu of taxes authorized under federal law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-050__subsec_m">
              <num>(m)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may by ordinance partially or totally exempt all or some types of economic development property from taxation for a designated period. A municipality may by ordinance permit deferral of payment of taxes on all or some types of economic development property for a designated period. A municipality may apply an exemption or deferral under this subsection to taxes levied for special services in a service area that is supervised by an elected service area board under
AS 29.35.460
unless the elected service area board objects to the exemption or deferral by resolution adopted not later than 60 days after the effective date of the municipal ordinance enacting the tax exemption or deferral. A municipality may adopt an ordinance under this subsection only if, before it is adopted, copies of the proposed ordinance made available at a public hearing on it contain written notice that the ordinance, if adopted, may be repealed by the voters through referendum. An ordinance adopted under this subsection must include specific eligibility requirements and require a written application for each exemption or deferral.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-050__subsec_n">
              <num>(n)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may by ordinance classify as to type inventories intended for export outside the state and partially or totally exempt all or some types of those inventories from taxation. The ordinance may provide for different levels of exemption for different classifications of inventories. An ordinance adopted under this subsection must include specific eligibility requirements and require a written application, which shall be a public document, for each exemption.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-050__subsec_o">
              <num>(o)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may by ordinance partially or totally exempt all or some types of deteriorated property from taxation for up to 10 years beginning on or any time after the day substantial rehabilitation, renovation, demolition, removal, or replacement of any structure on the property begins. A municipality may by ordinance permit deferral of payment of taxes on all or some types of deteriorated property for up to five years beginning on or any time after the day substantial rehabilitation, renovation, demolition, removal, or replacement of any structure on the property begins. However, if the entire ownership of property for which a deferral has been granted is transferred, all tax payments deferred under this subsection are immediately due, and the deferral ends. Otherwise, deferred tax payments become due as specified by the municipality at the time the deferral is granted. The amount deferred each year is a lien on that property for that year. Only one exemption and only one deferral may be granted to the same property under this subsection, and, if an exemption and a deferral are granted to the same property, both may not be in effect on the same portion of the property during the same time. An ordinance adopted under this subsection must include specific eligibility requirements and require a written application for each exemption or deferral. An application for a deferral must specify when payment of taxes for each year of deferral will become due, together with an explanation of the reasons for each proposed date for consideration by the municipality. In this subsection, deteriorated property means real property that, either at the time of application for exemption or deferral or at the time of completion of the project for which an exemption or deferral is requested, is</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-050__subsec_o__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>residential property located in a deteriorating or deteriorated area with boundaries that have been determined by the municipality, if the property is owned by an entity that owns at least two residential properties and eight or more residential units among those properties in that deteriorating or deteriorated area; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-050__subsec_o__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>commercial property not used for residential purposes or that is multi-unit residential property with at least eight residential units, and that meets one of the following requirements:
(A) within the last five years, has been the subject of an order by a government agency requiring environmental remediation of the property or requiring the property to be vacated, condemned, or demolished by reason of noncompliance with laws, ordinances, or regulations;
(B) has a structure on it not less than 15 years of age that has not undergone substantial rehabilitation, renovation, demolition, removal, or replacement, subject to any conditions prescribed in the ordinance; or
(C) is located in a deteriorating or deteriorated area with boundaries that have been determined by the municipality.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-050__subsec_p">
              <num>(p)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may by ordinance partially or totally exempt from taxation a private leasehold, contract, or other interest held by or through an applicant or proposed applicant in any property, assets, project, or development project owned by the Alaska Industrial Development and Export Authority under
AS 44.88
. Nothing in this subsection prohibits a municipality from entering into an agreement and receiving payments in lieu of taxes authorized under
AS 44.88.140
(b).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-050__subsec_q">
              <num>(q)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may by ordinance partially or totally exempt from taxation land from which timber is harvested that is infested by insects or at risk of being infested by insects due to an infestation in the area in which the land is located. A municipality may provide that an exemption for land under this subsection applies only to increases in assessed value that result from the timber harvest. A municipality may by ordinance partially or totally exempt from taxation improvements to real property, including personal property affixed to the improvements, if the improvements are</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-050__subsec_q__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>located on land from which timber is harvested that is infested by insects or at risk of being infested by insects due to an infestation in the area in which the land is located; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-050__subsec_q__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>used for or necessary to the harvest of the timber that is infested by insects or in danger of insect infestation.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-050__subsec_r">
              <num>(r)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may by ordinance exempt from taxation an amount not to exceed $10,000 of the assessed value of real property owned and occupied as a permanent place of abode by a resident who provides in the municipality volunteer (1) fire fighting services and is certified as a firefighter by the Department of Public Safety, or (2) emergency medical services or mobile intensive care paramedic services and is certified or licensed under
AS 18.08.082
. If two or more individuals are eligible for an exemption for the same property, not more than two exemptions may be granted.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-050__subsec_s">
              <num>(s)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may by ordinance partially or wholly exempt from taxation the real property owned and occupied as a permanent place of abode by a resident who is the widow or widower of a member of the armed forces of the United States injured serving on active duty while eligible for hostile fire or imminent danger pay who dies because of the injury or complications related to the injury or its treatment. The ordinance must include requirements for determining eligibility for the exemption and a procedure for applying for the exemption.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-050__subsec_t">
              <num>(t)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may by ordinance partially or totally exempt from taxation farm land and farm structures used exclusively for farming activity, or purposes directly related to farming activity, if the farm land or farm structure meets the criteria set out in this subsection. The farm land or farm structure must be owned or leased by a person that is actively engaged in farming, and the owner or lessee must sell at least $2,500 of agricultural products produced from the land during the tax year and file an Internal Revenue Service Schedule F (Form 1040) with the United States Internal Revenue Service. The farm land or farm structure must be used for</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-050__subsec_t__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the growing, storage, or processing of grains, fruits, vegetables, aquatic farm products as defined in
AS 16.40.199
, or other crops specified by ordinance and produced by the owner's or lessee's farming activity;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-050__subsec_t__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the storage or processing of
(A) feed for livestock;
(B)  livestock, poultry, or other animals used in the owner's or lessee's farming activity;
(C) milk or milk products produced by the owner's or lessee's farming activity; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-050__subsec_t__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>sheltering, stabling, or milking the owner's or lessee's dairy animals, poultry, or livestock.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-050__subsec_u">
              <num>(u)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may by ordinance classify and exempt or partially exempt from taxation all or a portion of privately owned real property rented or leased for use as a charter school established under
AS 14.03.250
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-050__subsec_v">
              <num>(v)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may by ordinance exempt or partially exempt from taxation for up to 10 years property in a military facility zone that creates or supports industry, development, or educational or training opportunities beneficial to a facility. An ordinance adopted under this subsection must include specific eligibility requirements and require a written application for each exemption. In this subsection, facility and military facility zone have the meanings given in
AS 26.30.900
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-050__subsec_w">
              <num>(w)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may by ordinance partially or wholly exempt from taxation all or a portion of the increase in assessed value directly attributable to the subdivision of a single parcel of property into three or more parcels and any improvements made to the property necessitated by its subdivision. An ordinance adopted under this subsection may not provide for an exemption that exceeds five years in duration. A municipality may also by ordinance provide that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-050__subsec_w__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the exemption is terminated when
(A) a lot in the subdivision is sold; or
(B) a residential or commercial use is established on a lot in the subdivision; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-050__subsec_w__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the exemption continues for the unsold lots in the subdivision after
(A) a lot in the subdivision is sold; or
(B) a residential or commercial use is established on a lot in the subdivision.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-050__subsec_x">
              <num>(x)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may by ordinance exempt from taxation up to two percent of the assessed value of a structure if the structure contains a fire protection system that is approved under
AS 18.70.081
, in operating condition, and incorporated as a fixture or part of the structure. An exemption under this subsection is limited to an amount that does not exceed two percent of the value of the structure based on the assessment</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-050__subsec_x__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for 1981, if the fire protection system was a fixture of the structure on January 1, 1981; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-050__subsec_x__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>as of January 1 of the year immediately following the installation of the fire protection system, if the fire protection system became a fixture of the structure after January 1, 1981.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-050__subsec_y">
              <num>(y)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In the event that an owner or lessee of farm use land does not sell $2,500 of agricultural products produced from the land during a tax year because of circumstances beyond the control of the owner or lessee, the owner may secure the exemption under (t) of this section if the farm use land qualified for the exemption under (t) of this section for the three preceding tax years. In this subsection, circumstances beyond the control of the owner or lessee includes crop failure or physical injury that prevents the owner or lessee from conducting farming activity.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-050__subsec_z">
              <num>(z)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, farming activity means raising and harvesting crops; feeding, breeding, and managing livestock; dairying; propagating, farming, or cultivating an aquatic farm product as defined in
AS 16.40.199
; or any combination of those activities.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-051">
            <num>29.45.051</num>
            <heading>Tax deferral for certain subdivided property.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-051__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may by ordinance permit deferral of payment of taxes on all or a portion of the increase in assessed value directly attributable to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-051__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the subdivision of a single parcel of property into three or more parcels; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-051__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>any improvements made to the property necessitated by its subdivision.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-051__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A deferral from taxation allowed under (a) of this section shall be limited to a maximum period of five years. A municipality may by ordinance provide for the deferral of payment of taxes permitted under (a) of this section to be of a shorter duration.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-051__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subject to (b) of this section, a municipality may also by ordinance provide that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-051__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the deferral is terminated when
(A) a lot in the subdivision is sold; or
(B) a residential or commercial building is built on a lot in the subdivision; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-051__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the deferral continues for the unsold lots in the subdivision after
(A) a lot in the subdivision is sold; or
(B) a residential or commercial building is constructed on a lot in the subdivision.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-052">
            <num>29.45.052</num>
            <heading>Tax deferral for primary residences.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-052__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may by ordinance provide for the deferral of all taxes on property that is owned, in whole or in part, by an individual</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-052__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>who occupies and has occupied the property for at least 10 consecutive years as the individual's primary residence; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-052__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>whose income is at or below federal poverty guidelines for the state set by the United States Department of Health and Human Services.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-052__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An individual must apply for each year that a deferral is sought and supply proof of eligibility for the deferral for that year in accordance with requirements set out in the ordinance that authorizes the deferral. Taxes for a year that are deferred do not become payable until ownership of the property is transferred from the individual who obtained the deferral. A municipality that provides for a deferral of property taxes under this subsection may not impose interest on the taxes deferred between the time the deferral is granted and the time the taxes become payable.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-053">
            <num>29.45.053</num>
            <heading>Exemption for certain residences of law enforcement officers.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-053__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may, by ordinance, provide for the designation of areas within its boundaries that are eligible for tax exemptions on parcels of residential property. The amount of the tax exemption provided in the ordinance may not exceed $150,000 of the assessed value of a parcel. The exemption may be granted for a parcel only if it is</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-053__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>entirely within an eligible area;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-053__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>primarily used for residential purposes; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-053__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>owned and occupied as the primary place of abode by a law enforcement officer.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-053__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Only one exemption may be granted for the same parcel under an ordinance adopted under (a) of this section, and, if two or more individuals are eligible for an exemption for the same parcel, the individuals shall decide between or among themselves who is to receive the benefit of the exemption.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-053__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The municipality that adopts the ordinance under (a) of this section may not request state funds to cover any loss of revenue to the municipality caused by the ordinance.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-053__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The ordinance adopted under (a) of this section must define law enforcement officer to include only some or all positions listed in the definition of peace officer in
AS 01.10.060
or in the definition of police officer in
AS 18.65.290
. The ordinance may include other eligibility requirements for an area; however, an eligible area must</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-053__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>meet the eligibility requirements under a federal program of special assistance for urban development, neighborhood revitalization, or law enforcement, without regard to whether an application for the federal assistance on behalf of the area has been made or whether the area has received or is receiving the federal assistance;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-053__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>have a statistically higher occurrence of crime than the municipality as a whole; the crime rate for an eligible area must be established in the ordinance; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-053__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>meet the requirements of (1) and (2) of this subsection.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-053__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The municipality may establish a specific area as an eligible area for purposes of this section only in the ordinance adopted under (a) of this section or by adopting a separate ordinance. The municipality is not required to establish as an eligible area for purposes of this section every area that meets the requirements of the ordinance that is adopted under (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-055">
            <num>29.45.055</num>
            <heading>Levy of flat tax on personal property.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-055__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may by ordinance levy a flat tax on personal property that has been totally exempted from ad valorem taxes under
AS 29.45.050
(b). A municipality that levies a flat tax may classify the property as to type based on any characteristic and tax each item of property of the same type at a specific amount. A flat tax may be levied on all or on only some types of personal property. The flat tax ordinance must include a procedure under which the taxpayer may appeal the determination of ownership or classification of property subject to the tax. The municipality may establish procedures necessary to collect the tax.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-055__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (a) of this section, adoption of a flat tax does not affect the authority of a municipality to levy other taxes or impose fees on the same or other personal property or on the use, possession, sale, or lease of the same or other personal property.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-060">
            <num>29.45.060</num>
            <heading>Farm or agricultural land.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-060__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Farm use land, and structures on farm use land that are used for farm operations, included in a farm unit and not dedicated or being used for nonfarm purposes shall be assessed on the basis of full and true value for farm use and may not be assessed as if subdivided or used for some other nonfarm purpose. The assessor shall maintain records valuing the land for both full and true value and farm use value. If the land is sold, leased, or otherwise disposed of for uses incompatible with farm use or converted to a use incompatible with farm use by the owner, the owner is liable to pay an amount equal to the additional tax at the current mill levy together with eight percent interest for the preceding seven years, as though the land had not been assessed for farm use purposes. Payment by the owner shall be made to the state to the extent of its reimbursement for revenue loss under (d) of this section for the preceding seven years. The balance of the payment shall be made to the municipality.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-060__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An owner of farm use land shall, to secure the assessment under this section, apply to the assessor on or before May 15 of each year in which the assessment is desired. The application shall be made on forms prescribed by the state assessor for the use of the local assessor, and must include information that may reasonably be required to determine the entitlement of the applicant. If the land is leased for farm use purposes, the applicant shall furnish to the assessor a copy of the lease bearing the signatures of both lessee and lessor along with the completed application. The applicant shall furnish the assessor a copy of the lease covering the period for which the exemption is requested. This subsection does not apply to a person with an interest in land that is classified by the state for agricultural use or that is restricted by the state for agricultural purposes.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-060__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In the event that an owner or lessee of farm use land does not sell $2,500 of agricultural products produced from the land during a tax year because of circumstances beyond the control of the owner or lessee, the owner may secure the assessment under this section if the farm use land qualified for the assessment under this section for the three preceding tax years. In this subsection, circumstances beyond the control of the owner or lessee includes crop failure or physical injury that prevents the owner or lessee from conducting farming activity.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-060__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subject to legislative appropriations for the purpose, the state shall reimburse a borough or city, as appropriate, for the property tax revenues lost to it by the operation of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-060__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>All land that is classified by the state for agricultural use or that is restricted by the state for agricultural purposes shall be assessed on the basis of full and true value based upon that restricted use.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-060__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This section does not apply to land for which the owner has granted, and has outstanding, a lease or option to buy the surface rights. A property owner wishing to file for farm use classification having no history of farm-related income may submit a declaration of intent at the time of filing the application with the assessor setting out the intended use of the land and certifying that the property owner intends to file an Internal Revenue Service Schedule F (Form 1040) with the United States Internal Revenue Service for the current tax year. An applicant using this procedure shall file with the assessor on or before April 15 of the following year a copy of the Schedule F (Form 1040) the applicant files with the Internal Revenue Service. Failure to make a filing required in this subsection forfeits the exemption.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-060__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-060__subsec_g__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>farm use means the use of land for the production of crops, fruits, or other agricultural products for human or animal consumption or for the sustenance or grazing of livestock if the owner or lessee sells at least $2,500 of agricultural products produced from the land during the tax year and files an Internal Revenue Service Schedule F (Form 1040) with the United States Internal Revenue Service;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-060__subsec_g__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>livestock includes cattle, hogs, sheep, goats, chickens, turkeys, pigeons, and other poultry raised to provide meat or other products for human consumption.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-062">
            <num>29.45.062</num>
            <heading>Land subject to a conservation easement.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-062__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Land that is subject to a conservation easement created under
AS 34.17.010
 34.17.060 and used consistent with the conservation easement shall be assessed on the basis of full and true value for use subject to the conservation easement and may not be assessed as though it was not subject to the conservation easement. The assessor shall maintain records valuing the land for both full and true value and value subject to the conservation easement. The municipality may, by ordinance, require that if the land is sold, leased, or otherwise disposed of for uses incompatible with the conservation easement or if the conservation easement is conveyed to the owner of the property, the owner shall pay to the municipality an amount equal to the additional tax at the current mill levy together with eight percent interest for the preceding 10 years, as though the land had not been assessed subject to the conservation easement.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-062__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To secure the assessment under this section, an owner of land subject to a conservation easement shall apply to the assessor before May 15 of each year in which the assessment is desired. The application must be made upon forms prescribed by the assessor and must include information that may reasonably be required to determine the entitlement of the applicant.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-065">
            <num>29.45.065</num>
            <heading>Assessment of private airports open for public use.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-065__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may provide by ordinance that airports located on private land and open and available for public use may be assessed at full and true value for airport use and not as if subdivided or used for some other nonairport use. The assessor shall maintain records valuing the land at both full and true value and airport use value. If the land is sold, leased, or otherwise disposed of for uses incompatible with airport use by the public or if the owner converts the land to a use incompatible with airport use by the public, the owner is liable to pay an amount equal to the additional tax at the current mill levy together with eight percent interest from the time of the incompatibility, as if the land had not been assessed for airport use. Payment of the additional tax and interest shall be made to the municipality.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-065__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To secure the assessment under this section, the owner of the airport shall show that the airport is on private land, is open and available for public use, and is of benefit to the public or municipality. The owner shall apply to the assessor before May 15 of each year that the assessment is desired on forms to be prescribed by the municipality for use of the local assessor and shall include information reasonably required to determine the entitlement of the applicant. If the land is leased for airport purposes, the applicant shall furnish the assessor with a copy of the lease bearing the signature of both the lessee and lessor for the period that the exemption is requested.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-065__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, airport means an area of land or water that is used for the landing, takeoff, movement, or parking of aircraft, and the appurtenant areas that are used for airport buildings or other airport facilities or right-of-way, together with airport buildings and facilities at the location.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-070">
            <num>29.45.070</num>
            <heading>Mobile homes.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 29.45.070.   Mobile homes.
Mobile homes, trailers, house trailers, trailer coaches, and similar property used or intended to be used for residential, office, or commercial purposes and permanently affixed to real property under
AS 34.85.150
are classified as real property for tax purposes unless expressly classified as personal property by ordinance. This section does not apply to house trailers and mobile homes that are unoccupied and held for sale by persons engaged in the business of selling mobile homes. In this section, mobile home has the meaning given to manufactured home in
AS 45.29.102
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-080">
            <num>29.45.080</num>
            <heading>Tax on oil and gas production and pipeline property.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-080__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may levy and collect taxes on taxable property taxable under
AS 43.56
only by using one of the methods set out in (b) or (c) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-080__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may levy and collect a tax on the full and true value of taxable property taxable under
AS 43.56
as valued by the Department of Revenue at a rate not to exceed that which produces an amount of revenue from the total municipal property tax equivalent to $1,500 a year for each person residing in its boundaries.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-080__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may levy and collect a tax on the full and true value of that portion of taxable property taxable under
AS 43.56
as assessed by the Department of Revenue which value, when combined with the value of property otherwise taxable by the municipality, does not exceed the product of the percentage determined in (f) of this section of the average per capita assessed full and true value of property in the state multiplied by the number of residents of the taxing municipality.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-080__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each assessment year, a taxing municipality shall inform the Department of Revenue, by</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-080__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>February 1, which method of taxation the municipality will use; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-080__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>May 1, the
(A) total value of the municipality's locally assessed property tax base; and
(B) payment amount for the principal of and interest on bonds that the municipality intends to apply in its mill rate calculation for the fiscal year corresponding to the tax year for which the assessment method selected by the municipality under this section will apply.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-080__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of this section, population shall be determined by the commissioner based on the latest statistics of the United States Bureau of the Census or on other reliable population data, and the commissioner shall advise each municipality of its population by January 15 of each year.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-080__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The percentage in (c) of this section is based on the total tax rate established by the municipality and levied each year under
AS 43.56.010</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-080__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and is as follows:
If the tax rate determined under
AS 43.56.010</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-080__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>is:The percentage is:
Not more than 18.0 mills375 percent
More than 18.0 mills but not more than 19.0 mills300 percent
More than 19.0 mills225 percent</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-090">
            <num>29.45.090</num>
            <heading>Tax limitation.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-090__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may not, during a year, levy an ad valorem tax for any purpose in excess of three percent of the assessed value of property in the municipality. All property on which an ad valorem tax is levied shall be taxed at the same rate during the year.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-090__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality, or combination of municipalities occupying the same geographical area, in whole or in part, may not levy taxes</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-090__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>that will result in tax revenues from all sources exceeding $1,500 a year for each person residing within the municipal boundaries; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-090__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>on value that, when combined with the value of property otherwise taxable by the municipality, exceeds the product of the percentage determined in (e) of this section of the average per capita assessed full and true value of property in the state multiplied by the number of residents of the taxing municipality.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-090__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall apportion the lawful levy and equitably divide the tax revenues on the basis of need, services performed, and other considerations in the public interest if two or more municipalities occupying the same geographical area, in whole or in part, attempt to levy a tax</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-090__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the combined levy of which would result in tax revenues from all sources exceeding $1,500 a year for each person residing within the municipal boundaries; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-090__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>on value that, when combined with the value of property otherwise taxable by the municipality, exceeds the product of the percentage determined in (e) of this section of the average per capita assessed full and true value of property in the state multiplied by the number of residents of the taxing municipality.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-090__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For the purpose of (b) and (c) of this section, population shall be determined by the commissioner based on the latest statistics of the United States Bureau of the Census or on other reliable population data.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-090__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The percentage in (b) and (c) of this section is based on the total tax rate established by the municipality and levied each year under
AS 43.56.010</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-090__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and is as follows:
If the tax rate determined under
AS 43.56.010</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-090__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>is:The percentage is:
Not more than 18.0 mills375 percent
More than 18.0 mills but not more than 19.0 mills300 percent
More than 19.0 mills225 percent</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-100">
            <num>29.45.100</num>
            <heading>No limitations on taxes to pay bonds.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 29.45.100.   No limitations on taxes to pay bonds.
The limitations provided for in
AS 29.45.080
 29.45.090 do not apply to taxes levied or pledged to pay or secure the payment of the principal and interest on bonds. Taxes to pay or secure the payment of principal and interest on bonds may be levied without limitation as to rate or amount, regardless of whether the bonds are in default or in danger of default.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-101">
            <num>29.45.101</num>
            <heading>Limitation on taxation of fuel.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 29.45.101.   Limitation on taxation of fuel.
A municipality may not levy or collect a property tax under
AS 29.45.010
or 29.45.055 on refined fuel unless the fuel has been physically loaded, unloaded, or stored in the municipality.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-103">
            <num>29.45.103</num>
            <heading>Taxation records.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-103__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Municipal records dealing with assessment, valuation, or taxation may be inspected by the state assessor or a designee.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-103__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a municipality's assessment and valuation has been done by a private contractor, records concerning the municipality's valuation and assessment shall be made available to the state assessor or a designee on request.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-103__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon request, a record described in (a) or (b) of this section shall promptly be made available to the child support services agency created in
AS 25.27.010
or the child support enforcement agency of another state. If the record is prepared or maintained in an electronic data base, it may be supplied by providing the requesting agency with a copy of the electronic records and a statement certifying its contents. The agency receiving information under this subsection may use the information only for child support purposes authorized under law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-105">
            <num>29.45.105</num>
            <heading>Errors in taxation procedures.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-105__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a municipality receives a notice from the state assessor that major errors have been found in its assessment, valuation, or taxation procedures, the municipality shall correct its procedures before the beginning of the next fiscal year or file an appeal under (b) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-105__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may appeal a notice from the state assessor that it has made a major error in assessment, valuation, or taxation procedures by filing an appeal with the commissioner within 30 days after receipt of notice of error.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-105__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner, after consulting with the Alaska Association of Assessing Officers, shall render a decision within 60 days after the receipt of a request under (b) of this section. If the commissioner determines that a major error has been made in assessment, valuation, or taxation procedures the commissioner shall notify the municipality of changes that must be made and the municipality shall correct its procedures before the beginning of the next fiscal year.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-105__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If errors in its assessment, valuation, or taxation procedures have resulted in a loss of revenue to the state, the municipality shall reimburse the state for the amount of revenues lost.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-110">
            <num>29.45.110</num>
            <heading>Full and true value.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-110__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The assessor shall assess property at its full and true value as of January 1 of the assessment year, except as provided in this section,
AS 29.45.060
, and 29.45.230. The full and true value is the estimated price that the property would bring in an open market and under the then prevailing market conditions in a sale between a willing seller and a willing buyer both conversant with the property and with prevailing general price levels. The assessor shall determine the full and true value as provided in standards adopted by the department under (e) of this section or another set of standards provided by ordinance.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-110__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Assessment of business inventories may be based on the average monthly method of assessment rather than the value existing on January 1.  The method used to assess business inventories shall be prescribed by the governing body.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-110__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In the case of cessation of business during the tax year, the municipality may provide for reassessment of business inventories using the average monthly method of assessment for the tax year rather than the value existing on January 1 of the tax year, and for reduction and refund of taxes.  In enacting an ordinance authorized by this section, the municipality may prescribe procedures, restrictions, and conditions of assessing or reassessing business inventories and of remitting or refunding taxes.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-110__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The provisions of this subsection apply to determine the full and true value of property that qualifies for a low-income housing credit under 26 U.S.C. 42:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-110__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>when the assessor acts to determine the full and true value of property that qualifies for a low-income housing credit under 26 U.S.C. 42, instead of assessing the property under (a) of this section, the assessor shall base assessment of the value of the property on the actual income derived from the property and may not adjust it based on the amount of any federal income tax credit given for the property; for property the full and true value of which is to be determined under this paragraph, to secure an assessment under this subsection, an owner of property that qualifies for the low-income housing credit shall apply to the assessor before May 15 of each year in which the assessment is desired; the property owner shall submit the application on forms prescribed by the assessor and shall include information that may reasonably be required to determine the entitlement of the applicant;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-110__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the governing body of the municipality shall determine by ordinance whether the full and true value of all property within the municipality that first qualifies for a low-income housing credit under 26 U.S.C. 42 on and after January 1, 2001, shall be exempt from the requirement of assessment under (1) of this subsection; thereafter, for property that first qualifies for a low-income housing credit under 26 U.S.C. 42 on and after January 1, 2001, and that, by ordinance, is exempt from the requirement of mandatory assessment under (1) of this subsection, the governing body
(A) may determine, by parcel, whether the property shall be assessed under (a) of this section or on the basis of actual income derived from the property without adjustment based on the amount of any federal income tax credit given for the property, as authorized by (1) of this subsection; and
(B) may not, under (A) of this paragraph, change the manner of assessment of the parcel of property if debt relating to the property incurred in conjunction with the property's qualifying for the low-income housing tax credit remains outstanding.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-110__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall adopt standards for assessing the full and true value of property under (a) of this section that are not inconsistent with standards adopted by the International Association of Assessing Officers and update the standards when necessary.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-115">
            <num>29.45.115</num>
            <heading>Assessor certification.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 29.45.115.   Assessor certification.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-120">
            <num>29.45.120</num>
            <heading>Returns.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-120__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The municipality may require each person having ownership or control of or an interest in property to submit a return in the form prescribed by the assessor, based on property values of property subject to an ad valorem tax existing on January 1, except as otherwise provided in this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-120__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The assessor may, by written notice, require a person to provide additional information within 30 days.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-130">
            <num>29.45.130</num>
            <heading>Independent investigation.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-130__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The assessor is not bound to accept a return as correct. The assessor may make an independent investigation of property returned or of taxable property on which no return has been filed. In either case, the assessor may make the assessor's own valuation of the property subject to an ad valorem tax and this valuation is prima facie evidence of the value of the property.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-130__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For investigation, the assessor or the assessor's agent may enter real property during reasonable hours to examine visible personal property and the exterior of a dwelling or other structure on the real property. The assessor or the assessor's agent may enter and examine the interior of a dwelling or other structure or the personal property in it only (1) if the structure is under construction and not yet occupied; (2) with the permission of a person in actual possession of the structure; or (3) in accordance with a court order to compel the entry and inspection. The assessor or the assessor's agent may examine all property records involved. A person shall, on request, furnish to the assessor or the assessor's agent assistance for the investigation and permit the assessor or the assessor's agent to enter a dwelling or other structure to examine the structure or personal property in it during reasonable hours. The assessor may seek a court order to compel entry and production of records needed for assessment purposes.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-130__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An assessor may examine a person on oath.  On request, the person shall submit to examination at a reasonable time and place selected by the assessor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-140">
            <num>29.45.140</num>
            <heading>Violations; authorization to prescribe penalties by ordinance.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 29.45.140.   Violations; authorization to prescribe penalties by ordinance.
For knowingly failing to file a tax statement required by ordinance or knowingly making a false affidavit to a statement required by a tax ordinance relative to the amount, location, kind, or value of property subject to taxation with intent to evade the taxation, a municipality may by ordinance prescribe a penalty not to exceed a fine of $1,000 or imprisonment for 90 days.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-150">
            <num>29.45.150</num>
            <heading>Reevaluation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 29.45.150.   Reevaluation.
A systematic reevaluation of taxable real and personal property undertaken by the assessor, whether of specific areas in which real property is located or of specific classes of real or personal property to be assessed, shall be made only in accordance with a resolution or other act of the municipality directing a systematic reevaluation of all taxable property in the municipality over the shortest period of time practicable, as fixed in the resolution or act.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-160">
            <num>29.45.160</num>
            <heading>Assessment roll.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-160__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The assessor shall prepare an annual assessment roll. The roll must contain</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-160__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a description of all property subject to an ad valorem tax;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-160__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the assessed value of all property subject to an ad valorem tax;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-160__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the names and addresses of persons with property subject to an ad valorem tax.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-160__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The assessor may list real property by any description that may be made certain. Real property is assessed to the record owner. The district recorder shall at least monthly provide the assessor a copy of each recorded change of ownership showing the name and mailing address of the owner and the name and mailing address of the person recording the change of ownership. Other persons having an interest in the property may be listed on the assessment records with the owner. The person in whose name property is listed as owner is conclusively presumed to be the legal record owner. If the property owner is unknown, the property may be assessed to unknown owner. An assessment is not invalidated by a mistake, omission, or error in the name of the owner, if the property is correctly described.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-170">
            <num>29.45.170</num>
            <heading>Assessment notice.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-170__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The assessor shall give each person named in the assessment roll a notice of assessment showing the assessed value of the person's property that is subject to an ad valorem tax. On each notice is printed a brief summary of the dates when taxes are payable, delinquent, and subject to penalty and interest, and the dates when the board of equalization will sit.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-170__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Sufficient assessment notice is given if mailed by first class mail 30 days before the equalization hearings. If the address is not known to the assessor, the notice may be addressed to the person at the post office nearest the property.  Notice is effective on the date of mailing.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-180">
            <num>29.45.180</num>
            <heading>Questions and corrections.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-180__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person receiving an assessment notice shall advise the assessor of errors or omissions in the assessment of the person's property. If requested by the person, the assessor or a person designated by the assessor shall meet with the person and answer reasonable questions relating to the methods used to assess the person's property. The meeting required under this subsection may be virtual or telephonic. The assessor may correct errors or omissions in the roll before the board of equalization hearing.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-180__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If errors found in the preparation of the assessment roll are adjusted, the assessor shall mail a corrected notice allowing 30 days for appeal to the board of equalization.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-190">
            <num>29.45.190</num>
            <heading>Appeal.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-190__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person whose name appears on the assessment roll or the agent or assigns of that person may appeal to the board of equalization for relief from an alleged error in valuation not adjusted by the assessor to the taxpayer's satisfaction.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-190__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The appellant shall, within 30 days after the date of mailing of notice of assessment, submit to the assessor a written appeal specifying grounds in the form that the board of equalization may require.  Otherwise, the right of appeal ceases unless the board of equalization finds that the taxpayer was unable to comply.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-190__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The assessor shall notify an appellant by mail of the time and place of hearing.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-190__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The assessor shall prepare for use by the board of equalization a summary of assessment data relating to each assessment that is appealed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-190__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A city in a borough may appeal an assessment to the borough board of equalization in the same manner as a taxpayer. Within five days after receipt of the appeal, the assessor shall notify the person whose property assessment is being appealed by the city.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-200">
            <num>29.45.200</num>
            <heading>Board of equalization.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-200__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The governing body shall appoint one or more boards of equalization for the purpose of hearing an appeal from a determination of the assessor. An appointed board shall be composed of not less than three persons, who shall be members of the governing body, municipal residents, or a combination of members of the governing body and residents. The governing body shall by ordinance establish the qualifications for membership. The governing body may by ordinance appoint itself to sit as a board of equalization.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-200__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board of equalization is governed in its proceedings by rules adopted by ordinance that are consistent with general rules of administrative procedure. The board may alter an assessment of a lot only pursuant to an appeal filed as to the particular lot.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-200__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding other provisions in this section, a determination of the assessor as to whether property is taxable under law may be appealed directly to the superior court.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-210">
            <num>29.45.210</num>
            <heading>Hearing.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-210__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If an appellant fails to appear, the board of equalization may proceed with the hearing in the absence of the appellant.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-210__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The appellant bears the burden of proof. The only grounds for adjustment of assessment are proof of unequal, excessive, improper, or under valuation based on facts that are stated in a valid written appeal or proven at the appeal hearing. The board of equalization may not raise the assessment in the current year unless requested to do so by the appellant. If the appellant provides a long form fee appraisal to support the appellant's valuation and the board of equalization does not find in favor of the appellant, the board shall make specific findings on the record to support its decision.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-210__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board of equalization shall certify its actions to the assessor within seven days. Except as to supplementary assessments, the assessor shall enter the changes and certify the final assessment roll by June 1.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-210__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An appellant or the assessor may appeal a determination of the board of equalization to the superior court as provided by rules of court applicable to appeals from the decisions of administrative agencies.  Appeals are heard on the record established at the hearing before the board of equalization.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-220">
            <num>29.45.220</num>
            <heading>Supplementary assessment rolls.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 29.45.220.   Supplementary assessment rolls.
The assessor shall include property omitted from the assessment roll on a supplementary roll, using the procedures set out in this chapter for the original roll.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-230">
            <num>29.45.230</num>
            <heading>Tax adjustments on property affected by a disaster.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-230__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The municipality may by ordinance provide for assessment or reassessment and reduction of taxes for property destroyed, damaged, or otherwise reduced in value as a result of a disaster.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-230__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An assessment or reassessment under this section may be made by the assessor only upon the receipt of a sworn statement of the taxpayer that losses exceed $1,000. A reduction of taxes may be made only on losses in excess of $1,000 for the remainder of the year following the disaster.  On reassessment, the municipality shall recompute this tax and refund taxes that have already been paid.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-230__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The municipality shall give notice of assessment or reassessment under this section and shall hold an equalization hearing as provided in this chapter, except that a notice of appeal must be filed with the board of equalization within 10 days after notice of assessment or reassessment is given to the person appealing.  Otherwise, the right of appeal ceases unless the board finds that the taxpayer is unable to comply.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-230__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In an ordinance authorized by this section, the municipality shall establish criteria for the reduction of taxes on property damaged, destroyed, or otherwise reduced in value as a result of disaster, and may, consistent with this section, prescribe procedures, restrictions, and conditions for assessing or reassessing property and for remitting, refunding, or forgiving taxes.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-230__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 3 ch 1 SLA 2004.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-240">
            <num>29.45.240</num>
            <heading>Establishment of levy and determination of rate.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-240__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The power granted to a municipality to assess, levy, and collect a property tax shall be exercised by means of an ordinance.  The rate of levy, the date of equalization, and the date when taxes become delinquent shall be fixed by resolution.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-240__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality shall annually determine the rate of levy before June 15.  By July 1 the tax collector shall mail tax statements setting out the levy, dates when taxes are payable and delinquent, and penalties and interest.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-250">
            <num>29.45.250</num>
            <heading>Rates of penalty and interest.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-250__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A penalty not to exceed 20 percent of the tax due may be added to all delinquent taxes, and interest not to exceed 15 percent a year shall accrue upon all unpaid taxes, not including penalty, from the due date until paid in full.  A municipality may impose a penalty not to exceed 20 percent of the tax due upon the late return of personal property assessment forms.  A penalty under this section may be imposed according to a formula that increases the amount of the penalty as the length of time increases during which payment is delinquent or assessment forms are not returned.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-250__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a taxpayer is given the right to pay the tax in two installments, penalty and interest on an unpaid installment accrues from the date the installment becomes due.
Article 2. Enforcement of Tax Liens.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-290">
            <num>29.45.290</num>
            <heading>Validity.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 29.45.290.   Validity.
Certified assessment and tax rolls are valid and binding on all persons, notwithstanding a defect, error, omission, or invalidity in the assessment rolls or proceedings pertaining to the assessment roll.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-295">
            <num>29.45.295</num>
            <heading>Collection of delinquent taxes on certain governmental property.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 29.45.295.   Collection of delinquent taxes on certain governmental property.
AS 29.45.300
 29.45.490 do not apply to property taxable under
AS 29.45.030
(a)(1)(B) or (C) or to federal property not exempted under
AS 29.45.030
(a)(8). A municipality may bring an action in the superior court to compel payment of property taxes due from the state, municipal, or federal entity if the entity does not pay the amount due within six months after the date that the taxes are due.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-300">
            <num>29.45.300</num>
            <heading>Tax liability.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-300__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The owner of assessed personal property is personally liable for the amount of taxes assessed against the property.  The tax, together with penalty and interest, may be collected in a personal action brought in the name of the municipality.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-300__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Property taxes, together with penalty and interest, are a lien upon the property assessed, and the lien is prior and paramount to all other liens or encumbrances against the property.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-310">
            <num>29.45.310</num>
            <heading>Enforcement of personal property tax liens by distraint and sale.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-310__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A lien for personal property taxes may be enforced by distraint and sale of the property. The municipality shall provide the procedure for distraint and sale by ordinance.  A seizure, levy, or distraint is not legal unless demand is first made of the person assessed for the amount of the tax, penalty, and interest, and a sale is not valid unless made at public auction no sooner than 15 days after notice is published.  The seizure is made by virtue of a warrant issued by the municipal clerk to a peace officer.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-310__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the personal property sold is not sufficient to satisfy the tax, penalty, and interest, and costs of sale, the warrant may authorize the seizure of other personal property sufficient to satisfy the tax, penalty, interest, and costs of sale.  If the property is sold for more money than is needed to satisfy the tax, the municipality shall remit the excess to the former record owner upon presentation of a proper claim.  A claim for the excess filed after six months of the date of sale is forever barred.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-320">
            <num>29.45.320</num>
            <heading>Real property tax collection.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-320__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The municipality shall enforce delinquent real property tax liens by annual foreclosure, unless otherwise provided by ordinance.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-320__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the tax on property described in
AS 29.45.070
or on a taxable interest in tax-exempt property is not paid when due, a municipality may enforce the tax by a personal action against the delinquent taxpayer brought in the district or superior court, in addition to other remedies available to enforce the lien.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-330">
            <num>29.45.330</num>
            <heading>Foreclosure list.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-330__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-330__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>annually present a petition for judgment and a certified copy of the foreclosure list for the previous year's delinquent taxes in the superior court for judgment;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-330__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>publish the foreclosure list for four consecutive weeks in a newspaper of general circulation distributed in the municipality or, if there is no newspaper of general circulation distributed in the municipality, post the list at three public places for at least 30 days;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-330__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>within 10 days after the first publication or posting, mail to the last known owner of each property as the owner's name and address appear on the list a notice advising of the foreclosure proceeding in which a petition for judgment of foreclosure has been filed and describing the property and the amount due as stated on the list.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-330__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The list shall be arranged in alphabetical order as to the last name and must include</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-330__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the last known owner;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-330__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the property description as stated on the assessment roll;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-330__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>years and amounts of delinquency;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-330__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>penalty and interest due;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-330__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a statement that the list is available for public inspection at the clerk's office;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-330__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a statement that the list has been presented to the superior court with a petition for judgment and decree.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-330__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Completion of the requirements of (a) of this section constitutes and has the same force and effect as the filing of an individual and separate complaint and service of summons to foreclose a lien against each property described on the foreclosure list.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-340">
            <num>29.45.340</num>
            <heading>Clearing delinquencies.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 29.45.340.   Clearing delinquencies.
During the publication or posting of the foreclosure list and up to the time of transfer to the municipality a person may pay the taxes, together with the penalty, interest, and costs. The collector shall note payment on the foreclosure list.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-350">
            <num>29.45.350</num>
            <heading>List to lienholder.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 29.45.350.   List to lienholder.
A holder of a mortgage or other lien on real property may request the clerk to send by certified mail notice of a foreclosure list that includes the real property.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-360">
            <num>29.45.360</num>
            <heading>General foreclosure.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 29.45.360.   General foreclosure.
A municipality shall bring one general foreclosure proceeding in rem against the properties included in the foreclosure list.  If the owner is unknown, the property is proceeded against as belonging to unknown owner.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-370">
            <num>29.45.370</num>
            <heading>Answer and objection.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 29.45.370.   Answer and objection.
A person having an interest in a lot on the foreclosure list may file an answer within 30 days after the date of last publication, specifying the person's objection.  The court shall make its decision in summary proceedings. The foreclosure list is prima facie evidence that the assessment and levy of the tax is valid and that the tax is unpaid.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-380">
            <num>29.45.380</num>
            <heading>Judgment.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 29.45.380.   Judgment.
The court shall in a proper case give judgment and decree that the tax liens be foreclosed.  It is a several judgment against each lot and a lien on each lot.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-390">
            <num>29.45.390</num>
            <heading>Transfer and appeal.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-390__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Foreclosed properties are transferred to the municipality for the lien amount.  When answers are filed the court may enter judgment against and order the transfer to the municipality of all other properties on the list pending determination of the matters in controversy.  The court shall hear and determine the issues raised by the complaint and answers in the same manner and under the same rules as it hears and determines other actions.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-390__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The court clerk shall deliver a certified copy of the judgment and decree to the municipal clerk. The certified judgment and decree constitutes a transfer to the municipality.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-390__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The judgment and decree stops objections to it that could have been presented before judgment and decree. Appeal from a judgment and decree of foreclosure, or from a final order in the proceeding, may be taken in a manner provided for appeals in civil actions.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-400">
            <num>29.45.400</num>
            <heading>Redemption period.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 29.45.400.   Redemption period.
Properties transferred to the municipality are held by the municipality for at least one year. During the redemption period a party having an interest in the property may redeem it by paying the lien amount plus penalties, interest, and costs, including all costs incurred under
AS 29.45.440
(a). Property redeemed is subject to all accrued taxes, assessments, liens, and claims as though it had continued in private ownership. Only the amount applicable under the judgment and decree must be paid in order to redeem the property.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-410">
            <num>29.45.410</num>
            <heading>Effect.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 29.45.410.   Effect.
Receipt of redemption money by the municipality releases the judgment obtained under
AS 29.45.380
. The clerk or the clerk's designee shall record the redemption and issue a certificate containing a property description, the redemption amount, and the dates of judgment and decree of foreclosure.  The clerk or the clerk's designee shall collect the recording fee at the time of redemption and shall file the certificate with the record as part of the judgment roll.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-420">
            <num>29.45.420</num>
            <heading>Additional liens.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 29.45.420.   Additional liens.
If a property included in a foreclosure list is removed after payment of delinquencies or redemption by another lienholder, the payment represented by receipt for payment constitutes an additional lien on the property, collectible by the lienholder in the same manner as the original lien.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-430">
            <num>29.45.430</num>
            <heading>Possession during redemption period.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 29.45.430.   Possession during redemption period.
Foreclosure does not affect the former owner's right to possession during the redemption period.  If waste is committed by the former owner or by anyone acting under the permission or control of the former owner, the municipality may declare an immediate forfeiture of the right to possession.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-440">
            <num>29.45.440</num>
            <heading>Expiration.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-440__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>At least 30 days before the expiration of the redemption period the clerk or the clerk's designee shall publish a redemption period expiration notice. The notice must contain the date of judgment, the date of expiration of the period of redemption, and a warning that all properties ordered sold under the judgment, unless redeemed, shall be deeded to the municipality immediately on expiration of the period of redemption and that every right or interest of a person in the properties will be forfeited forever to the municipality.  The notice appears once a week for four consecutive weeks in a newspaper of general circulation distributed in the municipality.  If there is no newspaper of general circulation distributed in the municipality, the notice is posted in three public places for at least four consecutive weeks.  The clerk shall send a copy of the notice by certified mail to each record owner of property against which a judgment of foreclosure has been taken and, if the assessed value of the property is more than $10,000, to all holders of mortgages or other liens of record on the property.  The notice shall be mailed within five days after the first publication.  The mailing shall be sufficient if mailed to the property owner and to the holder of a mortgage or recorded lien at the last address of record.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-440__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The right of redemption expires 30 days after the date of the first notice publication.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-440__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Costs incurred in the determination of holders of mortgages and other liens of record and costs of notice publication incurred by a municipality under (a) of this section are a lien on the property and may be recovered by the municipality.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-450">
            <num>29.45.450</num>
            <heading>Deed to borough or city.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-450__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unredeemed property in the area of the borough outside all cities is deeded to the borough by the clerk of the court. Unredeemed property in a city is deeded to the city subject to the payment by the city of unpaid borough taxes and costs of foreclosure levied against the property before foreclosure. The deed shall be recorded in the recording district in which the property is located.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-450__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Conveyance gives the municipality clear title, except for prior recorded tax liens of the United States and the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-450__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If unredeemed property lies in a city and if the city has no immediate public use for the property but the borough does have an immediate public use, the city shall deed the property to the borough.  If unredeemed property lies in the borough outside all cities and if the borough does not have an immediate public use for the property but a city does have an immediate public use, the borough shall deed the property to the city.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-450__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A deed is not invalid for irregularities, omissions, or defects in the proceedings under this chapter unless the former owner has been misled so as to be injured.  Two years after the date of the deed, its validity is conclusively presumed and a claim of the former owner or other person having an interest in the property is forever barred.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-460">
            <num>29.45.460</num>
            <heading>Disposition and sale of foreclosed property.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-460__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The municipality shall determine by ordinance whether foreclosed property deeded to the municipality shall be retained for a public purpose.  The ordinance must contain the legal description of the property, the address or a general description of the property sufficient to provide the public with notice of its location, and the name of the last record owner of the property as the name appears on the assessment rolls.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-460__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Tax-foreclosed property conveyed to a municipality by tax foreclosure and not required for a public purpose may be sold.  Before the sale of tax-foreclosed property held for a public purpose, the municipality, by ordinance, shall determine that a public need does not exist.  The ordinance must contain the information required under (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-460__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The clerk or the clerk's designee shall send a copy of the published notice of hearing of an ordinance to consider a determination required under (a) or (b) of this section by certified mail to the former record owner of the property that is the subject of the ordinance.  The notice shall be mailed within five days after its first publication and shall be sufficient if mailed to the last record owner of the property as the name appears on the assessment rolls of the municipality.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-460__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The provisions of (c) of this section do not apply with respect to property that has been held by the municipality for a period of more than 10 years after the close of the redemption period.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-470">
            <num>29.45.470</num>
            <heading>Repurchase by record owner.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-470__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The record owner at the time of tax foreclosure of property acquired by a municipality, or the assigns of that record owner, may, within 10 years and before the sale or contract of sale of the tax-foreclosed property by the municipality, repurchase the property. The municipality shall sell the property for the full amount applicable to the property under the judgment and decree plus</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-470__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>interest not to exceed 15 percent a year from the date of entry of the judgment of foreclosure to the date of repurchase;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-470__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>delinquent taxes assessed and levied as though it had continued in private ownership;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-470__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>costs of foreclosure and sale incurred by the municipality; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-470__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>costs of maintaining and managing the property incurred by the municipality including insurance, repairs, association dues, and management fees, that exceed amounts received by the municipality for the use of the property.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-470__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After adoption of an ordinance providing for the retention of tax-foreclosed property by the municipality for a public purpose, the right of the former record owner to repurchase the property ceases.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-480">
            <num>29.45.480</num>
            <heading>Proceeds of tax sale.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-480__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>On sale of foreclosed real or personal property the municipality shall divide the proceeds less cost of collection between the borough and the city having unpaid taxes against the property. The division is in proportion to the respective municipal taxes against the property at the time of foreclosure.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-480__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If tax-foreclosed real property that has been held by a municipality for less than 10 years after the close of the redemption period and never designated for a public purpose is sold at a tax-foreclosure sale, the former record owner is entitled to the portion of the proceeds of the sale that exceeds the amount of unpaid taxes, the amount equal to taxes that would have been assessed and levied after foreclosure if the property had continued in private ownership, penalty, interest, and costs to the municipality of foreclosing and selling the property, and costs to the municipality of maintaining and managing the property that exceed amounts received by the municipality for the use of the property. If the proceeds of the sale of tax-foreclosed property exceed the total of unpaid and delinquent taxes, penalty, interest, and costs, the municipality shall provide the former owner of the property written notice advising of the amount of the excess and the manner in which a claim for the balance of the proceeds may be submitted. Notice is sufficient under this subsection if mailed to the former record owner at the last address of record of the former record owner. On presentation of a proper claim, the municipality shall remit the excess to the former record owner. A claim for the excess filed after six months of the date of sale is forever barred.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-490">
            <num>29.45.490</num>
            <heading>Payment of taxes upon public utilization.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 29.45.490.   Payment of taxes upon public utilization.
If a municipality takes title to tax-foreclosed property for a public purpose, the municipality shall satisfy unpaid taxes and assessments against the property held by other municipalities, with accrued interest but without penalty.  If the amount required to satisfy the unpaid taxes and assessments exceeds the assessed value of the property, the municipality shall pay the other municipalities the assessed value, which shall be divided between the other municipalities in proportion to their respective taxes and assessments against the property at the time of foreclosure.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-500">
            <num>29.45.500</num>
            <heading>Refund of taxes.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-500__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a taxpayer pays taxes under protest, the taxpayer may bring suit in the superior court against the municipality for recovery of the taxes.  If judgment for recovery is given against the municipality, or, if in the absence of suit, it becomes obvious to the governing body that judgment for recovery of the taxes would be obtained if legal proceedings were brought, the municipality shall refund the amount of the taxes to the taxpayer with interest at eight percent from the date of payment plus costs.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-500__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If, in payment of taxes legally imposed, a remittance by a taxpayer through error or otherwise exceeds the amount due, and the municipality, on audit of the account in question, is satisfied that this is the case, the municipality shall refund the excess to the taxpayer with interest at eight percent from the date of payment.  A claim for refund filed one year after the due date of the tax is forever barred.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-500__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The governing body may correct manifest clerical errors at any time.
Article 3. City Property Tax.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-550">
            <num>29.45.550</num>
            <heading>Cities outside boroughs.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 29.45.550.   Cities outside boroughs.
Home rule and first class cities outside boroughs may assess, levy, and collect a property tax.  A property tax if levied must be assessed, levied, and collected as provided by
AS 29.45.010
 29.45.500.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-560">
            <num>29.45.560</num>
            <heading>Cities inside boroughs.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 29.45.560.   Cities inside boroughs.
Home rule and first class cities inside boroughs may levy a property tax.  A property tax, if levied, is subject to
AS 29.45.010
 29.45.050, 29.45.090    29.45.100, 29.45.250, 29.45.400    29.45.440 and 29.45.460   29.45.500.  The council shall by June 15 of each year present to the assembly a statement of the city's rate of levy unless a different date is agreed upon by the borough and city.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-580">
            <num>29.45.580</num>
            <heading>Differential tax zones.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 29.45.580.   Differential tax zones.
A city may by ordinance establish, alter, and abolish differential tax zones to provide and levy property taxes for services not provided generally in the city or a different level of service than that provided generally in the city.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-590">
            <num>29.45.590</num>
            <heading>Limited property taxing power for second class cities.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 29.45.590.   Limited property taxing power for second class cities.
A second class city may by referendum levy property taxes as provided for first class cities. However, levy of an ad valorem tax by a second class city may not exceed two percent of the assessed value of the property taxed, except that the limit does not apply to a levy necessary to avoid a default upon payment of principal and interest of bonded or other indebtedness that is secured by a pledge to levy ad valorem or other taxes without limit to meet debt payments.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-600">
            <num>29.45.600</num>
            <heading>Combining property tax with incorporation of a second class city.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 29.45.600.   Combining property tax with incorporation of a second class city.
A petition for second class city incorporation may request that a property tax proposal be placed on the same ballot. The petition must state the proposed tax rate.  The petition may request that incorporation be dependent on the passage of the property tax proposition.  If so, the incorporation proposition fails if the property tax fails.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-650">
            <num>29.45.650</num>
            <heading>Sales and use tax.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-650__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in
AS 04.21.010
(c),
AS 29.45.750
, and in (f), (h), (i), (j), (k), and (l) of this section, a borough may levy and collect a sales tax on sales, rents, and services provided in the borough. The sales tax may apply to any or all of these sources. Notwithstanding other statutes, exemptions may be granted by ordinance. A borough may wholly or partially exempt a source from a borough sales tax that is taxed by a city in that borough under
AS 29.45.700
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-650__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A borough levying a sales tax may also by ordinance levy a use tax on the storage, use, or consumption of tangible personal property in the borough. The use tax rate must equal the sales tax rate and the use tax shall be levied only on buyers.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-650__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who furnishes proof, in the form required by the borough tax collector, that the person has paid a sales tax on the source on which a use tax is levied by the borough is required to pay the use tax only to the extent of the difference between the amount of the sales tax paid and the amount of the use tax levied by the borough.  This subsection applies to a sales tax levied in any taxing jurisdiction whether inside or outside the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-650__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the assembly charges interest on sales taxes not paid when due, the rate of interest may not exceed 15 percent a year on the delinquent taxes and shall be charged from the due date until paid in full.  This subsection applies to home rule and general law municipalities.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-650__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A borough may provide for the creation, recording, and notice of a lien on real or personal property to secure the payment of a sales and use tax, and the interest, penalties, and administration costs in the event of delinquency.  When recorded, the sales tax lien has priority over all other liens except (1) liens for property taxes and special assessments; (2) liens that were perfected before the recording of the sales tax lien for amounts actually advanced before the recording of the sales tax lien; (3) mechanics' and materialmen's liens for which claims of lien under
AS 34.35.070
or notices of right to lien under
AS 34.35.064
have been recorded before the recording of the sales tax lien. This subsection applies to home rule and general law municipalities.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-650__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A borough may not levy and collect a sales tax on a purchase made with (1) food coupons, food stamps, or other type of allotment issued under 7 U.S.C. 2011  2036 (Food Stamp Program); or (2) food instruments, food vouchers, or other type of certificate issued under 42 U.S.C. 1786 (Special Supplemental Food Program for Women, Infants, and Children). For purposes of this subsection, the value of a food stamp allotment paid in the form of a wage subsidy as authorized under
AS 47.25.975</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-650__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>is not considered to be an allotment issued under 7 U.S.C. 2011  2036 (Food Stamp Program). This subsection applies to home rule and general law municipalities.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-650__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 2 ch 159 SLA 1990.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-650__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A borough may not levy or collect a sales tax on sales, rents, and services, or a use tax on the storage, use, or consumption of personal property on the following activities:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-650__subsec_h__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the sale, lease, rental, storage, consumption, or distribution in this state of or the provision of services relating to an orbital space facility, space propulsion system, or space vehicle, satellite, or station of any kind possessing space flight capacity, including the components of them;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-650__subsec_h__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the sale, lease, rental, storage, consumption, or use of tangible personal property placed on or used aboard an orbital space facility, space propulsion system, or space vehicle, satellite, or station of any kind, regardless of whether the tangible personal property is returned to this state for subsequent use, storage, or consumption; an exemption under this paragraph is not affected by the failure of a launch to occur, or the destruction of a launch vehicle or a component of a launch vehicle.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-650__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A borough may not levy or collect a sales or use tax on (1) the physical transfer of refined fuel, unless the transfer is made in connection with a sale or use in the borough, or (2) wholesale sales or transfers of fuel refined in the borough. A sale is in the borough if the fuel is delivered to the buyer in the borough. A use is in the borough if the fuel is consumed in the borough. This subsection applies to home rule and general law municipalities.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-650__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The prohibitions on the levy and collection of a sales or use tax on refined fuel in (i) of this section do not apply to a borough if, on the effective date of (i) of this section, the borough is</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-650__subsec_j__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>levying and collecting a sales or use tax on the sale, use, or transfer of refined fuel under an ordinance adopted before January 1, 2003; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-650__subsec_j__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>receiving payments in lieu of a sales or use tax on the sale, use, or transfer of refined fuel under an agreement entered into before January 1, 2003.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-650__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A borough may not levy or collect a sales or use tax on a construction contract awarded by the state or a state agency, or on a subcontract awarded in connection with the project funded under the construction contract. This subsection applies to home rule and general law municipalities.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-650__subsec_l">
              <num>(l)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A borough may not levy or collect a sales or use tax on the transfer of real property. This subsection applies to home rule and general law municipalities. In this subsection, transfer has the meaning given in
AS 34.70.200
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-660">
            <num>29.45.660</num>
            <heading>Notice of sales and use tax.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-660__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the borough levies and collects only a sales tax and use tax, the assembly shall provide a notice substantially in the form set out in
AS 29.45.020
.  In providing notice under this subsection, the assembly shall substitute for the millage equivalency its estimate of the equivalent sales tax rate for each of the categories of financial assistance set out in
AS 29.45.020
. Notice shall be provided</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-660__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>by publishing in a newspaper of general circulation in the borough a copy of the notice once each week for a period of three successive weeks, with publication to occur not later than 45 days after the final adoption of the borough's budget; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-660__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if there is no newspaper of general circulation in the borough, by posting a copy of the notice for at least 20 days in at least two public places in the borough, with posting to occur not later than 45 days after the final adoption of the borough's budget.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-660__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Compliance with the provisions of this section is a prerequisite to receipt of community assistance under
AS 29.60.850
 29.60.879. The department shall withhold annual allocations under those sections until municipal officials demonstrate that the requirements of this section have been met.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-670">
            <num>29.45.670</num>
            <heading>Referendum, adoption, and modification.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 29.45.670.   Referendum, adoption, and modification.
A new sales and use tax or an increase in the rate of levy of a sales tax approved by ordinance does not take effect until ratified by a majority of the voters at an election.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-680">
            <num>29.45.680</num>
            <heading>Combining sales and use tax with incorporation of a borough.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 29.45.680.   Combining sales and use tax with incorporation of a borough.
A petition for incorporation of a borough may request that a sales and use tax proposition be placed on the same ballot. The petition must state the proposed tax rate. The petition may request that incorporation be dependent on the passage of the tax proposition; if so, the incorporation proposition fails if the tax proposition fails.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-700">
            <num>29.45.700</num>
            <heading>Power of levy.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-700__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A city in a borough that levies and collects areawide sales and use taxes may levy sales and use taxes on all sources taxed by the borough in the manner provided for boroughs. Except as provided in (d), (e), (g), and (h) of this section, the assembly may by ordinance authorize a city to levy and collect sales and use taxes on other sources.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-700__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A city in a borough that does not levy and collect sales and use taxes for areawide borough functions may levy and collect sales and use taxes in the manner provided for boroughs.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-700__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A city outside a borough may levy and collect sales and use taxes in the manner provided for boroughs.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-700__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A city that levies and collects sales and use taxes under (a) of this section may not levy and collect a sales tax on a purchase made with (1) food coupons, food stamps, or other types of allotments issued under 7 U.S.C. 2011  2036 (Food Stamp Program); or (2) food instruments, food vouchers, or other type of certificate issued under 42 U.S.C. 1786 (Special Supplemental Food Program for Women, Infants, and Children). For purposes of this subsection, the value of a food stamp allotment paid in the form of a wage subsidy as authorized under
AS 47.25.975</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-700__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>is not considered to be an allotment issued under 7 U.S.C. 2011  2036 (Food Stamp Program). This subsection applies to home rule and general law municipalities.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-700__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A city that levies and collects sales and use taxes may not levy and collect a sales or use tax on (1) the physical transfer of refined fuel, unless the transfer is made in connection with a sale or use in the city, or (2) wholesale sales or transfers of fuel refined in the city. A sale is in the city if the fuel is delivered to the buyer in the city. A use is in the city if the fuel is consumed in the city. This subsection applies to home rule and general law municipalities.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-700__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The prohibitions on the levy and collection of a sales or use tax on refined fuel in (e) of this section do not apply to a city if, on September 16, 2003, the city is</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-700__subsec_f__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>levying and collecting a sales or use tax on the sale, use, or transfer of refined fuel under an ordinance adopted before January 1, 2003; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-700__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>receiving payments in lieu of a sales or use tax on the sale, use, or transfer of refined fuel under an agreement entered into before January 1, 2003.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-700__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A city may not levy or collect a sales or use tax on a construction contract awarded by the state or a state agency, or on a subcontract awarded in connection with the project funded under the construction contract. This subsection applies to home rule and general law cities.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-700__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A city may not levy or collect a sales or use tax on the transfer of real property. This subsection applies to home rule and general law municipalities. In this subsection, transfer has the meaning given in
AS 34.70.200
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-710">
            <num>29.45.710</num>
            <heading>Combining sales and use tax with incorporation of a second class city.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 29.45.710.   Combining sales and use tax with incorporation of a second class city.
A petition for incorporation of a second class city may request that a sales and use tax proposal be placed on the same ballot.  The petition must state the proposed tax rate. The petition may request that incorporation be dependent on the passage of the tax proposition. If so, the incorporation proposition fails if the tax fails.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-750">
            <num>29.45.750</num>
            <heading>Mobile Telecommunications Sourcing Act.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-750__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The provisions of 4 U.S.C. 116  126 (Mobile Telecommunications Sourcing Act) are incorporated in this chapter by reference and have effect as though fully set out in this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-750__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality that levies and collects a sales tax on mobile telecommunications services shall do so in accordance with the provisions of 4 U.S.C. 116  126 (Mobile Telecommunications Sourcing Act).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-750__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The procedures and remedies for correcting a tax, charge, fee, or assignment of place of primary use or taxing jurisdiction are as follows:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-750__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if a customer believes that an amount of tax, charge, or fee or an assignment of place of primary use or taxing jurisdiction included on a billing is erroneous, the customer shall notify the home service provider; the customer shall notify the home service provider of the street address for the customer's place of primary use, the account name and number for which the customer seeks a correction, a description of the error asserted by the customer, and any other information that the home service provider reasonably requires to process the request;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-750__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>within 60 days after receiving a notice under this section, the home service provider shall review the records and the electronic database or enhanced zip code used according to 4 U.S.C. 116  126 to determine the customer's taxing jurisdiction; if this review shows that the amount of tax, charge, or fee or assignment of place of primary use or taxing jurisdiction is in error, the home service provider shall correct the error and refund or credit the amount of tax, charge, or fee erroneously collected from the customer for a period of up to two years; if this review shows that the amount of tax, charge, or fee or assignment of place of primary use or taxing jurisdiction is correct, the home service provider shall provide a written explanation to the customer;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="29-45-750__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the procedures in this subsection are the first course of remedy available to a customer seeking correction of assignment of place of primary use or taxing jurisdiction or a refund of or other compensation for taxes, charges, and fees erroneously collected by the home service provider.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-750__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of this section, if a customer does not have a street address, the home service provider may accept from the customer as the customer's place of primary use an address that is not a street address if the address gives effect to the intent of 4 U.S.C. 116  126 (Mobile Telecommunications Sourcing Act).
Article 7. General Provisions.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-800">
            <num>29.45.800</num>
            <heading>Applicability ofAS 29.45.010 29.45.560.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 29.45.800.   Applicability of
AS 29.45.010
 29.45.560.
AS 29.45.010
  29.45.560 apply to home rule and general law municipalities.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-810">
            <num>29.45.810</num>
            <heading>Exemption from municipal taxation.</heading>
            <subsection eId="29-45-810__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A party to a contract approved by the legislature as a result of submission of a proposed contract developed under
AS 43.82
or as a result of acts by the legislature in implementing the purposes of
AS 43.82
, and the property, gas, products, and activities associated with the approved qualified project that is subject to the contract, are exempt, as specified in the contract, from all taxes identified in the contract that would be levied and collected by a municipality under state law as a consequence of the participation by the party in the approved qualified project.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="29-45-810__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This section applies to home rule and general law municipalities.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_29-45-820">
            <num>29.45.820</num>
            <heading>Taxes or fees on transportation by certain air carriers prohibited.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 29.45.820.   Taxes or fees on transportation by certain air carriers prohibited.
Notwithstanding other provisions of law, a municipality may not levy or collect a tax or fee on the air transportation of individuals or goods by a federally certificated air carrier other than a tax or fee authorized under 49 U.S.C. 40116(e) or 40117. This section applies to home rule and general law municipalities.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>