<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-45/chapter-50"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-45/chapter-50"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="45.50"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-45/chapter-50/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-45/chapter-50/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-45/chapter-50/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-45/chapter-50/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_45">
        <num>45</num>
        <heading>Trade and Commerce</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_45__chp_50">
          <num>50</num>
          <heading>Competitive Practices, Regulation of Competition, Consumer Protection</heading>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-010">
            <num>45.50.010</num>
            <heading>Registrability.</heading>
            <subsection eId="45-50-010__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A mark may not be registered if it consists of or comprises</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-010__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>immoral, deceptive, or scandalous matter;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-010__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>matter that may disparage or falsely suggest a connection with persons, living or dead, institutions, beliefs, or national symbols, or bring them into contempt or disrepute;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-010__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the flag, coat of arms, or other insignia of the United States, this or another state, a municipality of this or another state, a foreign nation, or simulation of any of these;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-010__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name, signature, or portrait identifying a living individual, except with the written consent of the individual;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-010__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a mark that, (A) when used on or in connection with goods or services of the applicant, is merely descriptive or deceptively misdescriptive of them; (B) when used on or in connection with the goods or services of the applicant, is primarily geographically descriptive or deceptively misdescriptive of them; (C) is primarily merely a surname; however, this paragraph does not prevent the registration of a mark used by the applicant that has become distinctive of the applicant's goods or services; the commissioner may accept as evidence that the mark has become distinctive, as used on or in connection with the applicant's goods or services, proof of continuous use of the mark as a mark by the applicant in this state for the five years immediately preceding the date on which the claim of distinctiveness is made;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-010__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a mark that so resembles a mark registered in the state or in the United States Patent and Trademark Office, or a mark previously used by another and not abandoned, as to be likely, when used on or in connection with the goods or services of the applicant, to cause confusion or mistake or to deceive; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-010__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a mark that so resembles the name of another organized entity, or a reserved or registered name, that the mark is likely to cause confusion or mistake or to deceive; the form of operation of the organized entity without the mark, or of the person without the mark who holds the right to the reserved or registered name, is not a factor in determining whether the mark resembles a name under this paragraph; in this paragraph, organized entity and reserved or registered name have the meanings given in
AS 10.35.040
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-010__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-010__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>descriptive means a word or combination of words that describes one or more of the characteristics of the goods or services, such as, what the goods or services are, what the goods are made of, or what the goods or services are used for; however, an otherwise descriptive word or combination of words can, as a secondary meaning, become accepted as identifying the goods or services of the applicant, in which case it is no longer merely descriptive;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-010__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>misdescriptive means a word or combination of words that falsely describes the nature, function, or capacity of goods or services.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-020">
            <num>45.50.020</num>
            <heading>Application for registration.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.020.   Application for registration.
Subject to limitations under
AS 45.50.010
 45.50.205, a person who uses a mark in the state may file with the commissioner, on a form furnished by the department and in a manner complying with
AS 45.50.010
 45.50.205, an application for registration of that mark setting out the following information:
(1) the name and business address of the registrant and, if the registrant is a
(A) corporation, the state of incorporation; or
(B) partnership, the state in which the partnership is organized and the names of the general partners;
(2) the goods or services on or in connection with which the mark is used, the manner in which the mark is used on or in connection with the goods or services, and the class of the goods or services;
(3) the date when the mark was first used anywhere and the date when it was first used in this state by the applicant or a predecessor in interest;
(4) a statement that the applicant is the owner of the mark, that the mark is in use, and that, to the knowledge of the individual signing the application, no other person has the right to use the mark either in the identical form or in a near resemblance to it as to be likely, when applied to the goods or services of another person, to cause confusion or mistake, or to deceive; and
(5) a statement as to whether the applicant, or a predecessor in interest, has filed an application to register the mark, or portions or a composite of the mark, with the United States Patent and Trademark Office, and, if so, information regarding that application, including the filing date and serial number, the status of that application, whether that application was refused registration or otherwise did not result in a registration, and, if so, the reasons that application did not result in a registration.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-025">
            <num>45.50.025</num>
            <heading>Procedure concerning application.</heading>
            <subsection eId="45-50-025__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon the filing of an application for registration of a mark and payment of the application fee, the commissioner shall examine the application for conformity with
AS 45.50.010
 45.50.205. The commissioner may request additional information, including a description of a design mark, suggest amendments to the application, or suggest that a new application be filed. The applicant may provide the additional information requested, authorize the commissioner to make amendments to the application, or withdraw the application and file a new one to respond to a potential objection or rejection.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-025__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>As a condition of registration, the commissioner may require the applicant to disclaim an unregistrable component of a mark, or an applicant may voluntarily disclaim a component of a mark originally sought to be registered. A disclaimer under this subsection does not prejudice or affect the rights of an applicant or registrant</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-025__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in the disclaimed matter that exist at the time of the disclaimer or that arise later; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-025__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to register the disclaimed matter in another application if the disclaimed matter is or becomes distinctive of the applicant's or registrant's goods or services.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-025__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If an applicant is found not to be entitled to registration of a mark, the commissioner shall notify the applicant and inform the applicant of the reasons for the finding. The commissioner shall give the applicant a reasonable period of time in which to reply or amend the application. If a reply or amendment is delivered to the commissioner within the designated period, the commissioner shall reexamine the application. Before making a final decision, an application may be amended and reexamined as many times as the commissioner determines to be necessary. However, if the applicant fails to reply or amend the application within the period designated by the commissioner, the application is considered abandoned.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-025__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the commissioner makes a final decision on the application, the commissioner shall notify the applicant in writing of the decision and that the decision is final, setting out the reasons for the decision if the application is disapproved. The applicant may appeal the commissioner's final decision to the superior court. The court may enter judgment setting aside, modifying, remanding, or affirming the decision.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-025__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the commissioner receives more than one application for registration of the same or a confusingly similar mark for the same or related goods or services, the commissioner shall grant the registration to the applicant who first filed the original application if the application otherwise qualifies for registration. A rejected applicant may bring an action in superior court for cancellation of the registration upon the grounds of prior or superior rights to the mark.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-030">
            <num>45.50.030</num>
            <heading>Form of application.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.030.   Form of application.
The application shall be signed by the applicant or by a member of the firm or an officer of the corporation, partnership, or association applying. The application shall be accompanied by three specimens showing the actual use of the mark on or in connection with the goods or services.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-040">
            <num>45.50.040</num>
            <heading>Filing fee.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.040.   Filing fee.
The application for registration shall be accompanied by a filing fee of $50 payable to the department.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-050">
            <num>45.50.050</num>
            <heading>Form and contents of certificate of registration.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.050.   Form and contents of certificate of registration.
Upon compliance by the applicant with the requirements of
AS 45.50.010
 45.50.205, the commissioner shall issue and deliver a certificate of registration to the applicant. The certificate of registration shall be issued under the signature of the commissioner and the seal of the state. The certificate must show
(1) the name and business address of the registrant and, if that registrant is a
(A) corporation, the state of incorporation; or
(B) partnership, the state in which the partnership is organized and the names of the general partners;
(2) the date claimed for the first use of the mark anywhere and the date claimed for the first use of the mark in this state;
(3) the class of goods or services and a description of the goods or services on or in connection with which the mark is used;
(4) a reproduction of the mark;
(5) the registration date; and
(6) the term of the registration.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-060">
            <num>45.50.060</num>
            <heading>Certificate of registration as evidence.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.060.   Certificate of registration as evidence.
A certificate of registration issued by the commissioner under
AS 45.50.010
 45.50.205 or a copy of it certified by the commissioner is admissible in evidence as competent and sufficient proof of the registration of the mark in an action or judicial proceeding in the state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-070">
            <num>45.50.070</num>
            <heading>Duration and renewal.</heading>
            <subsection eId="45-50-070__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Registration of a mark is effective for a term of five years from the date of registration. Upon application filed within six months before the expiration of the term in a manner complying with the requirements of the commissioner, the registration may be renewed for an additional term of five years.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-070__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An application for renewal of a registration must include a signed statement that the mark has been used and is still in use. Three specimens showing actual use of the mark on or in connection with the goods or services shall be submitted with the renewal application.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-080">
            <num>45.50.080</num>
            <heading>Fee for renewal of registration.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.080.   Fee for renewal of registration.
A renewal fee of $50 shall accompany the application for renewal of the registration.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-090">
            <num>45.50.090</num>
            <heading>Additional terms of renewal.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.090.   Additional terms of renewal.
A registration of a mark may be renewed for successive periods of five years in the manner provided in
AS 45.50.070
and 45.50.080.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-100">
            <num>45.50.100</num>
            <heading>Notification of expiration of registration period.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.100.   Notification of expiration of registration period.
The commissioner shall notify each registrant of the necessity of renewal at least six months preceding the expiration date of the registration. Notification shall be by writing to the last known address of the registrant.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-120">
            <num>45.50.120</num>
            <heading>Assignment.</heading>
            <subsection eId="45-50-120__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A mark and its registration are assignable with the goodwill of the business in which the mark is used, or with that part of the goodwill of the business connected with the use of and symbolized by the mark.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-120__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An assignment shall be in writing and may be filed with the commissioner upon the payment of a fee of $25 to the department. The commissioner shall file the assignment and shall issue in the name of the assignee a new certificate for the remainder of the term of the registration.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-120__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An assignment of registration is void as against a subsequent purchaser for valuable consideration without notice, unless it is filed with the commissioner within three months after the date of the assignment or before the subsequent purchase.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-125">
            <num>45.50.125</num>
            <heading>Name change and other filings.</heading>
            <subsection eId="45-50-125__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The name of a registrant or applicant may be changed by filing the change of name with the commissioner on a form furnished by the department that has been signed by the registrant or applicant and paying a filing fee of $25. The commissioner shall issue in the changed name of a registrant an amended certificate of registration.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-125__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Other signed and verified instruments that relate to a registered mark or an application for registration of a mark may be filed at the discretion of the commissioner upon payment of a filing fee established by regulation of the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-125__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A photocopy of an instrument shall be accepted by the commissioner for filing if it is certified by a party to the instrument or a successor of a party to be a true and correct copy of the original and if the commissioner would have accepted the original for filing under (a) or (b) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-125__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Acknowledgment is prima facie evidence for the commissioner of the execution of an assignment, change of name, or other instrument related to a registered mark or to registration of a mark. When the instrument is filed by the commissioner, the filing is prima facie evidence of execution of the instrument for all other purposes.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-130">
            <num>45.50.130</num>
            <heading>Commissioner to keep record of registration.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.130.   Commissioner to keep record of registration.
The commissioner shall keep for public examination a record of all marks registered or renewed under
AS 45.50.010
 45.50.205 and a record of all instruments filed under
AS 45.50.125
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-140">
            <num>45.50.140</num>
            <heading>Cancellation.</heading>
            <subsection eId="45-50-140__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall cancel in whole or in part</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-140__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a registration for which the commissioner receives a voluntary written request for cancellation from the registrant or the assignee of record;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-140__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>each registration that expires and is not renewed under
AS 45.50.070
and 45.50.090;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-140__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a registration found by a court to be
(A) abandoned;
(B) not owned by the registrant;
(C) granted improperly;
(D) obtained fraudulently;
(E) so similar, as to be likely to cause confusion or mistake or to deceive, to a mark registered by another person in the United States Patent and Trademark Office, before the date of filing of the application for registration by the registrant under
AS 45.50.010
 45.50.205, and not abandoned; however, if the registrant proves that the registrant is the owner of a concurrent registration of the mark in the United States Patent and Trademark Office covering an area including this state, the registration may not be canceled; or
(F) the generic name for all or a portion of the goods or services for which the mark has been registered;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-140__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>when a court orders cancellation of a registration on any ground.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-140__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of (a) of this section, registration of a mark is abandoned when use of the mark has been discontinued and the registrant has no intent to resume its use, or when the mark loses its significance as a mark due to action or failure to act by the registrant. The intent not to resume the use of a mark may be inferred from circumstances. No use of a mark by the registrant for at least a 24-month period constitutes prima facie evidence that its registration has been abandoned.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-150">
            <num>45.50.150</num>
            <heading>Classification.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.150.   Classification.
The department shall by regulation establish a classification of goods and services for convenience of administration of
AS 45.50.010
 45.50.205. However, the classification does not limit or extend the applicant's or registrant's rights, and a single application for registration of a mark may include all goods upon which, or services with which, the mark is actually being used comprised in a single class, but in no event may a single application include goods or services upon which the mark is being used that fall within different classes of goods or services. To the extent practical, the classification of goods and services should conform to the classification adopted by the United States Patent and Trademark Office.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-160">
            <num>45.50.160</num>
            <heading>Fraudulent registration.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.160.   Fraudulent registration.
A person who, for the person or on behalf of another, procures the filing or registration of a mark under
AS 45.50.010
 45.50.205 by knowingly making a false or fraudulent representation or declaration, orally or in writing, or by another fraudulent means, is liable to pay all damages sustained in consequence of the filing or registration, which may be recovered by or on behalf of the party injured in any court.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-170">
            <num>45.50.170</num>
            <heading>Infringement.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.170.   Infringement.
A person is liable in a civil action by the registrant for the remedies provided in
AS 45.50.180
if the person
(1) uses, without the consent of the registrant, a reproduction, counterfeit, copy, or colorable imitation of a mark registered under
AS 45.50.010
 45.50.205 in connection with the sale, distribution, offering for sale, or advertising of goods or services on or in connection with which the use is likely to cause confusion or mistake or to deceive as to the source of origin of the goods or services; or
(2) reproduces, counterfeits, copies, or colorably imitates the mark and applies the reproduction, counterfeit, copy, or colorable imitation to labels, signs, prints, packages, wrappers, receptacles, or advertisements intended to be used upon or in conjunction with the sale or distribution in this state of the goods or services; except that under this paragraph the registrant may not recover profits or damages unless the acts are committed with the intent to cause confusion or mistake or to deceive.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-180">
            <num>45.50.180</num>
            <heading>Remedies.</heading>
            <subsection eId="45-50-180__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A registrant may enjoin the manufacture, use, display, or sale of a counterfeit or imitation of the registrant's mark.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-180__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The court may grant an injunction to restrain the manufacture, use, display, or sale, and may require the defendant to pay to the registrant either the profits derived from or the damages suffered by reason of the wrongful manufacture, use, display, or sale, or both. The court may also order that the counterfeit or imitation in the possession or under the control of a defendant be delivered to an officer of the court, or to the complainant, to be destroyed. The court may also enter judgment for punitive damages in an amount not to exceed three times the profits and damages.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-180__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 29 ch 132 SLA 1996.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-180__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A registrant that owns a mark that is famous in the state is entitled to an injunction against another's dilution of the mark. If the user of the famous mark wilfully intended to trade on the registrant's reputation or to cause dilution of the mark, the registrant is also entitled to remedies set out in (b) of this section. In determining whether a mark is famous, a court may consider any factor, including the</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-180__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>degree of inherent or acquired distinctiveness of the mark in the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-180__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>duration and extent of use of the mark in connection with the goods and services;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-180__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>duration and extent of advertising and publicity of the mark in the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-180__subsec_d__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>geographical extent of the trading area in which the mark is used;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-180__subsec_d__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>channels of trade for the goods or services with which the mark is used;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-180__subsec_d__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>degree of recognition in the state of the mark in the registrant's trading area and channel of trade, and in the user's trading area and channel of trade; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-180__subsec_d__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>nature and extent of use of the same or similar mark by other persons.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-180__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of (d) of this section, dilution means the use of a word, symbol, or device, or a combination of one or more of these, in a manner that deprives or reduces the distinctiveness of a mark.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-200">
            <num>45.50.200</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.200.   Definitions.
In
AS 45.50.010
 45.50.205,
(1) applicant means the person filing an application for registration of a mark, or a legal representative, successor, or assign of that person;
(2) certification mark means a mark used upon or in connection with the goods or services of one or more persons other than the registrant to certify national or other origin, material, mode of manufacture, quality, accuracy, or other characteristics of the goods or services or that the work or labor on the goods or services was performed by members of a union or other organization;
(3) collective mark means a trademark or service mark used by the members of a cooperative, an association, or other collective group or organization and includes marks used to indicate membership in a union, an association, or other organization;
(4) commissioner means the commissioner of commerce, community, and economic development;
(5) department means the Department of Commerce, Community, and Economic Development;
(6) mark means a certification mark, a collective mark, a service mark, or a trademark;
(7) registrant means the person to whom the registration of a mark is issued, or a legal representative, successor, or assign of that person;
(8) service mark means a word, symbol, design, or a combination of one or more of these that identifies the services of a person;
(9) trademark means a word, symbol, or design, or a combination of one or more of these, used by a person to identify its goods and distinguish them from those of another;
(10) use or used means the bona fide use of a mark in the ordinary course of trade, and not made merely to reserve a right in the mark; a mark is considered to be in use on goods when it is placed in any manner on the goods, on the goods' container, on tags or labels affixed to the goods, on displays associated with the goods, or, if the nature of the goods makes other types of placement impracticable, on documents associated with the goods or with the sale of the goods when they are sold or transported in commerce in this state; a mark is considered to be in use on services when it is displayed in the sale or advertising of services that are performed in this state;
(11) verified means that a document has been certified to be true as provided in
AS 09.63.040
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-205">
            <num>45.50.205</num>
            <heading>Short title.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.205.   Short title.
AS 45.50.010
 45.50.205 may be cited as the Alaska Trademark Act.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-210">
            <num>45.50.210</num>
            <heading>Application for registration of distinctive brand.</heading>
            <subsection eId="45-50-210__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The owner of timber property that the owner puts or intends to put into a coastal water, lake, river, creek, or other waterway of the state for the purpose of rafting or transporting by floating or towing, shall apply to the department for the exclusive use of a distinctive brand to identify it.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-210__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The application shall be in writing and accompanied by an acceptable diagram or design on paper of the proposed brand, and the prescribed fee.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-210__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall promptly register the brand and issue a certificate of registration to the applicant granting the applicant the exclusive use of the brand for a period of five years.  The department may not register a brand that is so similar in design to one presently registered in the name of another person that one brand is not clearly distinguishable from the other.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-220">
            <num>45.50.220</num>
            <heading>Termination and renewal.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.220.   Termination and renewal.
The right to the exclusive use of a registered brand ceases at the end of five years from the date of registration.  The brand may be renewed by application before expiration, together with the payment of the prescribed fee.  Renewals may be made successively for five-year terms.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-230">
            <num>45.50.230</num>
            <heading>Presumption from display.</heading>
            <subsection eId="45-50-230__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each piece of timber property put or intended to be put in a coastal water, lake, river, creek, or other waterway of the state for the purpose of rafting or transporting by floating or towing shall display upon at least one end the registered brand and is presumed</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-230__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>while in the possession and control of the person in whose name the brand is registered, to be the sole property of that person; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-230__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to be abandoned property if, 30 days after the time public notice has expired as provided under
AS 45.50.234
or 90 days from the date of reporting required under
AS 45.50.232
or from the date of expiration of any extended recovery period under
AS 45.50.237
, it is not in the possession and control of the owner or rightful transporter and is
(A) adrift in the water of the state,
(B) stranded on the beaches, marshes, tideland, or shoreland of the water of the state, or
(C) partially or wholly submerged in the water of the state.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-230__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 7 ch 232 SLA 1976.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-232">
            <num>45.50.232</num>
            <heading>Reporting of lost logs to the department.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.232.   Reporting of lost logs to the department.
The owner or rightful transporter of timber property not in the possession or control of the owner or transporter, which has become adrift in the waters of the state, stranded on the beaches, marshes, tideland, or shoreland of the water of the state, or partially or wholly submerged in the water of the state, shall report the loss of the timber property within 15 days from the time the loss is discovered to the department, indicating the probable date lost, the place lost, if known, the probable area of recovery, and any other information that the department may require. Unless the time for recovery is extended under
AS 45.50.237
, the rightful transporter or owner of timber property has 90 days from the date the loss is reported to recover the timber property. After 90 days from the date of reporting or upon the expiration of any extension granted under
AS 45.50.237
, the timber property is considered to be abandoned, notice is not required to be published under
AS 45.50.234
, and the timber property is presumed to be the property of the state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-234">
            <num>45.50.234</num>
            <heading>Publication of notice of intent to claim abandoned property.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.234.   Publication of notice of intent to claim abandoned property.
Except as provided in
AS 45.50.232
, the department shall publish notice of its intent to claim abandoned timber property under
AS 45.50.210
 45.50.325 for not less than 30 days from the date that first notice is published under this section.  Notice shall be published once a week for at least three consecutive weeks in a newspaper of general circulation nearest the area where the timber property is located and, if feasible, posted in a centrally located public place within or in close proximity to the area where the timber property is located.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-235">
            <num>45.50.235</num>
            <heading>Ownership of unbranded and abandoned timber property.</heading>
            <subsection eId="45-50-235__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Timber property that is unbranded or on which a brand is not distinguishable and that is located in a coastal water, lake, river, creek, or other waterway of the state or on state owned coastline is presumed to be the property of the state. Timber property that is abandoned property as defined in
AS 45.50.230
(a)(2) is presumed to be the property of the state 90 days after the period of reporting as required in
AS 45.50.232
unless an extension has been granted, or 30 days after the period of notice has expired as provided under
AS 45.50.234
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-235__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Timber property that becomes state property under the provisions of this section may be sold under terms and conditions established by the director of the division of lands.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-237">
            <num>45.50.237</num>
            <heading>Extension of period for recovery of timber property.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.237.   Extension of period for recovery of timber property.
The department shall extend the 90-day period for recovery of timber property after reporting specified in
AS 45.50.232
if a good faith effort to salvage the timber property is being made by the person requesting the extension.  Extensions shall be granted for limited periods only but may be continued until salvage is completed, and guidelines shall be established specifying what constitutes a good faith effort for purposes of extension under regulations adopted by the department. Definition of a good faith effort must include the specification of extraordinary circumstances of weather and tide conditions that may preclude direct and immediate salvage operations.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-240">
            <num>45.50.240</num>
            <heading>Property rights in brand.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.240.   Property rights in brand.
Each registered brand is the property of the person in whose name it is registered.  It is personal property and may be sold, hypothecated, assigned, or otherwise transferred.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-250">
            <num>45.50.250</num>
            <heading>Recording brand.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.250.   Recording brand.
The commissioner shall file for record in the department files a true copy of each certificate of registration issued.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-260">
            <num>45.50.260</num>
            <heading>Registration upon transfer.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.260.   Registration upon transfer.
If a transfer of a brand is made, including transfer by assignment or sale, a true copy of the transfer instrument shall be filed for record with the department.  The fee for transfer is as specified by regulation.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-270">
            <num>45.50.270</num>
            <heading>Publication of current list of brands.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.270.   Publication of current list of brands.
The department shall publish a list of brands as of December 31 of each even numbered year.  The list must show the design of each brand, the name and address of the owner, the date of registration, and any transfer of a brand during the previous two years. Copies of the list shall be available to the public upon request.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-280">
            <num>45.50.280</num>
            <heading>Certified copies of certificate or transfer instrument.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.280.   Certified copies of certificate or transfer instrument.
Upon request and payment of the prescribed fee, the department shall furnish a certified copy of a brand certificate of registration or a certified copy of the instrument of transfer of a brand.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-290">
            <num>45.50.290</num>
            <heading>Certificate of registration as evidence.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.290.   Certificate of registration as evidence.
A certificate of registration of a brand or a certified copy of the certificate or of the instrument of transfer of a registered brand is prima facie evidence of the ownership of the timber property impressed with or displaying the registered brand.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-300">
            <num>45.50.300</num>
            <heading>Registration as constructive notice.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.300.   Registration as constructive notice.
Registration by the department and filing for record in the department files of a true copy of the certificate of registration or the transfer instrument is constructive notice of the ownership of the brand.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-310">
            <num>45.50.310</num>
            <heading>Disposition of fees.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.310.   Disposition of fees.
Fees collected under
AS 45.50.210
 45.50.325 by the department shall be deposited in the general fund of the state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-315">
            <num>45.50.315</num>
            <heading>Regulations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.315.   Regulations.
The department may adopt regulations necessary to implement
AS 45.50.210
 45.50.325.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-320">
            <num>45.50.320</num>
            <heading>Penalties for fraudulent branding or other acts.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.320.   Penalties for fraudulent branding or other acts.
A person who fraudulently brands timber property with a brand which the person knows or has reasonable cause to know is the registered brand of another person, or who knowingly alters, defaces, obliterates, or destroys a registered brand impressed or displayed upon timber property, or who knowingly sells or disposes of, or attempts to sell or dispose of, or to convert or appropriate to the person's own use, without the written consent of the owner, timber property impressed with or displaying upon it a registered brand of another person, is guilty of a misdemeanor and upon conviction is punishable by a fine of not more than $1,000, or by imprisonment in jail for not more than six months, or by both.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-325">
            <num>45.50.325</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.325.   Definitions.
In
AS 45.50.210
 45.50.325,
(1) brand includes a mark or other designation that has been registered with the department;
(2) commissioner means the commissioner of natural resources;
(3) department means the Department of Natural Resources;
(4) rightful transporter means a person who has an executory contract interest in the timber property the person is transporting, or that person's designee, or one who, in the normal usage of the trade, transports, or aids in the transportation of, timber property for the benefit of and authorized by the owner of the timber property;
(5) timber property means logs, pilings, poles, other timbers, boom sticks, and boom chains.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-471">
            <num>45.50.471</num>
            <heading>Unlawful acts and practices.</heading>
            <subsection eId="45-50-471__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unfair methods of competition and unfair or deceptive acts or practices in the conduct of trade or commerce are declared to be unlawful.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-471__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The terms unfair methods of competition and unfair or deceptive acts or practices include the following acts:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>fraudulently conveying or transferring goods or services by representing them to be those of another;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>falsely representing or designating the geographic origin of goods or services;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>causing a likelihood of confusion or misunderstanding as to the source, sponsorship, or approval, or another person's affiliation, connection, or association with or certification of goods or services;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>representing that goods or services have sponsorship, approval, characteristics, ingredients, uses, benefits, or quantities that they do not have or that a person has a sponsorship, approval, status, affiliation, or connection that the person does not have;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>representing that goods are original or new if they are deteriorated, altered, reconditioned, reclaimed, used, secondhand, or seconds;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>representing that goods or services are of a particular standard, quality, or grade, or that goods are of a particular style or model, if they are of another;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>disparaging the goods, services, or business of another by false or misleading representation of fact;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>advertising goods or services with intent not to sell them as advertised;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>advertising goods or services with intent not to supply reasonable expectable public demand, unless the advertisement prominently discloses a limitation of quantity;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>making false or misleading statements of fact concerning the reasons for, existence of, or amounts of price reductions;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>engaging in any other conduct creating a likelihood of confusion or of misunderstanding and that misleads, deceives, or damages a buyer or a competitor in connection with the sale or advertisement of goods or services;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>using or employing deception, fraud, false pretense, false promise, misrepresentation, or knowingly concealing, suppressing, or omitting a material fact with intent that others rely upon the concealment, suppression, or omission in connection with the sale or advertisement of goods or services whether or not a person has in fact been misled, deceived, or damaged;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_13">
                <num>(13)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>failing to deliver to the customer at the time of an installment sale of goods or services, a written order, contract, or receipt setting out the name and address of the seller and the name and address of the organization that the seller represents, and all of the terms and conditions of the sale, including a description of the goods or services, which must be stated in readable, clear, and unambiguous language;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_14">
                <num>(14)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>representing that an agreement confers or involves rights, remedies, or obligations that it does not confer or involve, or that are prohibited by law;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_15">
                <num>(15)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>knowingly making false or misleading statements concerning the need for parts, replacement, or repair service;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_16">
                <num>(16)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>misrepresenting the authority of a salesman, representative, or agent to negotiate the final terms of a consumer transaction;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_17">
                <num>(17)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>basing a charge for repair in whole or in part on a guaranty or warranty rather than on the actual value of the actual repairs made or work to be performed on the item without stating separately the charges for the work and the charge for the guaranty or warranty, if any;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_18">
                <num>(18)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>disconnecting, turning back, or resetting the odometer of a vehicle to reduce the number of miles indicated;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_19">
                <num>(19)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>using a chain referral sales plan by inducing or attempting to induce a consumer to enter into a contract by offering a rebate, discount, commission, or other consideration, contingent upon the happening of a future event, on the condition that the consumer either sells, or gives information or assistance for the purpose of leading to a sale by the seller of the same or related goods;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_20">
                <num>(20)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>selling or offering to sell a right of participation in a chain distributor scheme;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_21">
                <num>(21)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>selling, falsely representing, or advertising meat, fish, or poultry that has been frozen as fresh food;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_22">
                <num>(22)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>failing to comply with
AS 45.02.350
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_23">
                <num>(23)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>failing to comply with
AS 45.45.130
 45.45.240;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_24">
                <num>(24)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>counseling, consulting, or arranging for future services relating to the disposition of a body upon death whereby certain personal property, not including cemetery lots and markers, will be furnished or the professional services of a funeral director or embalmer will be furnished, unless the person receiving money or property deposits the money or property, and money or property is received, within five days of its receipt, in a trust in a financial institution whose deposits are insured by an instrumentality of the federal government designating the institution as the trustee as a separate trust in the name only of the person on whose behalf the arrangements are made with a provision that the money or property may only be applied to the purchase of designated merchandise or services and should the money or property deposited and any accrued interest not be used for the purposes intended on the death of the person on whose behalf the arrangements are made, all money or property in the trust shall become part of that person's estate; upon demand by the person on whose behalf the arrangements are made, all money or property in the trust, including accrued interest, shall be paid to that person; this paragraph does not prohibit the charging of a separate fee for consultation, counseling, or arrangement services if the fee is disclosed to the person making the arrangement; any arrangement under this paragraph that would constitute a contract of insurance under
AS 21
is subject to the provisions of
AS 21
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_25">
                <num>(25)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>failing to comply with the terms of
AS 45.50.800
 45.50.850 (Alaska Gasoline Products Leasing Act);</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_26">
                <num>(26)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>failing to comply with
AS 45.30
relating to mobile home warranties and mobile home parks;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_27">
                <num>(27)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>failing to comply with
AS 14.48.060</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_28">
                <num>(28)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>dealing in hearing aids and failing to comply with
AS 08.55
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_29">
                <num>(29)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>violating
AS 45.45.910</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_30">
                <num>(30)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>failing to comply with
AS 45.50.473
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_31">
                <num>(31)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>violating the provisions of
AS 45.45.400
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_32">
                <num>(32)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>knowingly selling a reproduction of a piece of art or handicraft that was made by a resident of the state unless the reproduction is clearly labeled as a reproduction; in this paragraph, reproduction means a copy of an original if the copy is
(A) substantially the same as the original; and
(B) not made by the person who made the original;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_33">
                <num>(33)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>violating
AS 08.66
(motor vehicle dealers);</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_34">
                <num>(34)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>violating
AS 08.66.260
 08.66.350 (motor vehicle buyers agents);</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_35">
                <num>(35)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>violating
AS 45.63
(solicitations by telephonic means);</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_36">
                <num>(36)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>violating
AS 45.68
(charitable solicitations);</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_37">
                <num>(37)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>violating
AS 45.50.474
(on board promotions);</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_38">
                <num>(38)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>referring a person to a dentist or a dental practice that has paid or will pay a fee for the referral unless the person making the referral discloses at the time the referral is made that the dentist or dental practice has paid or will pay a fee based on the referral;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_39">
                <num>(39)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>advertising that a person can receive a referral to a dentist or a dental practice without disclosing in the advertising that the dentist or dental practice to which the person is referred has paid or will pay a fee based on the referral if, in fact, the dentist or dental practice to which the person is referred has paid or will pay a fee based on the referral;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_40">
                <num>(40)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>violating
AS 45.50.477</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-471__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p> (c);</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_a__subsec_41">
                <num>(41)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>failing to comply with
AS 45.50.475
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_a__subsec_42">
                <num>(42)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>violating
AS 45.35
(lease-purchase agreements);</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_a__subsec_43">
                <num>(43)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>violating
AS 45.25.400
 45.25.590 (motor vehicle dealer practices);</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_a__subsec_44">
                <num>(44)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>violating
AS 45.66
(sale of business opportunities);</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_a__subsec_45">
                <num>(45)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>violating
AS 08.18.023</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-471__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or 08.18.152;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_46">
                <num>(46)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>violating
AS 45.50.479
(limitations on electronic mail);</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_47">
                <num>(47)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>violating
AS 17.06.010
(sale of, or offering to sell, organic food);</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_48">
                <num>(48)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>violating a labeling or advertising provision of
AS 17.20
(Alaska Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act);</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_49">
                <num>(49)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>violating
AS 45.45.920
(free trial period);</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_50">
                <num>(50)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>violating
AS 45.45.930
(opt-out marketing plans);</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_51">
                <num>(51)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>violating
AS 45.45.792
(deceptive acts or practices relating to spyware);</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_52">
                <num>(52)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>violating
AS 06.60.340
(mortgage lending regulation);</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_53">
                <num>(53)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>offering a check, through the mail or by other means, to promote goods or services, if the cashing or deposit of the check obligates the endorser or payee identified on the check to pay for goods or services; in this paragraph, services does not include the extension of credit or the lending of money;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_54">
                <num>(54)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>violating
AS 45.65.055
(authentic Alaska Native art identification seals);</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_55">
                <num>(55)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an information collector, other than a governmental agency, violating
AS 45.48.010
 45.48.090 (breach of security involving personal information); in this paragraph,
(A) governmental agency has the meaning given in
AS 45.48.090
;
(B) information collector has the meaning given in
AS 45.48.090
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_56">
                <num>(56)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>violating
AS 45.27
(marine products and motorized recreational products);</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-471__subsec_b__subsec_57">
                <num>(57)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>violating
AS 45.45.450
 45.45.459 (rental car fees).</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-471__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The unlawful acts and practices listed in (b) of this section are in addition to and do not limit the types of unlawful acts and practices actionable at common law or under other state statutes.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-471__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 21 ch 166 SLA 1978.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-473">
            <num>45.50.473</num>
            <heading>Disclosure of costs of certain telephone services.</heading>
            <subsection eId="45-50-473__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not provide an alternate operator service without disclosing to the consumer before a charge is incurred the cost of the service provided by the person and the identity of the person providing those services.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-473__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The owner of a place where telephone business from consumers is aggregated, including a hotel, motel, hospital, and pay telephone other than a telephone utility regulated by the Regulatory Commission of Alaska, shall disclose a surcharge added to the cost of local or long distance telephone service before the service is provided.  Disclosure may be made by posting the amount of the surcharge on or near the telephone instruments subject to the surcharge or by other reasonable written or oral means.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-473__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A violation of this section constitutes an unfair or deceptive act or practice under
AS 45.50.471
. It is presumed that actual damages to the consumer under
AS 45.50.531</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-473__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>are equal to the cost of the service provided plus $200. Additional damages must be proved.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-473__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, alternate operator service</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-473__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>means a connection to intrastate or interstate long-distance telecommunications facilities from a nonresidential location in the state including a hotel, motel, hospital, or customer-owned pay telephone, or from a place where business from consumers is aggregated, by a person that does not own any of the telecommunications facilities being connected through the service;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-473__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>does not include an intrastate or interstate long-distance carrier that contracts for operator services and charges rates for those services that are no greater than the rates charged by long-distance carriers regulated by the Regulatory Commission of Alaska or by the Federal Communications Commission.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-474">
            <num>45.50.474</num>
            <heading>Required disclosures in promotions and shoreside sales on board cruise ships.</heading>
            <subsection eId="45-50-474__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not conduct a promotion on board a cruise ship that mentions or features a business in a state port that has paid something of value for the purpose of having the business mentioned, featured, or otherwise promoted, unless the person conducting the promotion clearly and fully discloses in all written materials used in the promotion that the featured businesses have paid to be included in the promotion. If the value paid by the business is more than 10 percent of any single sale, the disclosure must also state that more than a 10 percent commission is being retained by the person making the promotion and that other alternatives may be available at a port of call; and the disclosure must provide the address, Internet website address, and telephone number of any existing visitors bureaus at each future port of call.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-474__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person or other entity aboard a cruise ship conducting or making a sale of tours, flightseeing operations, or other shoreside activities to be delivered by a vendor or other entity at a future port of call shall disclose, in writing at the point of sale,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-474__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>that the onboard sale is a retail-wholesale relationship between the cruise ship and the shoreside vendor that results in a percentage of the sale being retained by the cruise ship;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-474__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>that other alternatives at different prices and with different features may be available at a port of call;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-474__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the address, Internet website address, and telephone number of the existing visitors bureaus at each future port of call; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-474__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if the amount of commission or percentage of the total sale retained or returned to the person or entity making or attempting to make the sale exceeds 20 percent of the total cost of the services or goods provided by a shoreside vendor, that more than 20 percent of the total sale price is being retained as a commission by the person or entity making the sale.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-474__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A written notice of disclosure under (a) or (b) of this section must be in a type that is not less than 14-point typeface and in a contrasting color calculated to draw attention to the disclosure.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-474__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each violation of this section constitutes an unfair trade practice under
AS 45.50.471
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-474__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, cruise ship means a ship that operates at least 48 hours in length for ticketed passengers, provides overnight accommodations and meals for at least 250 passengers, is operated by an authorized cruise ship operator, and is certified under the International Convention for the Safety of Life at Sea or otherwise certified by the United States Coast Guard.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-475">
            <num>45.50.475</num>
            <heading>Unlawful, unwanted telephone advertisements and solicitations.</heading>
            <subsection eId="45-50-475__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person is in violation of
AS 45.50.471
(b)(41) if the person</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-475__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>[Repealed, § 35 ch 55 SLA 2004.]</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-475__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>engages in the telephone solicitation of a customer whose telephone number has been registered with the national do not call registry for the minimum amount of time required by the national do not call registry before the date the call is made;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-475__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>engages in the telephone solicitation of a customer who has previously communicated to the telephone solicitor, or to the business enterprise or charitable organization for which the person is calling, the customer's desire not to receive telephone solicitations to that number; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-475__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>originates a telephone call using an automated or recorded message as a telephonic advertisement or a telephone solicitation.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-475__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A local exchange telecommunications company and a company that provides a telephone directory on behalf of a local exchange telecommunications company shall provide for the identification in the telephone directory of those residential customers who do not wish to receive telephone solicitations. The local exchange telecommunications company may impose a reasonable charge for identification in the directory. The charge shall be based on the cost of providing the identification and is subject to the approval of the Regulatory Commission of Alaska.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-475__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 35 ch 55 SLA 2004.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-475__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who employs individuals to engage in telephone solicitations is not liable for a violation of (a)(1)  (3) of this section if the person establishes that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-475__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the person has adopted and implemented written procedures and policies to comply with (a)(1)  (3) of this section, including corrective actions if appropriate;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-475__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the person has trained its personnel in the procedures and policies established under (1) of this subsection;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-475__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the call that violated (a)(1)  (3) of this section was made contrary to the procedures and policies established by the person; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-475__subsec_d__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the call that violated (a)(1)  (3) of this section was made as a result of a good faith error.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-475__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An individual who solicits a telephone customer in violation of (a)(1)  (3) of this section is not liable for the violation if the individual establishes that the individual did not intend to make the call in violation of this section and did not recklessly disregard information or policies and procedures that would have avoided the improper call.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-475__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Local exchange telecommunications companies shall inform customers of the provisions of this section. Notification shall be made by</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-475__subsec_f__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>quarterly inserts in the billing statements mailed to customers; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-475__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>clear and conspicuous publication of the notice in the consumer information pages of local telephone directories.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-475__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-475__subsec_g__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>charitable organization has the meaning given in
AS 45.68.900
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-475__subsec_g__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>customer means a telephone customer of a telecommunications company;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-475__subsec_g__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>national do not call registry means the data base of telephone numbers of customers who do not wish to receive telephone solicitations established and maintained by the Federal Trade Commission and the Federal Communications Commission;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-475__subsec_g__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>telephone solicitation
(A) means the solicitation by a person by telephone of a customer at the residence of the customer or on a customer's cellular or mobile telephone for the purpose of encouraging the customer to purchase property, goods, or services, or make a donation;
(B) does not include</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-475__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>calls made in response to a request or inquiry by the called customer or communication made during a call made by the customer;
(ii) calls made by a charitable organization or volunteers on behalf of the charitable organization to a member of the organization or to a person who, within the last 18 months, has made a donation to the organization or expressed an interest in making a donation, but only if the charitable organization has not received a request from the member or person asking that the telephone solicitations cease;
(iii) calls limited to soliciting the expression of ideas, opinions, or votes;
(iv) business-to-business calls; or</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-475__subsec_v">
              <num>(v)</num>
              <content>
                <p>a person soliciting business from prospective purchasers who have, within the last 18 months, purchased from the person making the solicitation or from the business enterprise for which the person is calling but only if the person or business enterprise has not received a request from the prospective purchaser asking that telephone solicitations cease; the person or business enterprise is presumed to have received a written request no later than 10 days after the prospective purchaser mailed it, properly addressed and with the appropriate postage.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-477">
            <num>45.50.477</num>
            <heading>Use of titles relating to industrial hygiene.</heading>
            <subsection eId="45-50-477__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not use the title industrial hygienist, the initials I.H., another term that includes the phrase industrial hygiene or similar words, or represent to the public that the person is an industrial hygienist, unless the person has a baccalaureate or graduate degree in industrial hygiene, biology, chemistry, engineering, physics, or a closely related physical or biological science from a college or university accredited by a national or regional accreditation association recognized by the Council on Recognition of Postsecondary Accreditation, or a degree based on equivalent academic training, and has acquired competence in industrial hygiene through special studies or work experience sufficient to provide the person with the ability and competence to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-477__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>anticipate and recognize the environmental factors and stresses associated with work and work operations and to understand their effects on people and their well-being;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-477__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>evaluate, on the basis of training and demonstrated work experience and with the aid of quantitative measurement techniques, the magnitude of the factors and stresses identified under (1) of this subsection in terms of their ability to impair human health and well-being; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-477__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>prescribe methods to prevent, eliminate, control, or reduce the factors and stresses identified under (a) of this subsection when necessary to alleviate their effects.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-477__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not use the title industrial hygienist in training, the initials I.H.I.T., another term involving the phrase industrial hygienist in training or a variation of those words, or represent to the public that the person is an industrial hygienist in training, unless the person is certified as an industrial hygienist in training by the American Board of Industrial Hygiene.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-477__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not use the title certified industrial hygienist, the initials C.I.H., another term involving the phrase certified industrial hygienist or a variation of those words, or represent to the public that the person is a certified industrial hygienist unless the person is certified as a certified industrial hygienist by the American Board of Industrial Hygiene.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-477__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A state or local government agency may not prohibit or restrict the practice of industrial hygiene by a qualified individual who complies with this section except to the extent that a state statute allows the agency to regulate a specific activity that may be included in the practice of industrial hygiene.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-477__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, industrial hygiene means the science and practice devoted to the anticipation, recognition, evaluation, and control of environmental factors and stresses arising in or from the workplace that may cause illness, impaired health or well-being, or significant discomfort among workers and may also affect persons outside the workplace.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-479">
            <num>45.50.479</num>
            <heading>Limitation on electronic mail.</heading>
            <subsection eId="45-50-479__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not send unsolicited commercial electronic mail to another person from a computer located in this state or to an electronic mail address that the sender knows is held by a resident of this state if the commercial electronic mail contains information that consists of explicit sexual material that another law provides may only be viewed, purchased, rented, leased, or held by an individual who is 18 years of age or older, unless the subject line of the advertisement contains ADV:ADLT as the first eight characters.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-479__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In (a) of this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-479__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>commercial electronic mail means electronic mail consisting of advertising material for the lease, sale, rental, gift, offer, or other disposition of real property, goods, or services, including an extension of credit;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-479__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>explicit sexual material means material that visually or aurally depicts conduct described in
AS 11.41.455</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-479__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>unsolicited commercial electronic mail means commercial electronic mail sent to a person who
(A) does not have an existing personal or business relationship with the sender; and
(B) has not given permission for or requested the sending of the commercial electronic mail.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-481">
            <num>45.50.481</num>
            <heading>Exemptions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="45-50-481__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing in
AS 45.50.471
 45.50.561 applies to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-481__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an act or transaction regulated by a statute or regulation administered by the state, including a state regulatory board or commission, unless the statute or regulation does not prohibit the practices declared unlawful in
AS 45.50.471
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-481__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an act done by the publisher, owner, agent, or employee of a newspaper, periodical, or radio or television station in the publication or dissemination of an advertisement, when the owner, agent, or employee did not have knowledge of the false, misleading, or deceptive character of the advertisement or did not have a direct financial interest in the sale or distribution of the advertised product or service;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-481__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an act or transaction regulated under
AS 21.36
or
AS 06.05
or a regulation adopted under the authority of those chapters.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-481__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The exemption in (a)(3) of this section does not apply to an act or transaction between a bank and its borrowers, depositors, or other customers or potential customers.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-481__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The exemption in (a)(1) of this section does not apply to an act or transaction listed in
AS 45.50.471</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-481__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or regulated under
AS 06.60
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-491">
            <num>45.50.491</num>
            <heading>Regulations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.491.   Regulations.
The attorney general, in accordance with
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act), may adopt regulations interpreting and forms necessary for administering the provisions of
AS 45.50.471
 45.50.561.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-495">
            <num>45.50.495</num>
            <heading>Investigative power of attorney general.</heading>
            <subsection eId="45-50-495__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the attorney general has cause to believe that a person has engaged in, is engaging in, or is about to engage in a deceptive trade practice under
AS 45.50.471
, the attorney general may</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-495__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>request the person to file a statement or report in writing, under oath, on forms prescribed by the attorney general, setting out all facts and circumstances concerning the sale or advertisement of property by the person, and other information considered necessary;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-495__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>examine under oath any person in connection with the sale or advertisement of property;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-495__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>examine property or sample of the property, record, book, document, account, or paper that the attorney general considers necessary;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-495__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>make true copies of records, books, documents, accounts, or papers examined under (3) of this subsection, which may be offered in evidence in place of the originals in actions brought under
AS 45.50.471
 45.50.561; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-495__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>under an order of the superior court, impound samples of property that are material to the investigation and retain the sample until proceedings undertaken under
AS 45.50.471
 45.50.561 are completed.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-495__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The attorney general, in addition to other powers conferred by this section, may issue subpoenas to require the attendance of witnesses or the production of documents or other physical evidence, administer oaths, and conduct hearings to aid an investigation or inquiry.  Service of an order or subpoena shall be made in the same manner as a summons in a civil action in the superior court.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-501">
            <num>45.50.501</num>
            <heading>Restraining prohibited acts.</heading>
            <subsection eId="45-50-501__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the attorney general has reason to believe that a person has used, is using, or is about to use an act or practice declared unlawful in
AS 45.50.471
, and that proceedings would be in the public interest, the attorney general may bring an action in the name of the state against the person to restrain by injunction the use of the act or practice. The action may be brought in the superior court in the judicial district in which the person resides or is doing business or has the person's principal place of business in the state, or, with the consent of the parties, in any other judicial district in the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-501__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The court may make additional orders or judgments that are necessary to restore to any person in interest any money or property, real or personal, which may have been acquired by means of an act or practice declared to be unlawful by
AS 45.50.471
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-511">
            <num>45.50.511</num>
            <heading>Assurances of voluntary compliance.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.511.   Assurances of voluntary compliance.
In the administration of
AS 45.50.471
 45.50.561, the attorney general may accept an assurance of voluntary compliance with respect to any act or practice considered to be violative of
AS 45.50.471
 45.50.561 from a person who has engaged or was about to engage in such an act or practice.  The assurance shall be in writing and shall be filed with and is subject to the approval of the superior court in the judicial district in which the alleged violator resides or is doing business or has the principal place of business in the state.  The assurance of voluntary compliance is not considered an admission of violation for any purpose. Matters closed in this way may at any time be reopened by the attorney general for further proceedings in the public interest, under
AS 45.50.501
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-521">
            <num>45.50.521</num>
            <heading>When information and evidence confidential and nonadmissible.</heading>
            <subsection eId="45-50-521__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed by § 6 ch 53 SLA 1974.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-521__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subject to the provisions of
AS 45.50.501
(a), the attorney general may not make public the name of a person alleged to have committed an act or practice declared unlawful in
AS 45.50.471
during an investigation conducted by the attorney general under
AS 45.50.471
 45.50.561, nor are the records of investigation or intelligence information of the attorney general obtained under
AS 45.50.471
 45.50.561 considered public records available for inspection by the general public.  However, the attorney general is not prevented from issuing public statements describing or warning of a course of conduct or a conspiracy that constitutes or will constitute an unlawful act or practice, whether on a local, state, regional, or national basis.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-531">
            <num>45.50.531</num>
            <heading>Private and class actions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="45-50-531__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who suffers an ascertainable loss of money or property as a result of another person's act or practice declared unlawful by
AS 45.50.471
may bring a civil action to recover for each unlawful act or practice three times the actual damages or $500, whichever is greater. The court may provide other relief it considers necessary and proper. Nothing in this subsection prevents a person who brings an action under this subsection from pursuing other remedies available under other law, including common law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-531__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 4 ch 31 SLA 1987.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-531__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon commencement of an action brought under this section the clerk of the court shall mail a copy of the complaint or other initial pleading to the attorney general and, upon entry of an order or judgment in the action, shall mail a copy of the order or judgment to the attorney general.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-531__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 4 ch 31 SLA 1987.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-531__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A permanent injunction or final judgment against a person against whom an action was initiated under
AS 45.50.501
is prima facie evidence in an action brought under this section that the person used or employed an act or practice declared unlawful by
AS 45.50.471
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-531__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not commence an action under this section more than two years after the person discovers or reasonably should have discovered that the loss resulted from an act or practice declared unlawful by
AS 45.50.471
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-531__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 6 ch 96 SLA 1998.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-531__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the basis for the action is the fault of the manufacturer or supplier of the merchandise, the manufacturer or supplier who is at fault is liable for the damages awarded against the retailer under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-531__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a person receives an award of punitive damages under (a) of this section, the court shall require that 50 percent of the award be deposited into the general fund of the state under
AS 09.17.020
(j). This subsection does not grant the state the right to file or join a civil action to recover punitive damages.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-535">
            <num>45.50.535</num>
            <heading>Private injunctive relief.</heading>
            <subsection eId="45-50-535__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subject to (b) of this section and in addition to any right to bring an action under
AS 45.50.531
or other law, any person who was the victim of the unlawful act, whether or not the person suffered actual damages, may bring an action to obtain an injunction prohibiting a seller or lessor from continuing to engage in an act or practice declared unlawful under
AS 45.50.471
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-535__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not bring an action under (a) of this section unless</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-535__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the person first provides written notice to the seller or lessor who engaged in the unlawful act or practice that the person will seek an injunction against the seller or lessor if the seller or lessor fails to promptly stop the unlawful act or practice; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-535__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the seller or lessor fails to promptly stop the unlawful act or practice after receiving the notice.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-536">
            <num>45.50.536</num>
            <heading>Mediation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.536.   Mediation.
Notwithstanding the other provisions of
AS 45.50.471
 45.50.561, a civil action under
AS 45.50.531
or 45.50.535 may be submitted to mediation under the Alaska Rules of Civil Procedure. The mediation must begin within 30 days after the court's order for mediation. During mediation, the court may, if it is determined appropriate by the court, enjoin the defendant from engaging in the act or practice that is the subject of the civil action.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-537">
            <num>45.50.537</num>
            <heading>Attorney fees, costs, and damages.</heading>
            <subsection eId="45-50-537__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In an action brought by a private person under
AS 45.50.471
 45.50.561, a prevailing plaintiff shall be awarded costs as provided by court rule and full reasonable attorney fees at the prevailing reasonable rate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-537__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless the action is found to be frivolous, in an action brought by a private person under
AS 45.50.471
 45.50.561, a prevailing defendant shall be awarded attorney fees and costs as provided by court rule. If the action is found to be frivolous, the attorney fees to be awarded to the defendant shall be full reasonable attorney fees at the prevailing reasonable rate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-537__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding the other provisions of this section, in an action brought by a private person under
AS 45.50.471
 45.50.561, if the plaintiff is not the prevailing party and if the court finds that the action was brought by the plaintiff to obtain a competitive business advantage, the court shall award a prevailing defendant costs as provided by court rule, full reasonable attorney fees at the prevailing reasonable rate, and any damages suffered by the prevailing defendant as a result of the plaintiff's allegations.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-537__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In an action brought by the attorney general under
AS 45.50.471
 45.50.561, if the attorney general prevails, the state shall be awarded its actual attorney fees and costs, including costs of investigation, to the extent those fees and costs are reasonable.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-537__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, frivolous means</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-537__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>not reasonably based on evidence or on existing law or a reasonable extension, modification, or reversal of existing law; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-537__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>brought to harass the defendant or to cause unnecessary delay or needless expense.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-541">
            <num>45.50.541</num>
            <heading>Nonnegotiability of consumer paper.</heading>
            <subsection eId="45-50-541__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a contract for sale or lease of consumer goods or services on credit entered into between a retail seller and a retail buyer requires or involves the execution of a promissory note or instrument or other evidence of indebtedness of the buyer, the note, instrument, or evidence of indebtedness shall have printed on its face the words consumer paper, and the note, instrument, or evidence of indebtedness with the words consumer paper printed on it is not a negotiable instrument, within the meaning of
AS 45.01

AS 45.08
,
AS 45.12
,
AS 45.14
, and
AS 45.29
(Uniform Commercial Code).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-541__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding the absence of such a notice on a note, instrument, or evidence of indebtedness arising out of a consumer credit sale or consumer lease as described in this section, an assignee of the rights of the seller or lessor is subject to all claims and defenses of the buyer or lessee against the seller or lessor arising out of the sale or lease.  An agreement to the contrary has no effect in limiting the rights of a consumer.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-541__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The assignee's liability under this section may not exceed the amount owing to the assignee at the time the claim or defense is asserted against the assignee.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-542">
            <num>45.50.542</num>
            <heading>Provisions not waivable.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.542.   Provisions not waivable.
A waiver by a consumer of the provisions of
AS 45.50.471
 45.50.561 is contrary to public policy and is unenforceable and void.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-545">
            <num>45.50.545</num>
            <heading>Interpretation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.545.   Interpretation.
In interpreting
AS 45.50.471
due consideration and great weight should be given the interpretations of 15 U.S.C. 45(a)(1) (§ 5(a)(1) of the Federal Trade Commission Act).</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-551">
            <num>45.50.551</num>
            <heading>Civil penalties.</heading>
            <subsection eId="45-50-551__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who violates the terms of an injunction or restraining order issued under
AS 45.50.501
shall forfeit and pay to the state a civil penalty of not more than $50,000 for each violation. For the purposes of this section, the superior court in a judicial district issuing an injunction retains jurisdiction, and, in these cases, the attorney general acting in the name of the state may petition for recovery of the penalties.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-551__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In an action brought under
AS 45.50.501
, if the court finds that a person is using or has used an act or practice declared unlawful by
AS 45.50.471
, the attorney general, upon petition to the court, may recover, on behalf of the state, a civil penalty of not less than $1,000 and not more than $25,000 for each violation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-551__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed by § 21 ch 166 SLA 1978.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-561">
            <num>45.50.561</num>
            <heading>Definitions; short title.</heading>
            <subsection eId="45-50-561__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In
AS 45.50.471
  45.50.561</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-561__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>advertising includes the attempt directly or indirectly by publication, dissemination, solicitation, endorsement, or circulation, display in any manner, including solicitation or dissemination by mail, telephone or door-to-door contacts, or in any other way, to induce directly or indirectly a person to enter or not enter into an obligation or acquire title or interest in any merchandise or to increase the consumption of it or to make a loan;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-561__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>cemetery lot means a lot, plot, space, grave, niche, mausoleum, crypt, vault, or columbarium, used or intended to be used for the interment of human remains;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-561__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>chain distributor scheme means a sales device whereby a person, upon condition that the person make an investment, is granted a license or right to solicit or recruit for profit one or more additional persons who are also granted a license or right upon condition of making an investment and may further perpetuate the chain of persons who are granted a license or right upon the condition of investment; a limitation as to the number of persons who may participate, or the presence of additional conditions affecting eligibility for the license or right to solicit or recruit or the receipt of profit from these does not change the identity of the scheme as a chain distributor scheme; as used in this paragraph, investment means acquisition, for a consideration other than personal services, of tangible or intangible property, and includes franchises, business opportunities, and services; investment does not include sales demonstration equipment and materials furnished at cost for use in making sales and not for resale;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-561__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>consumer means a person who seeks or acquires goods or services by lease or purchase;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-561__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>dealing in hearing aids has the meaning given in
AS 08.55.200
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-561__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>documentary material means the original or a copy of a book, record, report, memorandum, paper, communication, tabulation, map, chart, photograph, mechanical transcription, or other tangible document or recording, wherever situate;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-561__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>examination of documentary material includes the inspection, study, or copying of the material, and the taking of testimony under oath or acknowledgment in respect of documentary material or copy of it;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-561__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>fresh means a condition of food that has never been frozen;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-561__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>goods or services includes goods or services provided in connection with a consumer credit transaction or with a transaction involving an indebtedness secured by the borrower's residence;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-561__subsec_a__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>hearing aid has the meaning given in
AS 08.55.200
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-561__subsec_a__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>knowingly means actual awareness of the falsity or deception, but actual awareness may be inferred where objective manifestations indicate that a person acted with actual awareness;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-561__subsec_a__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>seconds means manufactured items having flaws or consisting of a standard quantity or quality less than the manufacturer's quality standard.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-561__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>AS 45.50.471
 45.50.561 may be cited as the Alaska Unfair Trade Practices and Consumer Protection Act.
Article 4. Monopolies; Restraint of Trade.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-562">
            <num>45.50.562</num>
            <heading>Combinations in restraint of trade unlawful.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.562.   Combinations in restraint of trade unlawful.
Every contract, combination in the form of trust or otherwise, or conspiracy, in restraint of trade or commerce is unlawful.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-564">
            <num>45.50.564</num>
            <heading>Monopolies and attempted monopolies unlawful.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.564.   Monopolies and attempted monopolies unlawful.
It is unlawful for a person to monopolize, or attempt to monopolize, or combine or conspire with another person to monopolize any part of trade or commerce.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-566">
            <num>45.50.566</num>
            <heading>Transactions and agreements not to use or deal in commodities or services unlawful.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.566.   Transactions and agreements not to use or deal in commodities or services unlawful.
It is unlawful for a person to lease or make a sale or contract for sale of goods, wares, merchandise, machinery, supplies, or other commodities, or services, whether patented or unpatented, for use, consumption, enjoyment, or resale, or fix a price charged for it, or discount from, or rebate upon, that price, on the condition, agreement, or understanding that the lessee or purchaser will not use or deal in the goods, wares, merchandise, machinery, supplies, or other commodity or service of a competitor or competitors of the lessor or seller, if the effect of the lease, sale, or contract for sale, or of the condition, agreement, or understanding may be substantially to lessen competition or tend to create a monopoly in any line of commerce.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-568">
            <num>45.50.568</num>
            <heading>Mergers and acquisitions unlawful when competition lessened.</heading>
            <subsection eId="45-50-568__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>It is unlawful for a person to acquire and hold, directly or indirectly, the whole or a part of the stock, or other share capital, or assets of any corporation after August 5, 1975 if the effect of the acquisition and holding may be substantially to lessen competition or to tend to create a monopoly in any line of commerce in the state or in a section of the state. This subsection does not apply to persons purchasing such stock solely for investment if it is not used by voting or otherwise to bring about, or in attempting to bring about, the substantial lessening of competition.  Nothing in this subsection prevents a corporation from causing the formation of subsidiary corporations for the actual carrying on of their immediate lawful business, or the natural and legitimate branches or extensions of it, or from owning and holding all or a part of the stock of the subsidiary corporation, when the effect of the formation is not substantially to lessen competition.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-568__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the court finds that the effect of the holding of such stock, share capital, or assets is substantially to lessen competition or tends to create a monopoly and no other remedy will eliminate the lessening of competition or the tendency to create a monopoly, the court shall order the divestiture or other disposition of the stock, share capital, or assets and shall prescribe a reasonable time, manner, and degree of the divestiture or other disposition of it.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-568__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This section does not apply to mergers, acquisitions, or holding companies permitted by
AS 06.05.235
or to a merger carried out in accordance with
AS 21.69.590
 21.69.600, or to mergers, acquisitions, or holding companies permitted and regulated by a regulatory agency of the United States having jurisdiction and control over those mergers and acquisitions.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-570">
            <num>45.50.570</num>
            <heading>Interlocking directorates and relationships.</heading>
            <subsection eId="45-50-570__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>It is unlawful for a person to be at the same time a director, officer, partner, or trustee in any two or more firms, partnerships, trusts, associations, or corporations or any combination of them engaged in commerce, if these firms, partnerships, trusts, associations, or corporations or a combination of them, are by virtue of their business and location or operation, competitors and if the effect may be substantially to lessen competition or tend to create a monopoly.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-570__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not by the use of a representative accomplish the result prohibited in (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-570__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The validity or invalidity of an act of a director, officer, or trustee done by the director, officer, or trustee while occupying the position in violation of this section shall be determined by the statutory and common law of the state relating to corporations, trusts, or associations.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-570__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The attorney general may bring an action at any time to cause a director, officer, or trustee who may be occupying such a position in violation of this section to vacate the office or offices to effect the termination of the prohibited interlocking relationship.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-570__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person affected by an act of a director, officer, or trustee may bring an action at any time to cause the director, officer, or trustee who may be occupying the position in violation of this section to terminate the prohibited interlocking relationship.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-570__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The court, upon finding that a director, officer, or trustee is holding office in violation of this section, shall order the person to terminate the interlocking relationship, and, in the case of a trustee, the court may, when it considers it appropriate, order the trustee to vacate the office of the trustee. A remedy provided in this section does not limit and is in addition to any other remedy available under another section of this chapter or another law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-572">
            <num>45.50.572</num>
            <heading>Exemptions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="45-50-572__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>AS 45.50.562
  45.50.596 do not forbid the existence or operation of labor, agricultural, horticultural, or marine pilot organizations created for the purpose of mutual help, and not conducted for profit, or forbid or restrain members of those organizations from lawfully carrying out the legitimate objectives of them; nor are these organizations or members illegal combinations or conspiracies in restraint of trade under the provisions of
AS 45.50.562
  45.50.596.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-572__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>AS 45.50.562
  45.50.596 do not forbid actions or arrangements authorized or regulated under the laws of the United States that exempt these actions or arrangements from application of the antitrust laws of the United States or under the following statutes of this state:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-572__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>AS 06.05.235
and  06.05.570;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-572__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>AS 10.15
; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-572__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>AS 31.05.110
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-572__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>AS 45.50.562
  45.50.596 do not forbid persons engaged in the fishing industry as fishermen who catch, collect, or cultivate aquatic products from acting together in associations for the purpose of collectively catching, producing, preparing for market, processing, handling, and marketing their product. Associations may have marketing agencies in common and may make contracts and agreements necessary to achieve the purposes of this subsection. In this subsection, association means an association, corporate or otherwise, with or without capital stock, that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-572__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is operated for the mutual benefit of its members;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-572__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>does not deal in the aquatic products of nonmembers to an amount greater in value than the association handles for its members; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-572__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>either
(A) does not allow a member of the association more than one vote because of the amount of stock or membership capital the member may own in the association; or
(B) does not pay dividends on stock or membership capital in excess of eight percent a year.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-572__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>AS 45.50.562
  45.50.596 apply to long distance telecommunications services provided by public utilities.
AS 45.50.562
  45.50.596 do not apply to other services provided by public utilities that have been issued a certificate of public convenience and necessity under
AS 42.05
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-572__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 68 ch 21 SLA 1985.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-572__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 10 ch 75 SLA 1982.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-572__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>AS 45.50.562
  45.50.596 do not forbid activities expressly required by a regulatory agency of the state. Activities permitted by a regulatory agency of the state are not forbidden by this chapter if the regulatory agency has given due consideration to the possible anticompetitive effects before permitting the activities, and enforcement of the provisions of
AS 45.50.562
  45.50.596 would be disruptive of the regulatory scheme.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-572__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>AS 45.50.562
  45.50.596 do not forbid actions or arrangements necessary to carry out the provisions of the Alaska Native Claims Settlement Act.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-572__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>AS 45.50.562
  45.50.596 do not prohibit activities of the Alaska Housing Finance Corporation to stabilize the market price of and demand for residential housing in the state under
AS 18.56.210
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-572__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>AS 45.50.562
  45.50.596 do not forbid persons engaged in the fishing industry as fishermen, including fishermen acting through associations allowed under (c) of this section, from collectively agreeing with fish processors, including fish processors acting through associations of processors, on the (1) price paid to the fishermen for aquatic products; and (2) minimum price that fish processors will accept for the sale of processed aquatic products. Nothing in this subsection allows fish processors to agree among themselves on the price paid to fishermen or the minimum price that fish processors will accept for the sale of processed aquatic products if fishermen did not participate in the making of the agreement and are not a party to the agreement.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-572__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>AS 45.50.562
  45.50.596 do not apply to action taken by a person to comply with
AS 45.25
or to action refrained from by a person in order to comply with
AS 45.25
(motor vehicle transactions).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-572__subsec_l">
              <num>(l)</num>
              <content>
                <p>AS 45.50.562
  45.50.596 do not forbid the existence or operation of organizations of physicians acting in accordance with
AS 23.50
, or forbid or restrain members of those organizations from lawfully carrying out the legitimate objectives of them; nor are these organizations or members illegal combinations or conspiracies in restraint of trade under the provisions of
AS 45.50.562
  45.50.596.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-574">
            <num>45.50.574</num>
            <heading>Contracts voidable.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.574.   Contracts voidable.
A contract or agreement in violation of a provision of
AS 45.50.562
 45.50.596 is voidable by either party as to future performance by either party; however, the court may, in its discretion, order payment for goods or services already received to prevent unjust enrichment.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-576">
            <num>45.50.576</num>
            <heading>Suits by persons injured; treble damages; costs.</heading>
            <subsection eId="45-50-576__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who is injured in business or property by a violation of
AS 45.50.562
 45.50.570, or a person so injured because the person refuses to accede to a proposal for an arrangement that, if consummated, would be a violation of
AS 45.50.562
 45.50.570, may bring a civil action</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-576__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for damages sustained by the person, and, if the judgment is for the plaintiff, the plaintiff shall be awarded three times the amount of damages sustained by the person, plus the costs of the suit, including reasonable attorney fees; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-576__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to enjoin the unlawful practice, and, if the judgment is for the plaintiff, the plaintiff may be awarded costs of the suit, including reasonable attorney fees.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-576__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a home rule or general law city or borough or other governmental entity is injured by reason of a violation of
AS 45.50.562
 45.50.570, it may maintain an action in the same manner as prescribed in (a) of this section for an injured person, and the city, borough, or other governmental entity is entitled to the same relief as provided in (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-576__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In a civil action brought under
AS 45.50.562
 45.50.570, if judgment is for the defendant, the defendant shall be awarded the defendant's costs of the suit, including reasonable attorney fees in accordance with rules adopted by the supreme court for awarding costs and attorney fees to prevailing parties in civil actions. If the plaintiff in a civil action brought under this section in which judgment is for the defendant is a class certified under Rule 23, Alaska Rules of Civil Procedure, any award of costs and attorney fees to the defendant</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-576__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>may be satisfied only through funds, if any, that the class has collected from settlements with or judgments against other defendants; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-576__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is not a liability of any individual member of the class.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-577">
            <num>45.50.577</num>
            <heading>Enforcement by attorney general.</heading>
            <subsection eId="45-50-577__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The attorney general may bring a civil action in superior court to secure monetary relief as provided in this section on behalf of the state and its agencies injured either directly or indirectly by reason of any violation of
AS 45.50.562
 45.50.570.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-577__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The attorney general may bring a civil action in superior court in the name of the state, as parens patriae on behalf of governmental entities or persons doing business or residing in this state, to secure monetary relief as provided in this section for injuries directly or indirectly sustained by persons by reason of any violation of
AS 45.50.562
 45.50.570.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-577__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The court shall exclude from the amount of monetary relief awarded in an action under (a) or (b) of this section any amount of monetary relief that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-577__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>duplicates amounts that have been awarded for the same injury; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-577__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is properly allocable to persons who have excluded their claims under (e) of this section.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-577__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The court shall award the attorney general as monetary relief three times the total damage sustained as described in (a) or (b) of this section and, additionally, the costs of the action, including reasonable attorney fees.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-577__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In any action brought under (b) of this section, the attorney general, at the times, in the manner, and with the content the court directs, shall cause notice of the action to be given by publication. Any governmental entity or person on whose behalf an action is brought under (b) of this section may elect to exclude from civil action the portion of the state claim for monetary relief attributable to that governmental entity or person by filing notice of the election with the court within the time specified in the attorney general's notice given in accordance with this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-577__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The final judgment in an action under (a) or (b) of this section is res judicata as to any claim under
AS 45.50.576
by any governmental entity or person on whose behalf the action was brought and who fails to give notice of election to exclude under (e) of this section within the period specified in the attorney general's notice given under (e) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-577__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An action under (b) of this section may not be dismissed or compromised without the approval of the court, and notice of any proposed dismissal or compromise shall be given by publication at the times, in the manner, and with the content the court directs in accordance with (e) of this section and
AS 45.50.584
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-577__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Monetary relief recovered in an action under this section shall be (1) distributed in the manner the court, in its discretion, authorizes; or (2) deemed a civil penalty by the court and deposited in the general fund, and may be appropriated to the Alaska permanent fund (
AS 37.13.010
(a)) or for any other public purpose. A distribution procedure authorized by the court under this subsection must afford each governmental entity or person participating in the civil action a reasonable opportunity to secure that entity's or person's appropriate portion of the net monetary relief.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-577__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Only the attorney general, in a suit brought under this section, may seek monetary relief for injury indirectly sustained for a violation of
AS 45.50.562
 45.50.570.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-578">
            <num>45.50.578</num>
            <heading>Criminal and civil penalties.</heading>
            <subsection eId="45-50-578__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who violates
AS 45.50.562
or 45.50.564 is guilty of a class C felony and upon conviction is punishable,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-578__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if a natural person, by a fine of not more than $1,000,000, notwithstanding
AS 12.55.035
, or by imprisonment as provided in
AS 12.55
, or by both; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-578__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if not a natural person, by a fine of not more than $50,000,000, notwithstanding
AS 12.55.035
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-578__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to any other relief available, the attorney general may bring a civil action against a person who violates
AS 45.50.562
, 45.50.564, 45.50.568, or 45.50.570, or an injunction issued under
AS 45.50.580
, for a civil penalty of not more than</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-578__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>$1,000,000 if the person is a natural person;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-578__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>$50,000,000 if the person is not a natural person.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-579">
            <num>45.50.579</num>
            <heading>Proof of aggregate damages.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.579.   Proof of aggregate damages.
In a civil action brought by the attorney general under
AS 45.50.577
, the attorney general may recover aggregate damages by using statistical sampling or sampling methods, by the computation of illegal overcharges, or by a similar, reasonable system of estimating aggregate damages that the court, in its discretion, permits, without the necessity of separately proving the individual claim or amount of damage to governmental entities or persons on whose behalf the civil action was brought.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-580">
            <num>45.50.580</num>
            <heading>Injunction by attorney general.</heading>
            <subsection eId="45-50-580__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to any other relief provided by
AS 45.50.562
 45.50.596, the attorney general may bring an action to enjoin a violation of
AS 45.50.562
 45.50.596.  This action may be brought as a sole action or in conjunction with another action that the attorney general is authorized to bring.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-580__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The court may make additional orders or judgments as may be necessary to restore to a person in interest any money or property, real or personal, that may have been acquired by an act prohibited by
AS 45.50.562
 45.50.596, and as may be necessary to prevent continuing or future violations of
AS 45.50.562
 45.50.596.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-582">
            <num>45.50.582</num>
            <heading>Jurisdiction of court.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.582.   Jurisdiction of court.
An action arising under
AS 45.50.562
 45.50.596 shall be brought in the superior court.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-584">
            <num>45.50.584</num>
            <heading>Consent judgment.</heading>
            <subsection eId="45-50-584__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In an action maintained under
AS 45.50.562
 45.50.596, the parties to it may file with the court a consent judgment or decree.  The consent judgment or decree shall set out the alleged violations, future obligations of the parties, if any, damages, or other relief, the defendant agrees to make, if any, and the reasons for entering into the consent judgment or decree.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-584__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A consent judgment or decree does not become final until 60 days from its filing.  During the 60-day period an interested party may file verified exceptions to the form or substance of the consent judgment or decree, and the court, upon a full hearing on those exceptions, may approve or refuse to enter the consent judgment or decree.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-586">
            <num>45.50.586</num>
            <heading>Judgment in favor of the state as evidence in another action.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.586.   Judgment in favor of the state as evidence in another action.
A final judgment rendered in a civil or criminal action brought by the state under
AS 45.50.562
 45.50.596 is prima facie evidence against the defendant in any other action under
AS 45.50.562
 45.50.596 brought by another party, or by the state, a city, a borough, or other governmental entity; however, this section does not apply to consent judgments or decrees entered under
AS 45.50.584
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-588">
            <num>45.50.588</num>
            <heading>Limitation of actions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.588.   Limitation of actions.
An action to enforce a claim arising under
AS 45.50.562
 45.50.596 is barred unless commenced within four years after the claim accrues, except that when an action is brought by the attorney general under
AS 45.50.562
 45.50.596, the running of this period of limitation, with respect to every private right of action for damages that is based in whole or in part on a matter complained of in the action by the attorney general, shall be suspended during the pendency of the action brought by the attorney general.  For the purpose of this section, a claim for a continuing violation is considered to accrue at any time during the period of the violation.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-590">
            <num>45.50.590</num>
            <heading>Powers of the attorney general.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.590.   Powers of the attorney general.
If the attorney general determines, upon complaint or otherwise, that a person has engaged in, or engages in, or is about to engage in an act or practice prohibited or declared unlawful by
AS 45.50.562
 45.50.596, or that a person has assisted or participated in a plan, scheme, agreement, or combination of the nature described in
AS 45.50.562
 45.50.596, or when the attorney general believes it to be in the public interest, the attorney general may commence an investigation.  The attorney general may compel production of documentary material and take testimony, under oath, before the institution of an action under
AS 45.50.562
 45.50.596.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-592">
            <num>45.50.592</num>
            <heading>Investigatory demand for documentary evidence.</heading>
            <subsection eId="45-50-592__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the attorney general determines that a person is in possession, custody, or control of documentary evidence, wherever situated, that the attorney general believes to be relevant to an investigation authorized in
AS 45.50.590
, the attorney general may execute in writing and cause to be served on that person an investigative demand requiring the person to produce the documentary material, and permit inspection and copying.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-592__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each demand must</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-592__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>state the specific statute the alleged violation of which is under investigation, and the general subject matter of the investigation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-592__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>describe, with reasonable specificity so as fairly to indicate the material demanded, the documentary material to be produced;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-592__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>prescribe a return date within which the documentary material is to be produced; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-592__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>identify the state employees or representatives to whom the documentary material is to be made available for inspection and copying.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-592__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A demand may not</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-592__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>require the production of documentary material that would be privileged from disclosure if demanded by a subpoena duces tecum issued by a court of the state; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-592__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>contain a requirement that would be unreasonable or improper if contained in a subpoena duces tecum issued by a court of the state; however, this does not limit the power of the attorney general to require production of documents located outside the state that pertain to matters affecting the state.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-592__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The demand may be served by the attorney general or the designee of the attorney general by</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-592__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>delivering a copy of it to the person to be served or, if the person is not a natural person, to an officer of the person to be served;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-592__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>delivering a copy of it to a place of business in the state of the person to be served; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-592__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>mailing by registered or certified mail a copy of it addressed to the person to be served at a place of business in the state or, if the person has no place of business in the state, to the principal office or place of business of the person.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-592__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Documentary material produced pursuant to a demand, or copies of it, unless otherwise ordered by a superior court for good cause shown, may not be produced for inspection or copying by, nor may its contents be disclosed to, anyone other than an authorized employee of the state without the consent of the person who produced the material. However, under those reasonable terms and conditions the attorney general prescribes, copies of the documentary material shall be available for inspection and copying by the person who produced the material or an authorized representative of that person. The attorney general, or a designee, may use copies of the documentary material as the attorney general or designee considers necessary in the enforcement of
AS 45.50.562
 45.50.598, including presentation before a court; however, material that contains trade secrets may not be presented except with the approval of the court in which the action is pending after adequate notice to the person furnishing the material.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-592__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>At any time before the return date specified in the demand, or within 20 days after the demand has been served, whichever period is shorter, a petition to extend the return date for, or to modify or set aside a demand issued under (a) of this section, stating good cause, may be filed in the superior court for the judicial district where the parties reside.  A petition by a person on whom a demand is served, stating good cause, to require the attorney general or another person to act in accordance with the requirements of (e) of this section, and all other petitions in connection with a demand, may be filed in the superior court for the judicial district in which the person on whom the demand is served resides.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-592__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person on whom a demand is served under this section shall comply with the terms of the demand unless otherwise provided by an order of court issued in response to a petition filed under (f) of this section. A person who, with intent to avoid, prevent, or obstruct compliance, in whole or in part, with an investigative demand under this section, removes from any place, conceals, withholds, or destroys, mutilates, alters, or by any other means falsifies, documentary material in the possession, custody, or control of a person that is the subject of a demand duly served on any person, or who otherwise wilfully disobeys any such demand, is guilty of a misdemeanor, and is punishable upon conviction by a fine of not more than $5,000, or by imprisonment for a term of not more than one year, or by both. Failure of the state to serve the demand properly under (d) of this section is a defense to prosecution under this subsection, but invalidity of the demand under (b) or (c) of this section is not a defense, and that invalidity may be tested only in an action under (f) of this section to modify or set aside the demand.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-592__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing in this section impairs the authority of the attorney general or a designee to lay before a grand jury of this state evidence concerning a violation of
AS 45.50.562
 45.50.596, to invoke the power of a court to compel the production of evidence before a grand jury, or to file a civil complaint or criminal information alleging a violation of
AS 45.50.562
 45.50.596.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-594">
            <num>45.50.594</num>
            <heading>Investigatory demand for attendance of witness.</heading>
            <subsection eId="45-50-594__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In connection with an investigation authorized by
AS 45.50.590
, the attorney general may issue an investigative demand compelling the attendance of a person for examination under oath before the attorney general or before a court of record.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-594__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each demand shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-594__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>state the specific statute the alleged violation of which is under investigation, and the general subject matter of the investigation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-594__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>state the date, time, and place at which the examination is to take place.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-594__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A demand may be served by the attorney general, or a designee, in accordance with the procedures prescribed in
AS 45.50.592
(d).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-594__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a person ordered to attend the inquiry fails to attend without good cause, the person is guilty of a misdemeanor and upon conviction is punishable by a fine of not more than $5,000, or by imprisonment for not more than one year, or by both.  If a person in attendance at the inquiry refuses to answer a question on the ground that the person may be incriminated by the answer, and if the attorney general, or a designee, in a writing directed to the person being questioned orders the person to answer the question, the person shall comply with the order.  After complying, and if but for this section the person would have been privileged to withhold the answer given, the person may not be prosecuted for an offense or subjected to a penalty or forfeiture for or on account of a transaction, matter, or thing concerning which the person gave evidence. However, the person may nevertheless be prosecuted or subjected to penalty or forfeiture for a perjury, false swearing, or contempt committed in answering or failing to answer.  If a person refuses to testify after being granted immunity from prosecution and after being ordered to testify, the person may be adjudged in contempt and committed to jail until the time the person purges the contempt by testifying. A grant of immunity does not prevent the attorney general from instituting civil contempt proceedings against a person who violates any of the above provisions.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-596">
            <num>45.50.596</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.596.   Definitions.
In
AS 45.50.562
 45.50.596,
(1) asset includes any property, tangible or intangible, real, personal, or mixed and wherever located, and any other thing of value;
(2) documentary evidence includes an original or copy of a book, record, report, memorandum, paper, communication, tabulation, map, chart, photograph, mechanical tabulation, magnetic tape, or other computer data storage system, or other tangible document or recording;
(3) trade and commerce include trade in goods, merchandise, natural resources, whether or not severed, extracted, harvested, or produced, agricultural products, produce, choses in action, commodities, and any other article of commerce; trade and commerce include trade or business in service trades, transportation, banking, lending, advertising, bonding, and any other business whether or not that business furnishes a personal service.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-598">
            <num>45.50.598</num>
            <heading>Short title.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.598.   Short title.
AS 45.50.562
 45.50.598 may be cited as the Alaska Restraint of Trade Act.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-600">
            <num>45.50.600</num>
            <heading>Power and duty of director of civil defense.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.600.   Power and duty of director of civil defense.
The state director of civil defense
(1) may adopt regulations under
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act) defining fair standards in the advertising and sale of civil defense aids; and
(2) shall prohibit unfair or deceptive practices.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-601">
            <num>45.50.601</num>
            <heading>Content of regulations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.601.   Content of regulations.
Regulations adopted by the state director of civil defense must prohibit the following practices:
(1) exaggerated or misleading claims of protection afforded by shelters;
(2) the use of misleading pictures;
(3) the use of deceptive pricing practices;
(4) the use of guarantees in such a manner as to constitute a misrepresentation;
(5) representations of endorsement by a governmental agency; and
(6) any unfair or deceptive practice.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-602">
            <num>45.50.602</num>
            <heading>Content of installment or credit purchase plans.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.602.   Content of installment or credit purchase plans.
Installment or credit purchase plans for civil defense aids must include a clear statement of financial terms, including a statement of annual simple interest.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-603">
            <num>45.50.603</num>
            <heading>Prosecution by attorney general.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.603.   Prosecution by attorney general.
The attorney general shall prosecute any legal action on behalf of the state director of civil defense.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-604">
            <num>45.50.604</num>
            <heading>Criminal and civil penalties.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.604.   Criminal and civil penalties.
A person who violates a provision of
AS 45.50.600
 45.50.606 or a regulation adopted by the state director of civil defense under
AS 45.50.600
 45.50.606 is punishable by a fine of not more than $500, or by imprisonment for not more than six months, or, in the alternative, is subject to a civil penalty not more than $5,000.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-606">
            <num>45.50.606</num>
            <heading>Definition of civil defense aid.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.606.   Definition of civil defense aid.
In
AS 45.50.600
 45.50.606 civil defense aid means a product, service, structure, or improvement intended for use by civilians as a protection against a result of an attack by a foreign power on the United States and includes but is not limited to a protective shelter or improvement.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-800">
            <num>45.50.800</num>
            <heading>Disclosures to be made by distributors and refiners before conclusion of agreement.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.800.   Disclosures to be made by distributors and refiners before conclusion of agreement.
Before entry into a lease agreement, a refiner or distributor shall disclose to the dealer facts that would reasonably be considered material to the dealer's decision to enter into the lease. These facts must include, but not be limited to,
(1) ownership of property of the retail outlet;
(2) if the real property is not owned by a refiner or distributor, then the nature of the relationship between the real property owner and the refiner or distributor and the length of the underlying lease, if applicable;
(3) the last known addresses of dealers operating the retail outlet for the last five years;
(4) the gasoline gallonage history, if any, of the station for the last five years;
(5) any sales goals or quotas the refiners or distributors intend to apply to the station;
(6) the nearest gasoline outlet owned, controlled, or operated by the refiner or distributor and any plans the distributor or refiner has to open new retail outlets within the trade area of the retail outlet; and
(7) any plans the refiner or distributor has for the future of the subject retail outlet.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-810">
            <num>45.50.810</num>
            <heading>Violations.</heading>
            <subsection eId="45-50-810__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not, directly or indirectly, through officers, employees, or agents,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-810__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>require the dealer at the time of entering into the lease agreement to relieve any person from liability imposed by
AS 45.50.800
  45.50.850;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-810__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>require the dealer to agree to waive the right to a jury trial or any right of counterclaim the dealer may have;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-810__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>restrict or inhibit directly or indirectly the right of free association for any lawful purpose of the dealer;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-810__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>except as to the initial inventory, require a dealer to purchase or otherwise lease goods or services of a refiner or distributor or from an approved source of supply unless and to the extent that the refiner or distributor satisfies the burden of proving that such restricted purchasing agreements are reasonably necessary for lawful purposes justified on business grounds and do not substantially affect competition; in determining whether a requirement to purchase is lawful, the court shall be guided by the decisions of the courts of the United States in interpreting and applying the antitrust laws and the Federal Trade Commission Act of the United States;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-810__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>impose unreasonable standards of performance on the dealer;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-810__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>require a dealer to participate financially in the use of any premium coupon or giveaway or rebate in the operation of the business; however, a distributor may require the dealer to distribute premiums, coupons, or giveaways to customers that are provided to the dealer at the expense of the refiner or distributor or when the promotion is self-liquidating;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-810__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>fail to deal with the dealer in good faith;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-810__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>require the dealer to keep the retail outlet open for business more than 12 consecutive hours a day or more than six days a week; however, this paragraph may not be construed to prevent a retail outlet from being open when required to be open to conform to a state or federal law or regulation; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-810__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>require a dealer to purchase or rent a product or service for more than a fair and reasonable price.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-810__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A refiner or distributor may not, directly or indirectly, through any officer, agent, or employee, terminate, cancel, or fail to renew a dealer lease without first giving written notice setting out all of the reasons for the termination or cancellation, or intent not to renew to the dealer at least 45 days in advance of the termination, cancellation, or failure to renew except when</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-810__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the alleged grounds are voluntary abandonment by the dealer of the lessee relationship, the above notice may be given five days in advance of the termination, cancellation, or failure to renew;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-810__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the alleged grounds are the conviction of the dealer in a court of competent jurisdiction of a felony;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-810__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the lease specifically establishes a period of notice of less than 45 days in which either party may terminate the lease.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-810__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (d) of this section, a refiner or distributor may not terminate, cancel, or fail to renew a dealer lease without good cause. Good cause  includes</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-810__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the failure of a dealer to comply with the lawful material provisions of a lease between the distributor or refiner and the dealer and to cure each default after being given written notice and a reasonable opportunity to cure the default;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-810__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an adjudication that the dealer is a bankrupt or insolvent or if the dealer makes an assignment for the benefit of creditors or a similar disposition of assets of franchise business or voluntarily abandons the business or is convicted of or pleads guilty or no contest to a charge of violating any law relating to any business;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-810__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the good faith business decision of the lessor that the lessor no longer requires a retail outlet at that location for the marketing of gasoline; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-810__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the dealer's failure to sign the new agreement if at the time of renewal of the lease the distributor or refiner and the dealer cannot agree upon new terms and the terms offered by the refiner or distributor do not violate any other laws of the state or of the United States and the terms are essentially the same as those offered to other dealers in similar retail outlets and do not discriminate against the subject dealer.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-810__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A refiner or distributor  may provide in the lease for its termination without cause during a reasonable trial period, not to exceed one year, if the dealer involved has not already been a dealer of a refiner or distributor for that period of time.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-810__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A refiner or distributor may not engage in price discrimination between dealers if the effect of the discrimination may be substantially to lessen competition unless that discrimination is based upon quantity purchased or transportation costs or capital investment of the dealer. Nothing in this section prevents a refiner or distributor from offering a lower price or furnishing a service or facility to a dealer when the offer is made in good faith to meet an equally low price of a competitor, or the services or facilities furnished by that competitor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-820">
            <num>45.50.820</num>
            <heading>Obligation of distributor to repurchase upon termination, etc., of agreement.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.820.   Obligation of distributor to repurchase upon termination, etc., of agreement.
If the refiner or distributor terminates, cancels, or fails to renew under
AS 45.50.810
(c)(1), (2), or (3) or for any good cause other than under
AS 45.50.810
(c)(4), the refiner or distributor shall compensate the dealer for the fair market value of the business, excluding goodwill. Refiners or distributors terminating, canceling, or failing to renew under
AS 45.50.810
(c)(4) shall compensate the dealer for the fair market value of the business, including good will. Valuation other than good will shall include the fair market value of the dealer's inventory supplies, equipment, and furnishings purchased from the refiner or distributor exclusive of personalized materials that do not have a value to the refiner or distributor and inventory supplies, equipment, and furnishings not reasonably required in the conduct of the business. Compensation shall be made within 60 days from the date of termination unless it is necessary that a lawsuit be filed under
AS 45.50.830
. The refiner or distributor may offset against accounts owed by the dealer under this section any amount owed by the dealer to the refiner or distributor.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-825">
            <num>45.50.825</num>
            <heading>Right of first refusal of surviving spouse.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.825.   Right of first refusal of surviving spouse.
Unless provided otherwise by the lease, upon the death of the lessee the lease shall terminate and the surviving spouse shall have the right of first refusal of the new lease if the surviving spouse has been an active participant in the business and is qualified.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-830">
            <num>45.50.830</num>
            <heading>Court to determine fair market value when parties cannot agree.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.830.   Court to determine fair market value when parties cannot agree.
If under
AS 45.50.820
the distributor or refiner has good cause and the distributor or refiner and the dealer cannot agree on the fair market value of the business, then either party may initiate an action in the superior court where the retail outlet exists. Reasonable attorney fees and the appraiser fees shall be awarded to the dealer if the amount awarded to the dealer by the jury or the court is 10 percent higher than the final offer, if any, made by the refiner or distributor before the filing of the lawsuit.  If the amount awarded to the dealer by the jury or the court is 10 percent lower than the final offer, if any, made by the refiner or distributor before the filing of the lawsuit, reasonable attorney fees and the appraiser fees shall be awarded to the refiner or distributor.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-840">
            <num>45.50.840</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.840.   Definitions.
In
AS 45.50.800
 45.50.830, unless the context otherwise requires,
(1) dealer means a person primarily engaged in the sale of gasoline to the motoring public through a retail outlet leased from the refiner or distributor or its agent by the person and operated by the person;
(2) distributor means any person or corporation other than a refiner engaged in the sale, assignment, or distribution of gasoline to four or more dealer-operated retail outlets;
(3) gasoline means all products commonly or commercially known or sold as gasoline;
(4) lease means an oral or written contract or agreement or series of agreements, either express or implied, in which the dealer is required directly or indirectly to purchase 50 percent or more of the dealer's supply of gasoline from a distributor or refiner and in which the dealer is granted authority to occupy premises owned, leased, or in any way controlled, directly or indirectly, by the refiner or distributor;
(5) refiner means a company, corporation, or individual who owns or controls, or controls through a substantially owned subsidiary, partnership, or joint venture, a refinery used for the production of gasoline, diesel, or other motor vehicle fuels.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-850">
            <num>45.50.850</num>
            <heading>Short title.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.850.   Short title.
AS 45.50.800
 45.50.850 may be cited as the Alaska Gasoline Products Leasing Act.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-900">
            <num>45.50.900</num>
            <heading>Reproduction and sale of sound recordings without consent.</heading>
            <subsection eId="45-50-900__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who (1) reproduces for sale, sells, offers for sale, or knowingly advertises for sale any sound recording that has been reproduced without the written consent of the owner or (2) advertises, offers for sale or resale, or sells or resells a phonograph record, disc, wire, tape, film, or other article on which sounds are recorded, without clearly and conspicuously disclosing on the outside cover, box, or jacket the actual name and full address of the manufacturer and the name of the actual performer or group, is guilty of a misdemeanor and, upon conviction, is punishable by confiscation of the unlawful stock of the reproduced recording and by imprisonment for a period of not more than one year, or by a fine of not more than $1,000, or by both.  In this subsection owner means the person who owns the original fixation of sounds embodied in the master phonograph record, master disc, master tape, master film, or other device used for reproducing sounds on phonograph records, discs, tapes, films, or other articles upon which sound is recorded, and from which the transferred recorded sounds are directly derived.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-900__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The prohibition contained in (a) of this section is not applicable to the reproduction of a sound recording that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-900__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is used, or intended to be used, solely for broadcast by commercial or educational radio or television stations; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-900__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>constitutes the verbatim transcript, or other public record, of the proceedings of a judicial, legislative, or administrative agency, department, or other public body for which a charge or fee may or may not be made or collected for the reproduced recording.
Article 8. Alaska Uniform Trade Secrets Act.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-910">
            <num>45.50.910</num>
            <heading>Injunctive relief for misappropriation of trade secrets.</heading>
            <subsection eId="45-50-910__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A court may enjoin actual or threatened misappropriation of trade secrets. Upon application to the court, an injunction shall be terminated when the trade secret has ceased to exist, but the injunction may be continued for an additional reasonable period of time in order to eliminate commercial advantage that otherwise would be derived from the misappropriation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-910__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the court determines that it would be unreasonable to prohibit future use of a trade secret, an injunction may condition future use upon payment of a reasonable royalty for no longer than the period of time the use could have been prohibited.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-910__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In appropriate circumstances, affirmative acts to protect a trade secret may be compelled by court order.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-915">
            <num>45.50.915</num>
            <heading>Damages.</heading>
            <subsection eId="45-50-915__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to or in lieu of injunctive relief, a complainant may recover damages for the actual loss caused by misappropriation. A complainant also may recover for the unjust enrichment caused by misappropriation that is not taken into account in computing damages for actual loss.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-915__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If wilful and malicious misappropriation exists, the court may award exemplary damages in an amount not exceeding twice the damages awarded under (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-920">
            <num>45.50.920</num>
            <heading>Preservation of secrecy.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.920.   Preservation of secrecy.
In an action under
AS 45.50.910
 45.50.945, a court shall preserve the secrecy of an alleged trade secret by reasonable means, which may include granting protective orders in connection with discovery proceedings, holding in-camera hearings, sealing the records of the action, and ordering any person involved in the litigation not to disclose an alleged trade secret without prior court approval.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-925">
            <num>45.50.925</num>
            <heading>Limitation of actions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.925.   Limitation of actions.
An action for misappropriation must be brought within three years after the misappropriation is discovered or by the exercise of reasonable diligence should have been discovered. For the purposes of this section, a continuing misappropriation constitutes a single claim.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-930">
            <num>45.50.930</num>
            <heading>Effect on other laws.</heading>
            <subsection eId="45-50-930__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>AS 45.50.910
 45.50.945 displace conflicting tort, restitutionary, and other state laws pertaining to civil liability for misappropriation of a trade secret.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-930__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>AS 45.50.910
 45.50.945 do not affect</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-930__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>contractual or other civil liability or relief that is not based upon misappropriation of a trade secret; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-930__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>criminal liability for misappropriation of a trade secret.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="45-50-930__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>AS 45.50.910
 45.50.945 do not apply to investigations or actions by the attorney general under
AS 45.50.471
 45.50.561 (Alaska Unfair Trade Practices and Consumer Protection Act) or under
AS 45.50.562
 45.50.596 (Alaska Restraint of Trade Act).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-935">
            <num>45.50.935</num>
            <heading>Uniformity of application and construction.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.935.   Uniformity of application and construction.
AS 45.50.910
 45.50.945 shall be applied and construed to make the law uniform with respect to trade secrets among states enacting similar provisions.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-940">
            <num>45.50.940</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="45-50-940__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>used improper means to acquire knowledge of the trade secret; or
(ii) at the time of disclosure or use, knew or had reason to know that knowledge of the trade secret was derived from or through a person who had utilized improper means to acquire it or who owed a duty to the person seeking relief to maintain its secrecy or limit its use, or was acquired under circumstances giving rise to a duty to maintain its secrecy or limit its use; or
(iii) before a material change of the person's position, knew or had reason to know that it was a trade secret and that knowledge of it had been acquired by accident or mistake;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="45-50-940__subsec_i__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>trade secret means information that
(A) derives independent economic value, actual or potential, from not being generally known to, and not being readily ascertainable by proper means by, other persons who can obtain economic value from its disclosure or use; and
(B) is the subject of efforts that are reasonable under the circumstances to maintain its secrecy.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_45-50-945">
            <num>45.50.945</num>
            <heading>Short title.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 45.50.945.   Short title.
AS 45.50.910
 45.50.945 may be cited as the Alaska Uniform Trade Secrets Act.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>