<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-13/chapter-70"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-13/chapter-70"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="13.70"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-13/chapter-70/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-13/chapter-70/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-13/chapter-70/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-13/chapter-70/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_13">
        <num>13</num>
        <heading>Decedents' Estates, Guardianships, Transfers, Trusts, and Health Care Decisions</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_13__chp_70">
          <num>70</num>
          <heading>Disclaimer of Property Interests</heading>
          <section eId="sec_13-70-010">
            <num>13.70.010</num>
            <heading>Scope.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.70.010.   Scope.
This chapter applies to disclaimers of any interest in or power over property, whenever created.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-70-020">
            <num>13.70.020</num>
            <heading>Supplemented by other law.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-70-020__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless displaced by a provision of this chapter, the principles of law and equity supplement this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-70-020__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This chapter does not limit any right of a person to waive, release, disclaim, or renounce an interest in or power over property under a law other than this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-70-030">
            <num>13.70.030</num>
            <heading>Power to disclaim; general requirements; when irrevocable.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-70-030__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may disclaim, in whole or part, conditionally or unconditionally, any interest in or power over property, including a power of appointment. A person may disclaim the interest or power even if its creator imposed a spendthrift provision or similar restriction on transfer or a restriction, prohibition, or limitation on the right to disclaim. A disclaimer shall be considered to be unconditional and not subject to modification or revocation unless the disclaimant provides otherwise in the disclaimer.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-70-030__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>With court approval, a fiduciary may disclaim, in whole or part, any interest in or power over property, including a power of appointment. Without court approval, a fiduciary may not disclaim, in whole or in part, any interest in or power over property, including a power of appointment, except that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="13-70-030__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a fiduciary may disclaim, in whole or in part, any interest in or power over property, including a power of appointment, if and to the extent that the instrument creating the fiduciary relationship grants the fiduciary the right to disclaim;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-70-030__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in the absence of a court-appointed guardian, notwithstanding a provision in
AS 13.26
to the contrary, an individual having legal custody of a minor child may disclaim on behalf of the minor child, in whole or in part, any interest in or power over property, including a power of appointment, that the minor child is to receive solely as a result of another disclaimer, but only if the interest or power disclaimed by the individual having legal custody does not pass, as a result of the disclaimer, to or for the benefit of the individual having legal custody.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-70-030__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To be effective, a disclaimer must be in writing, declare that the writing is a disclaimer, describe the interest or power disclaimed, be signed by the person making the disclaimer, and be delivered or filed in the manner provided in
AS 13.70.100
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-70-030__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A partial disclaimer may be expressed as a fraction, percentage, monetary amount, term of years, limitation of a power, or any other interest or estate in the property.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-70-030__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A disclaimer becomes irrevocable when</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="13-70-030__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>any conditions to which the disclaimant has made the disclaimer subject are satisfied; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-70-030__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the disclaimer is delivered or filed under
AS 13.70.100
, or becomes effective as provided in
AS 13.70.040
 13.70.090, whichever occurs later.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-70-030__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A disclaimer made under this chapter is not a transfer, assignment, or release.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-70-040">
            <num>13.70.040</num>
            <heading>Disclaimer of interest in property.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-70-040__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except for a disclaimer governed by
AS 13.70.050
 13.70.065, the following rules apply to a disclaimer of an interest in property:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="13-70-040__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the disclaimer takes effect as of the time the instrument creating the interest becomes irrevocable or, if the interest arose under the law of intestate succession, as of the time of the intestate's death;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-70-040__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the disclaimed interest passes according to any provision in the instrument creating the interest providing for the disposition of the interest, should it be disclaimed, or of disclaimed interests in general;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-70-040__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if the instrument does not contain a provision described in (2) of this subsection, the following rules apply:
(A) if the disclaimant is not an individual, the disclaimed interest passes as if the disclaimant did not exist;
(B) if the disclaimant is an individual, except as otherwise provided in (C) and (D) of this paragraph, the disclaimed interest passes as if the disclaimant had died immediately before the interest was created, unless, under the governing instrument or other applicable law, the disclaimed interest is contingent on surviving to the time of distribution, in which case, the disclaimed interest passes as if the disclaimant had died immediately before the time for distribution;
(C) if, by law or under the instrument, the descendants of the disclaimant would share in the disclaimed interest by any method of representation had the disclaimant died before the time of distribution, the disclaimed interest passes only to the descendants of the disclaimant who survive the time of distribution;
(D) if the disclaimed interest would pass to the disclaimant's estate had the disclaimant died before the time of distribution, the disclaimed interest instead passes by representation to the descendants of the disclaimant who survive the time of distribution; if no descendant of the disclaimant survives the time of distribution, the disclaimed interest passes to those persons, including the state but excluding the disclaimant, and in the shares as would succeed to the transferor's intestate estate under the intestate succession law of the transferor's domicile had the transferor died at the time of distribution; however, if the transferor's surviving spouse is living but is remarried at the time of distribution, the transferor is considered to have died unmarried at the time of distribution;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-70-040__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>on the disclaimer of a preceding interest, a future interest held by a person other than the disclaimant takes effect as if the disclaimant had died or ceased to exist immediately before the time of distribution, but a future interest held by the disclaimant is not accelerated in possession or enjoyment as a result of the disclaimer.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-70-040__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For the purposes of (a)(3) of this section, a disclaimed interest</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="13-70-040__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is created at
(A) the death of the benefactor; or
(B) an earlier time, if any, when the benefactor's transfer of the interest is a completed gift for federal gift tax purposes; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-70-040__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in a revocable trust is treated as if the interest had been created under a will.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-70-040__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="13-70-040__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>benefactor means the creator of the interest that is subject to a disclaimer;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-70-040__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>future interest means an interest that takes effect in possession or enjoyment, if at all, later than the time of its creation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-70-040__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>time of distribution means the time when a disclaimed interest would have taken effect in possession or enjoyment.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-70-050">
            <num>13.70.050</num>
            <heading>Disclaimer of rights of survivorship in jointly held property.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-70-050__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>On the death of a holder of jointly held property, a surviving holder may disclaim, in whole or part, the greater of</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="13-70-050__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a fractional share of the property determined by dividing the number one by the number of joint holders alive immediately before the death of the holder to whose death the disclaimer relates; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-70-050__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>all of the property except that part of the value of the entire interest attributable to the contribution furnished by the disclaimant.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-70-050__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A disclaimer under (a) of this section takes effect as of the death of the holder of jointly held property to whose death the disclaimer relates.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-70-050__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An interest in jointly held property disclaimed by a surviving holder of the property passes as if the disclaimant predeceased the holder to whose death the disclaimer relates.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-70-060">
            <num>13.70.060</num>
            <heading>Disclaimer of interest in property held as a tenancy by the entirety.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-70-060__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The survivorship interest in property that is held as a tenancy by the entirety and to which the survivor succeeds by operation of law on the death of the cotenant may be disclaimed as provided in this chapter. For the purposes of this chapter only, the deceased tenant's interest in property held as a tenancy by the entirety is considered to be an undivided one-half interest.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-70-060__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A disclaimer under (a) of this section takes effect as of the death of the deceased tenant to whose death the disclaimer relates.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-70-060__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The survivorship interest in property held as a tenancy by the entirety and disclaimed by the surviving tenant passes as if the disclaimant had predeceased the tenant to whose death the disclaimer relates.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-70-065">
            <num>13.70.065</num>
            <heading>Disclaimer of interest by trustee.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.70.065.   Disclaimer of interest by trustee.
If a trustee who has the power to disclaim under a court order or under the instrument creating the fiduciary relationship disclaims an interest in property that otherwise would have become trust property, the interest does not become trust property.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-70-070">
            <num>13.70.070</num>
            <heading>Disclaimer of power of appointment or other power not held in fiduciary capacity.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.70.070.   Disclaimer of power of appointment or other power not held in fiduciary capacity.
If a holder disclaims a power of appointment or other power not held in a fiduciary capacity, the following rules apply:
(1) if the holder has not exercised the power, the disclaimer takes effect as of the time the instrument creating the power becomes irrevocable;
(2) if the holder has exercised the power and the disclaimer is of a power other than a presently exercisable general power of appointment, the disclaimer takes effect immediately after the last exercise of the power;
(3) the instrument creating the power is construed as if the power expired when the disclaimer became effective.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-70-080">
            <num>13.70.080</num>
            <heading>Disclaimer by appointee, object, or taker in default of exercise of power of appointment.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-70-080__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A disclaimer of an interest in property by an appointee of a power of appointment takes effect as of the time the instrument by which the holder exercises the power becomes irrevocable.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-70-080__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A disclaimer of an interest in property by an object or taker in default of an exercise of a power of appointment takes effect as of the time the instrument creating the power becomes irrevocable.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-70-090">
            <num>13.70.090</num>
            <heading>Disclaimer of power held in fiduciary capacity.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-70-090__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a fiduciary disclaims a power held in a fiduciary capacity that has not been exercised, the disclaimer takes effect as of the time the instrument creating the power becomes irrevocable.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-70-090__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a fiduciary disclaims a power held in a fiduciary capacity that has been exercised, the disclaimer takes effect immediately after the last exercise of the power.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-70-090__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A disclaimer under this section is effective as to another fiduciary if the disclaimer so provides and the fiduciary disclaiming has the authority to bind the estate, trust, or other person for whom the fiduciary is acting.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-70-100">
            <num>13.70.100</num>
            <heading>Delivery or filing.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-70-100__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subject to (b)  (l) of this section, delivery of a disclaimer may be effected by personal delivery, first class mail, or any other method likely to result in its receipt. A disclaimer sent by first class mail is considered to have been delivered on the date it is postmarked. Delivery by personal delivery or any other method is effective on receipt by the person to whom the disclaimer is to be delivered under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-70-100__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In the case of an interest created under the law of intestate succession or an interest created by will, other than an interest in a testamentary trust,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="13-70-100__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a disclaimer shall be delivered to the personal representative of the decedent's estate; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-70-100__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if a personal representative is not then serving, it shall be filed with a court having jurisdiction to appoint the personal representative.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-70-100__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In the case of an interest in a testamentary trust,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="13-70-100__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a disclaimer shall be delivered to the trustee then serving, or if a trustee is not then serving, to the personal representative of the decedent's estate; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-70-100__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if no personal representative is then serving, a disclaimer shall be filed with a court having jurisdiction to enforce the trust.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-70-100__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In the case of an interest in an inter vivos trust,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="13-70-100__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a disclaimer shall be delivered to the trustee then serving;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-70-100__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if no trustee is then serving, a disclaimer shall be filed with a court having jurisdiction to enforce the trust; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-70-100__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if the disclaimer is made before the time the instrument creating the trust becomes irrevocable, the disclaimer shall be delivered to the settlor of a revocable trust or the transferor of the interest, or the legal representative of the settlor or transferor.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-70-100__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In the case of an interest created by a beneficiary designation that is disclaimed before the designation becomes irrevocable, the disclaimer shall be delivered to the person making the beneficiary designation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-70-100__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In the case of an interest created by a beneficiary designation that is disclaimed after the designation becomes irrevocable, the disclaimer of an interest in</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="13-70-100__subsec_f__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>personal property shall be delivered to the person obligated to distribute the interest; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-70-100__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>real property shall be recorded in the office of the recorder in the recording district where the real property that is the subject of the disclaimer is located.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-70-100__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In the case of a disclaimer by a surviving holder of jointly held property or by the surviving tenant of property held as a tenancy by the entirety, the disclaimer shall be delivered to the person to whom the disclaimed interest passes, or, if the person cannot reasonably be located by the disclaimant, the disclaimer shall be delivered as provided by (b) of this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-70-100__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In the case of a disclaimer by an object or taker in default of exercise of a power of appointment at any time after the power was created,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="13-70-100__subsec_h__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the disclaimer shall be delivered to the holder of the power or to the fiduciary acting under the instrument that created the power; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-70-100__subsec_h__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if no fiduciary is then serving, the disclaimer shall be filed with a court having authority to appoint the fiduciary.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-70-100__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In the case of a disclaimer by an appointee of a nonfiduciary power of appointment,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="13-70-100__subsec_i__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the disclaimer shall be delivered to the holder, the personal representative of the holder's estate, or to the fiduciary under the instrument that created the power; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-70-100__subsec_i__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if no fiduciary is then serving, the disclaimer shall be filed with a court having authority to appoint the fiduciary.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-70-100__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In the case of a disclaimer by a fiduciary of a power over a trust or estate, the disclaimer shall be delivered as provided in (b)  (d) of this section, as if the power disclaimed were an interest in property.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-70-100__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In the case of a disclaimer of a power by an agent, except a power exercisable by a fiduciary over a trust or estate, the disclaimer shall be delivered to the principal or the principal's representative.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-70-100__subsec_l">
              <num>(l)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When a disclaimer of an interest in or relating to real property is recorded in the judicial district where the real property is located, there is a rebuttable presumption that the disclaimer has been delivered.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-70-100__subsec_m">
              <num>(m)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, beneficiary designation means an instrument, other than an instrument creating or amending a trust, naming the beneficiary of</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="13-70-100__subsec_m__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an annuity or insurance policy;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-70-100__subsec_m__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an account with a designation for payment on death;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-70-100__subsec_m__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a security registered in beneficiary form;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-70-100__subsec_m__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a pension, profit-sharing, retirement, or other employment-related benefit plan; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-70-100__subsec_m__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>any other nonprobate transfer at death.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-70-110">
            <num>13.70.110</num>
            <heading>When disclaimer permitted, barred, or limited.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-70-110__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A disclaimer is permitted unless barred under (b)  (f) of this section. A disclaimer is permitted even though the disclaimant is insolvent.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-70-110__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A disclaimer is barred by a written waiver of the right to disclaim.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-70-110__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A disclaimer of an interest in property is barred if any of the following events occurs before the disclaimer becomes effective:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="13-70-110__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the disclaimant accepts the interest sought to be disclaimed;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-70-110__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the disclaimant voluntarily assigns, conveys, encumbers, pledges, or transfers the interest sought to be disclaimed or contracts to assign, convey, encumber, pledge, or transfer the interest sought to be disclaimed; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-70-110__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a judicial sale or a nonjudicial foreclosure sale of the interest sought to be disclaimed occurs.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-70-110__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A disclaimer, in whole or part, of the future exercise of a power held in a fiduciary capacity is not barred by its previous exercise.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-70-110__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A disclaimer, in whole or part, of the future exercise of a power not held in a fiduciary capacity is not barred by its previous exercise unless the power is exercisable in favor of the disclaimant.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-70-110__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A disclaimer of an interest in or power over property under this chapter is barred and is not effective</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="13-70-110__subsec_f__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to the extent the disclaimant is in arrears in child support payments; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-70-110__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if the disclaimant is involved in a pending court or administrative proceeding to establish or modify the disclaimant's child support obligation or to establish whether the disclaimant is the biological father or mother of a child.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-70-110__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A disclaimer of a power over property that is barred by this section is ineffective. A disclaimer of an interest in property that is barred by this section takes effect as a transfer of the interest disclaimed to the persons who would have taken the interest under this chapter had the disclaimer not been barred.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-70-120">
            <num>13.70.120</num>
            <heading>Tax-qualified disclaimer.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-70-120__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding any other provision of this chapter, if, as a result of a disclaimer or transfer, the disclaimed or transferred interest is treated under the provisions of 26 U.S.C. (Internal Revenue Code) as never having been transferred to the disclaimant, then the disclaimer or transfer is effective as a disclaimer under this chapter. In this section, 26 U.S.C. (Internal Revenue Code) includes 26 U.S.C. as amended, any successor statute to 26 U.S.C. or 26 U.S.C. as amended, and regulations adopted under 26 U.S.C., 26 U.S.C. as amended, and any successor statute to 26 U.S.C. or 26 U.S.C. as amended.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-70-120__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A tax-qualified disclaimer under 26 U.S.C. (Internal Revenue Code) is subject to the time limits under 26 U.S.C., as amended, even though time limits are not specified under this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-70-130">
            <num>13.70.130</num>
            <heading>Recording of disclaimer.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.70.130.   Recording of disclaimer.
If an instrument transferring an interest in or power over property subject to a disclaimer is required or permitted by law to be filed, recorded, or registered, the disclaimer may be filed, recorded, or registered as required or permitted by law. Except as otherwise provided in
AS 13.70.100
(f)(2), failure to file, record, or register the disclaimer does not affect its validity as between the disclaimant and persons to whom the property interest or power passes by reason of the disclaimer.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-70-140">
            <num>13.70.140</num>
            <heading>Application to existing relationships.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.70.140.   Application to existing relationships.
Except as otherwise provided in
AS 13.70.110
, an interest in or power over property existing on September 7, 2010 as to which the time for delivering or filing a disclaimer under law superseded by this chapter has not expired may be disclaimed after September 7, 2010.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-70-150">
            <num>13.70.150</num>
            <heading>Uniformity of application and construction.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.70.150.   Uniformity of application and construction.
In applying and construing this chapter, consideration must be given to the need to promote uniformity of the law with respect to its subject matter among states that enact it.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-70-190">
            <num>13.70.190</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-70-190__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>an express trust, charitable or noncharitable, with additions to the express trust, whenever and however created; and
(ii) a trust created under a statute, judgment, or decree that requires the trust to be administered in the manner of an express trust;
(B) does not include a constructive trust or a resulting trust.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-70-195">
            <num>13.70.195</num>
            <heading>Short title.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.70.195.   Short title.
This chapter may be cited as the Uniform Disclaimer of Property Interests Act.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>