<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-25/chapter-25"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-25/chapter-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="25.25"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-25/chapter-25/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-25/chapter-25/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-25/chapter-25/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-25/chapter-25/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_25">
        <num>25</num>
        <heading>Marital and Domestic Relations</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_25__chp_25">
          <num>25</num>
          <heading>Uniform Interstate Family Support Act</heading>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-101">
            <num>25.25.101</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.25.101.   Definitions.
In this chapter,
(1) child means an individual, whether over or under the age of majority, who is or is alleged to be owed a duty of support by the individual's parent or who is or is alleged to be the beneficiary of a support order directed to the parent;
(2) child support order means a support order for a child, including a child who has attained the age of majority under the law of the issuing state or foreign country;
(3) convention means the Convention on the International Recovery of Child Support and Other Forms of Family Maintenance, concluded at The Hague on November 23, 2007;
(4) duty of support means an obligation imposed or imposable by law to provide support for a child, spouse, or former spouse, including an unsatisfied obligation to provide support;
(5) foreign country means a country, including a political subdivision of a country, other than the United States, that authorizes the issuance of support orders and
(A) that has been declared under the law of the United States to be a foreign reciprocating country;
(B) that has established a reciprocal arrangement for child support with this state as provided in
AS 25.25.308
(b);
(C) that has enacted a law or established procedures for the issuance and enforcement of support orders that are substantially similar to the procedures under this chapter; or
(D) in which the convention is in force with respect to the United States;
(6) foreign support order means a support order of a foreign tribunal;
(7) foreign tribunal means a court, administrative agency, or quasi-judicial entity of a foreign country that is authorized to establish, enforce, or modify support orders or determine parentage of a child; foreign tribunal includes a competent authority under the convention;
(8) home state means the state or the foreign country in which a child lived with a parent or a person acting as a parent for at least six consecutive months immediately preceding the time of filing of a complaint or comparable pleading for support and, if a child is less than six months old, the state or the foreign country in which the child lived from birth with a parent or person acting as a parent; a period of temporary absence of a parent or person acting as a parent is counted as part of the six-month or other period;
(9) income includes earnings or other periodic entitlements to money from any source and any other property subject to withholding for support under the law of this state;
(10) income withholding order means an order or other legal process directed to an obligor, an obligor's employer, an obligor's future employer, or another person, political subdivision, or department of the state, under
AS 25.27
to withhold support from the income of the obligor under
AS 25.27
;
(11) initiating tribunal means the tribunal of a state or foreign country from which a complaint or comparable pleading is forwarded or in which a complaint or comparable pleading is filed for forwarding to another state or foreign country;
(12) issuing foreign country means the foreign country in which a tribunal issues a support order or a judgment determining parentage of a child;
(13) issuing state means the state in which a tribunal issues a support order or a judgment determining parentage of a child;
(14) issuing tribunal means the tribunal of a state or foreign country that issues a support order or a judgment determining parentage of a child;
(15) law includes decisional and statutory law and rules and regulations having the force of law;
(16) obligee means
(A) an individual to whom a duty of support is or is alleged to be owed or in whose favor a support order or a judgment determining parentage of a child has been issued;
(B) a foreign country, state, or political subdivision of a state to which the rights under a duty of support or support order have been assigned or that has independent claims based on financial assistance provided to an individual obligee in place of child support;
(C) an individual seeking a judgment determining parentage of the individual's child; or
(D) a person that is a creditor in a proceeding under
AS 25.25.702
 25.25.714;
(17) obligor means an individual or the estate of a decedent that
(A) owes or is alleged to owe a duty of support;
(B) is alleged but has not been adjudicated to be a parent of a child;
(C) is liable under a support order; or
(D) is a debtor in a proceeding under
AS 25.25.702
 25.25.714;
(18) outside this state means a location in another state or a country other than the United States, whether or not the country is a foreign country;
(19) person means an individual, corporation, business trust, estate, trust, partnership, limited liability company, association, joint venture, public corporation, government or governmental subdivision, agency, or instrumentality, or any other legal or commercial entity;
(20) record means information that is inscribed on a tangible medium or that is stored in an electronic or other medium and is retrievable in perceivable form.
(21) register means to file in a tribunal of this state a support order or judgment issued in another state or a foreign country determining parentage of a child;
(22) registering tribunal means the tribunal in which a support order or judgment determining parentage of a child is registered;
(23) responding state means a state in which a complaint or comparable pleading for support or to determine parentage of a child is filed or to which a complaint or comparable pleading is forwarded for filing from another state or foreign country;
(24) responding tribunal means the authorized tribunal in a responding state or foreign country;
(25) spousal support order means a support order for a spouse or former spouse of the obligor;
(26) state means a state of the United States, the District of Columbia, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, the United States Virgin Islands, or any territory or insular possession subject to the jurisdiction of the United States; the term state includes an Indian nation or tribe;
(27) support enforcement agency means a public official, governmental entity, or private agency authorized to
(A) seek enforcement of support orders or laws relating to the duty of support;
(B) seek establishment or modification of child support orders;
(C) request determination of parentage of a child;
(D) attempt to locate obligors or their assets; or
(E) request determination of the controlling child support order;
(28) support order means a judgment, decree, order, decision, or directive, whether temporary, final, or subject to modification, issued in a state or foreign country for the benefit of a child, a spouse, or a former spouse, that provides for monetary support, health care, arrearages, retroactive support, or reimbursement for financial assistance provided to an individual obligee in place of child support; support order may include related costs and fees, interest, income withholding, automatic adjustment, reasonable attorney fees, and other relief;
(29) tribunal means a court, administrative agency, or quasi-judicial entity authorized to establish, enforce, or modify support orders or to determine parentage of a child.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-102">
            <num>25.25.102</num>
            <heading>State tribunal and support enforcement.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-25-102__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The superior court and the child support services agency are the tribunals of this state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-102__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The child support services agency created in
AS 25.27.010
is the support enforcement agency of this state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-103">
            <num>25.25.103</num>
            <heading>Remedies cumulative.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-25-103__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Remedies provided by this chapter are cumulative and do not affect the availability of remedies under other law or the recognition of a support order on the basis of comity.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-103__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This chapter does not</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-103__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide the exclusive method of establishing or enforcing a support order under the law of this state; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-103__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>grant a tribunal of this state jurisdiction to render judgment or issue an order relating to child custody or visitation in a proceeding under this chapter.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-104">
            <num>25.25.104</num>
            <heading>Application of this chapter to resident of foreign country and foreign support proceeding.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-25-104__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A tribunal of this state shall apply
AS 25.25.101
 25.25.616 and, as applicable,
AS 25.25.702
 25.25.714, to a support proceeding involving</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-104__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a foreign support order;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-104__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a foreign tribunal; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-104__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an obligee, obligor, or child residing in a foreign country.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-104__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A tribunal of this state that is requested to recognize and enforce a support order on the basis of comity may apply the procedural and substantive provisions of
AS 25.25.101
 25.25.616.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-104__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>AS 25.25.702
 25.25.714 apply only to a support proceeding under the convention. In such a proceeding, if a provision of
AS 25.25.702
 25.25.714 is inconsistent with
AS 25.25.101
 25.25.616,
AS 25.25.702
 25.25.714 controls.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-201">
            <num>25.25.201</num>
            <heading>Bases for jurisdiction over nonresident.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-25-201__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In a proceeding to establish or enforce a support order or to determine parentage of a child, a tribunal of this state may exercise personal jurisdiction over a nonresident individual or the individual's guardian or conservator if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-201__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the individual is personally served with a citation, summons, or notice within this state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-201__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the individual submits to the jurisdiction of this state by consent in a record, by entering a general appearance, or by filing a responsive document having the effect of waiving any contest to personal jurisdiction;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-201__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the individual resided with the child in this state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-201__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the individual resided in this state and provided prenatal expenses or support for the child;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-201__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the child resides in this state as a result of the acts or directives of the individual;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-201__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the individual engaged in sexual intercourse in this state and the child may have been conceived by that act of intercourse;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-201__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the individual acknowledged parentage of a child in a writing deposited with the Bureau of Vital Statistics under
AS 25.20.050
; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-201__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>there is another basis consistent with the constitutions of this state and the United States for the exercise of personal jurisdiction.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-201__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The bases of personal jurisdiction set out in (a) of this section or in any other law of this state may not be used to acquire personal jurisdiction for a tribunal of this state to modify a child support order of another state unless the requirements of
AS 25.25.611
are met or, in the case of a foreign support order, unless the requirements of
AS 25.25.615
are met.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-202">
            <num>25.25.202</num>
            <heading>Duration of personal jurisdiction.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.25.202.   Duration of personal jurisdiction.
Personal jurisdiction acquired by a tribunal of this state in a proceeding under this chapter or other law of this state relating to a support order continues as long as a tribunal of this state has continuing, exclusive jurisdiction to modify its order or continuing jurisdiction to enforce its order as provided by
AS 25.25.205
, 25.25.206, and 25.25.281.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-203">
            <num>25.25.203</num>
            <heading>Initiating and responding tribunal of this state.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.25.203.   Initiating and responding tribunal of this state.
Under this chapter, a tribunal of this state may serve as an initiating tribunal to forward proceedings to a tribunal of another state and as a responding tribunal for proceedings initiated in another state or a foreign country.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-204">
            <num>25.25.204</num>
            <heading>Simultaneous proceedings.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-25-204__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A tribunal of this state may exercise jurisdiction to establish a support order if the complaint or comparable pleading is filed after a complaint or comparable pleading is filed in another state or a foreign country only if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-204__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the complaint or comparable pleading in this state is filed before the expiration of the time allowed in the other state or the foreign country for filing a responsive pleading challenging the exercise of jurisdiction by the other state or the foreign country;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-204__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the contesting party timely challenges the exercise of jurisdiction in the other state or the foreign country; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-204__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if relevant, this state is the home state of the child.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-204__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A tribunal of this state may not exercise jurisdiction to establish a support order if the complaint or comparable pleading is filed before a complaint or comparable pleading is filed in another state or a foreign country if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-204__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the complaint or comparable pleading in the other state or the foreign country is filed before the expiration of the time allowed in this state for filing a responsive pleading challenging the exercise of jurisdiction by this state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-204__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the contesting party timely challenges the exercise of jurisdiction in this state; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-204__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if relevant, the other state or the foreign country is the home state of the child.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-205">
            <num>25.25.205</num>
            <heading>Continuing, exclusive jurisdiction to modify child support order.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-25-205__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A tribunal of this state that has issued a child support order consistent with the law of this state has and shall exercise continuing, exclusive jurisdiction to modify its child support order if the order is the controlling order and,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-205__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>at the time of the filing of a request for modification, this state is the residence of the obligor, the individual obligee, or the child for whose benefit the support order is issued; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-205__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>even if this state is not the residence of the obligor, the individual obligee, or the child for whose benefit the support order is issued, the parties consent in a record or in open court that the tribunal of this state may continue to exercise jurisdiction to modify its order.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-205__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A tribunal of this state that has issued a child support order consistent with the law of this state may not exercise continuing, exclusive jurisdiction to modify the order if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-205__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>all of the parties who are individuals file consent in a record with the tribunal of this state that a tribunal of another state that has jurisdiction over at least one of the parties who is an individual or that is located in the state of residence of the child may modify the order and assume continuing, exclusive jurisdiction; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-205__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the tribunal's order is not the controlling order.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-205__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a tribunal of another state has issued a child support order under this chapter or a law substantially similar to this chapter that modifies a child support order of a tribunal of this state, a tribunal of this state shall recognize the continuing, exclusive jurisdiction of the tribunal of the other state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-205__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A tribunal of this state that lacks continuing, exclusive jurisdiction to modify a child support order may serve as an initiating tribunal to request a tribunal of another state to modify a support order issued in that state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-205__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A temporary support order issued ex parte or pending resolution of a jurisdictional conflict does not create continuing, exclusive jurisdiction in the issuing tribunal.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-205__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 32 ch 102 SLA 2015.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-206">
            <num>25.25.206</num>
            <heading>Continuing jurisdiction to enforce child support order.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-25-206__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A tribunal of this state that has issued a child support order consistent with the laws of this state may serve as an initiating tribunal to request a tribunal of another state to enforce</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-206__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the order if the order is the controlling order and has not been modified by a tribunal of another state that assumed jurisdiction under this chapter; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-206__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a money judgment for arrears of support and interest on the order accrued before a determination that an order of a tribunal of another state is the controlling order.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-206__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A tribunal of this state having continuing jurisdiction over a support order may act as a responding tribunal to enforce the order.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-206__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 32 ch 102 SLA 2015.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-207">
            <num>25.25.207</num>
            <heading>Determination of controlling child support order.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-25-207__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a proceeding is brought under this chapter and only one tribunal has issued a child support order, the order of that tribunal is controlling and shall be recognized.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-207__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a proceeding is brought under this chapter and two or more child support orders have been issued by tribunals of this state, another state, or a foreign country with regard to the same obligor and same child, a tribunal of this state having personal jurisdiction over both the obligor and individual obligee shall apply the following rules and shall determine, by order, which order controls and must be recognized:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-207__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if only one of the tribunals would have continuing, exclusive jurisdiction under this chapter, the order of that tribunal is controlling and shall be recognized;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-207__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if more than one of the tribunals would have continuing, exclusive jurisdiction under this chapter,
(A) an order issued by a tribunal in the current home state of the child controls; or
(B) if an order has not been issued in the current home state of the child, the order most recently issued controls;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-207__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if none of the tribunals would have continuing, exclusive jurisdiction under this chapter, the tribunal of this state shall issue a child support order, which controls.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-207__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If two or more child support orders have been issued for the same obligor and same child, upon request of a party who is an individual or that is a support enforcement agency, a tribunal of this state having personal jurisdiction over both the obligor and the obligee who is an individual shall determine which order controls under (b) of this section. The request may be filed with a registration for enforcement or a registration for modification under
AS 25.25.601
 25.25.616 or may be filed as a separate proceeding.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-207__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The tribunal that issued the controlling order under (a), (b), or (c) of this section has continuing jurisdiction to the extent provided in
AS 25.25.205
or 25.25.206.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-207__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A tribunal of this state that determines, by order, which is the controlling child support order under (b)(1) or (2) or (c) of this section, or that issues a new controlling child support order under (b)(3) of this section, shall include in that order</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-207__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the basis upon which the tribunal made its determination;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-207__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the amount of prospective support, if any; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-207__subsec_e__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the total amount of consolidated arrears and accrued interest, if any, under all of the orders after all payments made are credited as provided by
AS 25.25.209
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-207__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Within 30 days after issuance of the order determining which is the controlling order, the party obtaining that order shall file a certified copy of that order in each tribunal that had issued or registered an earlier order of child support. Failure of the party or the support enforcement agency obtaining the order to file a certified copy as required under this subsection subjects that party to appropriate sanctions by a tribunal in which the issue of failure to file arises, but that failure has no effect on the validity or enforceability of the controlling order.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-207__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A request to determine which is the controlling order must be accompanied by a copy of every child support order in effect and the applicable record of payments. The requesting party shall give notice of the request to each party whose rights may be affected by the determination.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-207__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An order that has been determined to be the controlling order, or a judgment for consolidated arrears of support and interest, if any, made under this section must be recognized in proceedings under this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-208">
            <num>25.25.208</num>
            <heading>Child support orders for two or more obligees.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.25.208.   Child support orders for two or more obligees.
In responding to registrations or complaints for enforcement of two or more child support orders in effect at the same time with regard to the same obligor and different individual obligees, when at least one of the orders was issued by a tribunal of another state or a foreign country, a tribunal of this state shall enforce those orders in the same manner as if the orders had been issued by a tribunal of this state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-209">
            <num>25.25.209</num>
            <heading>Credit for payments.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.25.209.   Credit for payments.
A tribunal of this state shall credit amounts collected for a particular period under any child support order against the amounts owed for the same period under any other child support order for support of the same child issued by a tribunal of this state, another state, or a foreign country.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-280">
            <num>25.25.280</num>
            <heading>Application of this chapter to nonresident subject to personal jurisdiction.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.25.280.   Application of this chapter to nonresident subject to personal jurisdiction.
A tribunal of this state exercising personal jurisdiction over a nonresident in a proceeding under this chapter, under other law of this state relating to a support order, or recognizing a foreign support order may receive evidence from outside this state under
AS 25.25.316
, communicate with a tribunal outside this state under
AS 25.25.317
, and obtain discovery through a tribunal outside this state under
AS 25.25.318
. In all other respects,
AS 25.25.301
 25.25.616 do not apply, and the tribunal shall apply the procedural and substantive law of this state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-281">
            <num>25.25.281</num>
            <heading>Continuing, exclusive jurisdiction to modify spousal support order.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-25-281__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A tribunal of this state issuing a spousal support order consistent with the law of this state has continuing, exclusive jurisdiction to modify the spousal support order throughout the existence of the support obligation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-281__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A tribunal of this state may not modify a spousal support order issued by a tribunal of another state or a foreign country having continuing, exclusive jurisdiction over that order under the law of that state or foreign country.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-281__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A tribunal of this state that has continuing, exclusive jurisdiction over a spousal support order may serve as</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-281__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an initiating tribunal to request a tribunal of another state to enforce the spousal support order issued in this state; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-281__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a responding tribunal to enforce or modify its own spousal support order.
Article 3. Civil Provisions of General Application.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-301">
            <num>25.25.301</num>
            <heading>Proceedings under this chapter.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-25-301__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as otherwise provided in this chapter,
AS 25.25.301
 25.25.319 apply to all proceedings under this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-301__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 32 ch 102 SLA 2015.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-301__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An individual or a support enforcement agency may initiate a proceeding authorized under this chapter by filing a complaint or a comparable pleading in an initiating tribunal for forwarding to a responding tribunal or by filing a complaint or a comparable pleading directly in a tribunal of another state or a foreign country that has or can obtain personal jurisdiction over the respondent.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-302">
            <num>25.25.302</num>
            <heading>Proceeding by minor parent.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.25.302.   Proceeding by minor parent.
A minor parent, or a guardian or other legal representative of a minor parent, may maintain a proceeding on behalf of or for the benefit of the minor's child.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-303">
            <num>25.25.303</num>
            <heading>Application of law of this state.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.25.303.   Application of law of this state.
Except as otherwise provided in this chapter, a responding tribunal of this state shall
(1) apply the procedural and substantive law generally applicable to similar proceedings originating in this state and may exercise all powers and provide all remedies available in those proceedings; and
(2) determine the duty of support and the amount payable under the law and support guidelines of this state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-304">
            <num>25.25.304</num>
            <heading>Duties of initiating tribunal.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-25-304__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon the filing of a complaint or comparable pleading authorized by this chapter, an initiating tribunal of this state shall forward the complaint or comparable pleading and its accompanying documents</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-304__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to the responding tribunal or appropriate support enforcement agency in the responding state; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-304__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if the identity of the responding tribunal is unknown, to the state information agency of the responding state with a request that they be forwarded to the appropriate tribunal and that receipt be acknowledged.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-304__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If requested by the responding tribunal, a tribunal of this state shall issue a certificate or other documents and make findings required by the law of the responding state. If the responding tribunal is in a foreign country, upon request, the tribunal of this state shall specify the amount of support sought, convert the amount into the equivalent amount in the foreign currency under the applicable official or market exchange rate as publicly reported, and provide any other documents necessary to satisfy the requirements of the responding foreign tribunal.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-305">
            <num>25.25.305</num>
            <heading>Duties and powers of responding tribunal.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-25-305__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When a responding tribunal of this state receives a complaint or comparable pleading from an initiating tribunal or directly under
AS 25.25.301
(c), it shall cause the complaint or pleading to be filed and notify the petitioner where and when it was filed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-305__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A responding tribunal of this state, to the extent not prohibited by law, may do one or more of the following:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-305__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establish or enforce a support order, modify a child support order, determine the controlling child support order, or determine parentage of the child;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-305__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>order an obligor to comply with a support order, specifying the amount and the manner of compliance;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-305__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>order income withholding;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-305__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>determine the amount of any arrearages, and specify a method of payment;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-305__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>enforce orders by civil or criminal contempt, or both;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-305__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>set aside property for satisfaction of the support order;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-305__subsec_b__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>place liens and order execution on the obligor's property;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-305__subsec_b__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>order an obligor to keep the tribunal informed of the obligor's current residential address, electronic mailing address, telephone number, employer, address of employment, and telephone number at the place of employment;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-305__subsec_b__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>issue a bench warrant for an obligor who has failed after proper notice to appear at a hearing ordered by the tribunal and enter the bench warrant in any local and state computer systems for criminal warrants;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-305__subsec_b__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>order the obligor to seek appropriate employment by specified methods;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-305__subsec_b__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>award reasonable attorney fees and other fees and costs; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-305__subsec_b__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>grant any other available remedy.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-305__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A responding tribunal of this state shall include in a support order issued under this chapter, or in the documents accompanying the order, the calculations on which the support order is based.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-305__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A responding tribunal of this state may not condition the payment of a support order issued under this chapter upon compliance by a party with provisions for visitation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-305__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a responding tribunal of this state issues an order under this chapter, the tribunal shall send a copy of the order to the petitioner and the respondent and to the initiating tribunal, if any.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-305__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If requested to enforce a support order, arrears, or judgment or modify a support order stated in a foreign currency, a responding tribunal of this state shall convert the amount stated in the foreign currency to the equivalent amount in dollars under the applicable official or market exchange rate as publicly reported.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-306">
            <num>25.25.306</num>
            <heading>Inappropriate tribunal.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.25.306.   Inappropriate tribunal.
If a complaint or comparable pleading is received by an inappropriate tribunal of this state, the tribunal shall forward the complaint or pleading, and accompanying documents, to an appropriate tribunal in this state or another state and notify the petitioner where and when the complaint or pleading was sent.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-307">
            <num>25.25.307</num>
            <heading>Duties of child support services agency.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-25-307__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The child support services agency of this state, upon request, shall provide services to a petitioner in a proceeding under this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-307__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In providing services under this chapter to the petitioner, the child support services agency of this state shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-307__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>take all steps necessary to enable an appropriate tribunal of this state, another state, or a foreign country to obtain jurisdiction over the respondent;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-307__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>request an appropriate tribunal to set a date, time, and place for a hearing;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-307__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>make a reasonable effort to obtain all relevant information, including information as to income and property of the parties;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-307__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>send notice in a record from an initiating, responding, or registering tribunal to the petitioner within five days after receipt, exclusive of Saturdays, Sundays, and legal holidays;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-307__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>send a copy of a communication in a record from the respondent or the respondent's attorney to the petitioner within five days after receipt, exclusive of Saturdays, Sundays, and legal holidays; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-307__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>notify the petitioner if jurisdiction over the respondent cannot be obtained.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-307__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This chapter does not create or negate a relationship of attorney and client or other fiduciary relationship between the child support services agency or the attorney for the agency and the individual being assisted by the agency.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-307__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A support enforcement agency of this state that requests registration of a child support order in this state for enforcement or modification shall make reasonable efforts</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-307__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to ensure that the order to be registered is the controlling order; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-307__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if two or more child support orders exist and the identity of the controlling order has not been determined, to ensure that a request for the determination is made in a tribunal having jurisdiction to do so.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-307__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A support enforcement agency of this state that requests registration and enforcement of a support order, arrears, or judgment stated in a foreign currency shall convert the amounts stated in the foreign currency into the equivalent amounts in dollars under the applicable official or market exchange rate as publicly reported.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-307__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A support enforcement agency of this state shall issue or request a tribunal of this state to issue a child support order and an income withholding order that redirect payment of current support, arrears, and interest if requested to do so by a support enforcement agency of another state under
AS 25.25.319
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-308">
            <num>25.25.308</num>
            <heading>Duty of the Department of Revenue.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-25-308__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the Department of Revenue determines that the support enforcement agency is neglecting or refusing to provide services to an individual, the Department of Revenue may order the agency to perform its duties under this chapter or may provide those services directly to the individual.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-308__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Revenue may determine that a foreign country has established a reciprocal arrangement for child support with this state and take appropriate action for notification of the determination.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-309">
            <num>25.25.309</num>
            <heading>Private counsel.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.25.309.   Private counsel.
An individual may employ private counsel to represent the individual in proceedings authorized by this chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-310">
            <num>25.25.310</num>
            <heading>Duties of state information and locator agency.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.25.310.   Duties of state information and locator agency.
The child support services agency is the state information agency under this chapter, and it shall
(1) compile and maintain a current list, including addresses, of the tribunals in this state that have jurisdiction under this chapter and the appropriate agency offices in this state and transmit a copy to the state information agency of every other state;
(2) maintain a register of the names and addresses of tribunals and support enforcement agencies received from other states;
(3) forward to the appropriate tribunal in this state all documents concerning a proceeding under this chapter received from another state or a foreign country; and
(4) obtain information concerning the location of the obligor and the obligor's property within this state that is not exempt from execution by postal verification and federal or state locator services, examination of telephone directories, requests for the obligor's address from employers, and examination of governmental records, including, to the extent not prohibited by other law, those relating to real property, vital statistics, law enforcement, taxation, motor vehicles, driver's licenses, and social security.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-311">
            <num>25.25.311</num>
            <heading>Pleadings and accompanying documents.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-25-311__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In a proceeding under this chapter, a petitioner seeking to establish a support order to determine parentage of a child or to register and modify a support order of a tribunal of another state or a foreign country shall file a complaint or comparable pleading. Unless otherwise ordered under
AS 25.25.312
, or otherwise prohibited by law, the complaint or comparable pleading or accompanying documents must provide, so far as known, the name, residential address, and social security numbers of the obligor and the obligee or the parent and the alleged parent, and the name, sex, residential address, social security number, and date of birth of each child for whose benefit support is sought or whose parentage is to be determined. Unless filed at the time of registration, the complaint or comparable pleading must be accompanied by a copy of any support order known to have been issued by another tribunal. The complaint or comparable pleading may include other information that may assist in locating or identifying the respondent.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-311__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The complaint or comparable pleading must specify the relief sought. The complaint or comparable pleading and accompanying documents must conform substantially with the requirements imposed by the forms mandated by federal law for use in cases filed by a support enforcement agency.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-312">
            <num>25.25.312</num>
            <heading>Nondisclosure of information in exceptional circumstances.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.25.312.   Nondisclosure of information in exceptional circumstances.
If a party alleges in an affidavit or a pleading under oath that the health, safety, or liberty of a party or child would be jeopardized by disclosure of specific identifying information, that information must be sealed and may not be disclosed to the other party or the public. After a hearing in which a tribunal takes into consideration the health, safety, or liberty of the party or child, the tribunal may order disclosure of information that the tribunal determines to be in the interest of justice.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-313">
            <num>25.25.313</num>
            <heading>Costs and fees.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-25-313__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, including a rule of the Alaska Supreme Court, at the time a complaint or comparable pleading is filed under this chapter, a tribunal may not require the petitioner to pay a filing fee or other costs.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-313__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If an obligee prevails, a responding tribunal of this state may assess against an obligor filing fees, including fees that were waived under (a) of this section, reasonable attorney fees, other costs, necessary travel expenses, and other reasonable expenses incurred by the obligee and the obligee's witnesses. The tribunal may not assess fees, costs, or expenses against the obligee or the support enforcement agency of either the initiating or the responding state or foreign country except as required by other law or court rule. Attorney fees may be taxed as costs, and may be ordered paid directly to the attorney, who may enforce the order in the attorney's own name. Payment of support owed to the obligee has priority over fees, costs, and expenses assessed under this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-313__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The tribunal shall order the payment of costs and reasonable attorney fees, including filing fees that were waived under (a) of this section, by a party who requests a hearing under this chapter if it determines that the hearing was requested primarily for delay. In a proceeding under
AS 25.25.601
 25.25.612, a hearing is presumed to have been requested primarily for delay if a registered support order is confirmed or enforced without change; however, the party who requested the hearing may present evidence to rebut this presumption.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-314">
            <num>25.25.314</num>
            <heading>Limited immunity of petitioner.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-25-314__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Participation by a petitioner in a proceeding under this chapter before a responding tribunal, whether in person, by private attorney, or through services provided by the support enforcement agency, does not confer personal jurisdiction over the petitioner in another proceeding.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-314__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A petitioner is not amenable to service of civil process while physically present in this state to participate in a proceeding under this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-314__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The immunity granted by this section does not extend to civil litigation based on acts unrelated to a proceeding under this chapter committed by a party while present in this state to participate in the proceeding.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-315">
            <num>25.25.315</num>
            <heading>Nonparentage as defense.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.25.315.   Nonparentage as defense.
A party whose parentage of a child has been previously determined under law may not plead nonparentage as a defense to a proceeding under this chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-316">
            <num>25.25.316</num>
            <heading>Special rules of evidence and procedure.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-25-316__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The physical presence of a nonresident party who is an individual in a tribunal of this state is not required for the establishment, enforcement, or modification of a support order or the rendition of a judgment determining parentage of a child.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-316__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An affidavit, a document substantially complying with federally mandated forms, or a document incorporated by reference in any of them, which would not be excluded under the hearsay rule if given in person, is admissible in evidence if given under penalty of perjury by a party or witness residing outside this state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-316__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A copy of the record of child support payments certified as a true copy of the original by the custodian of the record may be forwarded to a responding tribunal. The copy is evidence of facts asserted in it and is admissible to show whether payments were made.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-316__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Copies of bills for testing for parentage of a child, and for prenatal and postnatal health care of the mother and child, furnished to the adverse party at least 10 days before trial or other proceeding, are admissible in evidence to prove the amount of the charges billed and that the charges were reasonable, necessary, and customary.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-316__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Documentary evidence transmitted from outside this state to a tribunal of this state by telephone, facsimile, or other electronic means that do not provide an original record may not be excluded from evidence on an objection based on the means of transmission.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-316__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In a proceeding under this chapter, a tribunal of this state shall permit a party or witness residing outside this state to be deposed or to testify under penalty of perjury by telephone, audiovisual means, or other electronic means at a designated tribunal or other location. A tribunal of this state shall cooperate with other tribunals in designating an appropriate location for the deposition or testimony.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-316__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a party called to testify at a civil hearing refuses to answer on the ground that the testimony may be self-incriminating, the trier of fact may draw an adverse inference from the refusal.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-316__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A privilege against disclosure of communications between spouses does not apply in a proceeding under this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-316__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The defense of immunity based on the relationship of husband and wife or parent and child does not apply in a proceeding under this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-317">
            <num>25.25.317</num>
            <heading>Communications between tribunals.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.25.317.   Communications between tribunals.
A tribunal of this state may communicate with a tribunal outside this state in a record, or by telephone, electronic mail, or other means, to obtain information concerning the laws, the legal effect of a judgment, decree, or order of that tribunal, and the status of a proceeding. A tribunal of this state may furnish similar information by similar means to a tribunal outside this state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-318">
            <num>25.25.318</num>
            <heading>Assistance with discovery.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.25.318.   Assistance with discovery.
A tribunal of this state may
(1) request a tribunal outside this state to assist in obtaining discovery; and
(2) upon request, compel a person over which it has jurisdiction to respond to a discovery order issued by a tribunal outside this state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-319">
            <num>25.25.319</num>
            <heading>Receipt and disbursement of payments.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-25-319__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The child support services agency of this state shall disburse promptly any amounts received under a support order, as directed by the order. The agency shall furnish to a requesting party or tribunal of another state or a foreign country a certified statement by the custodian of the record of the amounts and dates of all payments received.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-319__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If neither the obligor, nor the obligee who is an individual, nor the child resides in this state, upon request from the support enforcement agency of this state or another state, the support enforcement agency of this state or a tribunal of this state shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-319__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>direct that the support payment be made to the support enforcement agency of the state in which the obligee is receiving services; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-319__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>issue and send to the obligor's employer a conforming income withholding order or an administrative notice of change of payee, reflecting the redirected payments.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-319__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The support enforcement agency of this state receiving redirected payments from another state under a law similar to (b) of this section shall furnish to a requesting party or tribunal of the other state a certified statement by the custodian of the record of the amount and dates of all payments received.
Article 4. Establishment of Support Order or Determination of Parentage.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-401">
            <num>25.25.401</num>
            <heading>Establishment of support order.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-25-401__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a support order entitled to recognition under this chapter has not been issued, a responding tribunal of this state with personal jurisdiction over the parties may issue a support order if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-401__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the individual seeking the order resides outside this state; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-401__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the support enforcement agency seeking the order is located outside this state.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-401__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The tribunal may issue a temporary child support order if the tribunal determines that an order is appropriate and the individual ordered to pay is</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-401__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a presumed father of the child;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-401__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>petitioning to have the individual's paternity adjudicated;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-401__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>identified as the father of the child through genetic testing;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-401__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an alleged father who has declined to submit to genetic testing;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-401__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shown by clear and convincing evidence to be the father of the child;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-401__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an acknowledged father under
AS 25.20.050
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-401__subsec_b__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the mother of the child; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-401__subsec_b__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an individual who has been ordered to pay child support in a previous proceeding and the order has not been reversed or vacated.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-401__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 32 ch 102 SLA 2015.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-401__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If, after providing an obligor with notice and opportunity to be heard, an appropriate tribunal finds that the obligor owes a duty of support, the tribunal shall issue a support order directed to the obligor and may issue other orders under
AS 25.25.305
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-401__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before issuing an order under (b) of this section, the child support services agency shall adopt regulations for issuing such an order.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-402">
            <num>25.25.402</num>
            <heading>Proceeding to determine parentage.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.25.402.   Proceeding to determine parentage.
A tribunal of this state authorized to determine parentage of a child may serve as a responding tribunal in a proceeding to determine parentage of a child brought under this chapter or a law or procedure substantially similar to this chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-501">
            <num>25.25.501</num>
            <heading>Employer's receipt of income withholding order of another state.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.25.501.   Employer's receipt of income withholding order of another state.
An income withholding order issued in another state may be sent by or on behalf of the obligee, or by the support enforcement agency, to the person defined as the obligor's employer under
AS 25.27
without first filing a complaint or comparable pleading or registering the order with a tribunal of this state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-502">
            <num>25.25.502</num>
            <heading>Employer's compliance with income withholding order of another state.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-25-502__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon receipt of an order under
AS 25.25.501
, the obligor's employer shall immediately provide a copy of the order to the obligor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-502__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The employer shall treat an income withholding order issued in another state that appears regular on its face as if it were issued by a tribunal of this state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-502__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided by (d) of this section and
AS 25.25.503
, the employer shall withhold and distribute the funds as directed in the withholding order by complying with the terms of the order, as applicable, that specify</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-502__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the duration and the amount of periodic payments of current child support, stated as a sum certain;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-502__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the person designated to receive payments and the address to which the payments are to be forwarded;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-502__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>medical support, whether in the form of periodic cash payment, stated as a sum certain, or an order to the obligor to provide health insurance coverage for the child under a policy available through the obligor's employment;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-502__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the amount of periodic payments of fees and costs for a support enforcement agency, the issuing tribunal, and the obligee's attorney, stated as sums certain; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-502__subsec_c__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the amount of periodic payments of arrearages and interest on arrearages, stated as sums certain.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-502__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The employer shall comply with the law of the state of the obligor's principal place of employment for withholding from income with respect to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-502__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the employer's fee for processing an income withholding order;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-502__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the maximum amount permitted to be withheld from the obligor's income; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-502__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the time periods within which the employer must implement the withholding order and forward the child support payment.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-503">
            <num>25.25.503</num>
            <heading>Employer's compliance with two or more income withholding orders.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.25.503.   Employer's compliance with two or more income withholding orders.
If an obligor's employer receives two or more orders to withhold support from the earnings of the same obligor, the employer shall be considered to have satisfied the terms of the orders if the employer complies with the law of the state of the obligor's principal place of employment to establish the priorities for withholding and allocating income withheld for two or more child support obligees.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-504">
            <num>25.25.504</num>
            <heading>Immunity from civil liability.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.25.504.   Immunity from civil liability.
An employer that complies with an income withholding order issued in another state in accordance with
AS 25.25.501
 25.25.505 is not subject to civil liability to an individual or agency with regard to the employer's withholding of child support from the obligor's income.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-505">
            <num>25.25.505</num>
            <heading>Penalties for noncompliance.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.25.505.   Penalties for noncompliance.
An employer that wilfully fails to comply with an income withholding order issued in another state and received for enforcement is subject to the same penalties that may be imposed for noncompliance with an order issued by a tribunal of this state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-506">
            <num>25.25.506</num>
            <heading>Contest by obligor.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-25-506__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An obligor may contest the validity or enforcement of an income withholding order issued in another state and received directly by an employer in this state by registering the order in a tribunal of this state and filing a contest to that order as provided in
AS 25.25.601
 25.25.616 or otherwise contesting the order in the same manner as if the order were issued by a tribunal of this state. The provisions of
AS 25.25.604
apply to the contest.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-506__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The obligor shall give notice of the contest to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-506__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a support enforcement agency providing services to the obligee;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-506__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>each employer that has directly received an income withholding order relating to the obligor; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-506__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if
(A) a person is designated to receive payments in the income withholding order, to that person; or
(B) no person is designated to receive payments in the income withholding order, to the obligee.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-507">
            <num>25.25.507</num>
            <heading>Administrative enforcement of orders.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-25-507__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A party or support enforcement agency seeking to enforce a support order or an income withholding order, or both, issued in another state or a foreign support order may send the documents required for registering the order to the child support services agency of this state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-507__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon receipt of the documents, the child support services agency, without initially seeking to register the order, shall consider and, if appropriate, use any administrative procedure authorized by the law of this state to enforce a support order or an income withholding order, or both. If the obligor does not contest administrative enforcement, the order need not be registered. If the obligor contests the validity or administrative enforcement of the order, the child support services agency shall register the order under this chapter.
Article 6. Registration, Enforcement, and Modification of Support Order.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-601">
            <num>25.25.601</num>
            <heading>Registration of order for enforcement.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.25.601.   Registration of order for enforcement.
A support order or income withholding order issued in another state or a foreign support order may be registered in this state for enforcement.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-602">
            <num>25.25.602</num>
            <heading>Procedure to register order for enforcement.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-25-602__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in
AS 25.25.707
, a support order or income withholding order of another state or a foreign support order may be registered in this state by sending the following records to a tribunal of this state:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-602__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a letter of transmittal to the tribunal requesting registration and enforcement;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-602__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>two copies, including one certified copy, of the order to be registered, including any modification of the order;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-602__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a sworn statement by the person requesting registration or a certified statement by the custodian of the records showing the amount of any arrearage;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-602__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name of the obligor and, if known,
(A) the obligor's address and social security number;
(B) the name and address of the obligor's employer and any other source of income of the obligor; and
(C) a description and the location of property in this state of the obligor not exempt from execution; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-602__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>except as otherwise provided in
AS 25.25.312
, the name and address of the obligee and, if applicable, the person to whom support payments are to be remitted.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-602__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>On receipt of a request for registration, the registering tribunal shall file the order as an order of a tribunal of another state or a foreign support order, together with one copy of the documents and information, regardless of their form.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-602__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A complaint or comparable pleading seeking a remedy that must be affirmatively sought under other law of this state may be filed at the same time as the request for registration or later. The pleading must specify the grounds for the remedy sought.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-602__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If two or more orders are in effect, the person requesting registration shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-602__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>furnish to the tribunal a copy of every support order asserted to be in effect in addition to the documents specified in this section;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-602__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>specify the order alleged to be the controlling order, if any; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-602__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>specify the amount of consolidated arrears, if any.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-602__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A request for a determination of which is the controlling order may be filed separately or with a request for registration and enforcement or for registration and modification. The person requesting registration shall give notice of the request to each party whose rights may be affected by the determination.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-603">
            <num>25.25.603</num>
            <heading>Effect of registration for enforcement.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-25-603__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A support order or income withholding order issued in another state or a foreign support order is registered when the order is filed in the registering tribunal of this state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-603__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A registered support order issued in another state or a foreign country is enforceable in the same manner and is subject to the same procedures as an order issued by a tribunal of this state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-603__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as otherwise provided in this chapter, a tribunal of this state shall recognize and enforce, but may not modify, a registered support order if the issuing tribunal had jurisdiction.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-604">
            <num>25.25.604</num>
            <heading>Choice of law.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-25-604__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as otherwise provided in (d) of this section, the law of the issuing state or foreign country governs</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-604__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the nature, extent, amount, and duration of current payments under a registered support order;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-604__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the computation and payment of arrearages and accrual of interest on the arrearages under the support order; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-604__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the existence and satisfaction of other obligations under the support order.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-604__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In a proceeding for arrears under a registered support order, the statute of limitation of this state or of the issuing state or foreign country, whichever is longer, applies.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-604__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A responding tribunal of this state shall apply the procedures and remedies of this state to enforce current support and collect arrears and interest due on a support order of another state or a foreign country registered in this state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-604__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After a tribunal of this state or another state determines which is the controlling order and issues an order consolidating arrears, if any, a tribunal of this state shall prospectively apply the law of the state or foreign country issuing the controlling order, including its law on interest on arrears, on current and future support, and on consolidated arrears.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-605">
            <num>25.25.605</num>
            <heading>Notice of registration of order.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-25-605__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When a support order or income withholding order issued in another state or a foreign support order is registered, the registering tribunal of this state shall notify the nonregistering party. The notice must be accompanied by a copy of the registered order and the documents and relevant information accompanying the order.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-605__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A notice must inform the nonregistering party</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-605__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>that a registered order is enforceable as of the date of registration in the same manner as an order issued by a tribunal of this state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-605__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>that a hearing to contest the validity or enforcement of the registered order must be requested within 20 days after notice unless the registered order is under
AS 25.25.708
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-605__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>that failure to contest the validity or enforcement of the registered order in a timely manner will result in confirmation of the order and enforcement of the order and the alleged arrearages and precludes further contest of that order with respect to any matter that could have been asserted; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-605__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>of the amount of alleged arrearages.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-605__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon registration of an income withholding order for enforcement, the support enforcement agency or the registering tribunal shall notify the obligor's employer under
AS 25.27
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-605__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the registering party asserts that two or more orders are in effect, a notice must also</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-605__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>identify the orders, the order alleged by the registering party to be the controlling order, and the consolidated arrears, if any;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-605__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>notify the nonregistering party of the right to a determination of which is the controlling order;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-605__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>state that the procedures provided in (b) of this section apply to the determination of which is the controlling order; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-605__subsec_d__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>state that failure to contest the validity or enforcement of the order alleged to be the controlling order in a timely manner may result in confirmation that the order is the controlling order.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-606">
            <num>25.25.606</num>
            <heading>Procedure to contest validity or enforcement of registered support order.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-25-606__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A nonregistering party seeking to contest the validity or enforcement of a registered order in this state shall request a hearing within the time required by
AS 25.25.605
. The nonregistering party may seek to vacate the registration, to assert a defense to an allegation of noncompliance with the registered order, or to contest the remedies being sought or the amount of alleged arrearages under
AS 25.25.607
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-606__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the nonregistering party fails to contest the validity or enforcement of the registered support order in a timely manner, the order is confirmed by operation of law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-606__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a nonregistering party requests a hearing to contest the validity or enforcement of the registered order, the registering tribunal shall schedule the matter for hearing and give notice to the parties of the date, time, and place of the hearing.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-607">
            <num>25.25.607</num>
            <heading>Contest of registration or enforcement.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-25-607__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A party contesting the validity or enforcement of a registered support order or seeking to vacate the registration has the burden of proving one or more of the following defenses:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-607__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the issuing tribunal lacked personal jurisdiction over the contesting party;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-607__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the order was obtained by fraud;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-607__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the order has been vacated, suspended, or modified by a later order;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-607__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the issuing tribunal has stayed the order pending appeal;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-607__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>there is a defense under the law of this state to the remedy sought;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-607__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>full or partial payment has been made;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-607__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the statute of limitation under
AS 25.25.604
precludes enforcement of some or all of the alleged arrearages; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-607__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the alleged controlling order is not the controlling order.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-607__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a party presents evidence establishing a full or partial defense under (a) of this section, the tribunal may stay enforcement of a registered support order, continue the proceeding to permit production of additional relevant evidence, and issue other appropriate orders. An uncontested portion of the registered support order may be enforced by all remedies available under the law of this state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-607__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the contesting party does not establish a defense under (a) of this section to the validity or enforcement of a registered support order, the registering tribunal shall issue an order confirming the order.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-608">
            <num>25.25.608</num>
            <heading>Confirmed order.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.25.608.   Confirmed order.
Confirmation of a registered support order, whether by operation of law or after notice and hearing, precludes further contest of the order with respect to a matter that could have been asserted at the time of registration.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-609">
            <num>25.25.609</num>
            <heading>Procedure to register child support order of another state for modification.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.25.609.   Procedure to register child support order of another state for modification.
If a party or the child support services agency seeks to modify, or to modify and enforce, a child support order issued in another state but not registered in this state, the party or agency shall register that order in this state in the same manner provided in
AS 25.25.601
 25.25.608. A complaint for modification may be filed at the same time as a request for registration, or later. The pleading must specify the grounds for modification.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-610">
            <num>25.25.610</num>
            <heading>Effect of registration for modification.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.25.610.   Effect of registration for modification.
A tribunal of this state may enforce a child support order of another state registered for purposes of modification in the same manner as if the order had been issued by a tribunal of this state, but the registered support order may be modified only if the requirements of
AS 25.25.611
or 25.25.613 have been met.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-611">
            <num>25.25.611</num>
            <heading>Modification of child support order of another state.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-25-611__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If
AS 25.25.613
does not apply, upon complaint or comparable pleading, a tribunal of this state may modify a child support order issued in another state that is registered in this state, if, after notice and an opportunity for hearing, the tribunal finds that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-611__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the following requirements are met:
(A) neither the child, nor the obligee who is an individual, nor the obligor resides in the issuing state;
(B) a petitioner who is not a resident of this state seeks modification; and
(C) the respondent is subject to the personal jurisdiction of the tribunal of this state; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-611__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>this state is the residence of the child, or a party who is an individual is subject to the personal jurisdiction of the tribunal, and all of the parties who are individuals have filed consents in a record in the issuing tribunal providing that a tribunal of this state may modify the support order and assume continuing, exclusive jurisdiction.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-611__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Modification of a registered child support order is subject to the same requirements, procedures, and defenses that apply to the modification of an order issued by a tribunal of this state and the order may be enforced and satisfied in the same manner.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-611__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A tribunal of this state may not modify any aspect of a child support order that may not be modified under the law of the issuing state, including the duration of the obligation of support. If two or more tribunals have issued child support orders for the same obligor and child, the order that is controlling and must be recognized under the provisions of
AS 25.25.207
establishes the nonmodifiable aspects of the support order.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-611__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>On issuance of an order by a tribunal of this state modifying a child support order issued in another state, the tribunal of this state becomes the tribunal of continuing, exclusive jurisdiction.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-611__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In a proceeding to modify a child support order, the law of the state that is determined to have issued the initial controlling order governs the duration of the obligation of support. The obligor's fulfillment of the duty of support established by that order precludes imposition of a further obligation of support by a tribunal of this state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-611__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (a)  (e) of this section and
AS 25.25.201
(b), a tribunal of this state retains jurisdiction to modify an order issued by a tribunal of this state if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-611__subsec_f__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>one party resides in another state; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-611__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the other party resides outside the United States.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-612">
            <num>25.25.612</num>
            <heading>Recognition of order modified in another state.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.25.612.   Recognition of order modified in another state.
If a child support order issued by a tribunal of this state is modified by a tribunal of another state that assumed jurisdiction under the Uniform Interstate Family Support Act, a tribunal of this state
(1) may enforce its order that was modified only as to arrears and interest accruing before the modification;
(2) may provide appropriate relief for violations of its order that occurred before the effective date of the modification; and
(3) shall recognize the modifying order of the other state, upon registration, for the purpose of enforcement.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-613">
            <num>25.25.613</num>
            <heading>Jurisdiction to modify support order of another state when individual parties reside in this state.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-25-613__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If all of the individual parties reside in this state and the child does not reside in the issuing state, a tribunal of this state has jurisdiction to enforce and to modify the issuing state's child support order in a proceeding to register that order.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-613__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A tribunal of this state exercising jurisdiction as provided in this section shall apply the provisions of
AS 25.25.101
 25.25.209 and 25.25.601  25.25.614 to the enforcement or modification proceeding.
AS 25.25.301
 25.25.507, 25.25.702  25.25.714, 25.25.801, and 25.25.802 do not apply, and the tribunal shall apply the procedural and substantive law of this state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-614">
            <num>25.25.614</num>
            <heading>Notice to issuing tribunal of modification.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.25.614.   Notice to issuing tribunal of modification.
Within 30 days after issuance of a modified child support order, the party obtaining the modification shall file a certified copy of the order with the issuing tribunal that had continuing, exclusive jurisdiction over the earlier order and with each tribunal in which the party knows that an earlier order has been registered. Failure of the party obtaining the order to file a certified copy as required subjects that party to appropriate sanctions by a tribunal in which the issue of failure to file arises, but that failure has no effect on the validity or enforceability of the modified order of the new tribunal of continuing, exclusive jurisdiction.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-615">
            <num>25.25.615</num>
            <heading>Jurisdiction to modify child support order of foreign country.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-25-615__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as otherwise provided in
AS 25.25.712
, if a foreign country lacks or refuses to exercise jurisdiction to modify its child support order under its laws, a tribunal of this state may assume jurisdiction to modify the child support order and bind all individuals subject to the personal jurisdiction of the tribunal, regardless of whether the consent to modification of a child support order otherwise required of the individual under
AS 25.25.611
has been given or the individual seeking modification is a resident of this state or of the foreign country.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-615__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An order issued by a tribunal of this state modifying a foreign child support order under this section is the controlling order.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-616">
            <num>25.25.616</num>
            <heading>Procedure to register child support order of foreign country for modification.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.25.616.   Procedure to register child support order of foreign country for modification.
A party or support enforcement agency seeking to modify, or to modify and enforce, a foreign child support order not under the convention may register that order in this state under
AS 25.25.601
 25.25.608 if the order has not been registered. A complaint or comparable pleading for modification may be filed at the same time as a request for registration, or at another time. The complaint or comparable pleading must specify the grounds for modification.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-702">
            <num>25.25.702</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-25-702__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>is enforceable as a support order in the country of origin;
(ii) has been formally drawn up or registered as an authentic instrument by a foreign tribunal or authenticated by, or concluded, registered, or filed with, a foreign tribunal; and
(iii) may be reviewed and modified by a foreign tribunal;
(B) includes a maintenance arrangement or authentic instrument under the convention;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-702__subsec_i__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>United States central authority means the United States Secretary of Health and Human Services.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-703">
            <num>25.25.703</num>
            <heading>Applicability.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.25.703.   Applicability.
AS 25.25.702
 25.25.714 apply only to a support proceeding under the convention. In such a proceeding, if a provision of
AS 25.25.702
 25.25.714 is inconsistent with
AS 25.25.101
 25.25.616,
AS 25.25.702
 25.25.714 controls.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-704">
            <num>25.25.704</num>
            <heading>Relationship of child support services agency to United States central authority.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.25.704.   Relationship of child support services agency to United States central authority.
The child support services agency of this state is recognized as the agency designated by the United States central authority to perform specific functions under the convention.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-705">
            <num>25.25.705</num>
            <heading>Initiation by child support services agency of support proceeding under convention.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-25-705__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In a support proceeding under
AS 25.25.702
 25.25.714, the child support services agency of this state shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-705__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>transmit and receive applications; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-705__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>initiate or facilitate the institution of a proceeding regarding an application in a tribunal of this state.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-705__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The following support proceedings are available to an obligee under the convention:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-705__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>recognition or recognition and enforcement of a foreign support order;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-705__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>enforcement of a support order issued or recognized in this state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-705__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establishment of a support order if there is not an existing order, including, if necessary, determination of parentage of a child;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-705__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establishment of a support order if recognition of a foreign support order is refused under
AS 25.25.709</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-705__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>modification of a support order of a tribunal of this state; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-705__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>modification of a support order of a tribunal of another state or a foreign country.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-705__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The following support proceedings are available under the convention to an obligor against whom there is an existing support order:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-705__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>recognition of an order suspending or limiting enforcement of an existing support order of a tribunal of this state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-705__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>modification of a support order of a tribunal of this state; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-705__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>modification of a support order of a tribunal of another state or a foreign country.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-705__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A tribunal of this state may not require security, bond, or deposit, however described, to guarantee the payment of costs and expenses in proceedings under the convention.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-706">
            <num>25.25.706</num>
            <heading>Direct request.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-25-706__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An individual may file a direct request seeking establishment or modification of a support order or determination of parentage of a child. In the proceeding, the law of this state applies.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-706__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An individual may file a direct request seeking recognition and enforcement of a support order or support agreement. In the proceeding,
AS 25.25.707
 25.25.714 apply.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-706__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In a direct request for recognition and enforcement of a convention support order or foreign support agreement,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-706__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a security, bond, or deposit is not required to guarantee the payment of costs and expenses; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-706__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an obligee or obligor who has benefited from free legal assistance in the issuing country is entitled to benefit, at least to the same extent, from any free legal assistance provided for by the law of this state under the same circumstances.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-706__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An individual filing a direct request is not entitled to assistance from the child support services agency.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-706__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>AS 25.25.702
 25.25.714 do not prevent the application of laws of this state that provide simplified, more expeditious rules regarding a direct request for recognition and enforcement of a foreign support order or foreign support agreement.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-707">
            <num>25.25.707</num>
            <heading>Registration of convention support order.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-25-707__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as otherwise provided in
AS 25.25.702
 25.25.714, a party who is an individual or a support enforcement agency seeking recognition of a convention support order shall register the order in this state as provided in
AS 25.25.601
 25.25.616.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-707__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding
AS 25.25.311
and 25.25.602(a), a request for registration of a convention support order must be accompanied by</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-707__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a complete text of the support order or an abstract or extract of the support order drawn up by the issuing foreign tribunal, which may be in the form recommended by the Hague Conference on Private International Law;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-707__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a record stating that the support order is enforceable in the issuing country;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-707__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if the respondent did not appear and was not represented in the proceedings in the issuing country, a record attesting, as appropriate, either that the respondent had proper notice of the proceedings and an opportunity to be heard or that the respondent had proper notice of the support order and an opportunity to be heard in a challenge or appeal on fact or law before a tribunal;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-707__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a record showing the amount of arrears, if any, and the date the amount was calculated;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-707__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a record showing a requirement for automatic adjustment of the amount of support, if any, and the information necessary to make the appropriate calculations; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-707__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if necessary, a record showing the extent to which the applicant received free legal assistance in the issuing country.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-707__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A request for registration of a convention support order may seek recognition and partial enforcement of the order.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-707__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A tribunal of this state may vacate the registration of a convention support order without the filing of a contest under
AS 25.25.708
only if, acting on its own motion, the tribunal finds that recognition and enforcement of the order would be manifestly incompatible with public policy.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-707__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The tribunal shall promptly notify the parties of the registration or the order vacating the registration of a convention support order.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-708">
            <num>25.25.708</num>
            <heading>Contest of registered convention support order.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-25-708__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as otherwise provided in
AS 25.25.702
 25.25.714,
AS 25.25.605
 25.25.608 apply to a contest of a registered convention support order.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-708__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A party contesting a registered convention support order shall file a contest not later than 30 days after notice of the registration, but if the contesting party does not reside in the United States, the contest must be filed not later than 60 days after notice of the registration.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-708__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the nonregistering party fails to contest the registered convention support order by the time specified in (b) of this section, the order is enforceable.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-708__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A contest of a registered convention support order may be based only on grounds set out in
AS 25.25.709
. The contesting party bears the burden of proof.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-708__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In a contest of a registered convention support order, a tribunal of this state</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-708__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is bound by the findings of fact on which the foreign tribunal based its jurisdiction; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-708__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>may not review the merits of the order.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-708__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A tribunal of this state deciding a contest of a registered convention support order shall promptly notify the parties of its decision.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-708__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A challenge or appeal, if any, does not stay the enforcement of a convention support order unless there are exceptional circumstances.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-709">
            <num>25.25.709</num>
            <heading>Recognition and enforcement of registered convention support order.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-25-709__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as otherwise provided in (b) of this section, a tribunal of this state shall recognize and enforce a registered convention support order.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-709__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The following grounds are the only grounds on which a tribunal of this state may refuse recognition and enforcement of a registered convention support order:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-709__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>recognition and enforcement of the order is manifestly incompatible with public policy, including the failure of the issuing tribunal to observe minimum standards of due process, which include notice and an opportunity to be heard;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-709__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the issuing tribunal lacked personal jurisdiction consistent with
AS 25.25.201
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-709__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the order is not enforceable in the issuing country;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-709__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the order was obtained by fraud in connection with a matter of procedure;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-709__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a record transmitted in accordance with
AS 25.25.707
lacks authenticity or integrity;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-709__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a proceeding between the same parties and having the same purpose is pending before a tribunal of this state and that proceeding was the first to be filed;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-709__subsec_b__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the order is incompatible with a more recent support order involving the same parties and having the same purpose if the more recent support order is entitled to recognition and enforcement under this chapter in this state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-709__subsec_b__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>payment, to the extent alleged arrears have been paid, in whole or in part;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-709__subsec_b__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in a case in which the respondent neither appeared nor was represented in the proceeding in the issuing foreign country,
(A) if the law of that country provides for prior notice of proceedings, the respondent did not have proper notice of the proceedings and an opportunity to be heard; or
(B) if the law of that country does not provide for prior notice of the proceedings, the respondent did not have proper notice of the order and an opportunity to be heard in a challenge or appeal on fact or law before a tribunal; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-709__subsec_b__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the order was made in violation of
AS 25.25.712
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-709__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a tribunal of this state does not recognize a convention support order under (b)(2), (4), or (9) of this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-709__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the tribunal may not dismiss the proceeding without allowing a reasonable time for a party to request the establishment of a new convention support order; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-709__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the child support services agency shall take all appropriate measures to request a child support order for the obligee if the application for recognition and enforcement was received under
AS 25.25.705
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-710">
            <num>25.25.710</num>
            <heading>Partial enforcement.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.25.710.   Partial enforcement.
If a tribunal of this state does not recognize and enforce a convention support order in its entirety, it shall enforce any severable part of the order. An application or direct request may seek recognition and partial enforcement of a convention support order.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-711">
            <num>25.25.711</num>
            <heading>Foreign support agreement.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-25-711__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as otherwise provided in (c) and (d) of this section, a tribunal of this state shall recognize and enforce a foreign support agreement registered in this state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-711__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An application or direct request for recognition and enforcement of a foreign support agreement must be accompanied by</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-711__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a complete text of the foreign support agreement; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-711__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a record stating that the foreign support agreement is enforceable as an order of support in the issuing country.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-711__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A tribunal of this state may vacate the registration of a foreign support agreement only if, acting on its own motion, the tribunal finds that recognition and enforcement would be manifestly incompatible with public policy.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-711__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In a contest of a foreign support agreement, a tribunal of this state may refuse recognition and enforcement of the agreement if it finds</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-711__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>recognition and enforcement of the agreement is manifestly incompatible with public policy;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-711__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the agreement was obtained by fraud or falsification;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-711__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the agreement is incompatible with a support order involving the same parties and having the same purpose in this state, another state, or a foreign country if the support order is entitled to recognition and enforcement under this chapter in this state; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-711__subsec_d__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the record submitted under (b) of this section lacks authenticity or integrity.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-711__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A proceeding for recognition and enforcement of a foreign support agreement must be suspended during the pendency of a challenge to or appeal of the agreement before a tribunal of another state or a foreign country.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-712">
            <num>25.25.712</num>
            <heading>Modification of convention child support order.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-25-712__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A tribunal of this state may not modify a convention child support order if the obligee remains a resident of the foreign country where the support order was issued unless</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-712__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the obligee submits to the jurisdiction of a tribunal of this state, either expressly or by defending on the merits of the case, without objecting to the jurisdiction at the first available opportunity; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-712__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the foreign tribunal lacks or refuses to exercise jurisdiction to modify its support order or issue a new support order.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-712__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a tribunal of this state does not modify a convention child support order because the order is not recognized in this state,
AS 25.25.709</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-712__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>applies.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-713">
            <num>25.25.713</num>
            <heading>Personal information; limit on use.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.25.713.   Personal information; limit on use.
Personal information gathered or transmitted under
AS 25.25.702
 25.25.714 may be used only for the purposes for which it was gathered or transmitted.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-714">
            <num>25.25.714</num>
            <heading>Record original language; English translation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.25.714.   Record original language; English translation.
A record filed with a tribunal of this state under
AS 25.25.702
 25.25.714 must be in the original language and, if not in English, must be accompanied by an English translation.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-801">
            <num>25.25.801</num>
            <heading>Grounds for rendition.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-25-801__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The governor or a designee of the governor may</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-801__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>demand that the governor of another state surrender an individual found in the other state who is charged criminally in this state with having failed to provide for the support of an obligee; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-25-801__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>on the demand of the governor of another state, surrender an individual found in this state who is charged criminally in the other state with having failed to provide for the support of an obligee.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-801__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A provision for extradition of individuals not inconsistent with this chapter applies to the demand even if the individual whose surrender is demanded was not in the demanding state when the crime was allegedly committed and has not fled from that state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-802">
            <num>25.25.802</num>
            <heading>Conditions of rendition.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-25-802__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before making a demand that the governor of another state surrender an individual charged criminally in this state with having failed to provide for the support of an obligee, the governor of this state or the designee of the governor may require a prosecutor of this state to demonstrate that the obligee had initiated proceedings for support under this chapter at least 60 days previously or that the proceeding would be of no avail.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-802__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If, under this chapter or a law substantially similar to this chapter, or the former provisions of this chapter, the governor of another state makes a demand that the governor of this state surrender an individual charged criminally in that state with having failed to provide for the support of a child or other individual to whom a duty of support is owed, the governor or a designee of the governor may require a prosecutor to investigate the demand and report whether a proceeding for support has been initiated or would be effective. If it appears that a proceeding would be effective but has not been initiated, the governor or designee may delay honoring the demand for a reasonable time to permit the initiation of a proceeding.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-25-802__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a proceeding for support has been initiated and the individual whose rendition is demanded prevails, the governor or the designee of the governor may decline to honor the demand. If the petitioner prevails and the individual whose rendition is demanded is subject to a support order, the governor or designee may decline to honor the demand if the individual is complying with the support order.
Article 9. Miscellaneous Provisions.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-901">
            <num>25.25.901</num>
            <heading>Uniformity of application and construction.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.25.901.   Uniformity of application and construction.
In applying and construing this chapter, consideration must be given to the need to promote uniformity of the law with respect to its subject matter among states that enact it.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-902">
            <num>25.25.902</num>
            <heading>Severability.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.25.902.   Severability.
Under
AS 01.10.030
, if a provision of this chapter or its application to a person or circumstance is held invalid, the invalidity does not affect other provisions or applications of this chapter that can be given effect without the invalid provision or application.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-25-903">
            <num>25.25.903</num>
            <heading>Short title.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.25.903.   Short title.
This chapter may be cited as the Uniform Interstate Family Support Act.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>