<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-21/chapter-76"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-21/chapter-76"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="21.76"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-21/chapter-76/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-21/chapter-76/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-21/chapter-76/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-21/chapter-76/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_21">
        <num>21</num>
        <heading>Insurance</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_21__chp_76">
          <num>76</num>
          <heading>Joint Insurance Arrangements</heading>
          <section eId="sec_21-76-010">
            <num>21.76.010</num>
            <heading>Authority to establish joint insurance arrangements.</heading>
            <subsection eId="21-76-010__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Municipalities and their public corporations, city and borough school districts, and regional educational attendance areas may enter into cooperative agreements with each other for the purpose of establishing, operating, or participating in joint insurance arrangements through which the participating members agree to pool contributions in order to either assume risks from losses to the participants on a group basis or purchase coverage for the participants on a group basis.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-76-010__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A joint insurance arrangement may be for any kind of insurance defined by this title except for health insurance, life insurance, and title insurance.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-76-010__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A joint insurance arrangement shall be considered an alternative or supplement to any other policy or contract of insurance authorized or required by law, including insurance under
AS 21.75
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-76-010__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of
AS 23.30.075
, a joint insurance arrangement is considered to be an association duly authorized to transact workers' compensation insurance in the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_21-76-020">
            <num>21.76.020</num>
            <heading>Regulation by division of insurance and annual report.</heading>
            <subsection eId="21-76-020__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A joint insurance arrangement may not be considered insurance for the purpose of any other law of the state and is not subject to regulations adopted by the director.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-76-020__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>By October 1 of each year, the administrator of a joint insurance arrangement shall prepare and deliver to the Legislative Budget and Audit Committee and the director a report showing the true and correct financial condition of the joint insurance arrangement. The report must</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="21-76-020__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>be attested to by the administrator and the board of directors;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-76-020__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>include an analysis, certified by a member of the American Academy of Actuaries, of the sufficiency of the loss reserves; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-76-020__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>be certified by a certified public accountant.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_21-76-030">
            <num>21.76.030</num>
            <heading>General provisions of cooperative agreements.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 21.76.030.   General provisions of cooperative agreements.
A cooperative agreement must provide for the proper operation of the joint insurance arrangement and include provisions for
(1) administration of the arrangement by a board of directors, specifying the number of members of the board and other requirements necessary for the proper functioning of the board;
(2) appointment of an administrator and other persons as necessary for the proper functioning of the arrangement;
(3) organization of the arrangement, including a roster of participating members and the names of the members of the board of directors;
(4) procedures to establish and promote an aggressive risk management and program among the members of the arrangement, including procedures for identifying and reducing the risks that can be reduced through implementing better safety technologies and improved work techniques and procedures;
(5) enforcing the collection of contributions or payments in default from members of the arrangement;
(6) the addition of new members to the arrangement or the withdrawal of members from the arrangement;
(7) the method of apportioning costs and disposition of excess contributions;
(8) transmission of financial statements and audit reports of the arrangement to participating members;
(9) terminating the arrangement and disposing of its assets; and
(10) establishing and administering a joint insurance fund.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_21-76-040">
            <num>21.76.040</num>
            <heading>Financial provisions of agreements.</heading>
            <subsection eId="21-76-040__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A cooperative agreement must include a provision requiring an annual determination by a casualty actuary who is a member of the American Academy of Actuaries that procedures for establishing reserves for losses of the joint insurance arrangement are actuarially sound.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-76-040__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A joint insurance arrangement shall be subject to an annual independent audit.  The audit shall be conducted in accordance with generally accepted auditing standards and must include a review of the actuarial assumptions used for establishing the reserves under (a) of this section.  The audit report must include certification from a casualty actuary who is a member of the American Academy of Actuaries that the actuarial assumptions continue to be sound and the level of the reserves are adequate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_21-76-050">
            <num>21.76.050</num>
            <heading>Contracting with private administrators.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 21.76.050.   Contracting with private administrators.
A cooperative agreement may authorize the board of directors to enter into contracts for services necessary to perform the functions of a joint insurance arrangement.  The person contracting to perform the functions must be appropriately licensed under this title if this title so requires.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_21-76-060">
            <num>21.76.060</num>
            <heading>Delegation of power to settle claims.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 21.76.060.   Delegation of power to settle claims.
A cooperative agreement may delegate to the board of directors, or authorize delegation by the board to another person or group, the power to compromise, arbitrate, or otherwise settle claims on behalf of the arrangement.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_21-76-070">
            <num>21.76.070</num>
            <heading>Excess insurance.</heading>
            <subsection eId="21-76-070__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and (d) and 21.34.220 and has capital and policyholders surplus in an amount at least as great as would be required if the association were a domestic multiple line insurer.  An arrangement may purchase insurance under this section for property and liability risks from unauthorized insurers allowed for use by licensed Alaska surplus lines brokers.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_21-76-080">
            <num>21.76.080</num>
            <heading>Joint insurance fund.</heading>
            <subsection eId="21-76-080__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A joint insurance arrangement shall establish a joint insurance fund.  The fund consists of money</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="21-76-080__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>contributed by members of the joint insurance arrangement through budgetary appropriations or transfers from a self-insurance reserve;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-76-080__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>contributed by officers and employees of members of the joint insurance arrangement under an employee benefit plan; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-76-080__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>collected by the joint insurance arrangement through subrogation of a claim paid from the fund to a member of the arrangement.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-76-080__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An expenditure may be made from a joint insurance fund only to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="21-76-080__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>pay claims, losses, or benefits, including interest on them, and the administrative and adjustment expenses incurred in connection with them, involving the types of protection for which the fund provides coverage as specified in the joint insurance agreement;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-76-080__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>pay contractual obligations of a joint insurance fund established by a municipal joint insurance arrangement to the Alaska Municipal Bond Bank Authority or other lender; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="21-76-080__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>purchase insurance coverage for members of a municipal joint insurance arrangement on a group basis.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-76-080__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The administrator shall keep the fund separate from other funds of a member of a joint insurance arrangement.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-76-080__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For each type of protection offered by the joint insurance arrangement, the method of accounting must show the order, source, date, and amount of each payment from the fund.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-76-080__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Within 150 days of the end of the fiscal year, the administrator shall furnish a detailed report of the operation and condition of the fund to the board of directors and the director of the division of insurance.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-76-080__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Money held by a fund as reserves and money not needed for daily operations may be invested by the board of directors.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-76-080__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A fund may not be terminated unless the administrator certifies that an amount of money sufficient to pay accrued and contingent expenditures has been placed in a fully collateralized escrow account.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_21-76-090">
            <num>21.76.090</num>
            <heading>Filing of agreement.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 21.76.090.   Filing of agreement.
The board of directors shall file a copy of the cooperative agreement with the director of insurance at least 60 days before the effective date of the agreement.  The agreement shall be available for public inspection.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_21-76-100">
            <num>21.76.100</num>
            <heading>Regulations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 21.76.100.   Regulations.
A cooperative agreement may authorize the board of directors to adopt rules not inconsistent with law for the fair and equitable administration of the joint insurance arrangement and the joint insurance fund.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_21-76-110">
            <num>21.76.110</num>
            <heading>Subrogation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 21.76.110.   Subrogation.
A joint insurance arrangement has a right of subrogation with respect to its participants to the same extent that an insurer has a right of subrogation with respect to one of its insureds.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_21-76-120">
            <num>21.76.120</num>
            <heading>Debt financing.</heading>
            <subsection eId="21-76-120__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality or a municipal joint insurance arrangement may authorize the issuance of negotiable or nonnegotiable bonds, notes, or certificates of participation to establish reserves and to self-insure against liability not covered by excess insurance or reinsurance. A bond, note, or certificate issued under this subsection by a municipal joint insurance arrangement shall be secured and payable from participating members of the municipal joint insurance arrangement as provided in the cooperative agreement.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="21-76-120__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality that has entered into a municipal joint insurance arrangement may enter into contracts and agreements concerning debt issued under (a) of this section and provide for matters that affect the security of the debt. Bonds, notes, and certificates of participation issued under (a) of this section may be sold at either public or private sale as provided by the participants in the municipal joint insurance arrangement in the manner and at the price the participants determine.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_21-76-900">
            <num>21.76.900</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 21.76.900.   Definitions.
In this chapter,
(1) adjustment expenses means expenses for investigative, processing, legal, actuarial, arbitration, and settlement services incurred in the adjustment of losses, claims, or benefits;
(2) administrator means a person or group appointed by the board of directors to administer a joint insurance arrangement or a joint insurance fund;
(3) board or board of directors means the board of directors provided for in a cooperative agreement;
(4) cooperative agreement means a written agreement entered into by two or more entities described in
AS 21.76.010
for the purpose of establishing, operating, or participating in a joint insurance arrangement;
(5) fund or joint insurance fund means a fund established under
AS 21.76.080
;
(6) joint insurance arrangement means a joint insurance arrangement authorized under
AS 21.76.010
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>