<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-18/chapter-20"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-18/chapter-20"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="18.20"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-18/chapter-20/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-18/chapter-20/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-18/chapter-20/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-18/chapter-20/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_18">
        <num>18</num>
        <heading>Health, Safety, Housing, Human Rights, and Public Defender</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_18__chp_20">
          <num>20</num>
          <heading>Hospitals and Nursing Facilities</heading>
          <section eId="sec_18-20-075">
            <num>18.20.075</num>
            <heading>Risk management.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-20-075__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To be eligible for a license, each hospital shall have in operation an internal risk management program that shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-075__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>investigate the frequency and causes of incidents in hospitals that cause injury to patients;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-075__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>develop and implement measures to minimize the risk of injury to patients; in developing these measures each hospital shall take into account recommendations of its medical staff, private underwriters, industry standards, experience of other hospitals, and recommendations of licensing boards of other health care providers; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-075__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>analyze patient grievances that relate to patient care.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-20-075__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall adopt by regulation standards for the risk management programs in hospitals in the state which may vary according to the size of the hospital, the type of care offered by the hospital, and other factors found relevant by the department.  Regulations adopted under this subsection are subject to
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-20-080">
            <num>18.20.080</num>
            <heading>Inspection and consultation for alterations.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-20-080__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall make annual inspections and investigations of hospital facilities. The department may accept accreditation by the Joint Commission on the Accreditation of Hospitals in lieu of an annual inspection by the department for the year in which the accreditation was granted if the accreditation standards of the commission are substantially similar to the inspection standards of the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-20-080__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may by regulation require that a licensee or applicant desiring to make a specified type of alteration or addition to its facilities or to construct new facilities shall, before commencing the alteration, addition, or new construction, submit plans and specifications to the department for preliminary inspection and approval or recommendations with respect to compliance with its regulations and standards.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-20-085">
            <num>18.20.085</num>
            <heading>Hospital records retention.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-20-085__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless specified otherwise by the department a hospital shall retain and preserve records that relate directly to the care and treatment of a patient for a period of seven years following the discharge of the patient.  However, the records of a patient under 19 years of age shall be kept until at least two years after the patient has reached the age of 19 years or until seven years following the discharge of the patient, whichever is longer.  Records consisting of X-ray film are required to be retained for five years.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-20-085__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall by regulation define the types of records and the information required to be included in the records retained and preserved under (a) of this section.  The department may by regulation specify records and information to be retained for longer periods than those set out in (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-20-085__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a hospital ceases operation, it shall make immediate arrangements, as approved by the department, for the preservation of its records.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-20-085__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This section is subject to
AS 18.23.100
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-20-085__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, hospital includes those facilities defined as hospitals under
AS 18.20.130
and 18.20.210.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-20-095">
            <num>18.20.095</num>
            <heading>Mental health patient's right to select staff; duties of hospital staff.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-20-095__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (d) of this section, a patient 18 years of age or older who is receiving mental health treatment and being provided intimate care at a hospital shall have a right to have care provided by a staff member who is the gender that the patient requests.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-20-095__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A supervisor or manager employed by a hospital shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-095__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>post a notice of the right provided under (a) of this section in a conspicuous place; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-095__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if, after reasonable and good faith efforts to comply, the hospital is unable to comply with the requirement under (a) of this section,
(A) document in the patient record that intimate care was provided by a licensed staff member of the gender opposite to the gender requested by the patient under (a) of this section; or
(B) if a licensed staff member is not on duty at the time of the patient's request under (a) of this section, document in the patient record that the care was provided by an unlicensed staff member of the gender opposite to that requested under (a) of this section.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-20-095__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Staff members employed by a hospital shall, in regard to patients receiving mental health treatment,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-095__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide privacy for each patient, especially for patients who are the opposite gender and especially when patient care involves intimate bodily functions, unavoidable intimate touching, or nudity;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-095__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>except when necessitated by a medical emergency that is documented in the patient's record, avoid entering patient care areas for a person of the opposite gender and areas specified for persons of the opposite gender; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-095__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>conduct routine safety checks and rounds of bedrooms, bathrooms, and shower areas only of patients who are the same gender as the staff member.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-20-095__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A hospital is exempt from the requirements of (a) of this section if the treating psychiatrist for the patient at the hospital determines that compliance would adversely affect patient treatment and the psychiatrist documents the determination in the patient's record.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-20-095__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-095__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>intimate care means hygienic care, including bathing, dressing, changing, and toileting, that involves a patient's perineal area and, for a female patient, the patient's breasts; intimate care does not include activities done in preparation for medical procedures;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-095__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>licensed staff member means a person who is employed by the hospital to provide direct patient care and who is licensed or certified in the state as a physician or physician assistant under
AS 08.64
, direct-entry midwife under
AS 08.65
, nurse or nurse aide under
AS 08.68
, or physical therapist or occupational therapist under
AS 08.84
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-095__subsec_e__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>mental health treatment means admission to a hospital primarily for electroconvulsive treatment or treatment with psychotropic medication, or admission to and retention in a health care institution for other mental health treatment;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-095__subsec_e__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>staff member means a person employed by a hospital to provide direct patient care.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-20-130">
            <num>18.20.130</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.20.130.   Definitions.
In
AS 18.20.075
 18.20.130,
(1) department means the Department of Health;
(2) hospital means an institution or establishment, public or private, devoted primarily to providing diagnosis, treatment, or care over a continuous period of 24 hours each day for two or more nonrelated individuals suffering from illness, physical or mental disease, injury or deformity, or any other condition for which medical or surgical services would be appropriate.
Article 2. Alaska Hospital and Medical Facilities Survey and Construction Act.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-20-140">
            <num>18.20.140</num>
            <heading>Purpose.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.20.140.   Purpose.
The purpose of
AS 18.20.140
 18.20.220 is to make an inventory of existing hospitals and medical facilities, community mental health centers, and facilities for persons with intellectual and developmental disabilities; to survey the need for construction of hospitals and medical facilities, community mental health centers, and facilities for persons with intellectual and developmental disabilities; and to develop a program and plan of construction for each.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-20-141">
            <num>18.20.141</num>
            <heading>Department functions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.20.141.   Department functions.
The department shall be the sole agency for the administration of the plan as required by the federal act.  The department shall develop and administer any programs necessary for compliance with the federal act.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-20-150">
            <num>18.20.150</num>
            <heading>Duties of department.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-20-150__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For each of the following groups of facilities, hospitals and medical facilities (Group 1), community mental health centers (Group 2), and facilities for persons with intellectual and developmental disabilities (Group 3), the department shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-150__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>make a statewide inventory of existing public, nonprofit, and proprietary facilities;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-150__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>survey the need for construction of these facilities;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-150__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>on the basis of the inventory and survey, develop a program for the construction of public and other nonprofit facilities for each of these groups that will, in conjunction with existing facilities, afford the necessary physical facilities for furnishing adequate facility services to all residents of the state.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-20-150__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 19 ch 6 SLA 1998.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-20-150__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-150__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide for adequate facilities to furnish needed services for persons unable to pay for them in accordance with regulations adopted under the federal act;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-150__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>submit any reports that the surgeon general considers necessary for compliance with the federal act;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-150__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>do all things on behalf of the state necessary to obtain benefits under the federal act.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-20-160">
            <num>18.20.160</num>
            <heading>Priority of projects.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.20.160.   Priority of projects.
The state plan must set out the relative need for the projects included in the construction program determined in accordance with the regulations adopted under the federal act, and provide for the construction, maintenance, and operation to the extent financial resources permit, in the order of the relative need.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-20-170">
            <num>18.20.170</num>
            <heading>Application for construction projects.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.20.170.   Application for construction projects.
The state, a political subdivision of the state, or a public or other nonprofit agency requesting federal funds for a health facility construction project must apply to the department.  The application must conform to federal and state requirements.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-20-180">
            <num>18.20.180</num>
            <heading>Approval of applications.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.20.180.   Approval of applications.
The commissioner of the department shall give every applicant an opportunity for a fair hearing.  If, after giving reasonable opportunity for development and presentation of applications in the order of relative need, the commissioner of the department finds that a project application complies with the requirements of
AS 18.20.170
and conforms with the state plan, the commissioner shall approve and recommend the application and forward it to the surgeon general.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-20-190">
            <num>18.20.190</num>
            <heading>Inspection of projects.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.20.190.   Inspection of projects.
The commissioner of the department shall inspect each construction project approved by the surgeon general from time to time.  If the commissioner finds that work has been performed upon the project or purchases have been made in accordance with the approved plans and specifications, the commissioner shall certify to the surgeon general that this is the fact and that payment of an installment of federal funds is due the applicant.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-20-200">
            <num>18.20.200</num>
            <heading>Acceptance of grants.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.20.200.   Acceptance of grants.
The department may accept on behalf of the state and may deposit separate and apart from public money and funds, a grant from the federal government, or gift or contribution from any source made to assist in meeting the cost of carrying out the purposes of
AS 18.20.140
 18.20.220.  Federal funds received and not expended for these purposes shall be repaid to the United States.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-20-210">
            <num>18.20.210</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.20.210.   Definitions.
In
AS 18.20.140
 18.20.220,
(1) community mental health center means a facility providing services for the prevention or diagnosis of mental illness, or care and treatment of mentally ill patients, or rehabilitation of mentally ill persons, which services are provided principally for persons residing in a particular community or communities in or near which the facility is situated;
(2) department means the Department of Health;
(3) facility for persons with intellectual and developmental disabilities means a facility specially designed for the diagnosis, treatment, education, training, or custodial care of persons with intellectual and developmental disabilities, including facilities for training specialists and sheltered workshops for persons with intellectual and developmental disabilities, but only if the workshops are part of facilities that provide or will provide comprehensive services for persons with intellectual and developmental disabilities;
(4) federal act means Title VI of the Public Health Service Act (42 U.S.C. 291 et seq.) concerning hospitals and medical facilities and the Mental Retardation Facilities and Community Mental Health Centers Construction Act of 1963 (P.L. 88-164) concerning facilities for persons with intellectual and developmental disabilities and community mental health centers, both as now or hereafter amended;
(5) hospital includes a public health center and general, tuberculosis, mental, chronic disease, and other type of hospital, and related facilities, including laboratory, outpatient department, nurses' homes, and training facilities, and central services facilities operated in connection with a hospital, but does not include a hospital furnishing primarily domiciliary care;
(6) medical facilities means diagnostic and treatment centers, rehabilitation facilities, and nursing homes, as those terms are defined in the federal act, and other medical facilities for which federal aid may be authorized under the federal act;
(7) nonprofit facility for persons with intellectual and developmental disabilities and nonprofit community mental health center mean, respectively, a facility for persons with intellectual and developmental disabilities and a community mental health center that is owned and operated by one or more nonprofit corporations or associations no part of the net earnings of which inures, or may lawfully inure, to the benefit of any private shareholder or individual; and the term nonprofit private agency or organization means an agency or organization that is such a corporation or association or that is owned and operated by one or more of such corporations or associations;
(8) nonprofit hospital and nonprofit medical facility mean a hospital or medical facility owned and operated by a nonprofit corporation or association, no part of the net earnings of which inures, or may lawfully inure, to the benefit of a private shareholder or individual;
(9) public health center means a publicly owned facility providing public health services, including related facilities such as laboratory, clinic, and administrative offices operated in connection with the public health center;
(10) surgeon general means the Surgeon General of the Public Health Service or any other federal agency designated to administer the federal act.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-20-220">
            <num>18.20.220</num>
            <heading>Short title.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.20.220.   Short title.
AS 18.20.140
 18.20.220 may be cited as the Alaska Hospital and Medical Facilities Survey and Construction Act.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-20-300">
            <num>18.20.300</num>
            <heading>State policy.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.20.300.   State policy.
It is the policy of the state to ensure that the quality of care in nursing facilities in this state is maintained at a high standard in accordance with applicable state and federal law and regulations and to ensure the health, safety, and quality of life of nursing facility residents in Alaska is maintained or enhanced.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-20-305">
            <num>18.20.305</num>
            <heading>Nursing facility regulations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.20.305.   Nursing facility regulations.
The department shall adopt necessary regulations to implement
AS 18.20.300
 18.20.390 in accordance with
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act). The department shall, by regulation, specify criteria as to when and how the sanctions specified in
AS 18.20.310
will be applied. The criteria must provide for the imposition of incrementally more severe penalties for deficiencies that are uncorrected or pervasive, or that present a threat to the health, safety, or welfare of nursing facility residents.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-20-310">
            <num>18.20.310</num>
            <heading>Sanctions for noncompliance.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-20-310__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the department finds that a nursing facility, or a partner, officer, director, owner of five percent or more of the nursing facility's assets, or managing employee of the nursing facility substantially failed or refused to comply with
AS 08.68.340
 08.68.390,
AS 08.70
,
AS 18.20.075
 18.20.085,
AS 47.07
, or with a regulation adopted under any of those statutes, or, for a nursing facility that provides Medicaid services under
AS 47.07
, failed or refused to comply with the Medicaid requirements of 42 U.S.C. 1396r (Title XIX of the Social Security Act, as amended) or a regulation adopted under that statute, the department may take the following actions:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-310__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>ban the admission of new residents to the nursing facility;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-310__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>as provided in
AS 18.20.320
, deny payment under
AS 47.07
and
AS 47.25.120
 47.25.300 for any Medicaid or general relief-medical resident admitted to the nursing facility after notice by the department of denial of payment; residents who are eligible for Medicaid or general relief-medical are not responsible for payment when the department takes action under this paragraph;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-310__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>assess a civil fine in accordance with
AS 18.20.340
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-310__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>suspend or terminate the nursing facility's participation in the Medicaid program;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-310__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>suspend, revoke, or refuse to renew the nursing facility's license issued under this chapter;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-310__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>seek an appointment of temporary administration as provided in
AS 18.20.360
or of a receiver under
AS 18.20.370
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-310__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in case of an emergency, seek an order from the court either to close the nursing facility or to transfer residents from that facility, or both.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-20-310__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An order of the department imposing a sanction described in</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-310__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>(a)(1), (4), or (5) of this section takes effect immediately upon service of the order on the nursing facility; however, if the facility can demonstrate to the department's satisfaction that the deficiencies prompting the order do not jeopardize the health or safety of facility residents or seriously limit the nursing facility's capacity to provide adequate care, the department's order takes effect 10 days after service;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-310__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>(a)(2) or (3) of this section takes effect 10 days after service of the order on the nursing facility.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-20-310__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A hearing may be requested under
AS 18.20.330
regarding a sanction imposed by the department under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-20-320">
            <num>18.20.320</num>
            <heading>Denial of payment.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.20.320.   Denial of payment.
The department shall deny payment under
AS 47.07
or
AS 47.25.120
 47.25.300 to a nursing facility
(1) that is not in compliance, and, for the preceding three months, has not been in compliance, with the requirements of 42 U.S.C. 1396r (Title XIX of the Social Security Act, as amended), and regulations adopted under that statute, until correction of the deficiency; or
(2) if the department finds, on three consecutive reviews, that the nursing facility provided substandard quality of care; the department shall deny payment under this paragraph for new admissions until the facility has demonstrated to the satisfaction of the department that it is in compliance with the Medicaid requirements of 42 U.S.C. 1396r, and that it will remain in compliance with the requirements.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-20-330">
            <num>18.20.330</num>
            <heading>Appeal; hearing.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-20-330__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding
AS 44.62.330
 44.62.630, the department, by regulation, shall establish a hearing procedure by which a nursing facility may present evidence to refute a deficiency found by the department, and by which it may appeal, in a hearing conducted by the office of administrative hearings (
AS 44.64.010
), a sanction imposed by order of the department under
AS 18.20.310
. A request for a hearing shall be made in writing within 10 days after service of the department's order on the nursing facility. Except for an order that takes effect immediately under
AS 18.20.310
(b)(1), a request under this subsection has the effect of staying the department's order until the hearing is concluded and the department makes a final determination.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-20-330__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An appeal, or request for stay, regarding a sanction imposed by the court under
AS 18.20.310
(a)(6) or (7), 18.20.360, or 18.20.370, shall be filed with the court in accordance with the Rules of Civil Procedure.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-20-340">
            <num>18.20.340</num>
            <heading>Civil fines.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.20.340.   Civil fines.
In accordance with regulations adopted by the department under
AS 44.62.010
 44.62.300, the department may assess and collect, with interest, a civil fine of up to $10,000 a day for each day a nursing facility is or was out of compliance with any of the federal or state statutes or regulations listed in
AS 18.20.310
. The department shall annually increase the maximum amount of the civil fine authorized in this section by a percentage equal to the percentage of increase in all items of the Consumer Price Index for all urban consumers for Anchorage, Alaska. Each day upon which the same or a substantially similar noncompliance occurs is a separate violation subject to the assessment of a separate civil fine. A civil fine assessed under this section is not reimbursable under
AS 47.07
or
AS 47.25.120
 47.25.300. The department shall deduct the amount of a civil fine from reimbursement due or to be due the nursing facility under
AS 47.07
or
AS 47.25.120
 47.25.300. The department may also use any remedy available under law to pursue collection of an unpaid fine.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-20-350">
            <num>18.20.350</num>
            <heading>Nursing facility resident security fund.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-20-350__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>There is established in the department, as a fund separate from other public money of the state, the nursing facility resident security fund. This fund consists of all civil fines collected under
AS 18.20.310
(a)(3) and 18.20.340 related to noncompliance with 42 U.S.C. 1396r(b), (c), or (d), and all interest earned on money in the fund.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-20-350__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The nursing facility resident security fund shall be administered by the department. Money in the fund may only be used for the protection of the health or property of residents of nursing facilities found to be out of compliance with 42 U.S.C. 1396r(b), (c), or (d), or a regulation adopted under those statutes, including payment for the costs of relocation of residents to other facilities, maintenance of operation of a facility pending correction of deficiencies or closure, and reimbursement to a resident for personal money lost.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-20-360">
            <num>18.20.360</num>
            <heading>Temporary management.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-20-360__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the department determines that the health or safety of the residents of a nursing facility is immediately jeopardized as the result of the nursing facility's failure or refusal to comply with a state statute or regulation, or failure or refusal to comply with the Medicaid requirements in 42 U.S.C. 1396r (Title XIX of the Social Security Act) or a regulation adopted under that statute, the department shall immediately petition the superior court for an order for appointment of temporary administration to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-360__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>oversee the operation of the facility; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-360__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>ensure the health and safety of the facility's residents while orderly closure of the facility occurs or the deficiencies necessitating temporary administration are corrected.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-20-360__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The court shall grant the petition if it finds by a preponderance of the evidence that the conditions in (a) of this section exist.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-20-370">
            <num>18.20.370</num>
            <heading>Receivership.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-20-370__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may petition the superior court for establishment of a receivership for a nursing facility if the department finds that one of the following conditions exists and the current operator has demonstrated an inability or unwillingness to take action necessary to immediately correct the conditions alleged:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-370__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the facility is operating without a license;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-370__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the health, safety, or welfare of the facility's residents is immediately jeopardized;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-370__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the facility demonstrates a pattern and practice of violating state or federal statutes or regulations in such a way that minimum resident care is jeopardized.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-20-370__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The court shall grant the petition if it finds by a preponderance of the evidence that one or more of the conditions in (a) of this section exist and the current operator is unable or unwilling to take action necessary to correct the condition.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-20-390">
            <num>18.20.390</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.20.390.   Definitions.
In
AS 18.20.300
 18.20.390, unless the context requires otherwise,
(1) department means the Department of Health;
(2) general relief-medical means the medical assistance program authorized in
AS 47.25.120
 47.25.300;
(3) Medicaid means the medical assistance program authorized in
AS 47.07
;
(4) nursing facility means an institution, or a distinct part of an institution, as defined in 42 U.S.C. 1396r.
Article 4. Overtime Limitations for Nurses.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-20-400">
            <num>18.20.400</num>
            <heading>Limitations on nursing overtime.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-20-400__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (c) of this section, a nurse in a health care facility may not be required or coerced, directly or indirectly,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-400__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to work beyond a predetermined and regularly scheduled shift that is agreed to by the nurse and the health care facility; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-400__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to accept an assignment of overtime if, in the judgment of the nurse, the overtime would jeopardize patient or employee safety.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-20-400__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided by (c) of this section, after working a predetermined and regularly scheduled shift that is agreed to by the nurse and the health care facility as authorized by (a)(1) of this section, a nurse in a health care facility shall be allowed not less than 10 consecutive hours of off-duty time immediately following the end of that work.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-20-400__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subsection (a) of this section does not apply to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-400__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a nurse who is employed by a health care facility providing services for a school, school district, or other educational institution, when the nurse is on duty for more than 14 consecutive hours during an occasional special event, such as a field trip, that is sponsored by the employer;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-400__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a nurse voluntarily working overtime on an aircraft in use for medical transport, so long as the shift worked is allowable under regulations adopted by the Board of Nursing based on accreditation standards adopted by the Commission on Accreditation of Medical Transport Systems;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-400__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a nurse on duty in overtime status
(A) who is participating in the performance of a medical procedure or surgery that has begun but has not been completed;
(B) because of an unforeseen emergency situation that could jeopardize patient safety; in this subparagraph, unforeseen emergency situation means an unusual, unpredictable, or unforeseen situation caused by an act of terrorism, disease outbreak, natural disaster, major disaster as defined in 42 U.S.C. 5122, or disaster emergency under
AS 26.23.020
or 26.23.140, but does not include a situation in which a health care facility has reasonable knowledge of increased patient volume or inadequate staffing because of some other cause, if that cause is foreseeable;
(C) because the health care facility has a scheduling problem caused by unforeseen weather conditions that prevent a second nurse from arriving at the facility to relieve the nurse on duty; in this subparagraph, unforeseen weather conditions means unusual, unpredictable, or unforeseen weather so extreme as to impair travel to the health care facility, but does not include a situation in which the health care facility has knowledge of the weather conditions far enough in advance to act so that a scheduling problem under this subparagraph can reasonably be avoided; or
(D) at a health care facility located in a rural community that declares a temporary nurse staffing emergency under
AS 18.20.410
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-400__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a nurse fulfilling on-call time that is agreed on by the nurse and a health care facility before it is scheduled unless fulfilling the on-call time would, in the nurse's judgment, create an unacceptable risk to the physical safety of the nurse, a patient, or an employee of the facility;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-400__subsec_c__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a nurse voluntarily working overtime so long as the work is consistent with professional standards and safe patient care and does not exceed 14 consecutive hours;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-400__subsec_c__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a nurse voluntarily working beyond 80 hours in a 14-day period so long as the nurse does not work more than 14 consecutive hours without a 10-hour break and the work is consistent with professional standards and safe patient care;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-400__subsec_c__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a nurse who
(A) is employed</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-20-400__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>at a psychiatric treatment hospital that treats only children or at a residential psychiatric treatment center, as defined under
AS 18.07.111
, that treats only children; in this sub-subparagraph, children means persons under 19 years of age who are receiving psychiatric treatment from a hospital or center or who are residing in a center and who were under 18 years of age on the date that the treatment or period of residence commenced;
(ii) at a residential psychiatric treatment center as defined under
AS 47.32.900
; or
(iii) at a secure residential psychiatric treatment center as defined under
AS 47.12.990
;
(B) voluntarily agrees to work a 16-hour shift for the period between 5:00 p.m. on a Friday and 8:00 a.m. on the Monday that immediately follows and receives pay and benefits for that work that are equal to or greater than the pay and benefits the nurse would receive for working 20 regular hours in the same position; and
(C) during the period described in (B) of this paragraph does not work a 16-hour shift consecutive with another shift of eight hours or more without an intervening break of at least eight hours;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-400__subsec_i__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the first two hours on overtime status when the health care facility is obtaining another nurse to work in place of the nurse in overtime status, so long as the nurse in overtime status is not on duty for more than 14 consecutive hours.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-20-410">
            <num>18.20.410</num>
            <heading>Temporary nurse staffing emergency.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-20-410__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If, after making a substantial and reasonable effort to increase the number of available nurses on staff and failing in that effort, a health care facility in a rural community determines it is not able to meet the overtime limitations in
AS 18.20.400
without putting the safety of its patients at risk of serious harm, the health care facility may declare a temporary nurse staffing emergency. A declaration of a temporary nurse staffing emergency under this section</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-410__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>must be made in a writing, signed by the administrator of the health care facility or the administrator's designee, that describes the facility's reasonable effort to avoid the temporary nurse staffing emergency; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-410__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>may not exceed 30 days.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-20-410__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Immediately after declaring a temporary nurse staffing emergency under (a) of this section, a health care facility shall file with the division of labor standards and safety, Department of Labor and Workforce Development, a report that includes a copy of the signed writing required under (a) of this section. A report under this subsection is a public document.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-20-410__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to the requirements of (a) and (b) of this section, a health care facility shall notify the legislature immediately by delivery of a written report to the Alaska Legislative Council each time the facility declares a temporary nurse staffing emergency under
AS 18.20.400</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-20-410__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>that exceeds two occurrences in a six-month period that begins on January 1 or July 1 of the year in which the declaration occurs, or three occurrences in the one-year period that begins on January 1 of that year. A report under this subsection must include a copy of each report that is required of the health care facility under (b) of this section for the one-year period that begins on January 1 of the year the excessive declaration under this subsection occurs.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-20-420">
            <num>18.20.420</num>
            <heading>Health care facility complaint process for overtime work by nurses.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.20.420.   Health care facility complaint process for overtime work by nurses.
A health care facility shall provide for an anonymous process by which a patient or a nurse may make a complaint about staffing levels and patient safety that relate to overtime work by nurses and to limitations on overtime work by nurses under
AS 18.20.400
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-20-430">
            <num>18.20.430</num>
            <heading>Enforcement, offenses, and penalties.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-20-430__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall administer
AS 18.20.400
 18.20.499 and adopt regulations for implementing and enforcing
AS 18.20.400
 18.20.499.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-20-430__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A complaint alleging a violation of
AS 18.20.400
 18.20.499 must be filed with the commissioner within 30 days after the date of the alleged violation. The commissioner shall provide a copy of the complaint to the health care facility named in the filing within three business days after receiving the complaint.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-20-430__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the commissioner finds that a health care facility has knowingly violated an overtime provision of
AS 18.20.400
 18.20.499, the following civil penalties shall apply:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-430__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for a first violation of
AS 18.20.400
 18.20.499, the commissioner shall reprimand the health care facility;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-430__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for a second violation of
AS 18.20.400
 18.20.499 within 12 months, the commissioner shall reprimand the health care facility and assess a penalty of $500;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-430__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for a third violation of
AS 18.20.400
 18.20.499 within 12 months, the commissioner shall reprimand the health care facility and assess a penalty of not less than $2,500 but not more than $5,000;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-430__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for each violation of
AS 18.20.400
 18.20.499 after a third violation of
AS 18.20.400
 18.20.499 within 12 months, the commissioner shall reprimand the health care facility and assess a penalty of not less than $5,000 but not more than $25,000.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-20-430__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>As an employer, a health care facility violates an overtime provision of
AS 18.20.400
 18.20.499 knowingly when the facility is either aware that its conduct is of a nature prohibited by the overtime provision or aware that the circumstances described in the overtime prohibition exist; however, when knowledge of the existence of a particular fact is required to establish that the violation was knowing, that knowledge exists when the facility is aware of a substantial probability of its existence, unless the facility reasonably believes it does not exist.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-20-440">
            <num>18.20.440</num>
            <heading>Prohibition of retaliation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.20.440.   Prohibition of retaliation.
A health care facility may not discharge, discipline, threaten, discriminate against, penalize, or file a report with the Board of Nursing against a nurse for exercising rights under
AS 18.20.400
 18.20.499 or for the good faith reporting of an alleged violation of
AS 18.20.400
 18.20.499.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-20-450">
            <num>18.20.450</num>
            <heading>Report requirements.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-20-450__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A health care facility shall file with the division of labor standards and safety, Department of Labor and Workforce Development, a semiannual report on a form provided by the department. The report for the six-month period ending June 30 must be filed before the following August 1, and the report for the six-month period ending December 31 must be filed before the following February 1. The report must include, for each nurse employed by the health care facility or under contract with the health care facility, the number of overtime hours worked and the number of hours the nurse was on call. A health care facility that does not employ a nurse who worked overtime hours or who was on call during the reporting period is not required to describe hours worked as overtime and on-call hours for individual nurses but may instead complete the report by stating on the form that there are no reportable hours.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-20-450__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A primary care outpatient facility is not subject to the reporting requirements of (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-20-460">
            <num>18.20.460</num>
            <heading>Provisions not applicable to nurses employed in federal or tribal facilities.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.20.460.   Provisions not applicable to nurses employed in federal or tribal facilities.
The provisions of
AS 18.20.400
 18.20.499 do not apply to a nurse employed in a health care facility that is operated by
(1) the federal government; or
(2) a tribal organization as defined in 25 U.S.C. 450b.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-20-470">
            <num>18.20.470</num>
            <heading>Notice to employees.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.20.470.   Notice to employees.
A health care facility shall post and maintain, in places readily accessible to individuals in the service of the health care facility, printed statements that describe employee rights and employer obligations under
AS 18.20.400
 18.20.499 and regulations adopted under
AS 18.20.430
. The commissioner shall supply the printed statements to a health care facility without cost to the facility.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-20-499">
            <num>18.20.499</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.20.499.   Definitions.
In
AS 18.20.400
 18.20.499,
(1) commissioner means the commissioner of labor and workforce development;
(2) health care facility means a private, municipal, or state hospital; independent diagnostic testing facility; primary care outpatient facility; skilled nursing facility; kidney disease treatment center, including freestanding hemodialysis units; intermediate care facility; ambulatory surgical facility; Alaska Pioneers' Home or Alaska Veterans' Home administered by the Department of Family and Community Services under
AS 47.55
; correctional facility owned or administered by the state; private, municipal, or state facility employing one or more public health nurses; long-term care facility; psychiatric hospital; residential psychiatric treatment center, as defined in
AS 18.07.111
or
AS 47.32.900
; secure residential psychiatric treatment center under
AS 47.12.990
; juvenile detention facility or juvenile treatment facility, as those terms are defined in
AS 47.12.990
; or treatment institution as that term is defined in
AS 47.14.990
;
(3) nurse means an individual licensed to practice registered nursing or practical nursing under
AS 08.68
who provides nursing services through direct patient care or clinical services and includes a nurse manager when delivering in-hospital patient care;
(4) on-call means a status in which a nurse must be ready to report to the health care facility and may be called to work by the health care facility;
(5) overtime means the hours worked in excess of a predetermined and regularly scheduled shift that is agreed to by a nurse and a health care facility;
(6) rural community means a village or city that has a population of less than 10,000, as determined by the Department of Labor and Workforce Development, and is in
(A) the unorganized borough; or
(B) an organized borough that has a population of less than 25,000, as determined by the Department of Labor and Workforce Development.
Article 5. Discharge of Hospital Patients.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-20-500">
            <num>18.20.500</num>
            <heading>Aftercare assessment and designation of caregiver.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.20.500.   Aftercare assessment and designation of caregiver.
Before discharging a patient, a hospital shall assess the patient's ability for self-care after discharge and provide the patient with the opportunity to designate a caregiver who agrees to provide aftercare for the patient in a private residence after discharge.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-20-510">
            <num>18.20.510</num>
            <heading>Planning, instruction, and training.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-20-510__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A hospital shall give the patient and the patient's designated caregiver the opportunity to participate in planning for the patient's discharge from the hospital.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-20-510__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before discharge, a hospital shall provide a patient and the patient's designated caregiver with instruction and training as necessary for the designated caregiver to perform medical and nursing aftercare following discharge.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-20-520">
            <num>18.20.520</num>
            <heading>Notification of discharge.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.20.520.   Notification of discharge.
A hospital shall notify a patient's designated caregiver of the patient's discharge or transfer.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-20-530">
            <num>18.20.530</num>
            <heading>Discharge policies.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-20-530__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A hospital shall adopt and maintain written discharge policies. The policies must comply with
AS 18.20.500
 18.20.590.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-20-530__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The discharge policies of a hospital must specify the requirements for documenting the identity of a patient's designated caregiver and the details of the discharge plan for the patient, including professional follow-up as specified in the discharge plan.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-20-530__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The discharge policies of a hospital may incorporate established evidence-based practices that include</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-530__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>standards for accreditation adopted by a nationally recognized hospital accreditation organization; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-530__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the conditions of participation for hospitals adopted by the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-20-530__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The discharge policies of a hospital must ensure that the discharge planning is appropriate to the condition of the patient, and the hospital shall interpret the discharge policies in a manner and as necessary to meet the needs and condition of the patient and the abilities of the patient's designated caregiver.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-20-530__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>AS 18.20.500
 18.20.590 do not require that a hospital adopt discharge policies that would</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-530__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>delay a patient's discharge or transfer to another facility; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-20-530__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>require the disclosure of protected health information without obtaining a patient's consent as required by state and federal laws governing health information privacy and security.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-20-540">
            <num>18.20.540</num>
            <heading>Construction of provisions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.20.540.   Construction of provisions.
The provisions of
AS 18.20.500
 18.20.590 may not be construed to
(1) create a right of action against a hospital, a hospital employee, or a contractor of the hospital, including a person who contracts with the hospital to provide instruction to a designated caregiver, based on an action performed or not performed under
AS 18.20.500
 18.20.590; or
(2) replace, change, or otherwise affect rights or remedies that are provided under another provision of law, including common law.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-20-550">
            <num>18.20.550</num>
            <heading>Coordination with other authority.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.20.550.   Coordination with other authority.
AS 18.20.500
 18.20.590 may not be interpreted to interfere with the powers or duties of
(1) an agent operating under a valid advance health care directive under
AS 13.52
; or
(2) a legal guardian of the patient.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-20-590">
            <num>18.20.590</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.20.590.   Definitions.
In
AS 18.20.500
 18.20.590,
(1) aftercare includes
(A) assistance with the activities of daily living or activities that are instrumental to the activities of daily living;
(B) wound care, medication administration, medical equipment operation, mobility assistance, and other medical or nursing tasks; and
(C) other assistance related to the patient's condition at the time of discharge;
(2) designated caregiver means a caregiver designated by the patient who agrees to provide aftercare to the patient in a private residence;
(3) discharge means a patient's release from a hospital following the patient's admission to the hospital;
(4) hospital has the meaning given in
AS 18.20.130
, but does not include a hospital that is limited to the treatment of mental disorders;
(5) private residence does not include a rehabilitative facility, a hospital, a nursing home, an assisted living facility, a group home, or another licensed health care facility.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>