<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-47/chapter-90"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-47/chapter-90"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="47.90"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-47/chapter-90/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-47/chapter-90/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-47/chapter-90/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-47/chapter-90/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_47">
        <num>47</num>
        <heading>Welfare, Social Services, and Institutions</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_47__chp_90">
          <num>90</num>
          <heading>Displaced Homemakers</heading>
          <section eId="sec_47-90-010">
            <num>47.90.010</num>
            <heading>Program established.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-90-010__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner, in consultation with state and local government agencies, community groups, and groups concerned with displaced homemakers, may</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-90-010__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>contract with eligible private profit and nonprofit corporations for multipurpose service centers for displaced homemakers; contracting under this paragraph is governed by
AS 36.30
(State Procurement Code); and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-90-010__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>coordinate existing state programs for displaced homemakers.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-90-010__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall adopt regulations prescribing the standards to be met by each multipurpose service center for displaced homemakers in accordance with the policies established in this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-90-010__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 67 ch 106 SLA 1986.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-90-010__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To be eligible for an award of a contract under this chapter a private profit or nonprofit corporation must be governed by a board of directors whose membership is broadly representative of the community in which it operates as determined by the commissioner.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-90-020">
            <num>47.90.020</num>
            <heading>Services provided by centers.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-90-020__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A multipurpose service center for displaced homemakers established under
AS 47.90.010
may provide the following services:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-90-020__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>job counseling services that
(A) are specifically designed for displaced homemakers;
(B) counsel displaced homemakers regarding job opportunities; and
(C) consider and build on the skills and experience of a homemaker and emphasize job readiness as well as skill development;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-90-020__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>job training and job placement services that
(A) emphasize short-term training programs that expand upon homemaking skills and volunteer experience and that lead to gainful employment;
(B) develop through cooperation with state and local government agencies and private employers training and placement programs for jobs in the public and private sector;
(C) assist displaced homemakers in gaining admission to existing public and private job-training programs and opportunities including vocational education, reentry into secondary and post-secondary education, and apprenticeship training programs; and
(D) assist in identifying community needs and creating new jobs for displaced homemakers in the public and private sector;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-90-020__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>health counseling services including referral to existing health programs with respect to
(A) general principles of preventive health care;
(B) health care consumer education, particularly in the selection of physicians and health care services including health maintenance organizations and health insurance;
(C) mental health care and transitional counseling;
(D) family health care and nutrition;
(E) alcohol and drug abuse, including the abuse of prescription drugs; and
(F) other related health care matters;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-90-020__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>financial management services that provide information and assistance relating to insurance, taxes, estate and probate matters, mortgages, loans, and related financial matters;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-90-020__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>educational services including
(A) information relating to courses offering credit through secondary or postsecondary education programs and reentry programs, including bilingual programs if appropriate, and information relating to the availability of financial assistance; and
(B) information about other programs of benefit to displaced homemakers;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-90-020__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>legal counseling and referral services;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-90-020__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>information services with respect to federal and state employment, education, health, public assistance, and unemployment assistance programs that the commissioner determines to be of benefit to displaced homemakers.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-90-020__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A multipurpose center for displaced homemakers may provide assistance in obtaining child care, temporary babysitting expenses, and transportation when it will aid a displaced homemaker to receive services under (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-90-030">
            <num>47.90.030</num>
            <heading>Employment of displaced homemakers.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.90.030.   Employment of displaced homemakers.
The staff positions of multipurpose centers established under
AS 47.90.010
, including supervisory, technical, and administrative positions, shall to the maximum extent possible be filled by displaced homemakers.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-90-040">
            <num>47.90.040</num>
            <heading>Consultation and cooperation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.90.040.   Consultation and cooperation.
The commissioner shall consult and cooperate with the Department of Health; the Department of Education and Early Development; the director of the division of vocational rehabilitation; the University of Alaska, community colleges, and other colleges as appropriate; and other persons or agencies that the commissioner considers appropriate in the implementation of this chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-90-050">
            <num>47.90.050</num>
            <heading>State employment assistance.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.90.050.   State employment assistance.
Contractors operating programs under
AS 47.90.010
shall, to the maximum extent possible, provide displaced homemakers with assistance in qualifying on state employment registers under regulations of the commissioner.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-90-060">
            <num>47.90.060</num>
            <heading>Regulations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.90.060.   Regulations.
The commissioner may adopt regulations to implement this chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-90-070">
            <num>47.90.070</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.90.070.   Definitions.
In this chapter,
(1) commissioner means the commissioner of labor and workforce development;
(2) displaced homemaker means a person who
(A) has worked as a homemaker providing unsalaried services for the family for a period of at least three years;
(B) faces a significant reduction in family income or support through divorce, death, separation, desertion, or disability; and
(C) has encountered difficulty in finding employment.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>