<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-44/chapter-21"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-44/chapter-21"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="44.21"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-44/chapter-21/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-44/chapter-21/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-44/chapter-21/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-44/chapter-21/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_44">
        <num>44</num>
        <heading>State Government</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_44__chp_21">
          <num>21</num>
          <heading>Department of Administration</heading>
          <section eId="sec_44-21-010">
            <num>44.21.010</num>
            <heading>Commissioner of administration.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.21.010.   Commissioner of administration.
The principal executive officer of the Department of Administration is the commissioner of administration.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-21-020">
            <num>44.21.020</num>
            <heading>Duties of department.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.21.020.   Duties of department.
The Department of Administration shall
(1) make surveys and studies to improve administrative procedures, methods, and organization;
(2) keep general accounts;
(3) approve vouchers and disburse funds for all purposes;
(4) operate centralized purchasing and supply services, and necessary storerooms and warehouses;
(5) [Repealed, E.O. No. 122, § 35 (2022).]
(6) supervise telephone, mailing, messenger, duplicating, and similar services adaptable to centralized management;
(7) administer the public employees' retirement system and teachers' retirement system;
(8) administer a statewide personnel program, including central personnel services such as recruitment, assessment, position classification, and pay administration;
(9) administer and supervise a statewide automatic data processing program;
(10) study, design, implement, and manage the telecommunications systems and services of the state under
AS 44.21.305
 44.21.330.
(11) [Repealed, E.O. No. 120, § 3 (2021).]</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-21-030">
            <num>44.21.030</num>
            <heading>Contracting with United States.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.21.030.   Contracting with United States.
The Department of Administration may contract with the United States for the education, medical activities, agricultural assistance and social welfare, and relief of distress of Indians and Eskimos, and spend money appropriated by Congress for these activities in accordance with the provisions of the Act of Congress approved April 16, 1934.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-21-040">
            <num>44.21.040</num>
            <heading>Records or accounts of claims and warrants.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-21-040__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Administration shall keep books of account in permanent form of the claims presented and of the disbursements made. These records must show</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-040__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name of the claimant;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-040__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the amount of the claim;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-040__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the date of its presentation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-040__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the date of its allowance or disallowance;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-040__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the date and number of each disbursement made;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-040__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name of the payee; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-040__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the appropriation from which the disbursement is made.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-040__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Administration shall keep on file all original bills and claims presented, with the vouchers.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-21-045">
            <num>44.21.045</num>
            <heading>Information services fund; charges.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-21-045__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The information services fund is established as an internal services fund in the Department of Administration.  The fund consists of money appropriated to it, money transferred to the department by political subdivisions and state agencies as reimbursement for information services provided by the department, and the proceeds from the sale of surplus or other assets of the department used for information services.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-045__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Money transferred to the department by a political subdivision or state agency for information services for a fiscal year that exceeds the appropriation to the department for information services provided to the political subdivision or state agency for that fiscal year constitutes program receipts that are subject to the procedures of
AS 37.07.080
(h).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-045__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (b) of this section, money in the fund established under (a) of this section may be expended only in accordance with legislative appropriations. Money appropriated to the fund may be used for</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-045__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the costs of the commissioner in carrying out the commissioner's duties under
AS 44.21.350
 44.21.390, including the costs of performing reviews and studies considered necessary by the commissioner under
AS 44.21.350
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-045__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>necessary expenses of providing information services to political subdivisions and state agencies;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-045__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>additions, replacements, or improvement of capital equipment for information services; requests by the department for capital equipment expenditures shall be included in the budget submitted by the governor to the legislature under
AS 37.07
; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-045__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>other purposes as specified in an appropriation to the fund.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-045__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may charge and collect fees and surcharges for information services provided by it to agencies and political subdivisions of the state. The department shall maintain cost accounting records to support rates and billings for information services provided by the department. The department shall submit a report on the operation of the fund to the governor at the time of submission of the departmental budget and notify the legislature that the report is available.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-045__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A state agency that receives information services from the department shall include in its annual budget, as an identifiable item, its expected fees and surcharges for information services provided by the Department of Administration.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-045__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Fees and surcharges for information services of the department are subject to annual review and approval by the commissioner of the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-045__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, information services includes automatic data processing services provided under
AS 44.21.150
 44.21.170 and telecommunications services and operations described in
AS 44.21.305
 44.21.330.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-21-150">
            <num>44.21.150</num>
            <heading>Declaration of purpose.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.21.150.   Declaration of purpose.
It is the purpose of
AS 44.21.150
 44.21.170 to designate the Department of Administration as the department responsible for the operation and management of automatic data processing resources and activities of the executive branch of state government and the judicial and legislative branches to the extent requested by those branches, and to provide for periodic review of state automatic data processing procedures and mechanisms. It is further the purpose of these sections to encourage cooperation between the state government and local governments in the use of automatic data processing systems.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-21-160">
            <num>44.21.160</num>
            <heading>Powers and duties of department.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-21-160__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as otherwise provided in (g) of this section, the department shall comply with the state information systems plan adopted by the commissioner in providing automatic data processing services responsive to the needs of state government.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-160__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To carry out (a) of this section the department may, consistent with the state information systems plan adopted by the commissioner and with the departmental information systems plan,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-160__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>maintain a central staff of systems analysts, computer programmers, and other staff members sufficient to provide systems analysis and computer programming support required by the executive branch of state government;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-160__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>develop and maintain both short-range and long-range data processing plans for state government and provide managerial leadership in the use of automatic data processing;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-160__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>review all budget requests for automatic data processing services and recommend to the commissioner and the governor approval, modification, or disapproval;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-160__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>recommend implementation priorities of requested data processing systems;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-160__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>determine and satisfy the data processing equipment and supply requirements of the executive branch, departments, and agencies of state government;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-160__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide all facilities, equipment, and staff required to convert data to a form suitable for processing on automatic data processing equipment;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-160__subsec_b__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>develop and publish systems analysis, computer programming, and computer operations standards;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-160__subsec_b__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>review state automatic data processing systems to encourage effectiveness, measure performance, and assure adherence to the standards developed under
AS 44.21.150
 44.21.170;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-160__subsec_b__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>develop and conduct an automatic data processing training program designed to serve the technical and managerial needs of state government;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-160__subsec_b__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>charge a state agency or other governmental agency for the cost of the automatic data processing services provided or procured by the department for the agency.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-160__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may cooperate with political subdivisions of the state in the development and operation of data processing systems and may allow for the use of state facilities by political subdivisions.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-160__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In accordance with the state information systems plan adopted by the commissioner, the department and the University of Alaska may develop and implement a plan for the integration of automatic data processing facilities of the university with the state facilities.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-160__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the action is not contrary to the state information systems plan adopted by the commissioner, this section does not prohibit</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-160__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the department from obtaining necessary contractual assistance for automatic data processing activities;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-160__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the legislature from recruiting and employing data processing personnel or from obtaining necessary contractual assistance for automatic data processing activities;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-160__subsec_e__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the judicial branch from establishing independent data processing policies and implementation procedures; however, the policies and procedures must permit information exchange and implementation procedures compatible with other branches of government whenever practical.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-160__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall provide for the effective transfer of information by telecommunications through the establishment of compatible systems and common standards.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-160__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall provide or procure automatic data processing services under
AS 44.21.150
 44.21.170 for the judicial branch to the extent requested by that branch, and may charge the branch for the services.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-160__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 3 ch 156 SLA 1990.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-21-170">
            <num>44.21.170</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.21.170.   Definitions.
In
AS 44.21.150
 44.21.170,
(1) automatic data processing means
(A) those methods of processing data by using electrical accounting machinery (EAM) or electronic data processing equipment (EDP), including the activities and devices required to prepare data for automatic data processing;
(B) data communications devices and those systems used with automatic data processing equipment in the transmission and reception of data; and
(C) activities related to the design and development of automatic data processing systems;
(2) commissioner means the commissioner of administration;
(3) department means the Department of Administration.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-21-256">
            <num>44.21.256</num>
            <heading>Creation of Alaska Public Broadcasting Commission.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.21.256.   Creation of Alaska Public Broadcasting Commission.
There is created within the Department of Administration the Alaska Public Broadcasting Commission.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-21-258">
            <num>44.21.258</num>
            <heading>Membership and term of office.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-21-258__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission consists of nine members appointed by the governor, without regard to political affiliation, subject to confirmation by a majority of the members of the legislature in joint session. In making appointments to the commission, the governor shall give due consideration to representation from such fields as higher education, elementary and secondary education, communications, commercial broadcasting, public health, public works, labor, commerce, and the professions. Members may be removed only for cause.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-258__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The members of the commission shall serve staggered terms of five years.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-21-260">
            <num>44.21.260</num>
            <heading>Compensation and expenses.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.21.260.   Compensation and expenses.
Members of the commission receive no salary, but are entitled to per diem and travel expenses authorized by law for other commissions.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-21-262">
            <num>44.21.262</num>
            <heading>Chairman.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.21.262.   Chairman.
At the first meeting, the commission shall elect a chairman from among its members to serve for one year. A chairman may be elected and serve for more than one consecutive term.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-21-264">
            <num>44.21.264</num>
            <heading>Purpose of the commission.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.21.264.   Purpose of the commission.
The commission is created to encourage and supervise the development of an integrated public broadcasting system for the state and for the coordination of all public broadcasting stations.  The primary purpose of the commission is the encouragement and support of noncommercial public broadcasting in the state through the provision of operating and capital grants in support of the delivery of noncommercial programs intended for a general audience by locally controlled nonprofit broadcast stations or telecommunications entities. The commission may support stations and entities that also engage in the delivery of instructional, for-credit programs, and the commission may provide funds for those purposes, but the primary purpose of commission funds is the support of activities that result in the delivery of general audience, noncommercial material.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-21-266">
            <num>44.21.266</num>
            <heading>Duties of the commission.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.21.266.   Duties of the commission.
The commission shall
(1) apply for federal and private funds for public broadcasting purposes and receive all federal, state, or private funds, property, or assistance that may be appropriated, granted, or otherwise made available to the commission for public broadcasting purposes, and use and disburse funds and property for purposes consistent with the terms of
AS 44.21.256
 44.21.290, subject to reasonable limitations imposed by the grantor;
(2) provide consultative services in all aspects of public broadcasting to all public or private agencies in the state that request them;
(3) serve as a library and clearinghouse for public broadcasting information;
(4) through grants to qualified entities, develop an integrated public broadcasting network for the state;
(5) through grants to qualified entities, develop and distribute public broadcasting programming in the state;
(6) prepare and submit to the governor and the legislature, in compliance with the state information systems plan adopted by the commissioner of administration, a long-term plan for the development of public broadcasting stations and systems in the state, and biennially update the plan; and
(7) perform all other functions necessary to ensure the orderly and coordinated development of public broadcasting in the state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-21-268">
            <num>44.21.268</num>
            <heading>Powers of the commission.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-21-268__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission may</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-268__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>employ all consultative, technical and clerical personnel necessary for the implementation of
AS 44.21.256
 44.21.290, within the limits of available funds;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-268__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>employ a director, who shall be directly responsible to the commission in financial and administrative matters;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-268__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide grants to locally controlled non-profit telecommunications entities which lease, purchase, construct, own, operate and manage and are the licensees of public broadcasting stations, production centers, and other related equipment and facilities for the production and transmission of open circuit, closed circuit, 2,500 megahertz, and other transmission means necessary to provide fully effective public broadcasting in the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-268__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>appoint unpaid advisory committees to assist in development of programs for public television broadcasts;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-268__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide assistance to licensed commercial broadcasting stations for the broadcast of public affairs programming.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-268__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In performing its duties and exercising its authority under
AS 44.21.256
  44.21.290, the commission may not exercise control over the specific content or airing of any program material.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-21-270">
            <num>44.21.270</num>
            <heading>Commercial broadcasting.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.21.270.   Commercial broadcasting.
Nothing in
AS 44.21.256
 44.21.290 may be construed to restrict or control commercial broadcast stations or companies operating or licensed in the state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-21-290">
            <num>44.21.290</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.21.290.   Definitions.
In
AS 44.21.256
 44.21.290, unless the context otherwise requires,
(1) commission means the Alaska Public Broadcasting Commission;
(2) public broadcasting includes, but is not limited to, television and radio transmission by 2,500 megahertz, closed circuit or microwave video and audio programming, slow-scan television programming, programming via satellite, teletype or facsimile transmission, and distribution methods, when the transmission, programming, and distribution are intended to serve a noncommercial public purpose.
Article 4. Telecommunications Services and Operations.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-21-305">
            <num>44.21.305</num>
            <heading>Commissioner's responsibility.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.21.305.   Commissioner's responsibility.
The commissioner shall
(1) provide executive direction for the activities of the department related to telecommunications; and
(2) assure that department activities in no way constitute an influence on the content or airing of programming, and report to the governor and the Alaska Public Broadcasting Commission any request or attempt by an employee of the state to influence the content or airing of program material.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-21-310">
            <num>44.21.310</num>
            <heading>Telecommunications powers and duties.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-21-310__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In accordance with the state information systems plan adopted by the commissioner and with the departmental information systems plan, the department shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-310__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>advise the commissioner and the governor on matters of policy and comprehensive state planning for telecommunications services;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-310__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>coordinate, manage, and supervise state programs in telecommunications, including the management of those telecommunication services for the state obtained from common carriers and from the communications industry;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-310__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>when requested, provide technical and consulting assistance to the executive, judicial, and legislative branches of state government, to the University of Alaska, and to private noncommercial entities which request that assistance in facility procurement and leasing and in identifying long-range goals and objectives for the state and its political subdivisions in all aspects of telecommunications, including public, educational, and instructional telecommunications;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-310__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>prepare and maintain a state comprehensive telecommunications development plan to further state telecommunications development and to meet state telecommunications needs and prepare and maintain a comprehensive inventory of all state communications facilities;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-310__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>whenever feasible, procure services from private enterprise or certified and franchised utilities and contract for the construction, management, operation, and maintenance of telecommunications systems, and develop a procurement policy consistent with
AS 36.30
(State Procurement Code); the procurement policy must seek to achieve the maximum benefit to the public, and methods of procurement, including lease, purchase, rental, or combinations of lease, purchase, and rental, must be selected on the basis of factors such as the ratio of long-range costs versus benefits, life cycle costing, and the costs to the communications industry to the extent that these costs may affect local and long distance basic telephone rates; procurement, contracting, construction, and maintenance under this paragraph is governed by
AS 36.30
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-310__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide information and assistance to state agencies to promote governmental coordination and unity in the preparation of agency plans and programs involving the use of telecommunications;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-310__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>apply for and accept federal and private money, property, or assistance, that may be appropriated, granted, or otherwise made available to the department and use and disburse money and property for purposes consistent with
AS 44.21.305
 44.21.330 and
AS 44.21.256
 44.21.290, subject to reasonable limitations imposed by the grantor;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-310__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>participate with other governmental units in planning, and assist local governments and governmental conferences and councils in the state in planning and coordinating their activities relating to telecommunications;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-310__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide for the orderly transition to new telecommunications services and systems by state agencies;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-310__subsec_a__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>serve as a clearinghouse for information, data, and other materials that may be necessary or helpful to federal, state, or local governmental agencies in the development of telecommunication systems;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-310__subsec_a__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>coordinate department services and activities with those of other state departments and agencies to the fullest extent possible to avoid unnecessary duplication; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-310__subsec_a__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide that all activities of the department are responsive to state statutes and regulations, and to the regulations and rulings of the Federal Communications Commission.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-310__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-310__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>coordinate its functions with local, regional, state, and federal officials, private groups and individuals, and with officials of other countries, provinces, and states;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-310__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>enter into contracts and subcontracts on behalf of the state to carry out the provisions of
AS 44.21.305

AS 44.21.330
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-310__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>act for the state in the initiation, investigation, and evaluation of, or participation in, programs related to the purposes of the department that involve more than one government or governmental unit;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-310__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>on behalf of the state, apply for, accept, and expend gifts or grants made to the state if the gifts or grants are for the purposes of furthering the objectives of the department;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-310__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>hold public hearings to obtain information for the purpose of carrying out the provisions of
AS 44.21.305
 44.21.330; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-310__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide telecommunication services to commercial entities for television broadcast and charge for those services.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-310__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may not attempt to influence or affect the content or airing of program material.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-21-315">
            <num>44.21.315</num>
            <heading>Telecommunications services.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-21-315__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In accordance with the state information systems plan adopted by the commissioner and with the departmental information systems plan, the department shall provide</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-315__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>technical consultation to educational and public telecommunications users;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-315__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>coordination and support to telecommunications services for instruction, including technical assistance and assistance in preparation of applications for grants related to program development as may be requested by
(A) public school districts and the Department of Education and Early Development;
(B) the University of Alaska; and
(C) other state agencies as approved by the commissioner;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-315__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>coordination and support for health and safety-related functions, including the administrative and client services provided by state, federal, and private agencies;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-315__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>coordination and support to telecommunications services for public participation in state-financed services, including the public hearing process, as may be statutorily required or otherwise appropriate;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-315__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>assistance, through design, development, and promotion, to local school districts or other local and regional education agencies for the regionalization of instructional telecommunications services;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-315__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establishment of operational policies for public telecommunications services other than public broadcasting; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-315__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>assistance to the Alaska Public Broadcasting Commission and any commission-designated subcommitteees, as necessary to perform assigned department functions; the department shall cooperate with the commission and subcommittees in order to develop policies which are responsive to the user groups which are represented on the commission.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-315__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subject to available funding, the department may make grants to educational and public telecommunication users except grants for public broadcasting purposes.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-315__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall study, plan, and develop integrated instructional telecommunications services for all residents of the state and, after public hearings, submit to the governor and the legislature an annually updated long-term development plan prepared in consultation with the Department of Education and Early Development, the University of Alaska, local school districts, and other local and regional education areas.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-315__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall, after public hearings, submit to the governor an annually updated long-term development plan for teleconferencing facilities and services, including facilities and services used both by state agencies and groups other than state agencies.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-315__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may not own, operate, or be the licensee of a public noncommercial broadcast station or production center.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-315__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing in this section implies department responsibility for programming content.  Program design, production, and use are the responsibility of the program-sponsoring agency or other entity, not the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-21-320">
            <num>44.21.320</num>
            <heading>Telecommunications operations.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-21-320__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (d) of this section, the department may, consistent with the provisions of
AS 44.21.310
(a)(5)</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-320__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>plan, design, construct, manage, and operate all telecommunications systems owned or leased by state agencies;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-320__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>manage centrex and other telephone-related services of state agencies;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-320__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>be responsible generally for telecommunications systems and design for state agencies; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-320__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>coordinate with state agencies in performing their data and word processing tasks.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-320__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Within the limits of available financing, the department shall administer and operate the satellite television project, by</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-320__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>coordinating with the satellite television user groups and entities; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-320__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>providing liaison, management support, and technical assistance for the satellite television project.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-320__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Decisions and policies relating to programming under the satellite television project, including scheduling and allocation policies, may not be made by the department, but may only be made by a network that is representative of participating rural television users, by commercial broadcast users, or by other affected participating user groups and entities under procedures provided by statute or, if no statute applies, then by agreement of the affected user networks or groups.  The department shall assist users in preparing agreements that may be required under this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-320__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may not engage in any activity that interferes with a contract or program right relating to commercial television programming, including but not limited to any right protected by copyright.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-320__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing in
AS 44.21.305
 44.21.330 prohibits a state agency from developing telecommunications systems within its own agency if the agency is in compliance with the state information systems plan adopted by the commissioner and with the agency's own information systems plan and if the commissioner gives written authorization for the agency to engage in its own design, development, management, or operation. The commissioner may authorize independent development only upon a showing of necessity.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-320__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A state agency authorized to develop an internal telecommunications system shall, whenever feasible, coordinate its design development, management, and operation with the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-21-330">
            <num>44.21.330</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.21.330.   Definitions.
In
AS 44.21.305
 44.21.330,
(1) commissioner means the commissioner of administration;
(2) department means the Department of Administration;
(3) public broadcasting means the delivery of radio or television noncommercial programming intended for the general public by any method of telecommunications;
(4) public telecommunications means telecommunications which serve public broadcasting, general educational, instructional, medical, safety, emergency, or public participation functions;
(5) state agencies means all departments, divisions, and offices in the executive branch of state government; it does not mean an agency of the legislative or judicial branch of government or the University of Alaska;
(6) telecommunications means the transmission and reception of messages, impressions, pictures, and signals by means of electromagnetic transmission with or without benefit of a closed transmission medium including all instrumentalities, facilities, apparatus, and services, whether conveyed by cable or wire, radiated through space, or transmitted through other media within a specified area or between designated points;
(7) telecommunications systems means those systems in which the principal service and functions are telecommunications.
Article 5. Telecommunications Information.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-21-350">
            <num>44.21.350</num>
            <heading>Powers and duties.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-21-350__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-350__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establish guidelines and prepare a state short-range and long-range information systems plan to meet state needs;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-350__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in accordance with the state information systems plan, establish guidelines and direct state agencies to prepare agency information systems plans;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-350__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in accordance with statutes governing the availability and confidentiality of information, establish guidelines for the accessing of information by the public.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-350__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to the commissioner's duties under (a) of this section, the commissioner may establish information-related policies and engage in information-related activities the commissioner considers necessary or appropriate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-350__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This section does not grant the commissioner responsibility for broadcast programming content. Program design, production, and use are the responsibility of the program-sponsoring agency or other entity.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-350__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This section does not prohibit a state agency from developing information systems that are inconsistent with the guidelines established in (a) of this section if the commissioner gives written authorization for the user agency to engage in the independent design, development, management, or operation. The commissioner may authorize independent development only upon a showing of necessity. A description of authorization under this subsection shall be included in the annual report required under this section. Written authorization under this subsection is not required for intra-agency use of microcomputers.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-350__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A state agency, including an agency authorized to develop an independent system under (d) of this section, shall coordinate the design, development, management, and operation of its information systems with the commissioner.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-21-390">
            <num>44.21.390</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.21.390.   Definitions.
In
AS 44.21.350
 44.21.390,
(1) commissioner means the commissioner of administration;
(2) state agencies means all departments, divisions, and offices in the executive branch of state government; it does not mean the Alaska Railroad Corporation, the University of Alaska, or an agency of the judicial or legislative branches of government.
Article 6. Office of Public Advocacy.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-21-400">
            <num>44.21.400</num>
            <heading>Public advocacy office established.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.21.400.   Public advocacy office established.
There is created in the Department of Administration the office of public advocacy.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-21-410">
            <num>44.21.410</num>
            <heading>Powers and duties.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-21-410__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The office of public advocacy shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-410__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>perform the duties of the public guardian under
AS 13.26.700
 13.26.750;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-410__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide guardian ad litem services to children in child protection actions under
AS 47.17.030</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-410__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and to wards and respondents in guardianship proceedings who will suffer financial hardship or become dependent upon a government agency or a private person or agency if the services are not provided at state expense under
AS 13.26.041
;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-410__subsec_e__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide legal representation in cases involving judicial bypass procedures for minors seeking abortions under
AS 18.16.030
, in guardianship proceedings to respondents who are financially unable to employ attorneys under
AS 13.26.226</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-410__subsec_e__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide legal representation and guardian ad litem services under
AS 25.24.310
; in cases arising under
AS 47.15
(Interstate Compact for Juveniles); in cases involving petitions to adopt a minor under
AS 25.23.125</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-410__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or petitions for the termination of parental rights under
AS 25.23.180
(c)(2); in cases involving petitions to remove the disabilities of a minor under
AS 09.55.590
; in children's proceedings under
AS 47.10.050</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-410__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or under
AS 47.12.090
; in cases involving appointments under
AS 18.66.100</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-410__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>in petitions for protective orders on behalf of a minor; and in cases involving indigent persons who are entitled to representation under
AS 18.85.100
and who cannot be represented by the public defender agency because of a conflict of interests;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-410__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>develop and coordinate a program to recruit, select, train, assign, and supervise volunteer guardians ad litem from local communities to aid in delivering services in cases in which the office of public advocacy is appointed as guardian ad litem;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-410__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Provide guardian ad litem services in proceedings under
AS 12.45.046
or
AS 18.15.355
 18.15.395;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-410__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establish a fee schedule and collect fees for services provided by the office, except as provided in
AS 18.85.120
or when imposition or collection of a fee is not in the public interest as defined under regulations adopted by the commissioner of administration;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-410__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide guardians ad litem in proceedings under
AS 47.30.839
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-410__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide legal representation to an indigent parent of a child with a disability; in this paragraph, child with a disability has the meaning given in
AS 14.30.350
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-410__subsec_a__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>investigate complaints and bring civil actions under
AS 44.21.415</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-410__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>involving fraud committed against residents of the state who are 60 years of age or older; in this paragraph, fraud has the meaning given in
AS 44.21.415
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-410__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner of administration may</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-410__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>adopt regulations that the commissioner considers necessary to implement
AS 44.21.400
 44.21.470;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-410__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>report on the operation of the office of public advocacy when requested by the governor or legislature or when required by law;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-410__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>solicit and accept grants of funds from governments and from persons, and allocate or restrict the use of those funds as required by the grantor.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-410__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 28 ch 90 SLA 1991.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-21-415">
            <num>44.21.415</num>
            <heading>Office of elder fraud and assistance.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-21-415__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The office of elder fraud and assistance is established in the office of public advocacy to investigate complaints involving fraud committed against older Alaskans who are not otherwise able to bring a complaint without assistance, as defined in regulation, and to provide assistance to older Alaskans who are victims of fraud. The office shall work with local, state, and national law enforcement and social service agencies through cooperative agreements and may bring civil enforcement actions for injunctive and other relief for fraud committed against older Alaskans.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-415__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In conducting an investigation under this section, the office of elder fraud and assistance may issue subpoenas, conduct interviews, and examine the business records, advances, transactions, and relevant records associated with the alleged fraud committed against an older Alaskan. The office may enter into contracts with attorneys and seek a court order to enforce a subpoena.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-415__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to the functions described under (a) and (b) of this section, the office of elder fraud and assistance shall provide information, referrals, and other assistance to older Alaskans who are victims of fraud and make recommendations to the commissioner for regulations on eligibility for assistance needed to implement this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-415__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A cooperative agreement under (a) of this section must include a description of office operations and investigation protocols.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-415__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subject to the discretion of the court and standards established in regulation adopted by the commissioner of administration and taking into consideration the financial condition of the parties to a civil suit brought under this section, the office of public advocacy may seek recovery of all or part of litigation costs and fees from any party, including costs incurred during the investigation of the case, when the office of public advocacy is found to be a prevailing party after trial or settlement negotiation. The office of public advocacy shall enter into a fee agreement with a client that is consistent with this section, the Alaska Rules of Court, and the Alaska Rules of Professional Conduct.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-415__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing in this section prohibits the Department of Law from investigating or prosecuting a person for unfair methods of competition and unfair or deceptive acts or practices in the conduct of trade or commerce under
AS 45.50.471
and 45.50.495.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-415__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-415__subsec_g__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>fraud means
(A) robbery, extortion, and coercion under
AS 11.41.500
 11.41.530;
(B) offenses against property under
AS 11.46.100
 11.46.740; or
(C) exploitation of another person or another person's resources for personal profit or advantage with no significant benefit accruing to the person who is exploited;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-21-415__subsec_g__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>older Alaskan means a person residing in the state who is 60 years of age or older.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-21-420">
            <num>44.21.420</num>
            <heading>Employment of office personnel.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-21-420__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner of administration may employ guardians ad litem, public guardians, clerical staff, and other assistants that the commissioner determines are needed to perform the duties set out in
AS 44.21.410
.  Employees under this subsection are in the classified service under
AS 39.25.100
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-420__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner of administration may employ attorneys needed to perform the duties set out in
AS 44.21.410
. Attorneys employed by the commissioner of administration in the office of public advocacy are in the partially exempt service under
AS 39.25.120
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-420__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner may contract with attorneys to provide legal representation, and with other persons to provide guardian ad litem services, as needed to perform the duties set out in
AS 44.21.410
. The commissioner may determine the rate of compensation for contractual services, taking into account the time involved, the skill and experience required, and other pertinent factors.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-21-430">
            <num>44.21.430</num>
            <heading>Attorneys engaged by public advocacy office.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-21-430__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Only an attorney admitted to the practice of law in this state may be retained under contract by the office of public advocacy to provide legal representation. A person is not eligible to be an attorney employed by the office unless admitted to the practice of law in this state no later than 10 months following the commencement of the person's employment by the office.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-430__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An attorney employed by the office of public advocacy may not engage in the private practice of law unless the attorney provides services to the office as an independent contractor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-21-440">
            <num>44.21.440</num>
            <heading>Conflicts of interests.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-21-440__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Services and legal representation rendered by the office of public advocacy, whether performed by a person under contract or by an employee of the office, shall be provided in a manner that avoids conflicts of interests.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-440__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The office of public advocacy may not use improper pressure to influence the professional judgment of a person who is paid by the office of public advocacy to act as an attorney or a guardian ad litem for a guardianship or conservatorship established under
AS 13.26
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-21-450">
            <num>44.21.450</num>
            <heading>Civil liability of volunteer guardians.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-21-450__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A volunteer guardian ad litem under the supervision of the office of public advocacy is not civilly liable for acts or omissions during the good faith performance of duties as a guardian unless the acts or omissions constitute gross negligence.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-21-450__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This section does not affect the civil liability of the office of public advocacy.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-21-460">
            <num>44.21.460</num>
            <heading>Nonattorney volunteer guardians ad litem.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.21.460.   Nonattorney volunteer guardians ad litem.
A nonattorney volunteer guardian ad litem may not give legal advice or act in the capacity of attorney for a minor before a court or administrative agency.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-21-470">
            <num>44.21.470</num>
            <heading>Definition.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.21.470.   Definition.
In
AS 44.21.410
 44.21.460, volunteer guardian ad litem means a court-appointed special advocate (CASA).</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>