<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-16/chapter-52"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-16/chapter-52"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="16.52"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-16/chapter-52/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-16/chapter-52/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-16/chapter-52/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-16/chapter-52/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_16">
        <num>16</num>
        <heading>Fish and Game</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_16__chp_52">
          <num>52</num>
          <heading>Fishery Industrial Technology Center</heading>
          <section eId="sec_16-52-010">
            <num>16.52.010</num>
            <heading>Fishery Industrial Technology Center.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 16.52.010.   Fishery Industrial Technology Center.
There is established a Fishery Industrial Technology Center as part of the University of Alaska.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-52-020">
            <num>16.52.020</num>
            <heading>Duties.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 16.52.020.   Duties.
The center shall create employment opportunities in the state's fishing industry and other benefits to the state by
(1) providing training opportunities to citizens of the state on the most efficient and appropriate technologies for the harvesting, processing, and conservation of the fishery resources of the state;
(2) providing information and technical assistance on the adaptation of existing and new technologies to the users of the fishery resources of the state;
(3) providing research and development activities to adapt existing technologies to enhance the economic viability of the industry;
(4) providing research and development activities to create new technologies that will enhance the effectiveness of the industry, and provide economic benefits to state citizens; and
(5) encouraging joint projects between industry and government in order to use industrial experience and government programs to enhance the productivity of the industry.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-52-030">
            <num>16.52.030</num>
            <heading>Fishery Industrial Technology Policy Council.</heading>
            <subsection eId="16-52-030__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A Fishery Industrial Technology Policy Council is established to provide program and planning guidance to the center.  The policy council shall be composed of members of the state's fishing and processing industry.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-52-030__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The policy council consists of seven members appointed by the president of the University of Alaska, including</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="16-52-030__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>two members appointed from the seafood processing industry; the members appointed under this paragraph shall be owners or employees of firms that are in operation in the state and, insofar as possible, shall represent diverse processing operations;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-52-030__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>two members who are commercial fishermen; the members appointed under this paragraph shall be actively engaged in commercial fishing in the state and, insofar as possible, shall represent fishing for diverse fisheries resources;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-52-030__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>three public members.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-52-030__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A member of the policy council serves a term of two years.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-52-030__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>At least five members of the policy council shall be residents of the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-52-040">
            <num>16.52.040</num>
            <heading>Location.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 16.52.040.   Location.
The principal activities of the center shall be located in Kodiak, Alaska.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-52-050">
            <num>16.52.050</num>
            <heading>Annual report.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 16.52.050.   Annual report.
The Board of Regents of the University of Alaska shall prepare an annual report of the center's activities and notify the legislature by the 20th day of each regular session that the report is available. The report must include a description of the work conducted by the center, the training sessions held and number of students trained, and any other information that the Board of Regents determines should be included to describe the work of the center.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-52-060">
            <num>16.52.060</num>
            <heading>Cooperation with other agencies.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 16.52.060.   Cooperation with other agencies.
In the development of its programs the center shall consult with
(1) the Department of Fish and Game;
(2) the division of economic development of the Department of Commerce, Community, and Economic Development;
(3) the Department of Natural Resources;
(4) the Alaska Fisheries Development Foundation;
(5) the Alaska Seafood Marketing Institute;
(6) the North Pacific Fishery Management Council;
(7) the National Marine Fisheries Service;
(8) the Department of Education and Early Development; and
(9) the Department of Labor and Workforce Development.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-52-070">
            <num>16.52.070</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 16.52.070.   Definitions.
In this chapter,
(1) center means the Fishery Industrial Technology Center;
(2) policy council means the Fishery Industrial Technology Policy Council.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>