<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-9/chapter-19"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-9/chapter-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="9.19"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-9/chapter-19/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-9/chapter-19/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-9/chapter-19/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-9/chapter-19/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_9">
        <num>9</num>
        <heading>Code of Civil Procedure</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_9__chp_19">
          <num>19</num>
          <heading>Prisoner and Correctional Facility Litigation Against the State</heading>
          <section eId="sec_09-19-010">
            <num>09.19.010</num>
            <heading>Limitation on exemption from filing fees.</heading>
            <subsection eId="09-19-010__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A prisoner may not commence litigation against the state unless the prisoner has paid full filing fees to the court or is a claimant under
AS 23.20
, except that the court may exempt a prisoner from paying part of those fees if the court finds exceptional circumstances as described in this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="09-19-010__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To apply for a filing fee exemption, a prisoner shall submit to the court</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="09-19-010__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an affidavit that clearly discloses that the person is a prisoner and that sets out
(A) the prisoner's complete financial situation, including the prisoner's income, money in financial accounts, assets, and court-ordered payments;
(B) the circumstances that prevent the prisoner from paying full filing fees; and
(C) the nature of the action or appeal and specific facts that would, if proven, state a claim on which relief can be granted or entitle the prisoner to reversal on appeal;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="09-19-010__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a certified copy of the prisoner's account statement from the correctional facility in which the prisoner is being or has been held for the six-month period preceding the submission of the application; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="09-19-010__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>other documentation or financial information as the court may require.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="09-19-010__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Based on the submission under (b) of this section, the court may grant an exemption from part of the applicable filing fees if the court finds that exceptional circumstances prevent the prisoner from paying full filing fees. Imprisonment and indigency do not constitute exceptional circumstances if the prisoner has available income or resources that can be applied to the filing fee.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="09-19-010__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the court orders an exemption under (c) of this section, the court shall determine the amount of the exemption and set a filing fee to be paid by the prisoner. In setting the fee, the court, at a minimum, shall require the prisoner to pay filing fees equal to 20 percent of the larger of the average monthly deposits made to the prisoner's account described in (b)(2) of this section, or the average balance in that account, not to exceed the amount of the full filing fee required under applicable court rules.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="09-19-010__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The court shall mail or otherwise serve its order under (d) of this section on the prisoner. Along with its order, the court shall give written notice that the case or appeal will not be accepted for filing if payment of a filing fee is not made within 30 days after the date of distribution of the order, unless the time for payment is extended by the court. If timely payment is not made, the court may not accept any filing in the case or appeal. If payment is made, the prisoner's filing and supporting documents shall be accepted for filing with the court.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_09-19-020">
            <num>09.19.020</num>
            <heading>Dismissal for material misstatements.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 09.19.020.   Dismissal for material misstatements.
If a prisoner has filed litigation against the state, the court shall dismiss that litigation if the court finds that the pleadings filed by the prisoner or an application filed by the prisoner to obtain an exemption under
AS 09.19.010
contain a material statement made by the prisoner that is not true.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_09-19-030">
            <num>09.19.030</num>
            <heading>Stay in prisoner disciplinary appeals.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 09.19.030.   Stay in prisoner disciplinary appeals.
A superior court that reviews a disciplinary decision of the Department of Corrections as an administrative appeal may not enter an order staying disciplinary sanctions unless the pleadings filed by the prisoner establish by clear and convincing evidence that the prisoner has alleged a violation of a fundamental constitutional right and is likely to succeed on the merits in the appeal, that the prisoner faces irreparable harm if a stay is not granted, that the Department of Corrections can be adequately protected if a stay is granted, and that a stay will not adversely affect the public interest in effective penal administration.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_09-19-040">
            <num>09.19.040</num>
            <heading>Injunctions or orders imposing obligations in prisoner cases.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 09.19.040.   Injunctions or orders imposing obligations in prisoner cases.
In litigation against the state brought by a prisoner, a court may not enter an injunction or issue an order or decision that would impose an obligation on the state or its employees that would exceed the obligations imposed by the United States Constitution, the Constitution of the State of Alaska, and applicable federal and state statutes and regulations, unless the obligation is agreed to by the state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_09-19-050">
            <num>09.19.050</num>
            <heading>Discovery in prisoner cases.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 09.19.050.   Discovery in prisoner cases.
The automatic disclosure provisions of Rule 26, Alaska Rules of Civil Procedure, do not apply to litigation against the state brought by a prisoner.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_09-19-100">
            <num>09.19.100</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 09.19.100.   Definitions.
In this chapter,
(1) litigation against the state means a civil action or an appeal from a civil action or from the final decision of an administrative agency, a petition for review, a petition for hearing, an original application for relief, or another action filed under the Alaska Rules of Appellate Procedure that
(A) involves the state, an officer or agent of the state, or a state employee, or a former officer or agent of the state or state employee, regarding conduct that occurred during that former officer's, agent's, or employee's state employment or agency, whether the officer, agent, or employee is sued in an official or a personal capacity; and
(B) is related to a person's status or treatment as a prisoner, to a criminal charge against or involving the person, or to an alleged violation of the person's constitutional rights;
(2) prisoner has the meaning given in
AS 33.30.901
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_09-19-200">
            <num>09.19.200</num>
            <heading>Correctional facility litigation.</heading>
            <subsection eId="09-19-200__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (b) and (e) of this section, a court may not order prospective relief in a civil action with respect to correctional facility conditions unless the court finds that (1) the plaintiff has proven a violation of a state or federal right, (2) the prospective relief is narrowly drawn and extends no further than is necessary to correct the violation of the right, (3) the prospective relief is the least intrusive means necessary to correct the violation of the right, and (4) the prisoner exhausted all administrative remedies available to the prisoner before filing the civil action. When a court finds multiple violations of a state or federal right, when multiple remedies are ordered by the prospective relief, or when prospective relief applies to multiple correctional facilities, the findings required by this subsection shall be made as to each violation, each remedy, and each facility, as appropriate. In a civil action with respect to correctional facility conditions that has been certified as a class action, prospective relief applicable to the class may only be ordered after the court makes the findings required by this subsection and finds that the violation of a state or federal right is applicable to the entire class. In making the findings required under this subsection, the court shall give substantial weight to any adverse effect on public safety or the operation of a criminal justice system caused by the prospective relief.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="09-19-200__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In a civil action with respect to correctional facility conditions, to the extent otherwise authorized by law, the court may enter a temporary restraining order or an order for preliminary injunctive relief only if the court finds that the relief is (1) narrowly drawn and extends no further than is necessary to correct the harm that requires preliminary relief, and (2) the least intrusive means necessary to correct that harm. In making the findings required under this subsection, the court shall give substantial weight to any adverse effect on public safety or the operation of a criminal justice system caused by the preliminary relief. Preliminary injunctive relief shall automatically expire 90 days after the entry of the order unless the court orders final relief in the civil action before the expiration of the 90-day period.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="09-19-200__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Prospective relief ordered in a civil action with respect to correctional facility conditions, including prospective relief ordered under a consent decree, regardless of whether that civil action was filed or the relief ordered before or after August 30, 1999, shall be terminated upon the motion of the defendant unless the court finds that there exists a current violation of a state or federal right and makes the findings required by (a) of this section as to each current violation and as to each remedy and facility, as appropriate. A civil action that has been certified as a class action shall be terminated upon the motion of the defendant unless the court makes the findings required by this subsection and finds that the current violation of a state or federal right is applicable to the entire class. Prospective relief must be modified upon the motion of a party whenever, and to the extent, the findings required by this section no longer apply to one or more provisions of the prospective relief then in effect. This subsection and the time limits provided in (d) of this section do not prevent a party from seeking modification or termination before the relief is otherwise terminable under this section to the extent that modification or termination would otherwise be legally permissible.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="09-19-200__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A defendant may not file a motion to modify or terminate under (c) of this section until</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="09-19-200__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>two years after the date the court ordered the prospective relief if the order occurred after August 30, 1999;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="09-19-200__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>one year after the date the court entered an order denying modification or termination of prospective relief made under (1) or (3) of this subsection; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="09-19-200__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in the case of an order issued on or before August 30, 1999, one year after August 30, 1999.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="09-19-200__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (a) of this section, in a civil action with respect to correctional facility conditions, a court may order prospective relief as provided in a consent decree without complying with (a) of this section, provided the prospective relief does not continue for a period of more than two years unless the court finds and orders that the continuation of the relief is appropriate under the standards in (c) of this section. In addition, parties may enter into private settlement agreements that do not comply with the limitations of relief set out in (a) of this section if the terms of the agreements are not subject to court enforcement other than the reinstatement of the civil proceedings that the agreements settled.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="09-19-200__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The court shall promptly rule on a motion to modify or terminate prospective relief in a civil action with respect to correctional facility conditions. A motion to modify or terminate prospective relief made under this section stays the order for prospective relief beginning on the 90th day after the motion is filed, and the stay ends on the date the court enters a final order ruling on the motion. An automatic stay under this subsection may be postponed by the court for not more than 30 days for good cause.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="09-19-200__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="09-19-200__subsec_g__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>civil action with respect to correctional facility conditions means a civil proceeding arising under state or federal law with respect to the conditions of confinement or the effects of actions by government officials on the lives of persons confined in correctional facilities;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="09-19-200__subsec_g__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>consent decree means a court order that is based on the agreement of the parties; the term consent decree does not include a private settlement agreement;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="09-19-200__subsec_g__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>prisoner
(A) means a person held in a state correctional facility or under authority of state or municipal law in official detention as defined in
AS 11.81.900</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="09-19-200__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>under
AS 47.12.030
, 47.12.065, or 47.12.100, the minor has been charged, prosecuted, or convicted as an adult; or
(ii) under
AS 47.12.160
(e), the minor has been ordered transferred to the custody of the commissioner of corrections or a municipality;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="09-19-200__subsec_i__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>private settlement agreement means an agreement entered into among the parties that is not subject to judicial enforcement other than the reinstatement of the civil proceeding that the agreement settled;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="09-19-200__subsec_i__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>prospective relief means all relief other than compensatory monetary damages;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="09-19-200__subsec_i__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>relief means any legal or equitable remedy in any form that may be ordered by the court, and includes a consent decree but does not include a private settlement agreement;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="09-19-200__subsec_i__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>state or federal right means a right arising from the United States Constitution, the Constitution of the State of Alaska, or a federal or state statute.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>