<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-3/chapter-22"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-3/chapter-22"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="3.22"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-3/chapter-22/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-3/chapter-22/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-3/chapter-22/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-3/chapter-22/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_3">
        <num>3</num>
        <heading>Agriculture, Animals, and Food</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_3__chp_22">
          <num>22</num>
          <heading>Plant Materials Center</heading>
          <section eId="sec_03-22-010">
            <num>03.22.010</num>
            <heading>Establishment of plant materials center.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 03.22.010.   Establishment of plant materials center.
The Department of Natural Resources, in cooperation with the college or department of the University of Alaska responsible for the Agricultural and Forestry Experiment Station, shall establish and maintain a plant materials center.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_03-22-020">
            <num>03.22.020</num>
            <heading>Purpose of center.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 03.22.020.   Purpose of center.
The objectives of the plant materials center, in cooperation with the college or department of the University of Alaska responsible for the Agricultural and Forestry Experiment Station, are to
(1) assemble, evaluate, select, and increase plant materials needed in soil and water conservation, agriculture, and industry, and maintain genetic purity of these materials;
(2) increase promising plant materials for field scale testing;
(3) test the promising materials in field plantings on sites that represent soil and climatic conditions not found at the center;
(4) maintain and provide for increase of basic seed stocks of plant materials for agricultural and conservation interests;
(5) make seed and plant materials available, for a fee if necessary, in such a manner as to avoid monopolistic control of basic stocks of these materials and encourage the development of a seed industry, noncommercial transfer of seed, and community seed libraries established under
AS 03.20.120
;
(6) support but not duplicate activities carried on by state or federally funded research programs in the state;
(7) prepare, publish, and disseminate a summary report on all studies as they are completed.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_03-22-030">
            <num>03.22.030</num>
            <heading>Center site, buildings, and equipment.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 03.22.030.   Center site, buildings, and equipment.
The department shall obtain a site, either by donation, lease, or purchase, and erect suitable buildings on the site, if they are needed for the use of the plant materials center.  The department shall also acquire the agricultural land, scientific instruments, and equipment necessary to carry on the work of the center.  Acquisition of scientific instruments and equipment under this section is governed by
AS 36.30
(State Procurement Code).</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_03-22-040">
            <num>03.22.040</num>
            <heading>Personnel.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 03.22.040.   Personnel.
The department shall ensure that competent professional, secretarial, and subprofessional personnel necessary to carry on the work of the center are employed. The administrator of the plant materials center is a joint appointment between the Department of Natural Resources and the college or department of the University of Alaska responsible for the Agricultural and Forestry Experiment Station.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_03-22-050">
            <num>03.22.050</num>
            <heading>Department to cooperate.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 03.22.050.   Department to cooperate.
The department shall cooperate with the college or department of the University of Alaska responsible for the Agricultural and Forestry Experiment Station and the United States Department of Agriculture, Natural Resources Conservation Service, by a formal memorandum of understanding and may cooperate with any department or agency of federal, state, or local government, research organization, or other organization concerned with conservation or agriculture.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_03-22-060">
            <num>03.22.060</num>
            <heading>Reports.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 03.22.060.   Reports.
The department shall annually prepare a detailed report of the operation of the center and notify the legislature that the report is available. The report must include a statement of all receipts and disbursements.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_03-22-070">
            <num>03.22.070</num>
            <heading>Acceptance of assistance.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 03.22.070.   Acceptance of assistance.
The department may request, accept, and receive from federal, state, and nongovernment sources financial and other aid and assistance, including personnel and equipment, for the construction, equipment, maintenance, and operation of the center.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_03-22-080">
            <num>03.22.080</num>
            <heading>Payments and vouchers.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 03.22.080.   Payments and vouchers.
Appropriations made by the state for the construction, maintenance, and operation of the center shall be expended upon vouchers approved by the department in the manner prescribed by it.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>