<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-24/chapter-20"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-24/chapter-20"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="24.20"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-24/chapter-20/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-24/chapter-20/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-24/chapter-20/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-24/chapter-20/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_24">
        <num>24</num>
        <heading>Legislature and Lobbying</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_24__chp_20">
          <num>20</num>
          <heading>Agencies and Permanent Committees</heading>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-010">
            <num>24.20.010</num>
            <heading>Legislative council established.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 24.20.010.   Legislative council established.
The Alaska Legislative Council is established as a permanent interim committee and service agency of the legislature.  The establishment of the council recognizes the need of the legislature for full-time technical assistance in accomplishing the research, reporting, bill drafting, and examination and revision of statutes, and general administrative services essential to the development of sound legislation in the public interest.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-020">
            <num>24.20.020</num>
            <heading>Membership.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 24.20.020.   Membership.
The legislative council is composed of the president of the senate and six other senators appointed by the president, and the speaker of the house of representatives and six other representatives appointed by the speaker.  The membership from each house shall include at least one member from each of the two major political parties.  The appointing authority in each house shall make and announce the appointment or reappointment of members of the council within 15 days after the convening of the first regular session of each legislature.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-030">
            <num>24.20.030</num>
            <heading>Term of membership.</heading>
            <subsection eId="24-20-030__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Members serve for the duration of the legislature during which they are appointed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="24-20-030__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When a member of the council files a declaration of candidacy for an elective office other than that of member of either house of the legislature, and the member has not resigned from membership on the council, the member's council membership terminates on the date of filing.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-040">
            <num>24.20.040</num>
            <heading>Vacancies.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 24.20.040.   Vacancies.
When a vacancy occurs in the statutory or appointive membership of the council, the presiding officer of the house incurring the vacancy shall fill the vacancy within 30 days. If the office of the president of the senate or speaker of the house of representatives becomes vacant and a vacancy occurs among the appointed members of the council, the remaining council members from the house incurring the vacancy shall appoint a new member.  A legislator appointed to fill a vacancy shall be a member of the same political party as the member vacating the seat, when possible.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-050">
            <num>24.20.050</num>
            <heading>Executive director and staff.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 24.20.050.   Executive director and staff.
The council hires an executive director and determines the director's salary. The executive director shall serve as the executive officer for the council in the accomplishment of its functions through the Legislative Affairs Agency.  The executive director serves at the direction and at the pleasure of the council.  The executive director is authorized to employ and determine the compensation of the members of the professional and clerical staffs of the agency within the limitation of the budget approved by the council.  The executive director and the members of the professional staff shall maintain the integrity of the council's functions and services on behalf of the legislative branch by refraining from joining or supporting any partisan political organization, faction, or activity that would tend to undermine the essential nonpartisan nature of their functions and services. However, this section does not restrict the executive director or members of the professional staff from expressing private opinion, registering, or voting.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-055">
            <num>24.20.055</num>
            <heading>Information systems.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 24.20.055.   Information systems.
The executive director of the Legislative Affairs Agency shall establish information systems guidelines and prepare a short-range and long-range information systems plan for the legislative branch. The guidelines and plan must be adapted to the special needs of the legislative branch as determined by the Alaska Legislative Council and, when it is in the agency's best interest, consistent with the telecommunications information guidelines and plan adopted by the commissioner of administration under
AS 44.21.350
 44.21.390.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-060">
            <num>24.20.060</num>
            <heading>Powers.</heading>
            <subsection eId="24-20-060__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>if the exercise involves the rent or lease of facilities, and to
AS 36.30.085
if the exercise involves the acquisition of facilities by lease-purchase or lease-financing agreement;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-060__subsec_c__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to produce, publish, distribute, and to contract for the printing of reports, memoranda, and other materials it finds necessary to the accomplishment of its work;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-060__subsec_c__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to take appropriate action for the preconvening and post-session work of each legislative session including the employment one week in advance of each session of not more than 10 temporary legislative employees; the continuing employment of the temporary legislative employees is subject to legislative approval when the session convenes;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-060__subsec_c__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to establish a legislative internship program on a cooperative basis with the University of Alaska that will provide for the assignment of interns to standing committees of each house of the legislature during regular sessions of the legislature; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-060__subsec_c__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to establish reasonable fees for services and materials provided by the Legislative Affairs Agency to entities outside of the legislative branch of state government and charges for collecting the fees; all fees and charges collected under this paragraph shall be deposited into the general fund.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-061">
            <num>24.20.061</num>
            <heading>Administrative services for legislature.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 24.20.061.   Administrative services for legislature.
All administrative services necessary to the operation of the legislature during and between sessions are provided by the legislative council.  These services include procurement, storage, and maintenance of all supplies and equipment; interim control of legislative space; fiscal and personnel services except for the legislative budget and audit committee; supervision of duplicating, distributing, and mailing services; and budget preparation.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-062">
            <num>24.20.062</num>
            <heading>Legislative internship program.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 24.20.062.   Legislative internship program.
A legislative internship program established by the legislative council under
AS 24.20.060
(8) shall provide that
(1) the University of Alaska provide academic support and credit to the program;
(2) students enrolled and in good standing at any accredited postsecondary educational institution who have successfully completed at least two years of study are eligible to participate in the program;
(3) interns will be selected by a committee composed of members of the legislature appointed by the legislative council and representatives of the university appointed by the university;
(4) interns will be selected on the basis of their experience and interest in subjects which the legislative council feels are likely to be considered during a legislative session;
(5) legislative interns are entitled to receive academic credit and payment of $30 for each day of participation in the program during the legislative session.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-065">
            <num>24.20.065</num>
            <heading>Examination of regulations and opinions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="24-20-065__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The legislative council shall annually examine administrative regulations, published opinions of state and federal courts and of the Department of Law, and final decisions adopted under
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act) that rely on state statutes or the common law of the state to determine if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-065__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the courts and agencies are properly implementing legislative purposes;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-065__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>there are court or agency expressions of dissatisfaction with state statutes or the common law of the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-065__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the opinions, decisions, or regulations indicate unclear or ambiguous statutes;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-065__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the courts have modified or revised the common law of the state.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="24-20-065__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The legislative council shall prepare a comprehensive report of the annual examination with recommendations and, at the start of each regular session, notify the legislature that the report is available.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-070">
            <num>24.20.070</num>
            <heading>Revision of statutes.</heading>
            <subsection eId="24-20-070__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The legislature may direct the council to revise the laws of the state in the form of a bulk formal revision.  At the direction of the legislature and within the limit of appropriations made, the council may enter into contracts for the printing, annotating, indexing, and distribution of a revision of the laws of the state.  The council receives sufficient copies of a revision for exchange with other states and jurisdictions.  A revision prepared by the council under authority of this section shall be referred to the legislature for enactment or adoption.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="24-20-070__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Statute revision is a continuing responsibility of the council.  The general and permanent acts of each regular and special session of the legislature shall be integrated with and published as annual supplements to or replacement pamphlets for the Alaska Statutes.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-080">
            <num>24.20.080</num>
            <heading>Intergovernmental cooperation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 24.20.080.   Intergovernmental cooperation.
The council may encourage and arrange conferences with officials of other states and nations and of other units of government and propose cooperation between this state and other states and nations. The council constitutes the Alaska Commission on Interstate Cooperation in participating in and carrying out the programs of the Council of State Governments as they apply to Alaska. The chairman of the council serves as chairman of the commission.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-090">
            <num>24.20.090</num>
            <heading>Assignment of projects.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 24.20.090.   Assignment of projects.
The council may be assigned projects or subjects for study, reporting, or drafting. Assignment shall be by resolution. The council may determine a schedule of priorities for these and other assignments or requests based on feasibility, time, and the availability of funds and staff.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-100">
            <num>24.20.100</num>
            <heading>Research and drafting services for legislators.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 24.20.100.   Research and drafting services for legislators.
Members of the legislature may utilize the research and bill drafting services of the Legislative Affairs Agency. Requests by members of the legislature are confidential. Staff services for members of the legislature shall be accomplished subject only to the priority of assignments determined by the council.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-105">
            <num>24.20.105</num>
            <heading>Review of proposed regulations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 24.20.105.   Review of proposed regulations.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-105">
            <num>24.20.105</num>
            <heading>Review of proposed regulations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 24.20.105.   Review of proposed regulations.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-110">
            <num>24.20.110</num>
            <heading>Meetings.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 24.20.110.   Meetings.
The legislative council may meet during sessions of the legislature and during intervals between sessions at such times and places inside the state as the chairman may determine. The council shall meet immediately after the appointment of its membership at the first regular session of each legislature for purposes of organization. Minutes of each meeting shall be kept. One-half of the membership constitutes a quorum to do business. Members may receive, for the minimum time required to get to and from meetings and while attending meetings, the same travel fare and per diem allowances provided by law for members of the legislature when attending sessions.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-120">
            <num>24.20.120</num>
            <heading>Reports.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 24.20.120.   Reports.
The council shall prepare a summary report of its findings and recommendations for each legislature and notify the legislature that the report is available. The council shall, from time to time, submit memorandum reports to the legislature on matters referred to it or coming before it. Bills supporting council recommendations may be filed or prefiled in accordance with the uniform rules of the legislature. Reports released by the council are public and may be made available at a reasonable cost.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-130">
            <num>24.20.130</num>
            <heading>Budgets.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 24.20.130.   Budgets.
The council shall submit a budget of its anticipated needs for each fiscal year to the finance committees of the legislature. The executive director shall annually submit an estimated budget to the governor for information purposes in the preparation of the executive budget. The council staff shall also assist, as needed, in preparing a budget of the anticipated annual needs of the legislature.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-132">
            <num>24.20.132</num>
            <heading>Legislative budget and expenses.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 24.20.132.   Legislative budget and expenses.
The estimate of operating expenses for the legislature shall be included in the annual budget submitted by the legislative council.  A summary total by major item shall be submitted by the council to the governor for information purposes in the preparation of the executive budget.  A detailed budget document shall be submitted to the house and senate finance committees. All disbursements from legislative appropriations shall be certified by the bonded certifying officer designated by the council.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-140">
            <num>24.20.140</num>
            <heading>Appropriations.</heading>
            <subsection eId="24-20-140__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Appropriations for carrying out
AS 24.20.010
 24.20.140 shall be set out in the appropriation bill authorizing operating expenditures submitted to the legislature under
AS 37.07.020
(a)(2) or other bills as may be necessary. The council may direct the executive director to transfer amounts from one appropriation to another if the transfer is considered necessary to accomplish the work of the council. The council may not exceed the total amount of the authorized appropriation. All expenditures of the council are subject to an independent audit that shall be made annually.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="24-20-140__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to transfers under (a) of this section, the council may direct the executive director to transfer amounts from any appropriation to an office, agency, or committee in the legislative branch to an appropriation for another office, agency, or committee in the legislative branch. A transfer under this subsection may only be made with the written approval of the head of the legislative office or agency or the chair of the committee to which the appropriation was originally made, and the amount transferred from that appropriation may not exceed the amount indicated in the written approval.
Article 2. Legislative Budget and Audit Committee.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-151">
            <num>24.20.151</num>
            <heading>Legislative Budget and Audit Committee established.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 24.20.151.   Legislative Budget and Audit Committee established.
The Legislative Budget and Audit Committee is established as a permanent interim committee of the legislature. The establishment of the committee recognizes the need of the legislature for full-time technical assistance in accomplishing the fiscal analysis, budget review, and post-audit functions.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-156">
            <num>24.20.156</num>
            <heading>Purposes.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 24.20.156.   Purposes.
The purposes of the Legislative Budget and Audit Committee include
(1) monitoring and reporting
(A) the performance of the agencies of the state that perform lending or investment functions;
(B) the extent to which the performance of these agencies has contributed to the fiscal, financial, economic, and social improvement of the state and its citizens;
(C) the extent to which these agencies and the executive have prepared and coordinated short-term and long-term economic, fiscal, investment, and financial planning;
(2) holding these agencies accountable to statutory intent in their performance by recommending, where appropriate, changes in policy to the agencies or changes in legislation to the legislature;
(3) annually reviewing the extent of capitalization of the investment funds of the state and alternative investment policy for the general fund surplus and recommending needed legislation.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-161">
            <num>24.20.161</num>
            <heading>Membership.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 24.20.161.   Membership.
The Legislative Budget and Audit Committee is composed of 10 members: the chairmen of the senate and house finance committees; one member selected from each of the senate and house finance committees and appointed by the president of the senate and the speaker of the house, respectively; and three members appointed from each house by the respective presiding officer.  The chairman of the finance committee may choose not to serve on the committee.  If this occurs, the presiding officer of the appropriate house shall appoint a replacement from the finance committee.  The membership from each house shall include at least one member from each of the two major political parties.  The committee shall select its own chairman.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-165">
            <num>24.20.165</num>
            <heading>Alternate members.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 24.20.165.   Alternate members.
The Legislative Budget and Audit Committee shall have two alternate members in addition to the members designated in
AS 24.20.161
.  The president of the senate shall appoint one alternate member from the senate finance committee and the speaker of the house shall appoint one alternate member from the house finance committee.  The alternate members shall serve on the committee when a meeting of the committee has been called and the chairman determines that there will not be enough members in attendance at the meeting to provide a quorum.  While serving as alternates, the alternate members have the same duties and responsibilities as committee members appointed under
AS 24.20.161
, and they are entitled to the same travel and per diem allowances.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-171">
            <num>24.20.171</num>
            <heading>Organization of committee; term of membership.</heading>
            <subsection eId="24-20-171__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The committee shall be organized within 10 days after the organization of each legislature. Members serve for the duration of the legislature during which they are appointed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="24-20-171__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When a member of the committee files a declaration of candidacy for an elective office other than that of member of either house of the legislature, and the member has not resigned from membership on the committee, the member's committee membership terminates on the date of filing.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-181">
            <num>24.20.181</num>
            <heading>Vacancies.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 24.20.181.   Vacancies.
When a vacancy occurs in the statutory or appointive membership of the committee, the presiding officer of the house incurring the vacancy shall choose a successor.  If the office of the president of the senate or speaker of the house of representatives becomes vacant and a vacancy from the affected house occurs among the membership of the committee, the remaining committee members from the house incurring the vacancy shall appoint a new member.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-191">
            <num>24.20.191</num>
            <heading>Meetings.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 24.20.191.   Meetings.
The budget and audit committee may meet during sessions of the legislature and during the interim between sessions at such times and places in the state as the chairman may determine. Members may receive, for the minimum time required to get to and from meetings and for the period while attending meetings, the same travel and per diem allowances provided by law for members of the legislature when attending sessions, except that members of the committee receive no per diem during legislative sessions other than the per diem allowance paid to other members of the legislature.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-201">
            <num>24.20.201</num>
            <heading>Powers.</heading>
            <subsection eId="24-20-201__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Legislative Budget and Audit Committee has the power to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-201__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>organize, adopt rules for the conduct of its business, and prescribe procedures for the comprehensive fiscal analysis, budget review, and post-audit functions;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-201__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>hold public hearings, administer oaths, issue subpoenas, compel the attendance of witnesses and production of papers, books, accounts, documents, and testimony, and have the deposition of witnesses taken in a manner prescribed by court rule or law for taking depositions in civil actions;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-201__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>require all state officials and agencies of state government to give full cooperation to the committee or its staff in assembling and furnishing requested information;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-201__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>review revenue projections, state agency appropriation requests, the expenditure of state funds, including the relationship between state agency program accomplishments and legislative intent, and the fiscal policies and procedures of state government;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-201__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>review and approve proposed changes to agency authorized budgets as provided in
AS 37.07
(Executive Budget Act);</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-201__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>make recommendations concerning appropriations, their expenditure, and the fiscal policies and procedures of state government to the governor when appropriate, and to the legislature;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-201__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>prepare and distribute reports, memoranda, or other necessary materials;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-201__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>sue in the name of the legislature during the interim between sessions if authorized by majority vote of the full membership of the committee;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-201__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>[Repealed, § 7 ch 67 SLA 2003.]</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-201__subsec_a__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>make recommendations to the legislature and to agencies of the state that perform lending or investment functions concerning the structure and operating practices of the agencies;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-201__subsec_a__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>enter into and enforce all contracts necessary or desirable for the functions of the committee;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-201__subsec_a__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide for annual post audits of the Alaska Housing Finance Corporation, the Alaska Aerospace Corporation, and the Alaska Industrial Development and Export Authority.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="24-20-201__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing in this chapter authorizes the referral by the presiding officer of legislation to the committee at regular or special sessions of the legislature.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="24-20-201__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Legislative Budget and Audit Committee may delegate the powers authorized by (a)(2) of this section to the legislative fiscal analyst and the legislative auditor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-206">
            <num>24.20.206</num>
            <heading>Duties.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 24.20.206.   Duties.
The Legislative Budget and Audit Committee shall
(1) annually review the long-range operating plans of all agencies of the state that perform lending or investment functions;
(2) review periodic reports from all agencies of the state that perform lending or investment functions;
(3) prepare a complete report of investment programs, plans, performance, and policies of all agencies of the state that perform lending or investment functions and notify the legislature on or before the first day of each regular session that the report is available;
(4) in conjunction with the finance committee of each house, recommend annually to the legislature the investment policy for the general fund surplus and for the income from the permanent fund;
(5) provide for an annual post audit and annual operational and performance evaluation of the Alaska Permanent Fund Corporation investments and investment programs;
(6) provide for an annual operational and performance evaluation of the Alaska Housing Finance Corporation and the Alaska Industrial Development and Export Authority; the performance evaluation must include, but is not limited to, a comparison of the effect on various sectors of the economy by public and private lending, the effect on resident and nonresident employment, the effect on real wages, and the effect on state and local operating and capital budgets of the programs of the Alaska Housing Finance Corporation and the Alaska Industrial Development and Export Authority;
(7) provide assistance to the trustees of the trust established in
AS 37.14.400
 37.14.450 in carrying out their duties under
AS 37.14.415
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-209">
            <num>24.20.209</num>
            <heading>Records.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 24.20.209.   Records.
The Legislative Budget and Audit Committee shall keep a complete file of all reports presented to it and all reports presented by it to the legislature or to a legislative committee.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-211">
            <num>24.20.211</num>
            <heading>Legislative finance division.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 24.20.211.   Legislative finance division.
The legislative finance division is established as a permanent staff agency responsible to the Legislative Budget and Audit Committee for performance of fiscal analysis and budget review functions.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-221">
            <num>24.20.221</num>
            <heading>Staff.</heading>
            <subsection eId="24-20-221__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The committee shall hire and determine the salary of the legislative fiscal analyst who shall serve both at the direction and pleasure of the committee.  The fiscal analyst shall serve as head of the finance division and, within the limits of the budget approved by the committee, shall employ and determine the compensation of the professional and clerical staff of the division.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="24-20-221__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The fiscal analyst and members of the professional and clerical staff may not join or support a partisan political organization.  This prohibition does not prevent the fiscal analyst or members of the staff from joining social organizations, expressing private opinion, registering as to party, or voting.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-231">
            <num>24.20.231</num>
            <heading>Duties.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 24.20.231.   Duties.
The legislative finance division shall
(1) analyze the budget and appropriation requests of each department, institution, bureau, board, commission, or other agency of state government;
(2) analyze the revenue requirements of the state;
(3) provide the finance committees of the legislature with comprehensive budget review and fiscal analysis services;
(4) cooperate with the office of management and budget in establishing a comprehensive system for state budgeting and financial management as set out in
AS 37.07
(Executive Budget Act);
(5) complete studies and prepare reports, memoranda, or other materials as directed by the Legislative Budget and Audit Committee;
(6) with the governor's permission, designate the legislative fiscal analyst to serve ex officio on the governor's budget review committee;
(7) not later than the first legislative day of each first regular session of each legislature,
(A) conduct a review in accordance with
AS 24.20.235
of the report provided to the division under
AS 43.05.095
; and
(B) conduct a review of inactive state accounts and funds, make recommendations regarding which inactive state accounts and funds, if any, should be repealed, and submit an electronic report of the division's recommendations to the governor, the president of the senate, the speaker of the house of representatives, the chair of the finance committee of each house of the legislature, the senate secretary, and the chief clerk of the house of representatives, and notify the legislature that the report is available.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-235">
            <num>24.20.235</num>
            <heading>Indirect expenditure report.</heading>
            <subsection eId="24-20-235__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Every two years, the legislative finance division shall deliver to the chair of the finance committee in each house of the legislature a report analyzing the indirect expenditure report created under
AS 43.05.095
for the appropriate agencies listed in this subsection. The first review shall occur in the calendar year set out after each agency's name, as follows, and subsequent reviews of each agency shall occur every six years:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-235__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Department of Commerce, Community, and Economic Development, 2015;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-235__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Department of Fish and Game, 2015;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-235__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Department of Health, 2027;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-235__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Department of Labor and Workforce Development, 2015;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-235__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Department of Revenue, 2015;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-235__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Alaska Court System, 2017;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-235__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Department of Administration, 2017;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-235__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Department of Education and Early Development, 2017;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-235__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Department of Environmental Conservation, 2017;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-235__subsec_a__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Department of Natural Resources, 2017;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-235__subsec_a__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Department of Transportation and Public Facilities, 2017;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-235__subsec_a__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Department of Family and Community Services, 2027;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-235__subsec_a__subsec_13">
                <num>(13)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>all remaining agencies, 2019.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="24-20-235__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The report prepared under this section must provide</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-235__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an estimate of the revenue foregone by the state because of the indirect expenditure;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-235__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an estimate of the monetary benefit of the indirect expenditure to the recipients of the benefit of the indirect expenditure;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-235__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a determination of whether the legislative intent of the indirect expenditure is being met and, if necessary, a determination of why the legislative intent of the indirect expenditure is not being met;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-235__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a recommendation as to whether each indirect expenditure should be continued, modified, or terminated, a basis for the recommendation, and the expected effect on the economy of the state if the recommendation is executed; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-235__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an explanation of the methodology and assumptions used in preparing the report.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-241">
            <num>24.20.241</num>
            <heading>Legislative audit division.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 24.20.241.   Legislative audit division.
The legislative audit division is established as a permanent staff agency responsible to the Legislative Budget and Audit Committee for completion of the post-audit function.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-251">
            <num>24.20.251</num>
            <heading>Qualifications and appointment of legislative auditor.</heading>
            <subsection eId="24-20-251__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The legislative auditor shall be a certified public accountant of this state, or of another state having requirements equivalent to those of this state, with at least five years of practice in the profession, or the equivalent, before the appointment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="24-20-251__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Legislative Budget and Audit Committee shall examine persons to serve as legislative auditor and, upon completion of the examination, place the name of the person selected in nomination before the legislature.  If the legislature is not in session, the person nominated shall carry out the duties of the office until the next session of the legislature at which time the name of the person nominated shall be presented to the legislature for appointment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="24-20-251__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The legislative auditor serves at the pleasure of the legislature.  However, when the legislature is not in session, the auditor may be removed for cause by a majority vote of the Legislative Budget and Audit Committee after notice by, and a hearing before, the committee.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-261">
            <num>24.20.261</num>
            <heading>Staff.</heading>
            <subsection eId="24-20-261__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The legislative auditor shall serve as head of the audit division and, within the limits of the budget approved by the committee, shall employ and determine the compensation of the professional and clerical staff of the division.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="24-20-261__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The auditor and members of the professional and clerical staff may not join or support any partisan political organization. This prohibition does not prevent the auditor or members of the staff from joining social organizations, expressing private opinion, registering as to party, or voting.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-271">
            <num>24.20.271</num>
            <heading>Powers and duties.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 24.20.271.   Powers and duties.
The legislative audit division shall
(1) conduct a performance post-audit of boards and commissions designated in
AS 44.66.010
and make the audit, together with a written report, available to the legislature not later than the first day of the regular session of the legislature convening in each year set out with reference to boards and commissions whose activities are subject to termination as prescribed in
AS 44.66
; the division shall notify the legislature that the audit and report are available;
(2) [Repealed, § 11 ch 19 SLA 2013.]
(3) audit at least once every three years the books and accounts of all custodians of public funds and all disbursing officers of the state;
(4) at the direction of the Legislative Budget and Audit Committee, conduct performance post-audits on any agency of state government;
(5) cooperate with state agencies by offering advice and assistance as requested in establishing or improving the accounting systems used by state agencies;
(6) require the assistance and cooperation of all state officials and other state employees in the inspection, examination, and audit of state agency books and accounts;
(7) have access at all times to the books, accounts, reports, or other records, whether confidential or not, of every state agency;
(8) ascertain, as necessary for audit verification, the amount of agency funds on deposit in any bank as shown on the books of the bank; no bank may be held liable for making information required under this paragraph available to the legislative audit division;
(9) complete studies and prepare reports, memoranda, or other materials as directed by the Legislative Budget and Audit Committee;
(10) have direct access to any information related to the management of the University of Alaska and have the same right of access as exists with respect to every other state agency;
(11) [Repealed, § 2 ch 25 SLA 2022.]
(12) [Repealed, § 7 ch. 35 SLA 2015.]</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-281">
            <num>24.20.281</num>
            <heading>Special audit.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 24.20.281.   Special audit.
A member of the legislature may, in writing and with at least six days notice, request that the budget and audit committee direct a special audit of any state agency or determine the propriety of any expenditure of state funds received by any political subdivision or other entity obtaining state funds. Should a majority of the committee vote to approve the request, the legislative audit division shall make the audit.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-291">
            <num>24.20.291</num>
            <heading>Conflict of interest.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 24.20.291.   Conflict of interest.
The legislative auditor, the supervisor of audit, the legislative fiscal analyst, and members of the staff of the legislative finance and audit divisions may not serve in ex officio or other capacity on any board, except as authorized in
AS 24.20.231
(6), commission or other administrative agency of state government; nor may they have a financial interest in transactions involving any agency of state government.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-301">
            <num>24.20.301</num>
            <heading>Records.</heading>
            <subsection eId="24-20-301__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The legislative audit division shall keep a complete file of all audit reports, performance review reports, and other reports or releases issued by the division, and a complete file of audit work papers, performance review work papers, and other related supportive material. The division shall also keep a complete and accurate record of all fiscal transactions involving the division. Audit records and performance review records are confidential, and audit reports and performance review reports are confidential unless the report has been approved for release under
AS 24.20.311
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="24-20-301__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The legislative finance division shall keep a complete file of all budget reports and other reports or releases issued by the division and a complete and accurate record of all fiscal transactions involving the division.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-311">
            <num>24.20.311</num>
            <heading>Reports.</heading>
            <subsection eId="24-20-311__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The committee shall file copies of its approved audit reports including any committee recommendations with the governor, the agency concerned, and the legislature. An annual report summarizing the audit reports and committee recommendations made during the year shall be filed with the governor and with the legislature on or before the first day of each regular session of the legislature. Reports shall be approved by a majority of the committee before their release and shall be open to public inspection after their release to the legislature.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="24-20-311__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 11 ch. 19 SLA 2013.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-650">
            <num>24.20.650</num>
            <heading>Joint Armed Services Committee established.</heading>
            <subsection eId="24-20-650__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Joint Armed Services Committee is established as a permanent interim committee of the legislature.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="24-20-650__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The committee is composed of</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-650__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>five members of the senate, at least one of whom is a member of the minority, appointed by the president of the senate;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-650__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>five members of the house of representatives, at least one of whom is a member of the minority, appointed by the speaker of the house of representatives;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-650__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a state resident, other than a member of the state legislature, who is appointed jointly by the president of the senate and the speaker of the house of representatives after considering the recommendations of the Alaska chapters of each of the following organizations:
(A) the Association of the United States Army;
(B) the Air and Space Forces Association;
(C) the Navy League of the United States;
(D) the Marine Corps Association;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-650__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a state resident, other than a member of the state legislature, who is appointed jointly by the president of the senate and the speaker of the house of representatives after considering the recommendation of the Seventeenth Coast Guard District Auxiliary;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-650__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a state resident, other than a member of the state legislature, who is appointed jointly by the president of the senate and the speaker of the house of representatives after considering the recommendation of the mayor of the Municipality of Anchorage;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-650__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a state resident, other than a member of the state legislature, who is appointed jointly by the president of the senate and the speaker of the house of representatives after considering the recommendation of the mayor of the Fairbanks North Star Borough;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-650__subsec_b__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a state resident, other than a member of the state legislature, who is appointed jointly by the president of the senate and the speaker of the house of representatives after considering the recommendation of the adjutant general of the Department of Military and Veterans' Affairs; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-650__subsec_b__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a state resident, other than a member of the state legislature, who is appointed jointly by the president of the senate and the speaker of the house of representatives after considering the joint recommendations of the Alaska Federation of Natives and the Alaska Municipal League.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-655">
            <num>24.20.655</num>
            <heading>Terms of office; vacancies.</heading>
            <subsection eId="24-20-655__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each legislative member serves for the duration of the legislature during which the member is appointed. Each public member serves for three years. An individual who has served on the committee may be reappointed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="24-20-655__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A legislator ceases to be a member of the Joint Armed Services Committee if the legislator ceases to be a member of the house from which the legislator was appointed. When a seat on the committee becomes vacant, it shall be filled within 30 days in the manner of the original appointment. An individual appointed to fill a vacancy serves for the remainder of the term to which appointed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-660">
            <num>24.20.660</num>
            <heading>Travel and per diem allowances.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 24.20.660.   Travel and per diem allowances.
Members of the Joint Armed Services Committee are entitled to reimbursement for travel expenses. Members of the committee shall receive per diem allowances in accordance with the policy adopted by the legislative council under
AS 24.10.130
(c).</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-665">
            <num>24.20.665</num>
            <heading>Meetings.</heading>
            <subsection eId="24-20-665__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Eight members of the Joint Armed Services Committee constitute a quorum.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="24-20-665__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The committee members shall select one member from the senate and one member from the house of representatives to serve as co-chairs of the committee.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="24-20-665__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The committee may meet during sessions of the legislature and during intervals between sessions at the times and places the co-chairs may determine. Whenever possible, meetings shall be teleconferenced to reduce travel cost.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-670">
            <num>24.20.670</num>
            <heading>Administration.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 24.20.670.   Administration.
The legislative council shall provide administrative and other services to the Joint Armed Services Committee. Within the limits of the amounts made available to the committee by the legislative council, the committee may make expenditures and enter into contracts to carry out the purposes of
AS 24.20.650
 24.20.675. Contracts must be approved by a majority of the members of the committee and are otherwise subject to procedures adopted by the legislative council under
AS 36.30.020
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_24-20-675">
            <num>24.20.675</num>
            <heading>Powers and duties.</heading>
            <subsection eId="24-20-675__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Joint Armed Services Committee shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-675__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>monitor the military base realignment and closure activities of the federal government for bases in the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-675__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>work on specific realignments and closures proposed by the federal government for bases in the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-675__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>work with the state's congressional delegation regarding federal military base realignments and closings in the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-675__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>attend meetings and hearings related to federal realignments and closures of military bases in the state and provide testimony as necessary;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-675__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>review the effect on the state and its communities of federal realignments and closures of military bases in the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-675__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>monitor the development of the national ballistic missile defense system and work with the congressional delegation of the state, other state and local government organizations, and community groups to advocate and expedite the deployment of the system in this state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-675__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>investigate opportunities to increase joint and combined military training in the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-675__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>advocate the stationing of reconfigured power projection forces at bases located in the state; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="24-20-675__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>prepare and submit a report of its activities to the legislature on the first day of each second regular session.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="24-20-675__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The committee may appoint a citizens' advisory board. Individuals appointed to an advisory board may not receive reimbursement for travel expenses or per diem allowances.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>