<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-28/chapter-01"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-28/chapter-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="28.01"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-28/chapter-01/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-28/chapter-01/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-28/chapter-01/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-28/chapter-01/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_28">
        <num>28</num>
        <heading>Motor Vehicles</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_28__chp_01">
          <num>01</num>
          <heading>Alaska Uniform Traffic Laws Act</heading>
          <section eId="sec_28-01-010">
            <num>28.01.010</num>
            <heading>Provisions uniform throughout state.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-01-010__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The provisions of this title and the regulations adopted under this title are applicable within all municipalities of the state.  A municipality may not enact an ordinance that is inconsistent with the provisions of this title or the regulations adopted under this title.  A municipality may not incorporate into a publication of traffic ordinances a provision of this title or the regulations adopted under this title without specifically identifying the provision or regulation as a state statute or regulation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-01-010__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may adopt by reference all or a part of this title and regulations adopted under this title, and may request and shall receive from the Department of Commerce, Community, and Economic Development and, as appropriate, either the Department of Administration or the Department of Public Safety, assistance in the drafting of model ordinances for adoption by reference. Notwithstanding (a) of this section, a municipality may enact necessary ordinances to meet specific local requirements.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-01-010__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A copy of all traffic ordinances enacted by a municipality shall be forwarded to the commissioner of public safety and specific notice of any inconsistent ordinances shall be given by the municipality when the copy of the ordinances is forwarded. So far as practicable, the section number identifying a particular municipal traffic ordinance must be the same as the section number identifying a corresponding provision of this title or regulations adopted under this title.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-01-010__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality shall erect necessary official traffic control devices on streets and highways within its jurisdiction that as far as practicable conform to the current edition of the Alaska Traffic Manual prepared by the Department of Transportation and Public Facilities. The municipality</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-01-010__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall post a sign indicating that the school is a drug-free school zone at each location in which it has installed a sign identifying the location of a school;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-01-010__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>may post a sign at each recreation and youth center indicating that the center is a drug-free recreation and youth center zone; in this paragraph, recreation or youth center has the meaning given in
AS 11.71.900
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-01-010__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Copies of all traffic ordinances enacted by a municipality shall be incorporated in a manual and made available to the general public.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-01-010__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Regulations adopted pertaining to a matter partially or wholly governed by this title must be mutually consistent and compatible, and must complement each other, as far as practicable. For the purpose of uniformity, the Department of Administration or the Department of Public Safety, whichever is appropriate, shall offer and receive reasonable assistance in the coordination and adoption of these regulations.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-01-010__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Regulations adopted under this title must, as far as practicable, conform to the recommendations of the current edition of the Uniform Vehicle Code adopted by the National Committee on Uniform Traffic Laws and Ordinances.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-01-010__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may issue a citation for a traffic offense only if the citation complies with the provisions of
AS 12.25.175
and 12.25.200.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-01-010__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipal parking citation trial or appeal process and fees charged for it must be substantially similar to the applicable trial or appeal process adopted by the Alaska Supreme Court or imposed by law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-01-010__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A court may not enforce a municipal ordinance prescribing a penalty for driving while under the influence of an alcoholic beverage, inhalant, or controlled substance or refusal to submit to a chemical test unless that ordinance imposes ignition interlock device requirements under this title.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-01-015">
            <num>28.01.015</num>
            <heading>Municipal impoundment and forfeiture.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-01-015__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding other provisions in this title, a municipality may adopt an ordinance providing for the impoundment or forfeiture of a</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-01-015__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>motor vehicle, watercraft, or aircraft involved in the commission of an offense under
AS 28.35.030
, 28.35.032, or an ordinance with elements substantially similar to
AS 28.35.030
or 28.35.032;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-01-015__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>motor vehicle involved in the commission of an offense under
AS 28.15.291
or an ordinance with elements similar to
AS 28.15.291
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-01-015__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>motor vehicle used by a person whose license is suspended under
AS 28.22.041
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-01-015__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>motor vehicle used by a person who fails to carry proof of insurance as required under
AS 28.22.019
; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-01-015__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>motor vehicle used by a person who has $1,000 or more in delinquent traffic fines for moving violations committed within the municipality.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-01-015__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An ordinance adopted under (a) of this section may</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-01-015__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>include a fee for the administrative costs incurred by the municipality; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-01-015__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>be more stringent than or the same as but may not be less stringent than applicable provisions under this title or regulations adopted under this title.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-01-017">
            <num>28.01.017</num>
            <heading>Municipal regulation of cellular telephone use.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.01.017.   Municipal regulation of cellular telephone use.
Notwithstanding other provisions of this title, a municipality may adopt an ordinance prohibiting the use of a cellular telephone by a person driving a motor vehicle while on school property or in an active school zone designated under the current edition of the Alaska Traffic Manual prepared by the Department of Transportation and Public Facilities. A municipal ordinance adopted under this section may not prohibit the hands-free use of a cellular telephone.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-01-020">
            <num>28.01.020</num>
            <heading>Short title.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.01.020.   Short title.
This chapter may be cited as the Alaska Uniform Traffic Laws Act.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>