<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-44/chapter-99"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-44/chapter-99"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="44.99"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-44/chapter-99/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-44/chapter-99/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-44/chapter-99/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-44/chapter-99/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_44">
        <num>44</num>
        <heading>State Government</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_44__chp_99">
          <num>99</num>
          <heading>Miscellaneous Provisions and Policies</heading>
          <section eId="sec_44-99-002">
            <num>44.99.002</num>
            <heading>Employment of radio stations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.99.002.   Employment of radio stations.
The governor may employ one or more radio stations, located south of the Gulf of Alaska and suitable for distribution of news, executive proclamations and inquiries, information concerning the state, general information, and other matters suitable for broadcasting that the governor prescribes and that may be of service and benefit to the people to be served.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-99-003">
            <num>44.99.003</num>
            <heading>Qualifications of radio station.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.99.003.   Qualifications of radio station.
A radio station used for the purposes set out in
AS 44.99.002
shall
(1) be licensed by the appropriate agency of the federal government to operate a broadcasting station of not less than 250 watt capacity in the state;
(2) have operated radio broadcasting continuously for a least one year before the date of its employment by the governor and during this period have broadcast daily radio programs totaling at least 75 hours in each month;
(3) have broadcast programs that have been received by the public over long wave radio receivers over a radius of at least 300 miles from the broadcasting station, and on demand shall furnish letters from the radio audience confirming reception within the required area;
(4) have invested at least $20,000 in real estate, buildings, transmitters, power equipment, antenna, radio masts, musical instruments, office equipment and other property, used or useful in the operation of the radio station exclusively.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-99-004">
            <num>44.99.004</num>
            <heading>Prescribing proof of capacity and suitability of station and of service and allotment of radio time.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.99.004.   Prescribing proof of capacity and suitability of station and of service and allotment of radio time.
The governor shall prescribe the proof required of the capacity and suitability of a station for broadcasting.  The governor may prescribe the service to be given, except that the state may, at its option, use not less than six hours of the station's time on the air for each $100 paid for the service.  The total time to which the state is entitled shall be distributed over the period of one year.  Not more than one hour may be used in any one day and not more than one-fifty-second of the total time in any one week. The governor may yield portions of the governor's allotted use of time to the University of Alaska or to state officials. A state official, except the governor, may not be allotted or use time within 30 days before a primary or general election.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-99-005">
            <num>44.99.005</num>
            <heading>Cost of radio service.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.99.005.   Cost of radio service.
The cost of the radio service is a lawful charge against the state treasury if the owner or operator of the station files an affidavit that the station has during the period covered by payment complied with
AS 44.99.002
 44.99.005 and has furnished the service.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-99-006">
            <num>44.99.006</num>
            <heading>Agreement for an Alaska Maritime Academy.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.99.006.   Agreement for an Alaska Maritime Academy.
The governor may enter into an agreement with the federal Maritime Administration to provide for an Alaska Maritime Academy.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-99-007">
            <num>44.99.007</num>
            <heading>Emergency transfer of seat of government.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.99.007.   Emergency transfer of seat of government.
When, due to an emergency resulting from the effects of enemy attack or an imminent enemy attack, it becomes imprudent, inexpedient, or impossible to conduct the affairs of state government at the normal location of the state capital, the governor shall, as often as the exigencies of the situation require, declare by proclamation an emergency temporary location or locations for the seat of government at a place or places, inside or outside the state, that would not normally be considered military target sites and that the governor may consider advisable under the circumstances.  The governor shall take such action and issue such orders as may be necessary for an orderly transition to the emergency temporary location or locations.  The temporary location or locations shall remain the emergency seat of government until the emergency is declared to be ended by the governor and the seat of government is returned to its normal location.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-99-008">
            <num>44.99.008</num>
            <heading>Validity of official action.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.99.008.   Validity of official action.
During the time the seat of government remains at the emergency temporary location or locations, all official acts now or hereafter required by law to be performed at the seat of government by an officer, agency, department, or authority of the state, including the convening and meeting of the legislature in regular or special session, shall be valid and binding when performed at the emergency temporary location or locations as if performed at the permanent location of the seat of government.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-99-020">
            <num>44.99.020</num>
            <heading>Use of paper.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.99.020.   Use of paper.
A state agency shall use both sides of paper when feasible. In this section, state agency means a department, institution, board, commission, division, authority, public corporation, or other administrative unit of the executive, legislative, or judicial branch of state government, including the University of Alaska, the Alaska Railroad Corporation, and legislative committees.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-99-030">
            <num>44.99.030</num>
            <heading>Lobbying contracts prohibited.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-99-030__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding other provisions of law, the following entities may not contract with a person to pay the person money or other thing of value to lobby the state, a municipality of the state, or an agency of the state or municipality:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-030__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Alaska Aerospace Corporation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-030__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Alaska Commercial Fishing and Agriculture Bank;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-030__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Alaska Energy Authority;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-030__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Alaska Housing Finance Corporation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-030__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Alaska Industrial Development and Export Authority;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-030__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Alaska Medical Facility Authority;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-030__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Alaska Mental Health Trust Authority;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-030__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Alaska Municipal Bond Bank Authority;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-030__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Alaska Permanent Fund Corporation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-030__subsec_a__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Alaska Railroad Corporation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-030__subsec_a__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>[Repealed, § 8 ch 2 SLA 2004.]</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-030__subsec_a__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Alaska Seafood Marketing Institute;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-030__subsec_a__subsec_13">
                <num>(13)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Alaska Student Loan Corporation.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-99-030__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-030__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>lobby a municipality or an agency of a municipality means to engage in an activity for the purpose of influencing municipal legislative or administrative action if the activity is substantially the same as activity that would have required registration under
AS 24.45.121
if the activity was for the purpose of influencing state legislative or administrative action;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-030__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>lobby the state or an agency of the state means to engage in an activity for which registration is required under
AS 24.45.121
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-99-040">
            <num>44.99.040</num>
            <heading>Limitation on use of assets.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-99-040__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A state or municipal agency may not use or authorize the use of an asset to implement or aid in the implementation of a requirement of an order of the President of the United States, a federal regulation, or a law enacted by the United States Congress that is applied to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-040__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>infringe on a person's right, under the Second Amendment to the Constitution of the United States, to keep and bear arms;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-040__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>deny a person a right to due process, or a protection of due process, that would otherwise be available to the person under the Constitution of the State of Alaska or the Constitution of the United States.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-99-040__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-040__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>asset means funds, facilities, equipment, services, or other resources of a state or municipal agency;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-040__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>state or municipal agency means the University of Alaska, the Alaska Aerospace Corporation, the Alaska Housing Finance Corporation, the Alaska Industrial Development and Export Authority, the Alaska Energy Authority, the Alaska Railroad Corporation, or a department, institution, board, commission, division, council, committee, authority, public corporation, school district, regional educational attendance area, or other administrative unit of a municipality or of the executive, judicial, or legislative branch of state government, and includes employees of those entities.
Article 2. General State Policies.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-99-100">
            <num>44.99.100</num>
            <heading>Declaration of state economic development policy.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-99-100__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To further the goals of a sound economy, stable employment, and a desirable quality of life, the legislature declares that the state has a commitment to foster the economy of Alaska through purposeful development of the state's abundant natural resources and productive capacity.  It is the legislature's intent that this development</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-100__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>offer long-term benefits and increased employment to Alaskans by strengthening and diversifying the state's economic base and encouraging new activities;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-100__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide opportunities for increased personal income or reduced living costs by creating activity in economic sectors;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-100__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>have a positive effect on the revenue needs and fiscal conditions of the state and local communities;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-100__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>be undertaken after consideration of the social and economic views of citizens impacted by the development, and only after adequate protection is assured for Alaska's environment.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-99-100__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To take advantage of investment opportunities afforded by Alaska's abundant natural resources and productive capacity, the legislature finds that the state should undertake activities that serve as a catalyst to responsible economic development in the state for the benefit of its citizens.  It is the policy of the state to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-100__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>develop and provide information to domestic and foreign investors to use in evaluating project feasibility;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-100__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>with cooperation from investors, identify constraints to orderly and beneficial economic development and work with government agencies to eliminate unnecessary impediments to economic development;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-100__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>with cooperation from investors, identify constraints to economic development that would impede the extraction, production, and transport of resources to markets and manufactured products, and implement capital improvement or other programs to resolve the deficiencies;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-100__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide a stable tax and regulatory climate that encourages expansion of the state's economic base;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-100__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>encourage value-added processing in the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-100__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>improve the state's domestic and international competitive position by offering economic incentives that support the constitutional mandates for utilization, development, and conservation of natural resources.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-99-105">
            <num>44.99.105</num>
            <heading>Declaration of state Arctic policy.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-99-105__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>It is the policy of the state, as it relates to the Arctic, to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-105__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>uphold the state's commitment to economically vibrant communities sustained by development activities consistent with the state's responsibility for a healthy environment, including efforts to
(A) ensure that Arctic residents and communities benefit from economic and resource development activities in the region;
(B) improve the efficiency, predictability, and stability of permitting and regulatory processes;
(C) attract investment through the establishment of a positive investment climate and the development of strategic infrastructure;
(D) sustain current, and develop new, approaches for responding to a changing climate, and adapt to the challenges of coastal erosion, permafrost melt, and ocean acidification;
(E) encourage industrial and technological innovation in the private and academic sectors that focuses on emerging opportunities and challenges;
(F) maintain a strong, sustainable fisheries industry and increase fisheries research and monitoring;
(G) continue to prepare the residents of the state for emerging economic activities by using multiple education and training opportunities and implementing state workforce plans;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-105__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>collaborate with all levels of government, tribes, industry, and nongovernmental organizations to achieve transparent and inclusive Arctic decision-making, including efforts to
(A) strengthen and expand cross-border relationships and international cooperation, especially bilateral engagements with Canada and Russia;
(B) sustain and enhance state participation in the Arctic Council;
(C) pursue opportunities to participate meaningfully as a partner in the development of federal and international Arctic policies, thereby incorporating state and local knowledge and expertise;
(D) strengthen support for and collaboration with Arctic Council Permanent Participant organizations that include Indigenous peoples of the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-105__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>enhance the security of the Arctic region of the state and, thereby, the security of the entire state, including efforts to
(A) enhance disaster and emergency prevention and response, oil spill prevention and response, and search and rescue capabilities in the region;
(B) provide safe, secure, and reliable maritime transportation in the areas of the state adjacent to the Arctic;
(C) sustain current, and develop new, community, response, and resource-related infrastructure;
(D) coordinate with the federal government for an increase in United States Coast Guard presence, national defense obligations, and levels of public and private sector support; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-105__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>value and strengthen the resilience of communities and respect and integrate the culture, language, and knowledge of Arctic peoples, including efforts to
(A) recognize Arctic Indigenous peoples' cultures and unique relationship to the environment, including traditional reliance on a subsistence way of life for food security, which provides a spiritual connection to the land and the sea;
(B) build capacity to conduct science and research and advance innovation and technology in part by providing support to the University of Alaska for Arctic research consistent with state priorities;
(C) employ integrated, strategic planning that considers scientific, local, and traditional knowledge;
(D) safeguard the fish, wildlife, and environment of the Arctic for the benefit of residents of the state;
(E) encourage more effective integration of local and traditional knowledge into conventional science and research.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-99-105__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>It is important to the state, as it relates to the Arctic, to support the strategic recommendations of the implementation plan developed by the Alaska Arctic Policy Commission and to encourage consideration of recommendations developed by the Alaska Arctic Policy Commission. Priority lines of effort for the Arctic policy of the state include</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-105__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>promoting economic and resource development;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-105__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>addressing the infrastructure and response capacity gap in order to support the Arctic region;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-105__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>supporting healthy communities; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-105__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>supporting existing and fostering new science and research that aligns with state priorities for the Arctic.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-99-105__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, Arctic means the area of the state north of the Arctic Circle, north and west of the boundary formed by the Porcupine, Yukon, and Kuskokwim Rivers, all contiguous seas, including the Arctic Ocean, and the Beaufort, Bering, and Chukchi Seas, and the Aleutian Chain, except that, for the purpose of international Arctic policy, Arctic means the entirety of the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-99-110">
            <num>44.99.110</num>
            <heading>Declaration of state mineral policy.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.99.110.   Declaration of state mineral policy.
The legislature, acting under art. VIII, sec. 1 of the Constitution of the State of Alaska, in an effort to further the economic development of the state, to maintain a sound economy and stable employment, and to encourage responsible economic development within the state for the benefit of present and future generations through the proper conservation and development of the abundant mineral resources within the state, including metals, industrial minerals, and coal, declares as the mineral policy of the state that
(1) mineral exploration and development be given fair and equitable consideration with other resource uses in the multiple use management of state land;
(2) mineral development be encouraged through reasonable and consistent nonduplicative regulations and administrative stipulations;
(3) mineral development and the entry into the market place of mineral products be considered in developing a statewide transportation infrastructure system;
(4) mineral development be encouraged through appropriate public information and education, scientific research, technical studies, and University of Alaska program involvement;
(5) economic development with respect to the state mineral industry be encouraged with Pacific Rim nations.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-99-115">
            <num>44.99.115</num>
            <heading>Declaration of state energy policy.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.99.115.   Declaration of state energy policy.
The State of Alaska recognizes that the state's economic prosperity is dependent on available, reliable, and affordable residential, commercial, and industrial energy to supply the state's electric, heating, and transportation needs. The state also recognizes that worldwide supply and demand for fossil fuels and concerns about global climate change will affect the price of fossil fuels consumed by Alaskans and exported from the state to other markets. In establishing a state energy policy, the state further recognizes the immense diversity of the state's geography, cultures, and resource availability. Therefore, it is the policy of the state to
(1) institute a comprehensive and coordinated approach to supporting energy efficiency and conservation by
(A) encouraging statewide energy efficiency codes for new and renovated residential, commercial, and public buildings;
(B) decreasing public building energy consumption through conservation measures and energy-efficient technologies; and
(C) initiating and supporting a program to educate state residents on the benefits of energy efficiency and conservation, including dissemination of information on state and federal programs that reward energy efficiency;
(2) encourage economic development by
(A) promoting the development of renewable and alternative energy resources, including geothermal, wind, solar, hydroelectric, hydrokinetic, tidal, and biomass energy, for use by Alaskans;
(B) promoting the development, transport, and efficient use of nonrenewable and alternative energy resources, including natural gas, coal, oil, gas hydrates, heavy oil, and nuclear energy, for use by Alaskans and for export;
(C) working to identify and assist with development of the most cost-effective, long-term sources of energy for each community statewide;
(D) creating and maintaining a state fiscal regime and permitting and regulatory processes that encourage private sector development of the state's energy resources; and
(E) promoting the efficiency of energy used for transportation;
(3) support energy research, education, and workforce development by investing in
(A) training and education programs that will help create jobs for Alaskans and that address energy conservation, efficiency, and availability, including programs that address workforce development and workforce transition; and
(B) applied energy research and development of alternative and emerging technologies, including university programs, to achieve reductions in state energy costs and stimulate industry investment in the state;
(4) coordinate governmental functions
(A) by reviewing and streamlining regulatory processes and balancing the economic costs of review with the level of regulation necessary to protect the public interest;
(B) by using one office or agency, as may be specified by law, to serve as a clearinghouse in managing the state's energy-related functions to avoid fragmentation and duplication and to increase effectiveness; and
(C) by actively collaborating with federal agencies to achieve the state's energy goals and to meet emissions, renewable and alternative energy, and energy production targets.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-99-120">
            <num>44.99.120</num>
            <heading>Declaration of nuclear freeze policy.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.99.120.   Declaration of nuclear freeze policy.
It is the policy of the State of Alaska
(1) to recognize that the greatest challenge facing the earth is to prevent the occurrence of nuclear war by accident or design;
(2) to recognize that the nuclear arms race is dangerously increasing the risk of a holocaust that would be humanity's final war;
(3) to promote a mutual and verifiable freeze followed by reductions in nuclear warheads, missiles, and other delivery systems in order to halt the nuclear arms race and to reduce the risk of nuclear war.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-99-125">
            <num>44.99.125</num>
            <heading>Implementation of policy.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-99-125__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The governor shall conduct the affairs of state and carry out state programs in conformity with this policy.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-99-125__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The lieutenant governor shall deliver copies of this Act to Congress and the President of the United States.
Article 3. State Publications.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-99-200">
            <num>44.99.200</num>
            <heading>Production of publications.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.99.200.   Production of publications.
The publications of a state agency shall be produced at a private sector facility located in the state when practicable. The Department of Administration shall establish standards for the production of publications by state agencies, except that the Board of Regents of the University of Alaska shall establish the standards for the university. The standards shall be designed to promote simplicity, low cost, and consistency.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-99-205">
            <num>44.99.205</num>
            <heading>Use of pictures and messages.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-99-205__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A state agency may not place a picture of an elected state official on an application form, a warrant, or a direct deposit notice provided by the agency.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-99-205__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A state agency may not place a message on or with an application form, a warrant, or a direct deposit notice provided by the agency unless the message is</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-205__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>from a state agency employee who is not an elected state official; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-205__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>required by law, necessary for the operation of the document, related to seasonal health issues including flu shot reminders, or related to a program or activity of a state agency.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-99-205__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-205__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>direct deposit notice means a written notice that a deposit has been made by the state agency;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-205__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>elected state official means the governor, the lieutenant governor, a lieutenant governor who serves as acting governor or who succeeds to the office of the governor, or a legislator, including a person who has been appointed a member of the legislature by the governor to fill a vacancy in the legislature;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-205__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>program includes the permanent fund dividend program under
AS 43.23
and the longevity bonus program under
AS 47.45.010
- 47.45.160;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-205__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>state agency has the meaning given in
AS 44.99.240
(2)(A) and (B).</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-99-210">
            <num>44.99.210</num>
            <heading>Disclosures on publication.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.99.210.   Disclosures on publication.
If the actual annual costs for a publication of a state agency that are paid from the general fund exceed $1,500, or if the actual annual costs of a state agency publication that is a report required by law are paid from a source other than the general fund and exceed $1,500, the publication must include a statement that gives the name of the agency releasing the publication, the purpose of the publication, the cost for each copy of the publication, and the city and state where the printing was done. The statement must read: This publication was released by... (name of state agency)..., produced at a cost of $..... per copy to... (statement of purpose)..., and printed in...... (city and state where printed). If the publication is required by law, the statement must also include: This publication is required by... (appropriate citation to Alaska law). The statement may include, if applicable, a declaration of the revenue raised by the sale of the publication or from the purchase of advertising in the publication. The statement shall be printed in one conspicuous place in the body of the publication in a type size that is not smaller than 12 points and shall be placed in a box composed of at least two point rule. In this section, cost for each copy means the figure that results after dividing the total contract cost of producing the publication by the number of copies produced. This section does not apply to a publication that is intended primarily for foreign or other out-of-state use, to a program for a public ceremony of a state agency, or to materials used by a state agency to develop a market for the agency's services or products.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-99-220">
            <num>44.99.220</num>
            <heading>Review of publications.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-99-220__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each state agency shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-220__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>compile a list of all publications the agency produces as required by law or regulation or as directed by the legislature;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-220__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>identify and highlight on the list compiled under (1) of this subsection the publications that are
(A) outdated, duplicative, or excessive, or that could be improved or consolidated with other publications; or
(B) currently delivered physically that could be delivered electronically; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-220__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>by October 31 of every even-numbered year, electronically submit the list of publications compiled under (1) of this subsection, including the highlighted publications under (2) of this subsection, to the governor and to the senate secretary and chief clerk of the house of representatives and notify the legislature that the list is available.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-99-220__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to the budget, bills, and fiscal plan submitted under
AS 37.07.020</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-99-220__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and (b), in every even-numbered year, the governor shall submit a bill to eliminate or modify publication requirements for publications that have been identified under (a) of this section</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-220__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>as outdated, duplicative, or excessive, or that could be improved or consolidated with other publications; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-220__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>that could be exclusively delivered electronically.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-99-220__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, state agency means a department, institution, board, commission, division, authority, public corporation, or other administrative unit of the executive branch, including the University of Alaska.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-99-240">
            <num>44.99.240</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.99.240.   Definitions.
In
AS 44.99.200
 44.99.240,
(1) publication means a written document, including books, brochures, flyers, manuals, newsletters, pamphlets, programs, reports, and similar documents, but does not include standard forms, letterhead stationery, letterhead envelopes, election ballots, construction plans and specifications, location and design study reports, the Alaska Statutes, the Alaska Administrative Code, the Alaska Rules of Court, publications produced by the University of Alaska press, and papers that are submitted to a publisher, including a publisher of journals and anthologies, that is not a state agency;
(2) state agency means
(A) a department, institution, board, commission, division, authority, public corporation, or other administrative unit of the executive branch, including the University of Alaska and the Alaska Railroad Corporation;
(B) a committee, division, or administrative unit of the legislative branch, including the Alaska Legislative Council, the leadership of each house, the office of victims' rights, and the office of the ombudsman;
(C) an administrative unit of the judicial branch, including the Alaska Judicial Council and the Commission on Judicial Conduct.
Article 4. Copyrights by State Agencies.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-99-400">
            <num>44.99.400</num>
            <heading>Software copyrights.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.99.400.   Software copyrights.
A state agency may hold the copyright for software created by the agency or developed by a private contractor for an agency, and may enforce its rights to protect the copyright. In this section, state agency means a department, institution, board, commission, division, authority, public corporation, committee, or other administrative unit of the executive, judicial, or legislative branch of state government, including the University of Alaska, the Alaska Aerospace Corporation, and the Alaska Railroad Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-99-500">
            <num>44.99.500</num>
            <heading>State policy, declarations, and requirements concerning certain firearms not in interstate commerce and not subject to federal regulation.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-99-500__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A personal firearm, a firearm accessory, or ammunition that is possessed in this state or manufactured commercially or privately in this state and that remains in the state is not subject to federal law or federal regulation, including registration, under the authority of the United States Congress to regulate interstate commerce as those items have not traveled in interstate commerce.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-99-500__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This section applies to a firearm, a firearm accessory, or ammunition that is possessed in this state or manufactured in this state from basic materials and that can be manufactured without the inclusion of any significant parts imported from another state. Generic and insignificant parts that have other manufacturing or consumer product applications are not firearms, firearm accessories, or ammunition, and their importation into this state and incorporation into a firearm, a firearm accessory, or ammunition manufactured in this state does not subject the firearm, firearm accessory, or ammunition to federal regulation. Basic materials, such as unmachined steel and unshaped wood, are not firearms, firearm accessories, or ammunition and are not subject to congressional authority to regulate firearms, firearm accessories, and ammunition under interstate commerce as if they were actually firearms, firearm accessories, or ammunition. The authority of the United States Congress to regulate interstate commerce in basic materials does not include authority to regulate firearms, firearm accessories, and ammunition possessed in this state or made in this state from those materials. Firearm accessories that are imported into this state from another state and that are subject to federal regulation as being in interstate commerce do not subject a firearm to federal regulation under interstate commerce because they are attached to or used in conjunction with a firearm in this state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-99-500__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A firearm manufactured or sold in this state and not subject to federal regulation under this section must have the words Made in Alaska clearly stamped on a central metallic part, such as the receiver or frame.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-99-500__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The attorney general may defend a citizen of this state who is prosecuted by the government of the United States under the congressional power to regulate interstate commerce for violation of a federal law concerning the manufacture, sale, transfer, or possession of a firearm, a firearm accessory, or ammunition possessed in this state or manufactured and retained within this state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-99-500__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A federal statute, regulation, rule, or order adopted, enacted, or otherwise effective on or after June 21, 2013 is unenforceable in this state by an official, agent, or employee of this state, a municipality, or the federal government if the federal statute, regulation, rule, or order violates the Second Amendment to the Constitution of the United States or art. I, sec. 19, Constitution of the State of Alaska, by</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-500__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>banning or restricting ownership of a semiautomatic firearm or a magazine of a firearm; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-500__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>requiring a firearm, magazine, or other firearm accessory to be registered.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-99-500__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The attorney general shall, under the Second Amendment to the Constitution of the United States or art. I, sec. 19, Constitution of the State of Alaska, file legal action necessary to prevent the implementation of a federal statute, regulation, rule, or order that violates the rights of a resident of the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-99-500__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-500__subsec_g__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>generic and insignificant parts includes springs, screws, nuts, and pins;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-500__subsec_g__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>manufactured means a firearm, a firearm accessory, or ammunition that has been created from basic materials for functional usefulness, including forging, casting, machining, or other processes for working materials.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-99-510">
            <num>44.99.510</num>
            <heading>Infringements on the right to keep and bear arms; disaster.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-99-510__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>During a disaster emergency declared under
AS 26.23.020
, the governor, a state agency, or a municipality may not issue or adopt an order, proclamation, regulation, ordinance, or policy</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-510__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>forbidding the possession, use, or transfer of a firearm, a firearm part, a firearm accessory, ammunition, or other weapon for personal use;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-510__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>ordering the seizure or confiscation of a firearm, a firearm part, a firearm accessory, ammunition, or other weapon for personal use;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-510__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>limiting the quantity or placing other restrictions on the sale or service of firearms, firearm parts, firearm accessories, ammunition, or other weapons for personal use;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-510__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>unless a closure or limitation applies equally to all forms of commerce within the jurisdiction, closing or limiting the operating hours of
(A) an entity engaged in the sale or service of firearms, firearm parts, firearm accessories, ammunition, or other weapons for personal use; or
(B) an indoor or outdoor shooting range;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-510__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>suspending or revoking a permit to carry a concealed handgun issued under
AS 18.65.700
, except as provided in
AS 18.65.735
and 18.65.740; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-510__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>refusing to accept an application to carry a concealed handgun, provided the application contains the information required under
AS 18.65.710
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-99-510__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This section does not apply to the possession of a firearm, a firearm part, a firearm accessory, ammunition, or other weapon by a person who is prohibited from legally possessing a firearm, a firearm part, a firearm accessory, ammunition, or other weapon under state law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-99-510__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may bring a civil action in superior court if the person is adversely affected by a violation of (a) of this section and the person is</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-510__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>qualified under state law to possess a firearm, a firearm part, a firearm accessory, ammunition, or other weapon; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-99-510__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a membership organization consisting of two or more individuals eligible under (1) of this subsection that is dedicated in whole or in part to the protection of the rights of persons who possess or use firearms or other weapons.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-99-520">
            <num>44.99.520</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.99.520.   Definitions.
In
AS 44.99.500
 44.99.520,
(1) firearm has the meaning given in
AS 11.81.900
(b);
(2) firearm accessory means an item that is used in conjunction with or mounted on a firearm but is not essential to the basic function of a firearm, including a telescopic or laser sight, magazine, flash or sound suppressor, folding or aftermarket stock and grip, speedloader, ammunition carrier, and light for target illumination;
(3) firearm part means a component of a firearm that is essential to the basic function of a firearm, including a component of an action or lock, the stock, and the barrel.
Article 6. Compact for a Balanced Budget.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-99-600">
            <num>44.99.600</num>
            <heading>Entry into agreement.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.99.600.   Entry into agreement.
The Compact for a Balanced Budget is hereby enacted into law and entered into with all jurisdictions legally joining it in a form substantially as contained in
AS 44.99.610
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-99-610">
            <num>44.99.610</num>
            <heading>Compact terms.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.99.610.   Compact terms.
The terms and provisions of the compact referred to in
AS 44.99.600
are as follows:</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>