<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-62"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-62"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="8.62"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-62/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-62/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-62/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-62/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_8">
        <num>8</num>
        <heading>Business and Professions</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_8__chp_62">
          <num>62</num>
          <heading>Marine Pilots</heading>
          <section eId="sec_08-62-010">
            <num>08.62.010</num>
            <heading>Creation and membership of board.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.62.010.   Creation and membership of board.
There is created the Board of Marine Pilots. It consists of two pilots licensed under this chapter who have been actively engaged in piloting on vessels subject to this chapter, two registered agents or managers of vessels subject to this chapter who are actively engaged in the procurement of pilotage services, two public members in accordance with
AS 08.01.025
, and the commissioner or the commissioner's designee. Not more than one pilot and one registered agent or manager may be from any one pilotage region established by the board. Not more than one registered agent or manager may be employed by, be a contractor for, or hold a financial interest in the same marine industry business entity, including commonly owned, affiliated, or subsidiary business entities. All members of the board shall be residents of the state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-62-020">
            <num>08.62.020</num>
            <heading>Appointment and term of office.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.62.020.   Appointment and term of office.
The governor shall appoint the members of the board under
AS 08.01.020
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-62-030">
            <num>08.62.030</num>
            <heading>Meetings.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.62.030.   Meetings.
The board shall hold at least three regularly scheduled meetings each year. The board may hold special meetings at the call of the chair or at the request of a majority of the members of the board.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-62-040">
            <num>08.62.040</num>
            <heading>Powers, duties, and limitations.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-62-040__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-040__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide for the maintenance of efficient and competent pilotage service on the inland and coastal water of and adjacent to the state to assure the protection of shipping, the safety of human life and property, and the protection of the marine environment;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-040__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>consistent with the law, adopt regulations, subject to
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act), establishing the qualifications of and required training for pilots and providing for the examination of pilots and the issuance of original or renewal pilot licenses to qualified persons;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-040__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>keep a register of licensed pilots, licensed deputy pilots, and agents;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-040__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>adopt regulations establishing
(A) pilotage regions in the state;
(B) the criteria for concurring in the amount of license, application, training, investigation, and audit fees proposed by the department under
AS 08.01.065
;
(C) the criteria for recognizing pilot organizations under
AS 08.62.175
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-040__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>make available, upon request, copies of this chapter and the regulations adopted under this chapter;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-040__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>review and approve the articles, bylaws, and rules of pilot organizations;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-040__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>audit a pilot organization or an individual pilot as necessary to implement and enforce this chapter;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-040__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>review and approve training programs conducted by pilot organizations; the board shall cooperate with the Department of Environmental Conservation in the review and approval of training programs for pilots of tank vessels;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-040__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establish and publish the dates of future license examinations; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-040__subsec_a__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>approve or disapprove rates for pilotage services as provided under
AS 08.62.046
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-040__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board may, by regulation, make any other provision for proper and safe pilotage upon the inland and coastal water of and adjacent to the state and for the efficient administration of this chapter, including establishing</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-040__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>different licensing criteria for a pilotage region if justified by regional differences in piloting;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-040__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a mandatory drug and alcohol testing program, including random tests, post-incident tests, and tests based upon reasonable cause, for pilots licensed under this chapter and for trainees and apprentices seeking a license or endorsement under this chapter; the board may delegate responsibility for administration of all or a portion of a testing program to pilot organizations;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-040__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>criteria for trainee selection and for training programs conducted by pilot organizations;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-040__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>standards under which a pilot may receive a license or an endorsement to a license to pilot vessels in more than one pilotage region under
AS 08.62.080</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-040__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>procedures for the review of proposed rates by the board under
AS 08.62.046
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-040__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board may, for good cause, require a pilot licensed under this chapter to submit to a physical or mental examination to determine the pilot's fitness to perform the duties of a pilot.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-040__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding the exemption from
AS 45.50.562
 45.50.596 granted to pilot organizations under
AS 45.50.572
(a), the board may not adopt a regulation or take other action resulting in anti-competitive activities that, if the board were subject to
AS 45.50.562
 45.50.596, would violate
AS 45.50.562
 45.50.596.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-040__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board may delegate duties to the marine pilot coordinator as necessary to assist the board in administering and enforcing this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-040__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board may impose a civil fine on the owner or operator of a pleasure craft of foreign registry who, in violation of this chapter, fails to employ a pilot licensed under this chapter or fails to comply with the pilotage requirement under
AS 08.62.180
(b). Notwithstanding
AS 08.01.075
, the amount of the civil penalty may not exceed $10,000 for each violation. Each entry into state water in violation of this chapter or
AS 08.62.180</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-040__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>is a separate violation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-62-046">
            <num>08.62.046</num>
            <heading>Rates for pilotage services.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-62-046__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A pilot organization recognized by the board shall adopt and publish rates for the provision of pilotage services. The pilot organization shall adopt rates for pilotage services as provided under this section. Notwithstanding this section, a pilot organization may enter into agreements with the master, owner, operator, or agent of a master, owner, or operator, of a vessel for the provision of pilotage services at rates of compensation that are different from the rates adopted under this section. Unless a pilot organization has an agreement with the master, owner, operator, or agent of a master, owner, or operator, of a vessel that sets rates for the provision of a pilotage service, the pilot organization may not charge a rate for the provision of the pilotage service to the vessel that is different from the rate adopted or established under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-046__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a pilot organization intends to adopt a new or revised rate for the provision of a pilotage service, the pilot organization shall, before October 15, send a notice of intent to adopt a rate for provision of the pilotage service to the board and to all registered agents and publish the notice on at least three days during a period of 14 consecutive days in a newspaper of general circulation in the state. The notice of intent to adopt a rate must include a copy of the proposed rate and the name and mailing address of the pilot organization that intends to adopt the rate. If no objection to the proposed rate is filed with the board under (c) of this section, the rate takes effect on January 1 of the year following the year in which the notice of the intent to adopt the rate was filed with the board.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-046__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The master, owner, operator, or agent of the master, owner, or operator, of a vessel required to employ a pilot under this chapter may object to the proposed rate for a specific pilotage service by filing a written notice of objection, containing the grounds for the objection and relevant evidence demonstrating that the rate is not reasonable, with the board within 60 days after the final date of publication of the proposed rate in a newspaper of general circulation. The pilot organization that proposed the rate has until 15 days after the close of the period for filing objections to the proposed rate to provide its written response to the notice of objection and relevant evidence demonstrating that the rate is reasonable. If the pilot organization does not respond to the notice of objection by the close of the 15-day period for response to the objection, the board may not take action on the proposed rate and the proposed rate does not take effect. If the pilot organization does respond to the notice of objection before the close of the response period, the board shall hold a hearing to determine whether the proposed rate is reasonable. If the board finds that the proposed rate is reasonable, the rate is approved and takes effect retroactive to January 1 of the calendar year in which the rate would have taken effect under (b) of this section if no objection had been filed. If the board finds that the proposed rate is not reasonable, the proposed rate is disapproved and does not take effect. In determining what constitutes a reasonable rate, the board shall consider the following factors:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-046__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>current and historical rates charged for comparable pilotage services;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-046__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the actual time aboard the vessel, time engaged in preparing to provide the pilotage services, seasonal and weather conditions, and risks;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-046__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the reasonable expenses incurred in providing the pilotage services such as dispatch, transportation, overhead, and other associated expenses;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-046__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the financial effect of pilotage expenses on the owner of the vessel, except that this factor shall only be considered if the owner provides all financial information that the board determines is necessary to determine the financial effect;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-046__subsec_c__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the number of vessels and volume of pilotage services at issue in the dispute and the number of members of the pilot organization;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-046__subsec_c__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the effect of the determination on the income of affected pilots relative to prior years, taking into account changes in vessel tonnage and vessel traffic in the pilotage region from year-to-year;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-046__subsec_c__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>prior determinations under this subsection; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-046__subsec_c__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>other factors the board considers relevant.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-046__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Pending the review and approval of the proposed rate for a specific pilotage service by the board under (c) of this section, the current rate then in effect for that pilotage service remains in effect until the board approves the proposed rate. If the proposed rate approved by the board is greater than the current rate, then the master, owner, or operator of the vessel or the vessel is liable for the payment of the additional amount owed for the provision of pilotage services during the pendency of the review by the board due to retroactive application of the approved rate under (c) of this section. If the proposed rate is less than the current rate, then the pilot organization is liable to the master, owner, or operator of the vessel or the vessel for reimbursement of the amount overpaid for the provision of pilotage services during the pendency of the review by the board due to the retroactive application of the approved rate under (c) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-046__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the board finds under (c) of this section that a proposed rate is not reasonable, the pilot organization may propose a new rate for that pilotage service within 60 days after the decision of the board is issued by sending a notice of intent to adopt a rate for provision of the pilotage service to the board and to all registered agents and publishing the notice on at least three days during a period of 14 consecutive days in a newspaper of general circulation in the state. The notice of intent to adopt a rate must include a copy of the proposed rate and the name and mailing address of the pilot organization that intends to adopt the rate. If a timely objection to the proposed rate is not filed with the board under (c) of this section, the rate takes effect retroactive to January 1 of the same calendar year in which the initial rate proposed under (b) of this section would have taken effect if no objection had been filed. If a timely objection is filed, the provisions of (c) and (d) of this section apply to the proposed rate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-046__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board shall provide a schedule of rates adopted under this section to agents registered under
AS 08.62.187
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-62-050">
            <num>08.62.050</num>
            <heading>Marine pilot coordinator.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-62-050__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department, with the approval of the board, may hire a marine pilot coordinator who is qualified to assist the board in administering and enforcing the provisions of this chapter. The coordinator is in the partially exempt service under
AS 39.25.120
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-050__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The person who is hired as coordinator may not</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-050__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>be an active member of a pilot organization in the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-050__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>work as a pilot while employed as the coordinator, except to the extent required by official duties; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-050__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>have a financial interest in a pilot organization or in a pilot vessel or other equipment used by a pilot organization.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-050__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to other duties as may be assigned by the board, the marine pilot coordinator may review applications for examination and licensure to ascertain whether the applicant satisfies the applicable requirements.
Article 2. Licensing.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-62-080">
            <num>08.62.080</num>
            <heading>License required; restrictions and conditions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-62-080__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not pilot a vessel subject to this chapter unless the person is licensed under this chapter and is a member of a pilot organization recognized by the board.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-080__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A pilot may not be licensed in more than one pilotage region at one time unless the commissioner determines that an actual or imminent shortage of licensed pilots exists in a pilotage region. If the commissioner makes the determination described in this subsection, the board may, after consultation with the recognized pilot organizations and registered agents in the affected pilotage region, issue temporary licenses for the affected pilotage region to pilots who already hold a license for another pilotage region. The board shall ensure that sufficient pilots are available to provide pilotage services in the affected pilotage region to all vessels required to employ a pilot under this chapter. A temporary license issued under this subsection is valid for a period of not more than one year.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-080__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A license issued under this chapter must identify the specific waterways and ports in each pilotage region in which a licensee is authorized by the board to pilot vessels. The board shall authorize a licensee to pilot vessels in a specific waterway or port in a pilotage region upon the licensee satisfying the training and other qualifying requirements required by the board to pilot vessels in that waterway or port.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-62-090">
            <num>08.62.090</num>
            <heading>Application.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-62-090__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who desires to be licensed under this chapter shall apply in writing to the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-090__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The application shall provide the information and be made on a form prescribed by the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-090__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In order to be eligible to take the next scheduled examination, a person shall file the application with the board at least 60 days before the date of the examination.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-62-093">
            <num>08.62.093</num>
            <heading>Qualifications for deputy marine pilot license.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-62-093__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board shall issue a deputy marine pilot license for a marine pilotage region to a person who</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-093__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is a citizen of the United States;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-093__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>passes the written and oral examinations that may be required by the board;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-093__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has completed training requirements established by the board; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-093__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>satisfies (b) and (c) of this section.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-093__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who applies for a deputy marine pilot license under this chapter shall provide proof satisfactory to the board of the following experience:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-093__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>one year of service as a master on ocean or coastwise vessels while holding a United States Coast Guard license as master of ocean steam or motor vessels of any gross tons;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-093__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>two years of service as a master on United States Coast Guard inspected vessels of not less than 1,000 gross tons or tug and tow of not less than 1,600 combined gross tons while holding at least a United States Coast Guard license as master of steam or motor vessels of not more than 1,600 gross tons;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-093__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>two years of service as a chief officer on ocean or coastwise vessels of not less than 1,600 gross tons while holding a United States Coast Guard license as master of ocean steam or motor vessels of any gross tons;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-093__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>two years of service as commanding officer of United States commissioned vessels of not less than 1,600 gross tons and hold a United States Coast Guard license as master of ocean steam or motor vessels of any gross tons;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-093__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>three years of experience as a member of a professional pilot's organization, during which the person actively engaged in piloting while holding at least a United States Coast Guard license as a master of steam or motor vessels of not more than 1,600 gross tons; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-093__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>four years of experience gained in a board approved deputy marine pilot apprenticeship program in the pilotage region for which the deputy marine pilot license is sought and hold at least a United States Coast Guard license as master of steam or motor vessels of not more than 1,600 gross tons.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-093__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who applies for a deputy marine pilot license under this section shall possess an endorsement of first class pilotage on the person's United States Coast Guard license without tonnage restrictions for the pilotage region for which the person seeks the deputy marine pilot license.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-093__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person licensed as a deputy marine pilot under this section may, except as otherwise provided by the board, pilot vessels of 25,000 gross tons or less in a marine pilotage region for which the license is issued.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-093__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 22 ch 74 SLA 1995.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-62-097">
            <num>08.62.097</num>
            <heading>Training programs for deputy marine pilot license.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-62-097__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board shall establish standards for training programs for a deputy marine pilot license. The standards may include requirements for</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-097__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>supervised familiarization and training trips on vessels subject to this chapter;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-097__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>supervised dockings, undockings, and tug assisted maneuvers;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-097__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>special training or experience necessary to qualify for a deputy marine pilot license for a particular marine pilotage region;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-097__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>completion of the training program within a specified period;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-097__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>other training or experience that the board considers appropriate.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-097__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who supervises the training of persons who are seeking a deputy marine pilot license under this chapter shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-097__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>hold a marine pilot license issued under
AS 08.62.100
; however, if the board finds that there are no marine pilots licensed in a pilotage region who are available to supervise training under this section, the board may authorize a person who is licensed in that pilotage region as a deputy marine pilot to supervise the training of persons who are seeking a deputy marine pilot license in that pilotage region;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-097__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>receive prior authorization from the board to supervise the training of those persons;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-097__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>maintain a written log and evaluation on a form provided by the board of the training and progress of the person being supervised.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-62-100">
            <num>08.62.100</num>
            <heading>Qualifications for a marine pilot license.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-62-100__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board shall issue a marine pilot license for a marine pilotage region to a person who</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-100__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is a citizen of the United States;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-100__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>passes examinations that may be required by the board;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-100__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has three years experience as a deputy marine pilot licensed under this chapter; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-100__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>satisfies additional requirements as may be required by the board by regulation.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-100__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (a) of this section, a person who holds a marine pilot license of any type on the day before July 2, 1991 shall, subject to continued eligibility for the license under this chapter and regulations adopted under this chapter, receive a renewable marine pilot license of the same type and subject to the same qualifications and endorsements as that which the person held on July 1, 1991. A person who receives a license under this subsection may change the type of marine pilot license and the qualifications and endorsements attached to the license in accordance with regulations adopted by the board.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-62-120">
            <num>08.62.120</num>
            <heading>Renewal of licenses.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-62-120__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In order to renew a marine pilot license, a person who is licensed under
AS 08.62.100
shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-120__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>submit an application for renewal of the license on a form provided by the department;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-120__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>submit proof of continued qualification under
AS 08.62.100
to receive a marine pilot license;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-120__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide evidence of satisfactory completion of a physical examination by a licensed physician within 60 days before the date of renewal of the license;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-120__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>submit proof satisfactory to the board that the person has
(A) engaged in piloting vessels subject to this chapter in the marine pilotage region for which the license is to be renewed during at least 120 days in the licensing period immediately preceding the licensing period for which renewal is sought; or
(B) completed the minimum number of familiarization trips required by the board for renewal of a marine pilot license for a marine pilotage region for which the license is to be renewed.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-120__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board shall establish criteria for the renewal of a deputy marine pilot license.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-62-130">
            <num>08.62.130</num>
            <heading>Lapsed license.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-62-130__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board shall reinstate a lapsed marine pilot license if, in addition to complying with the requirements of
AS 08.01.100</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-130__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p> (c) and
AS 08.62.120
, the pilot takes and passes a written and oral examination if the license has been lapsed one year or more.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-130__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board shall establish criteria for reinstatement of a lapsed deputy marine pilot license.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-62-140">
            <num>08.62.140</num>
            <heading>Fees.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-62-140__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall set fees under
AS 08.01.065
for applications, licenses, agent registrations, investigations, audits, and training.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-140__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The fee for an application for an exemption under
AS 08.62.180</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-140__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>from the mandatory pilotage requirement of this chapter is $250 plus $50 for each whole foot in overall length of the vessel that exceeds 65 feet.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-62-150">
            <num>08.62.150</num>
            <heading>Denial, revocation, or suspension.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-62-150__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board shall impose a disciplinary sanction on a person licensed under this chapter when the board finds that the person</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-150__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is incompetent in the performance of pilotage duties;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-150__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is chemically impaired;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-150__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>illegally possesses, uses, or sells narcotic or hallucinogenic drugs;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-150__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>makes a false statement to obtain a license;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-150__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>violates a provision of this chapter or a regulation adopted under this chapter;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-150__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is guilty of misconduct during the course of employment;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-150__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has had the person's United States Coast Guard pilot license conditioned, suspended, or revoked; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-150__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>charges, collects, or receives an amount for pilotage services that is different from the rate adopted under
AS 08.62.046
or the rate agreed to under
AS 08.62.175</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-150__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>by the pilot organization of which the person is a member.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-150__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 4 ch 60 SLA 1987.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-62-155">
            <num>08.62.155</num>
            <heading>Disciplinary sanctions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-62-155__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board may take disciplinary action against a person licensed under this chapter under
AS 08.01.075
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-155__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board may impose a civil fine not to exceed $5,000 on a marine pilot organization recognized by the board if the organization violates this chapter or a regulation adopted under this chapter. The board may also suspend or revoke the recognition of a pilot organization that fails to comply with its articles, bylaws, and rules, so as to no longer satisfy the minimum standards for recognition by the board.
Article 3. Miscellaneous Provisions.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-62-157">
            <num>08.62.157</num>
            <heading>Duties of licensed pilots.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-62-157__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person licensed under this chapter has a primary duty to safely navigate vessels under the pilot's direction and control and to protect life and property and the marine environment while engaged in the provision of pilot services.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-157__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person licensed under this chapter shall report to the appropriate authority all violations of a federal or state pilotage law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-62-160">
            <num>08.62.160</num>
            <heading>Mandatory employment of licensed pilots.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.62.160.   Mandatory employment of licensed pilots.
A vessel subject to this chapter navigating the inland or coastal water of or adjacent to the state as determined by the board in regulation shall employ a pilot holding a valid license under this chapter. The board shall define the mandatory pilotage water of the state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-62-163">
            <num>08.62.163</num>
            <heading>Pilots as independent contractors.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-62-163__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Pilots licensed under this chapter are independent contractors and may not be employed as an employee of the owner or operator of a vessel subject to this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-163__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The owner or operator of a vessel subject to this chapter may not employ a person licensed under this chapter as an employee.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-62-165">
            <num>08.62.165</num>
            <heading>Limitation of liability.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-62-165__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A pilot licensed under this chapter is not liable for damages in excess of $250,000 per incident for damages or loss occurring as a result of the error, omission, fault, or neglect of the pilot in performing pilotage services, except that the limitation does not apply in a case where</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-165__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the pilot is either grossly negligent or guilty of wilful misconduct; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-165__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the error, omission, fault, or neglect of the pilot constitutes an act for which the board shall impose a disciplinary sanction under
AS 08.62.150</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-165__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing in this section exempts a vessel, a vessel's cargo, or the owner or operator of a vessel or cargo from liability for damage or loss caused by the vessel, the vessel's cargo, or the owner or operator of the vessel or cargo to the vessel, the vessel's cargo, another person, or other property on the ground that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-165__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the vessel was piloted by a pilot licensed under this chapter; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-165__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the damage or loss occurred as a result of the error, omission, fault, or neglect of a pilot licensed under this chapter.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-165__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An organization of pilots is not liable for claims arising from acts or omissions of a pilot who is a member of the organization or for acts or omissions of another organization of pilots that relate to pilotage of a vessel. A pilot is not liable, directly or as a member of an organization of pilots, for claims arising from acts or omissions of another pilot or organization of pilots that relate to pilotage of a vessel. This subsection does not apply to acts or omissions relating to the ownership or operation of pilot boats or the transportation of pilots to and from a vessel to be piloted.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-62-170">
            <num>08.62.170</num>
            <heading>Pilot's lien for compensation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.62.170.   Pilot's lien for compensation.
Each vessel, its tackle, apparel, and furniture and the owner of the vessel are jointly and severally liable for the compensation of a pilot employed on the vessel and the pilot has a lien on the vessel, the vessel's tackle, apparel, and furniture for the pilot's compensation.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-62-175">
            <num>08.62.175</num>
            <heading>Regional marine pilot organizations.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-62-175__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To the extent permitted under federal and state law, persons licensed under this chapter may form organizations of pilots within each pilotage region established by the board.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-175__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board shall recognize pilot organizations that satisfy the minimum standards established by the board by regulation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-175__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A pilot organization recognized by the board shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-175__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>promote a safe and reliable system of marine pilotage for the region in which the organization is recognized;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-175__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide for the dispatch of pilots who are members of the organization;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-175__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>adopt and revise rates for the provision of pilotage services not covered by an agreement under (e) of this section;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-175__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>subject to the membership application and approval provisions contained in the articles and bylaws of the organization, be open to membership by all persons licensed under this chapter to pilot vessels in the pilotage region in which the organization is recognized;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-175__subsec_c__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>operate or participate in a training program for pilots and deputy pilots that is approved by the board; a training program for deputy pilots may include a deputy marine pilot apprenticeship program approved by the board;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-175__subsec_c__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>cooperate with and assist the board in implementing this chapter;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-175__subsec_c__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>by February 1 of each year, submit a report to the board that includes information on the status of training and apprenticeship programs, the number of members of the pilot organization who are state residents, and other information requested by the board.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-175__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A pilot organization recognized by the board may not begin operating until the articles, bylaws, and rules of the pilot organization are approved by the board on the basis of</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-175__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>uniform and nondiscriminatory application of the articles, bylaws, and rules to marine pilots and deputy marine pilots licensed under this chapter and trainees for marine pilot licenses;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-175__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>compliance with applicable laws; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-175__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>effectiveness in
(A) promoting an efficient, reliable, and professional marine pilotage system in the region;
(B) maintaining a sufficient number of qualified pilots available for dispatch to serve the needs of vessels visiting the region during each hour of the day and each day of the year to the extent that it is reasonably possible given the size of the membership of the pilot organization;
(C) promoting training programs for marine pilots and deputy marine pilots that are approved by the board.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-175__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A pilot organization recognized by the board may enter into agreements with the master, owner, operator, or agent of a master, owner, or operator, of a vessel concerning the terms and conditions under which the pilot organization will provide pilotage services.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-175__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A pilot organization recognized by the board shall dispatch a person who is licensed under this chapter and who is a member of the organization to provide pilotage services upon the request of a representative of a vessel required to employ a pilot under
AS 08.62.160
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-62-180">
            <num>08.62.180</num>
            <heading>Exemptions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-62-180__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This chapter does not apply to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-180__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>vessels subject to federal pilot requirements under 46 U.S.C. 8502 except as provided in
AS 08.62.185
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-180__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>fishing vessels, including fish processing and fish tender vessels, registered in the United States or in British Columbia, Canada;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-180__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>vessels propelled by machinery and not more than 65 feet in length over deck, except tugboats and towboats propelled by steam;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-180__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>vessels of United States registry of less than 300 gross tons and towboats of United States registry and vessels owned by the State of Alaska, engaged exclusively
(A) on the rivers of Alaska; or
(B) in the coastwise trade on the west or north coast of the United States including Alaska and Hawaii, and including British Columbia, Yukon Territory, and Northwest Territories, Canada;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-180__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>vessels of Canada, built in Canada and manned by Canadian citizens, engaged in frequent trade between
(A) British Columbia and Southeastern Alaska on the inside water of Southeastern Alaska south of 59 degrees, 29 minutes North latitude, if reciprocal exemptions are granted by Canada to vessels owned by the State of Alaska and those of United States registry; or
(B) northern Alaska north of 68 degrees, 7 minutes North latitude and Yukon Territory or Northwest Territories;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-180__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>pleasure craft of United States registry;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-180__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>pleasure craft of foreign registry of 65 feet or less in overall length; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-180__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>vessels of the Canadian Navy or Canadian Coast Guard that have a home port in British Columbia, Canada, while navigating the inside water of Southeastern Alaska.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-180__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The operator of a pleasure craft of foreign registry of more than 65 feet overall length but less than 175 feet overall length may apply for an exemption from the pilotage requirement of this chapter. If an exemption is applied for and the fee prescribed under
AS 08.62.140</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-180__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>is paid, the board may issue the exemption to the operator of the vessel. The exemption is valid for one year from the date on which the exemption is issued. The application for an exemption must be submitted to the board at least 30 days before the vessel enters the state. The board shall approve or deny an application for the exemption within 10 working days after the application is received by the board. If the board does not approve or disapprove the application within 10 working days, the exemption is considered to be approved, and the board shall issue the exemption. The 10-day period for action by the board is suspended while the board is waiting for a response to a request by the board for additional information from the applicant. An exemption issued under this subsection may be revoked by the board if the vessel is not operated in a manner that is appropriate to protect human life, property, and the marine environment or if the vessel does not comply with all applicable local, state, and federal laws. The exemption must remain on the vessel while the vessel is in state water. An exemption issued under this subsection does not exempt a vessel from the requirement to employ a pilot licensed under this chapter while the vessel is in Wrangell Narrows or in the water between Chatham Strait and Sitka via Peril Strait.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-180__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The operator of a pleasure craft of foreign registry of more than 65 feet overall length but not more than 125 feet overall length that has received an exemption under (b) of this section shall proceed upon initial entry into state water to the first port of call to receive navigational and safety information from an agent registered under
AS 08.62.040
(a)(3) who is employed by the operator of the vessel. The navigational and safety information provided by the agent must be approved by the marine pilot coordinator and annually reviewed, revised, and approved as appropriate by the board at its spring meeting.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-180__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The operator of a pleasure craft of foreign registry of more than 125 feet overall length but less than 175 feet overall length that has received an exemption under (b) of this section shall employ a pilot licensed under this chapter from initial entry into compulsory pilotage water of the state to the first port of call. The marine pilot shall provide navigational and safety information relating to the pilotage region to the operator of the vessel.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-180__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In (b)  (d) of this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-180__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for hire means for consideration contributed as a condition of carriage on a vessel, whether directly or indirectly flowing to the owner, charterer, operator, agent, or other person having an interest in the vessel;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-62-180__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>pleasure craft means a vessel that does not carry passengers or freight for hire.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-62-185">
            <num>08.62.185</num>
            <heading>Certain licensed pilots required for oil tankers.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-62-185__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Any oil tanker, whether enrolled or registered, of 50,000 dead weight tons or greater, shall, when navigating in state water beyond Alaska pilot stations employ a pilot licensed by the state under this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-185__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The pilot required in (a) of this section shall control the vessel during all docking operations.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-62-187">
            <num>08.62.187</num>
            <heading>Registration of agents required.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.62.187.   Registration of agents required.
A person may not act as an agent of a vessel subject to this chapter unless the person's name appears on the register of agents kept under
AS 08.62.040
(a)(3).</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-62-190">
            <num>08.62.190</num>
            <heading>Penalties.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-62-190__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A master or owner of a vessel required by this chapter to employ a licensed pilot who fails to do so when a licensed pilot is available, unless the perils or hazards of the sea prevent the employment of a pilot, is guilty of a misdemeanor and, upon conviction, is punishable by a fine of not less than $5,000 nor more than $15,000 for the first offense and not less than $10,000 nor more than $30,000 for the second offense.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-190__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who violates any other provision of this chapter or a regulation adopted under this chapter is guilty of a misdemeanor and, upon conviction, is punishable by a fine of not less than $1,000 nor more than $5,000.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-62-190__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of (a) of this section, the board shall define by regulation the phrase when a licensed pilot is available.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-62-900">
            <num>08.62.900</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.62.900.   Definitions.
In this chapter,
(1) board means the Board of Marine Pilots;
(2) commissioner means the commissioner of the Department of Commerce, Community, and Economic Development;
(3) department means the Department of Commerce, Community, and Economic Development;
(4) pilot means a person licensed under this chapter as a pilot or a deputy pilot;
(5) vessel means all vessels not exempt under
AS 08.62.180
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-62-990">
            <num>08.62.990</num>
            <heading>Short title.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.62.990.   Short title.
This chapter may be cited as the Alaska Marine Pilotage Act.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>