<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-3/chapter-58"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-3/chapter-58"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="3.58"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-3/chapter-58/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-3/chapter-58/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-3/chapter-58/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-3/chapter-58/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_3">
        <num>3</num>
        <heading>Agriculture, Animals, and Food</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_3__chp_58">
          <num>58</num>
          <heading>Organic Food and Agricultural Products</heading>
          <section eId="sec_03-58-010">
            <num>03.58.010</num>
            <heading>Prohibition.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 03.58.010.   Prohibition.
A person may not sell, offer for sale, represent, or label a raw or processed agricultural product, including ingredients, as organic unless the product has been produced, handled, and certified under 7 U.S.C. 65016522, as amended, or under the state organic certification program established under
AS 03.58.015
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_03-58-015">
            <num>03.58.015</num>
            <heading>State organic certification program.</heading>
            <subsection eId="03-58-015__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may establish a state organic certification program for producers and handlers of agricultural products within the state that meets the requirements for approval under 7 U.S.C. 6501  6522, as amended.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="03-58-015__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may apply under 7 U.S.C. 6514, as amended, for accreditation as a certifying agent under 7 U.S.C. 6501  6522, as amended.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_03-58-020">
            <num>03.58.020</num>
            <heading>Disclosure.</heading>
            <subsection eId="03-58-020__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (b) of this section, a person may not sell food represented as organic food unless the name and address of the producer of the food are displayed with the food. If the food is not displayed at the purchase site, a written statement with the name and address of the producer must be given to the purchaser unless the name and address are identified on a package containing the purchased food. This subsection does not apply to a sale for consumption on the premises.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="03-58-020__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Advertising for the mail order sale of food represented as organic food must include the name and address of the producer of the food.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_03-58-030">
            <num>03.58.030</num>
            <heading>Sworn statement of compliance.</heading>
            <subsection eId="03-58-030__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A producer may not sell to a vendor food represented as organic food unless before the sale the producer provides the vendor with a sworn statement that the producer has grown, raised, or otherwise produced the food in compliance with
AS 03.58.010
. If a producer sells the food to the same vendor more than one time during a calendar year, one statement for the calendar year is sufficient to comply with this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="03-58-030__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 7 ch 64 SLA 2003.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_03-58-040">
            <num>03.58.040</num>
            <heading>Records.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 03.58.040.   Records.
A person who sells food represented as organic food shall maintain the records relating to this chapter that the department reasonably requires and shall furnish them to the department when requested by the department.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_03-58-050">
            <num>03.58.050</num>
            <heading>Regulations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 03.58.050.   Regulations.
The department may adopt regulations under
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act) to carry out this chapter, including regulations to establish reasonable fees for services provided by the department.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_03-58-060">
            <num>03.58.060</num>
            <heading>Enforcement.</heading>
            <subsection eId="03-58-060__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the department determines that a person is violating a provision of this chapter, or a regulation adopted under this chapter, the department shall order the person to stop the violation and to refrain from future violations.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="03-58-060__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a person violates this chapter or a regulation adopted under this chapter, the person is liable to the state for</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="03-58-060__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a civil fine established by the department by regulation plus the state's estimated costs of investigating and taking appropriate administrative and enforcement actions for the violation, including attorney fees;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="03-58-060__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an additional civil penalty of three times the value of the product knowingly sold in violation of this chapter.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="03-58-060__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The provisions of this section are in addition to the remedies available under
AS 45.50.471
 45.50.561 and federal statute and regulation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_03-58-065">
            <num>03.58.065</num>
            <heading>Applicability.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 03.58.065.   Applicability.
This chapter does not apply to meat, fish, or poultry.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>