<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-15/chapter-07"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-15/chapter-07"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="15.07"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-15/chapter-07/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-15/chapter-07/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-15/chapter-07/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-15/chapter-07/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_15">
        <num>15</num>
        <heading>Elections</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_15__chp_07">
          <num>07</num>
          <heading>Registration of Voters</heading>
          <section eId="sec_15-07-010">
            <num>15.07.010</num>
            <heading>Who may vote.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.07.010.   Who may vote.
The precinct election officials at any election shall allow a person to vote whose name is on the official registration list for that precinct and who is qualified under
AS 15.05
. A person whose name is not on the official registration list shall be allowed to vote a questioned ballot.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-07-030">
            <num>15.07.030</num>
            <heading>Who may register.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-07-030__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who has the qualifications of a voter as set out in
AS 15.05.010</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-030__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p> (3) or who will have the qualifications at the succeeding primary or general election is entitled to be registered as a voter in the precinct in which the person resides.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-030__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person qualified under
AS 15.05.011
to vote by absentee ballot in a federal election is entitled to be registered as a voter in the house district in which the person resided immediately before departure from the United States.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-07-040">
            <num>15.07.040</num>
            <heading>Time for registration.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.07.040.   Time for registration.
A person who is qualified under
AS 15.05.010
(1)  (3) is entitled to register at any time throughout the year except that a person under 18 years of age may register at any time within 90 days immediately preceding the person's 18th birthday.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-07-050">
            <num>15.07.050</num>
            <heading>Manner of registration; party affiliation.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-07-050__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Registration may be made</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-050__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in person before a registration official or through a voter registration agency;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-050__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>by another individual on behalf of the voter if the voter has executed a written general power of attorney or a written special power of attorney authorizing that other individual to register the voter;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-050__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>by mail;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-050__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>by facsimile transmission, scanning, or another method of electronic transmission that the director approves; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-050__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>by completing a permanent fund dividend application under
AS 43.23.015
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-050__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (c) of this section, only the voter or the individual authorized by the voter in a written power of attorney under (a) of this section may mark the voter's choice of party affiliation on the voter registration application form.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-050__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may supply a voter registration application form with a political party or group affiliation indicated to a voter only if the voter is already registered as affiliated with the political party or group indicated.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-07-055">
            <num>15.07.055</num>
            <heading>Voter registration agencies.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-07-055__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The following agencies are designated voter registration agencies:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-055__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the administrative component of the Department of Administration that administers motor vehicle and driver's license laws;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-055__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>divisions of the Department of Health that provide public assistance through the food stamp program, Medicaid program, Special Supplemental Food Program for Women, Infants, and Children (WIC), and Alaska temporary assistance program;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-055__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the division of the Department of Commerce, Community, and Economic Development that is responsible for municipal and regional assistance programs; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-055__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>all recruitment offices of the armed forces of the United States located in Alaska.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-055__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The director shall designate state-funded agencies that primarily provide services to persons with disabilities as voter registration agencies.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-055__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The director may designate other state or local agencies as voter registration agencies. The director may designate a federal or nongovernmental office as a voter registration agency with the agreement of that office.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-055__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A voter registration agency shall distribute voter registration materials, assist applicants in completing voter registration forms, and accept and transmit completed voter registration forms to the director in accordance with regulations adopted by the director to comply with 42 U.S.C. 1973gg (National Voter Registration Act of 1993) and other requirements of federal law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-055__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The director shall enter into an agreement with the Department of Administration, the Department of Corrections, and the Department of Revenue to match identifying information provided by a voter with existing identification records</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-055__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>maintained by the administrative component of the Department of Administration that administers motor vehicle and driver's license laws, by the administrative component of the Department of Corrections that issues identification cards, and by the administrative component of the Department of Revenue that administers the permanent fund dividend laws; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-055__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>bearing the same identifying number, name, and date of birth provided on the registration.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-07-060">
            <num>15.07.060</num>
            <heading>Required registration information.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-07-060__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each applicant who requests registration or reregistration shall supply the following information:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-060__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the applicant's name and sex;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-060__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if issued, the applicant's State of Alaska driver's license number or State of Alaska identification card number, or the last four digits of the applicant's social security number;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-060__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the applicant's date of birth;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-060__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the applicant's Alaska residence address;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-060__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a statement of whether the applicant has previously been registered to vote in another jurisdiction, and, if so, the jurisdiction and the address of the previous registration;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-060__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a declaration that the applicant will be 18 years of age or older within 90 days after the date of registration;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-060__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a declaration that the applicant is a citizen of the United States;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-060__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the date of application;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-060__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the applicant's signature or mark;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-060__subsec_a__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>any former name under which the applicant was registered to vote in the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-060__subsec_a__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an attestation that the information provided by the applicant in (1)  (10) of this subsection is true; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-060__subsec_a__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a certification that the applicant understands that a false statement on the application may make the applicant subject to prosecution for a misdemeanor under this title or
AS 11
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-060__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the applicant has been previously registered to vote in another jurisdiction, the director shall notify the chief elections officer in that jurisdiction that the applicant has registered to vote in Alaska and request that that jurisdiction cancel the applicant's voter registration there.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-060__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each applicant who requests registration in person before a registration official shall exhibit one form of identification to the official, including a driver's license, state identification card, current and valid photo identification, birth certificate, passport, or hunting or fishing license. A registration official who knows the identity of the applicant may waive the identification requirement.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-060__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the applicant requests reregistration, the applicant shall supply under oath any former name under which the applicant was registered to vote in the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-060__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For an applicant requesting initial registration by mail, by facsimile or other electronic transmission approved by the director under
AS 15.07.050
, or by completing a permanent fund dividend application, the director shall verify the information provided in compliance with (a)(2) and (3) of this section through state agency records described in
AS 15.07.055
(e). If the applicant cannot comply with the requirement of (a)(2) of this section because the applicant has not been issued any of the listed numbers, the applicant may instead submit a copy of one of the following forms of identification: a driver's license, state identification card, current and valid photo identification, birth certificate, passport, or hunting or fishing license.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-060__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If an applicant who requests registration cannot comply with the requirement of (a)(2) of this section because the applicant has not been issued any of the listed numbers, the division shall assign the applicant a unique identifying number.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-07-064">
            <num>15.07.064</num>
            <heading>Information required for voter registration.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-07-064__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A voter requesting registration or reregistration shall provide the director with sufficient information to determine</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-064__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the location of the residence of the voter within the district;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-064__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the precinct in which the voter is qualified to vote;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-064__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the other local or regional election jurisdictions in which the voter is eligible to vote.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-064__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In determining the sufficiency of the registration information provided by the voter in an application to register, the director may consider</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-064__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>whether the voter is applying in person, by mail from a location within the state, or by mail from a location outside the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-064__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the location, size, or density of the population within the municipality, established village, or geographic area in which the voter claims residence;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-064__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>whether the municipality, established village, or geographic area has been divided into precincts or local or regional election subdivisions;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-064__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>whether specific locations within the municipality, established village, or geographic area have been identified by street name, subdivisions, or other commonly known official descriptions; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-064__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>other circumstances considered significant by the director.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-064__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A voter requesting registration in a municipality or established village that has been divided into more than one precinct or that includes more than one section of a local or regional election subdivision shall provide the director with information that describes the location of the residence of the voter.  In this subsection, the use of a post office box, a postal service center box, a rural route number, general delivery, or other description identified only as a mailing address does not establish the residence of the voter.  In addition to the name of the municipality or established village, the voter shall provide the director with information that describes a physical location that may be</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-064__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a street name, including a number on the street if one exists;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-064__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a highway name and mile post number;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-064__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a mobile home court and space number;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-064__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a boat harbor and slip number;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-064__subsec_c__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name of a subdivision;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-064__subsec_c__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name of a building, institution, military or other reservation for which the location is fixed; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-064__subsec_c__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>another descriptive phrase from which the specific physical location of the residence of the voter within the municipality or established village can be determined.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-064__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The director is not required to request a voter who claims residence within a municipality or established village to provide the information required under (c) of this section if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-064__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the municipality or established village is entirely within a single precinct; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-064__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a local or regional election subdivision is not divided into sections within the boundaries of the municipality or the area of the established village.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-064__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The director shall review the information contained within an application by a voter for registration. The director may not reject an application of a voter who qualifies under (d) of this section because the voter provided information in excess of that required to establish qualifications, including excess information qualifying as a mailing address. The director may consider an application for registration within a municipality or established village described in (d) of this section to comply with law based on other information contained in the application, including evidence that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-064__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the application was made in person before a voting registrar, election official, or absentee voting official appointed to serve in the municipality or established village;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-064__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the application of a voter registering by mail was postmarked by the postal official in the municipality or established village; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-064__subsec_e__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>other information contained in the application does not negate the presumption of residency provided under (a) of this section.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-064__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A voter who resides in a building, institution, military or other reservation may establish residency for voting purposes by naming that place instead of naming a municipality or established village.  In this subsection the use of a post office box, a postal service center box, a rural route number, general delivery, or other description qualifying as a mailing address does not establish the residence of the voter.  The director is not required to request a voter who claims residence by naming the building, institution, military or other reservation to provide the information required under (c) of this section if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-064__subsec_f__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the physical location of the place named in the application is fixed; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-064__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the place named in the application is contained within the boundaries of a single precinct.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-064__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (a)  (f) of this section, the director may substitute a mailing address provided by the voter for the permanent fund dividend program under
AS 43.23
as the mailing address for the voter on the registration records of the director under procedures specified in regulations of the director if necessary to maintain accuracy of voting registration records.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-064__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, established village means an unincorporated community that is in</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-064__subsec_h__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the unorganized borough and that has 25 or more permanent residents; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-064__subsec_h__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an organized borough, has 25 or more permanent residents, and
(A) is on a road system and is located more than 50 miles outside the boundary limits of a unified municipality, or
(B) is not on a road system and is located more than 15 miles outside the boundary limits of a unified municipality.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-07-070">
            <num>15.07.070</num>
            <heading>Procedure for registration.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-07-070__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The director may adopt regulations under
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act) relating to the registration of voters consistent with the requirements of this section and federal law, including  42 U.S.C. 1973gg (National Voter Registration Act of 1993).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-070__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To register by mail or by facsimile, scanning, or other electronic transmission approved by the director under
AS 15.07.050
, the director, the area election supervisor, or a voter registration agency shall furnish, at no cost to the voter, forms prepared by the director on which the registration information required under
AS 15.07.060
shall be inserted by the voter, by a person on behalf of the voter if that person is designated to act on behalf of the voter in a power of attorney, or by a person on behalf of the voter if the voter is physically incapacitated. The director may require proof of identification of the applicant as required by regulations adopted by the director under
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act). Upon receipt and approval of the completed registration forms, the director or the election supervisor shall forward to the voter an acknowledgment, and the voter's name shall immediately be placed on the master register. If the registration is denied, the voter shall immediately be informed in writing that registration was denied and the reason for denial. When identifying information has been provided by the voter as required by this chapter, the election supervisor shall forward to the voter a registration card.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-070__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The names of persons submitting completed registration forms by mail that are postmarked at least 30 days before the next election, or submitting completed registration forms by facsimile or other electronic transmission approved by the director under
AS 15.07.050
that are received at least 30 days before the next election, shall be placed on the official registration list for that election. If a registration form received by mail less than 30 days before an election does not have a legible and dated postmark, the name of the person submitting the form shall be placed on the official registration list for that election if the form was signed and dated by the person at least 30 days before the election and if the form is received by the director or election supervisor at least 25 days before the election. The name of a person submitting a completed registration form by mail or by facsimile or other electronic transmission that does not meet the applicable requirements of this subsection may not be placed on the official registration list for that election but shall be placed on the master register after that election.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-070__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Qualified voters may register in person before a registration official or through a voter registration agency at any time throughout the year, except that a person registering within 30 days preceding an election is not eligible to vote at that election. Upon receipt and approval of the registration forms, the director or the election supervisor shall forward to the voter an acknowledgment in the form of a registration card, and the voter's name shall immediately be placed on the master register. Names of persons registering 30 or more days before an election shall be placed on the official registration list for that election.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-070__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 38 ch 116 SLA 1972.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-070__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Incomplete or inaccurate registration forms may not be accepted. A person who submitted an incomplete or inaccurate registration form may register by reexecuting and resubmitting a registration form in person, by mail, or by facsimile or other electronic transmission approved by the director under
AS 15.07.050
. The requirements of (c) or (d) of this section apply to a registration form resubmitted under this subsection. Notwithstanding the foregoing, an application made under
AS 43.23.015
that contains the information required by
AS 15.07.060
(a)(1)  (4) and (7)  (9), and an attestation that such information is true, shall not be deemed an incomplete registration form and shall be accepted in accordance with
AS 15.07.070
(i).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-070__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The director shall provide voter registration forms prepared under (b) of this section to voter registration agencies designated under
AS 15.07.055
for distribution to the public.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-070__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The director shall design the form of the voter's certificate appearing on the envelope that is used for voting an absentee in-person or questioned ballot so that all information required for registration by
AS 15.07.060</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-070__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>may be obtained from a voter who votes an absentee in-person or questioned ballot. If the voter voting an absentee in-person or questioned ballot has completed all information on the voter registration portion of the absentee in-person or questioned ballot voter's certificate, the director shall place the name of the voter on the official registration list.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-070__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The division shall register voters who submit an application to receive a permanent fund dividend in accordance with (j)  (m) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-070__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The division shall cooperate with the Department of Revenue under
AS 43.23.101
to ensure that the permanent fund dividend application form furnished by the Department of Revenue under
AS 43.23.015
allows an applicant, a person who is designated in a power of attorney to act on behalf of an applicant, or a person acting on behalf of a physically disabled applicant to submit voter registration information required under
AS 15.07.060
(a)(1)  (4) and (7)  (9), and an attestation that such information is true. The director may require proof of identification of the applicant, if not already in the Department of Revenue's possession, as required by regulations adopted by the director under
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-070__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon receipt of the registration information, the director shall, as soon as practicable and in accordance with a schedule established by the director by rule, notify by United States mail and any other means authorized by the director, each applicant not already registered to vote at the address provided in the applicant's application</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-070__subsec_k__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>of the processes to
(A) decline to be registered as a voter;
(B)  maintain an existing voter registration or be newly registered at a valid place of residence not provided in the applicant's application; and
(C)  adopt a political party affiliation; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-070__subsec_k__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>that failure to respond to the notification shall constitute the applicant's consent to cancel any registration to vote in another jurisdiction.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-070__subsec_l">
              <num>(l)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If an applicant does not decline to be registered as a voter within 30 calendar days after the director issues the notification, the application under
AS 43.23.015
will constitute a completed registration form. The name of the applicant shall be placed on the master register if the director determines that the person is qualified to vote under
AS 15.05.010
, and the director shall forward to the applicant a registration card. If registration is denied, the applicant shall immediately be informed in writing that registration was denied and the reason for denial.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-070__subsec_m">
              <num>(m)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Any person who is not eligible to vote and who becomes registered under this provision through human or mechanical error shall not be found on that basis to have had the intent to unlawfully register to vote.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-07-075">
            <num>15.07.075</num>
            <heading>Voters unaffiliated with a political party.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.07.075.   Voters unaffiliated with a political party.
The director shall consider a voter to be a voter registered as
(1) nonpartisan and without a preference for a political party if the voter registers as nonpartisan on a voter registration form;
(2) undeclared if the voter
(A) registers as undeclared on a voter registration form;
(B) fails to declare an affiliation with a political group or political party on a voter registration form; or
(C) declares an affiliation with an entity other than a political party or political group on a voter registration form; or
(3) other if the voter declares on a voter registration form an affiliation with a political group.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-07-081">
            <num>15.07.081</num>
            <heading>Registration officials.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.07.081.   Registration officials.
The director shall appoint one or more registration officials to serve in each precinct polling place in all elections during the hours the polling places are open. An election official appointed under
AS 15.10
may also serve as a registration official.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-07-090">
            <num>15.07.090</num>
            <heading>Voting after change of name; reregistration; amendment or transfer of registration.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-07-090__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A voter whose name is changed by marriage or court order may vote under the previous name, but a voter who desires to use a new name shall vote a questioned ballot.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-090__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A voter shall reregister if the voter's registration is cancelled as provided in
AS 15.07.130
. The reregistration is effective for the next election that occurs at least 30 days after the date of reregistration.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-090__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The director shall transfer the registration of a voter from one precinct to another within a house district when requested by the voter. The request shall be made 30 or more days before the election day. The director shall transfer the registration of a voter from one house district to another when requested by the voter. The voter must reside in the new house district for at least 30 days in order to vote.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-090__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who claims to be a registered voter, but for whom no evidence of registration in the precinct can be found, shall be granted the right to vote in the same manner as that of a questioned voter and the ballot shall be treated in the same manner. The ballot shall be considered to be a questioned ballot and shall be so designated. The director or the director's representative shall determine whether the voter is registered in the house district before counting the ballot. A voter who has failed to obtain a transfer as provided in (c) of this section shall vote a questioned ballot in the precinct in which the voter resides.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-07-100">
            <num>15.07.100</num>
            <heading>Registration officials.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-07-100__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A registration official shall be a qualified state voter and shall take an oath to honestly, faithfully, and promptly perform the duties of the office.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-100__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Training for registration officials shall be provided by the director.  On the completion of training, the director may require that officials demonstrate their competence by a test or other method.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-100__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A registration official serves at the pleasure of the director.  Each registration official shall be periodically evaluated by the director based on the completeness of the registration forms, timely filing of registration forms, and the voter registration activity attributed to the registration official.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-100__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A registration official shall transmit completed voter registration forms to the election supervisor within five days following completion by the voter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-07-120">
            <num>15.07.120</num>
            <heading>Custody of registers.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.07.120.   Custody of registers.
A master register shall at all times remain in the custody of the director. The person who is the area election supervisor shall likewise maintain a register of all voters within the precincts of the area house district that person supervises.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-07-125">
            <num>15.07.125</num>
            <heading>Official registration list.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-07-125__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or (d). A list of persons eligible to vote in each precinct at that election shall be prepared from the official registration list.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-07-127">
            <num>15.07.127</num>
            <heading>Preparation of master register.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.07.127.   Preparation of master register.
The director shall prepare both a statewide list and a list by precinct of the names and addresses of all persons whose names appear on the master register and their political party affiliation. Subject to the limitations of
AS 15.07.195
, any person may obtain a copy of the list, or a part of the list, or an electronic format containing both residence and mailing addresses of voters, by applying to the director and paying to the state treasury a fee as determined by the director.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-07-130">
            <num>15.07.130</num>
            <heading>Voter registration list maintenance.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-07-130__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Periodically, at times of the director's choosing, but no less frequently than in January of each calendar year, the director shall examine the master register maintained under
AS 15.07.120
and shall send, by nonforwardable mail to the voter's registration mailing address, a notice requesting address confirmation or correction to each voter</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-130__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>whose mail from the division has been returned to the division in the two years immediately preceding the examination of the register;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-130__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>who has not contacted the division in the two years immediately preceding the examination of the register; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-130__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>who has not voted or appeared to vote in the two general elections immediately preceding the examination of the register.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-130__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a registered voter has not, within the preceding four calendar years, contacted the division and has neither voted nor appeared to vote in a local, regional school board, primary, special, or general election during the last four calendar years and a notice sent to the voter under (a) of this section was returned as undeliverable, the voter shall be advised by a notice sent by forwardable mail to the voter's last known address that registration will be inactivated unless the voter responds to the notice no later than 45 days after the date of the notice sent under this section. The director shall maintain on the master register the name of a voter whose registration is inactivated. The director shall cancel a voter's inactive registration in accordance with the procedures set out in 42 U.S.C. 1973gg-6 (sec. 8, National Voter Registration Act of 1993) after the second general election that occurs after the registration becomes inactive if the voter does not contact the division or vote or appear to vote.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-130__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The director shall obtain from the bureau of vital statistics a certified list of all residents over 18 years of age who have died or who have been presumptively declared dead. Promptly after receipt of each list, but, in any event, at least once each month, the director shall cancel the registration of all deceased voters.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-130__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The notice sent under (b) of this section must include a postage prepaid and pre-addressed return card on which the voter may state the voter's current address. The notice must indicate</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-130__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>that the voter should return the card not later than 45 days after the date of the notice if the voter did not change residence;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-130__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>that failure to return the card by the 45-day deadline could result in removal of the voter's name from the official registration list for a subsequent election;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-130__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>that the voter's registration will be cancelled if the voter does not contact the division during, or vote or appear to vote in an election held during, the period beginning on the date of the notice and ending on the day after the last day of the fourth calendar year that occurs after the date of notice; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-130__subsec_d__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>how the voter can continue to be eligible to vote if the voter has changed residence.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-130__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of (b) and (d) of this section, a voter appears to vote if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-130__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the voter is present at a polling place or at an absentee voting station at a time when the polling place or absentee voting station is operating, for the purpose of casting a vote;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-130__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the voter applies to the division to obtain an absentee ballot; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-130__subsec_e__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in an election conducted by mail under
AS 15.20.800
, a voter who has not received a ballot by mail makes a timely request to the division for a ballot.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-130__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For the purpose of this section, a voter contacts the division if the voter notifies the division of a change of address, responds to a notice sent under this section, signs a petition for a ballot measure, requests a new voter registration card, or otherwise communicates with the division other than to vote or register to vote.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-07-135">
            <num>15.07.135</num>
            <heading>Cancellation of registration of convicted persons.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-07-135__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The director shall make reasonable efforts to obtain the names of persons convicted of a felony involving moral turpitude. Promptly after receipt of evidence satisfactory to the director that a person has been convicted of a felony involving moral turpitude, the director shall cancel the registration of the person.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-135__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon presenting proof that a person whose registration was canceled under (a) of this section has been unconditionally discharged from custody, the person may register. The director shall make reasonable efforts to verify the unconditional discharge of persons applying for registration under this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-07-137">
            <num>15.07.137</num>
            <heading>Voting information from municipalities.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.07.137.   Voting information from municipalities.
Within 60 days after each election held in a municipality, the municipal clerk shall certify and send to the director the official registration list containing the names, residence addresses, and voter identification numbers of all persons voting in each precinct in that election. The names of the persons who voted in the municipal election shall be indicated on the official registration list sent to the director by the municipal clerk.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-07-140">
            <num>15.07.140</num>
            <heading>General administrative supervision by director.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.07.140.   General administrative supervision by director.
The director shall provide general administrative supervision over the registration and reregistration of voters. The director shall, no later than 120 days before any general election, arrange to have the list of registered voters in a usable electronic format provided free of charge to each political party. Upon request by the mayor or manager of a municipality, the director shall furnish registration information for all precincts all or part of which are within the boundaries of the local government unit.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-07-150">
            <num>15.07.150</num>
            <heading>Appeals from denial of registration.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.07.150.   Appeals from denial of registration.
When a person is refused registration by a registration official, the official shall at the time of the refusal give to the registration applicant, in writing, the reason or reasons for the refusal.  The person shall have the right to an immediate appeal to the area election supervisor, which appeal may be taken informally, and either verbally or in writing. When a voter is refused registration by an area election supervisor the action shall be reviewed by the superior court of the judicial district; the area election supervisor shall file a petition with the superior court for a judicial determination.  If the petition is filed within 45 days before the date of a statewide election, the petition shall be given precedence over other matters pending before the court.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-07-160">
            <num>15.07.160</num>
            <heading>Unlawful action.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-07-160__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in
AS 15.07.135
, a registration official may not refuse to register a person who is qualified to vote under provisions of
AS 15.05.010</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-160__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p> (3).</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-160__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person knowingly lacking the qualifications of a voter may not register under
AS 15.07.030
to vote.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-160__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 231 ch 100 SLA 1980.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-07-180">
            <num>15.07.180</num>
            <heading>Fees prohibited.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.07.180.   Fees prohibited.
A registration official may not accept a fee from an applicant applying for registration.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-07-190">
            <num>15.07.190</num>
            <heading>Violation ofAS 15.07.180.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.07.190.   Violation of
AS 15.07.180
.
A person who violates
AS 15.07.180
is guilty of a misdemeanor and upon conviction is punishable by imprisonment for not more than one year, or by a fine of not more than $1,000, or by both.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-07-195">
            <num>15.07.195</num>
            <heading>Certain information in voter registration records confidential.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-07-195__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The following information set out in state voter registration records is confidential and is not open to public inspection:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-195__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the voter's age or date of birth;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-195__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the voter's social security number, or any part of that number;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-195__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the voter's driver's license number;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-195__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the voter's voter identification number;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-195__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the voter's place of birth;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-195__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the voter's signature.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-195__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to the information in (a) of this section, a voter may elect in writing to keep the voter's residential address confidential and not open to public inspection if the voter provides a separate mailing address.  However, notwithstanding an election under this subsection, a voter's residential address may be disclosed to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-195__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a watcher appointed under
AS 15.10.170
and, in the case of a watcher appointed by an organization or group sponsoring or opposing an initiative, referendum, or recall group, authorized by the director;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-195__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an observer of a recount provided under
AS 15.20.440</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-195__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>by a candidate, political party, or organized group having a direct interest in the recount; or</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-195__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the subject of a recall election if the voter voted in the recall election.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-195__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding other provisions, and in compliance with federal law, information made confidential by this section may be released by the division</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-195__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to a local, state, or federal government agency, including to the child support services agency created in
AS 25.27.010
or the child support enforcement agency of another state; the agency receiving information under this paragraph may use the information only for governmental purposes authorized under law;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-195__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in compliance with a court order;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-195__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to a person holding a writ of execution against the person or property of the voter;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-195__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if the voter about whom information has been requested has provided written consent to the release; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-07-195__subsec_c__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to another state or an organized group of states for the purpose of ensuring the accuracy of the state's voter registration list prepared under
AS 15.07.125
and the eligibility of persons on the list to vote in state elections, if the other state or organized group of states maintains the confidentiality of the information using information security management policies and procedures that comply with
(A)  the information security standards of the International Organization for Standardization; or
(B)  a published information security standard used by the state and approved by the Department of Administration.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-07-195__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing in this section shall prohibit the release of a voter's voter ascension number if that information may be released under other provisions of law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-07-200">
            <num>15.07.200</num>
            <heading>Registration supervision.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.07.200.   Registration supervision.
The registration program is under the supervision of the director in accordance with
AS 15.10.105
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>