<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-28/chapter-33"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-28/chapter-33"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="28.33"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-28/chapter-33/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-28/chapter-33/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-28/chapter-33/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-28/chapter-33/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_28">
        <num>28</num>
        <heading>Motor Vehicles</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_28__chp_33">
          <num>33</num>
          <heading>Commercial Motor Vehicles</heading>
          <section eId="sec_28-33-030">
            <num>28.33.030</num>
            <heading>Operating a commercial motor vehicle while under the influence of an alcoholic beverage, inhalant, or controlled substance.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-33-030__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person commits the crime of operating a commercial motor vehicle while under the influence of an alcoholic beverage, inhalant, or controlled substance if the person operates a commercial motor vehicle</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-030__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>while under the influence of an alcoholic beverage, inhalant, or any controlled substance;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-030__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>when, as determined by a chemical test taken within four hours after the alleged offense was committed, there is 0.04 percent or more by weight of alcohol in the person's blood or 40 milligrams or more of alcohol per 100 milliliters of blood, or when there is 0.04 grams or more of alcohol per 210 liters of the person's breath; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-030__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>while under the combined influence of an alcoholic beverage, inhalant, and a controlled substance.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-33-030__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Operating a commercial motor vehicle while under the influence of an alcoholic beverage, inhalant, or controlled substance is a class A misdemeanor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-33-030__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The sentencing of a person convicted under this section shall be in accordance with the minimum periods of imprisonment, fines, rehabilitative treatment, and other provisions of
AS 28.35.030
, as if the person had been convicted of a violation of
AS 28.35.030
. For purposes of sentencing, convictions for operating a commercial motor vehicle while under the influence of an alcoholic beverage, inhalant, or controlled substance under this section, and for refusal to submit to a chemical test under
AS 28.35.032
, if arising out of a single transaction, are considered one previous conviction.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-33-031">
            <num>28.33.031</num>
            <heading>Implied consent for operators of commercial motor vehicles.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-33-031__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who operates a commercial motor vehicle in this state is considered to have given consent to a chemical test or tests</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-031__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>of the person's breath if lawfully arrested for an offense arising out of acts alleged to have been committed when the person was operating the commercial motor vehicle while under the influence of an alcoholic beverage, inhalant, or controlled substance; the test or tests may be administered at the direction of a law enforcement officer who has probable cause to believe that the person was operating a commercial motor vehicle while under the influence of an alcoholic beverage, inhalant, or controlled substance in violation of
AS 28.33.030
or
AS 28.35.030
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-031__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>of the person's breath and blood for the purpose of determining the alcoholic content of the person's breath and blood and is considered to have given consent to a chemical test or tests of the person's blood and urine for the purpose of determining the presence of controlled substances in the person's blood and urine if the person is involved in a motor vehicle accident that causes death or serious physical injury to another person; the test or tests may be administered at the direction of a law enforcement officer who has probable cause to believe that the person was operating a commercial motor vehicle that was involved in an accident causing death or serious physical injury to another person.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-33-031__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Refusal to submit to a chemical test authorized under this section is punishable under
AS 28.35.032
. A chemical test may be administered without consent under
AS 28.35.035
. A person who is disqualified as the result of department action under
AS 28.15.165
, following a test administered under this section, can obtain review of that action under
AS 28.15.166
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-33-031__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who operates a commercial motor vehicle is considered to have given consent to a preliminary breath test, at the direction of a law enforcement officer, for the purpose of determining the alcoholic content of the person's blood or breath. A law enforcement officer may administer a preliminary breath test if the officer has probable cause to believe that the person's ability to operate a commercial motor vehicle is impaired by the ingestion of alcoholic beverages and that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-031__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the commercial motor vehicle caused injury to person or property;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-031__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the person violated the provisions of
AS 28.33.130</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-33-031__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or violated the terms of an out-of-service order issued under
AS 28.33.130
; or</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-031__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the person unlawfully operated a commercial motor vehicle; in this paragraph, unlawfully means in violation of any federal, state, or municipal statute, regulation, or ordinance.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-33-031__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before administering a preliminary breath test under (c) of this section, the officer shall advise the person that refusal may be used against the person in a civil or criminal action arising out of the incident and that refusal is a misdemeanor. If the person refuses to submit to the test, the test may not be administered.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-33-031__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The result of the preliminary test under (c) of this section may be used by the law enforcement officer to determine whether the operator should be arrested. If an operator is arrested, the provisions of (a) of this section apply. The preliminary breath test authorized under (c) of this section is in addition to any chemical tests authorized under (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-33-031__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Refusal to submit to a preliminary breath test at the request of a law enforcement officer is a class B misdemeanor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-33-033">
            <num>28.33.033</num>
            <heading>Presumptions and chemical analysis of breath or blood.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-33-033__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon the trial of a civil or criminal action or proceedings arising out of acts alleged to have been committed by a person operating a commercial motor vehicle while under the influence of an alcoholic beverage in violation of
AS 28.33.030
, the following rules apply with regard to the amount of alcohol in the person's blood or breath at the time alleged:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-033__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if there was less than 0.04 percent by weight of alcohol in the person's blood, or less than 40 milligrams of alcohol per 100 milliliters of the person's blood, or less than 0.04 grams of alcohol per 210 liters of the person's breath, that fact does not give rise to a presumption that the person was or was not under the influence of an alcoholic beverage, but that fact may be considered with other competent evidence in determining whether the person was under the influence of an alcoholic beverage;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-033__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if there was 0.04 percent or more by weight of alcohol in the person's blood, or 40 milligrams or more of alcohol per 100 milliliters of the person's blood, or 0.04 grams or more of alcohol per 210 liters of the person's breath, it is presumed that the person was under the influence of an alcoholic beverage.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-33-033__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of this chapter, percent by weight of alcohol in the blood is based upon milligrams of alcohol per 100 milliliters of blood.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-33-033__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The provisions of (a) of this section may not be construed to limit the introduction of any other competent evidence bearing upon the question of whether the person was or was not under the influence of an alcoholic beverage.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-33-033__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The person tested may have a physician, or a qualified technician, chemist, registered or advanced practice registered nurse, or other qualified person of the person's own choosing administer a chemical test in addition to the test administered at the direction of a law enforcement officer. The failure or inability to obtain an additional test by a person does not preclude the admission of evidence relating to the test taken at the direction of a law enforcement officer; the fact that the person under arrest sought to obtain an additional test, and failed or was unable to do so, is likewise admissible in evidence.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-33-033__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon the request of the person who submits to a chemical test at the request of a law enforcement officer, full information concerning the test, including the results of it, shall be made available to the person or person's attorney.
Article 2. Commercial Vehicle Operators.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-33-100">
            <num>28.33.100</num>
            <heading>License to drive commercial motor vehicle.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-33-100__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not drive a commercial motor vehicle until the person applies for and is issued a license for that purpose under
AS 28.15.041
. The department may issue a</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-100__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>domiciled license to drive a commercial motor vehicle only if the applicant
(A) is at least 18 years of age, to operate in intrastate commerce, or at least 21 years of age, to operate in interstate commerce, except as provided in (f) of this section;
(B) has successfully completed all required driving tests and written and physical examinations;
(C) either does not have a driver's license issued by another jurisdiction or surrenders all driver's licenses issued by other jurisdictions; and
(D) is domiciled in this state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-100__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>non-domiciled license to drive a commercial motor vehicle if the applicant
(A)  is domiciled in</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-33-100__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>a foreign jurisdiction that meets the requirements set out in 49 C.F.R. 383.23(b)(1); or
(ii)  another state that meets the requirements set out in 49 C.F.R. 383.23(b)(2);
(B)  meets the applicable requirements set out in this subsection and 49 C.F.R. 383.71;
(C)  is at least 18 years of age, to operate in intrastate commerce, or at least 21 years of age, to operate in interstate commerce, except as provided in (f) of this section; and
(D)  has successfully completed all required driving tests and written and physical examinations.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-33-100__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to the information required under
AS 28.15.111
, a commercial driver's license shall include information determined by the United States Secretary of Transportation to be appropriate to identify the licensee.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-33-100__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who has been a state resident for 30 days or longer may not drive a commercial motor vehicle under the authority of a commercial driver's license issued by another jurisdiction.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-33-100__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The licensing requirements of this section are in addition to the requirements imposed on a school bus driver under
AS 28.15.046
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-33-100__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall disqualify a person for a period of 60 consecutive days, and shall reevaluate the person's application or license to drive a commercial motor vehicle, if the department determines that the person knowingly provided false information required under</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-100__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>this section or
AS 28.15
in an application to the department for a commercial driver's license; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-100__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>AS 28.33.110</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-33-100__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>in an application for employment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-33-100__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may authorize a person who is at least 18 years of age but under 21 years of age to operate a commercial motor vehicle in interstate commerce if the person</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-100__subsec_f__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>holds a valid commercial driver's license under (a) of this section; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-100__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is authorized to operate a commercial motor vehicle in interstate commerce under federal law.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-33-100__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A non-domiciled commercial driver's license must be marked with non-domiciled on the face of the document.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-33-100__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A non-domiciled commercial driver's license expires</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-100__subsec_h__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for an applicant under (a)(2)(A)(i) of this section, on the earlier of
(A) the expiration date determined by the United States Department of Homeland Security that is stated on the form required for the applicant under 49 C.F.R. 383.71(f)(2)(i); or
(B) one year from the date of issuance;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-100__subsec_h__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for an applicant under (a)(2)(A)(ii) of this section, one year from the date of issuance.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-33-100__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to the requirements under (a) of this section, the holder of a non-domiciled commercial driver's license shall notify the department of any adverse action taken by a foreign or domestic jurisdiction or governmental agency against the person's driving privileges as required by federal law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-33-110">
            <num>28.33.110</num>
            <heading>Notification requirements for drivers of commercial motor vehicles.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-33-110__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A driver of a commercial motor vehicle holding a commercial driver's license issued by the state who is convicted of violating a federal or state law or local ordinance relating to motor vehicle traffic control in this or another state, or a federal, provincial, territorial, or municipal law relating to motor vehicle traffic control in Canada, other than parking violations, shall notify the driver's employer, in writing, of the conviction within 30 days after the date of conviction.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-33-110__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A driver whose operating privilege is suspended, revoked, or canceled by a state, who loses the privilege to operate a commercial motor vehicle in a state for any period, or who is disqualified from operating a commercial motor vehicle for any period, shall notify the driver's employer of that fact before the end of the business day following the day the driver received notice of the suspension, revocation, cancellation, loss, or disqualification.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-33-110__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who applies for employment as a commercial motor vehicle driver shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-110__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide the person's prospective employer, at the time of application for employment, with the following information for the 10 years preceding the date of application:
(A) a list of the names and addresses of employers for which the applicant was a driver of a commercial motor vehicle;
(B) the dates between which the applicant drove for each employer;
(C) the reason for leaving each employer;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-110__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>certify that the information provided under this subsection is true and complete; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-110__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide additional information required by the employer.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-33-120">
            <num>28.33.120</num>
            <heading>Responsibilities of employers of commercial motor vehicle driver.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.33.120.   Responsibilities of employers of commercial motor vehicle driver.
An employer of a commercial motor vehicle driver
(1) shall require an applicant for employment to provide the information required under
AS 28.33.110
(c);
(2) may not knowingly allow, require, permit, assign, or authorize a driver to drive a commercial motor vehicle during a period in which
(A) the driver's license is suspended, revoked, or canceled by a state;
(B) the driver has lost the privilege to drive a commercial motor vehicle in a state;
(C) the driver has been disqualified from driving a commercial motor vehicle;
(D) the driver has more than one driver's license;
(E) the driver is not licensed to drive a commercial motor vehicle; or
(3) may not knowingly allow, require, permit, assign, or authorize the driver to operate a commercial motor vehicle in violation of a federal or state statute or regulation, or a local law or ordinance, relating to railroad-highway grade crossings.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-33-130">
            <num>28.33.130</num>
            <heading>Out-of-service orders.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-33-130__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not operate a commercial motor vehicle or be on duty</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-130__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if, within the preceding four hours, the person
(A) consumed or was under the influence of</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-33-130__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>an alcoholic beverage;
(ii) a controlled substance not prescribed by a physician; or
(iii) a controlled substance prescribed by a physician that might impair a person's ability to operate a commercial motor vehicle; or
(B) had any measurable alcohol concentration within the blood or breath or any detectable presence of alcohol;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-130__subsec_i__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>while in possession of an alcoholic beverage or a controlled substance not prescribed by a physician unless
(A) the alcoholic beverage or controlled substance is manifested and documented as part of an authorized shipment of cargo; or
(B) under
AS 04
, the alcoholic beverage may be legally served to passengers being carried for hire;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-130__subsec_i__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>after being placed out of service for violation of a regulation adopted under
AS 19.10.060</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-33-130__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or
AS 28.05.011
; or</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-130__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>with an invalid operator's or commercial operator's license.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-33-130__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An employer, or a peace officer, who has reasonable grounds to believe that a person has violated (a) of this section, shall immediately give the person a written notice ordering the person out of service. If it is not possible to issue a written out of service order, a verbal order may be issued. An employer may not knowingly allow, require, permit, assign, or authorize a person to operate a commercial motor vehicle or be on duty during a period in which</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-130__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the person has been ordered out of service under this section; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-130__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the person has violated (a) of this section, even if an out-of-service order has not been issued.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-33-130__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who is ordered out of service</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-130__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>may not operate a commercial motor vehicle or be on duty for 24 hours following issuance of the out-of-service order; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-130__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall report that fact, in writing,
(A) within 24 hours to the person's employer; and
(B) within 30 days to the department if the person possesses a commercial motor vehicle license.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-33-130__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, on duty means the period of time in which a person is</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-130__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>required by the person's employer to be ready to immediately operate a commercial motor vehicle, including time spent waiting to be assigned to operate a commercial motor vehicle;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-130__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>inspecting, servicing, or conditioning a commercial motor vehicle;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-130__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in or upon a commercial motor vehicle, except time spent resting in a sleeper berth;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-130__subsec_d__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>loading or unloading, or supervising the loading or unloading of, a commercial motor vehicle, or giving or receiving receipts for shipments loaded or unloaded;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-130__subsec_d__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>taking action, as required by state or federal law, following an accident involving a commercial motor vehicle; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-130__subsec_d__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>repairing or obtaining assistance for a disabled commercial motor vehicle.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-33-140">
            <num>28.33.140</num>
            <heading>Conviction resulting in disqualification from driving commercial vehicle.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-33-140__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to any court action or administrative action in this or any other jurisdiction, conviction of a person who holds or is required to have a commercial driver's license or commercial instruction permit of any of the following offenses is grounds for immediate disqualification from driving a commercial motor vehicle for the periods set out in this section:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-140__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>operating a commercial motor vehicle while under the influence of an alcoholic beverage, inhalant, or controlled substance in violation of
AS 28.33.030
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-140__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>refusal to submit to a chemical test in violation of
AS 28.35.032
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-140__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>operating a motor vehicle while under the influence of an alcoholic beverage, inhalant, or controlled substance in violation of
AS 28.35.030
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-140__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>leaving the scene of an accident in violation of
AS 28.35.060
, or failing to file, or providing false information in, an accident report in violation of
AS 28.35.110
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-140__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a felony under state or federal law that was facilitated because the person used a motor vehicle;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-140__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a serious traffic violation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-140__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>taking one of the following actions in violation of regulations adopted under
AS 19.10.060</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-33-140__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or
AS 28.05.011
:
(A) driving after being placed out of service; or
(B) operating a commercial vehicle that has been placed out of service;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-140__subsec_c__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>operating a commercial motor vehicle in violation of a federal or state statute or regulation, or a local law or ordinance, relating to railroad-highway grade crossings;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-140__subsec_c__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>operating a commercial motor vehicle while the driver's commercial motor vehicle license is suspended, revoked, or canceled, or the driver is disqualified;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-140__subsec_c__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>causing a fatality through the negligent operation, or operation in violation of a felony criminal law, of a commercial motor vehicle.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-33-140__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 31 ch 23 SLA 2007.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-33-140__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon a conviction by a court of a person of an offense described in (a)(6) of this section, the department shall disqualify that person from driving a commercial motor vehicle for not less than 60 days if the person has been previously convicted once, and 120 days if the person has been previously convicted more than once. The disqualification period under this subsection is in addition to any other previously imposed period of disqualification. As used in this subsection, previously convicted means having been convicted in this or another jurisdiction, within three years preceding the date of the present offense, of an offense described in (a)(6) of this section, or of another law or ordinance with substantially similar elements, arising out of a separate incident.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-33-140__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon conviction by a court of a person of an offense described in (a)(1)  (5), (9), or (10) of this section, the department shall disqualify that person from driving a commercial motor vehicle for not less than one year for a first offense, except that, if the offense was</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-140__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>facilitated by a commercial motor vehicle transporting a hazardous material that required that placards be placed on the vehicle under 49 U.S.C. 5101  5127, the period of disqualification is not less than three years;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-140__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a felony offense that involved the manufacture, distribution, or dispensing, or possession with intent to manufacture, distribute, or dispense, a controlled substance, the disqualification is for life and the license may not be reinstated under (g) of this section.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-33-140__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon conviction by a court of a person of an offense described in (a)(1)  (5), (9), or (10) of this section, the department shall disqualify that person from driving a commercial motor vehicle for life if the person has been previously convicted. As used in this subsection, previously convicted means having been convicted in this or another jurisdiction of an offense described in (a)(1)  (5), (9), or (10) of this section, or of another law or ordinance with substantially similar elements.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-33-140__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who is disqualified under this section may not obtain a limited license under
AS 28.15.201
to permit driving a commercial motor vehicle.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-33-140__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person disqualified for life under (e) of this section may apply to the department for reinstatement of a commercial driver's license if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-140__subsec_g__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the person has successfully completed an appropriate rehabilitation program satisfactory to the department;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-140__subsec_g__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the person has not committed a felony offense, or a misdemeanor offense involving operation of a motor vehicle, during the period of disqualification; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-140__subsec_g__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the person has undergone a minimum disqualification period of 10 years.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-33-140__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A disqualified driver reinstated under (g) of this section who is subsequently convicted of a disqualifying offense described in (a)(1)  (5) of this section is permanently disqualified for life and is ineligible to again apply for reinstatement under (g) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-33-140__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to the requirements of
AS 28.15.191
, a court that disqualifies a person from driving a commercial motor vehicle shall require the surrender of the license, and shall immediately forward the license to the department with the record of conviction and notification of the effective date of the disqualification. If the disqualification occurs by administrative action as described in (a) of this section, the person disqualified from driving shall surrender the license to the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-33-140__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon conviction by a court of a person of an offense described in (a)(7) of this section, the department shall disqualify that person from driving a commercial motor vehicle for the following periods: (1) if the person has not been previously convicted of violating an out-of-service order, not less than 180 days; (2) if the person has been previously convicted once of violating an out-of-service order, not less than two years; (3) if the person has been previously convicted more than once of violating an out-of-service order, not less than three years; (4) if the person operates a commercial motor vehicle transporting hazardous materials or a vehicle designed to transport 16 or more passengers, including the driver, in violation of an out-of-service order, not less than 180 days; (5) if the person has been previously convicted of operating a commercial motor vehicle transporting hazardous materials or a vehicle designed to transport 16 or more passengers, including the driver, in violation of an out-of-service order two or more times in separate incidents within a 10-year period, not less than three years. In this subsection, previously convicted means having been convicted in this or another jurisdiction of an offense described in (a)(7) of this section within 10 years preceding the date of the present offense.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-33-140__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon conviction by a court of a person of an offense described in (a)(8) of this section, the department shall disqualify that person from operating a commercial motor vehicle for the following periods: (1) if the person has not been previously convicted of violating a federal or state statute or regulation, or a local law or ordinance, relating to railroad-highway grade crossings, not less than 60 days; (2) if the person has been previously convicted once of violating a federal or state statute or regulation, or a local law or ordinance, relating to railroad-highway grade crossings, not less than 120 days; (3) if the person has been previously convicted more than once of a violation of a federal or state statute or regulation, or a local law or ordinance, relating to railroad-highway grade crossings, not less than one year. In this subsection, previously convicted means having been convicted in this or another jurisdiction of an offense described in (a)(8) of this section within three years proceeding the date of the present offense.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-33-140__subsec_l">
              <num>(l)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who operates a commercial motor vehicle whose driving is determined by the United States Department of Transportation to constitute an imminent hazard is subject to disqualification as specified by the department in regulation. The regulations adopted by the department under this subsection must be substantially similar to those set by the federal government.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-33-140__subsec_m">
              <num>(m)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who violates the standards for operating a commercial motor vehicle or who knowingly operates a commercial motor vehicle that has been placed out of service as set out by the department in regulation is subject to civil penalties established by the department in regulation. An employer who knowingly allows an employee to drive in violation of an out-of-service order or in violation of a railroad-highway grade crossing is subject to civil penalties as described in 49 U.S.C. 521(b) as established by the department in regulation. The department may adopt regulations under
AS 44.62
to implement this subsection. The regulations adopted under this subsection must be substantially similar to any applicable federal regulations. In this subsection, knowingly has the meaning given in
AS 11.81.900
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-33-150">
            <num>28.33.150</num>
            <heading>Driving a commercial motor vehicle without being lawfully licensed.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-33-150__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person is guilty of a class A misdemeanor if the person drives a commercial motor vehicle in this state</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-150__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>without being licensed or privileged in this state to drive a commercial motor vehicle;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-150__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>during a period when that person's driver's license, privilege to drive, or privilege to obtain a license has been canceled, suspended, or revoked, or the person has been disqualified, in this or another jurisdiction;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-150__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in violation of a limitation placed upon that person's license or privilege to drive in this or another jurisdiction;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-150__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>during a period when that person has been disqualified from driving a commercial motor vehicle by a court or an administrative agency in this or another jurisdiction; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-150__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in violation of an out-of-service order issued under
AS 28.33.130
or under a law in another jurisdiction having substantially similar requirements.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-33-150__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon conviction under (a)(2)  (5) of this section, the court</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-150__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall impose a minimum sentence of imprisonment
(A) if the person has not been previously convicted, of not less than 20 days with 10 days suspended, including a mandatory condition of probation that the defendant complete not less than 80 hours of community work service; or
(B) if the person has been previously convicted, of not less than 60 days and a fine of $1,000;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-150__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>may impose additional conditions of probation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-150__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>may not
(A) suspend execution of sentence or grant probation except on condition that the person serve a minimum term of imprisonment and perform required community work service as provided in (1) of this subsection;
(B) suspend imposition of sentence; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-150__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall revoke the person's license, privilege to drive, or privilege to obtain a license, and the person may not be issued a new license nor may the privilege to drive or obtain a license be restored for an additional period of not less than 90 days after the date that the person would have been entitled to restoration of driving privileges.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-33-150__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, previously convicted means having been convicted in this or another jurisdiction, within 10 years preceding the date of the present offense, of a violation of this section,
AS 28.15.291
, or another law or ordinance with substantially similar elements.
Article 3. General Provisions.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-33-190">
            <num>28.33.190</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-33-190__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or
AS 28.05.011
that prohibits an owner or operator of a commercial motor vehicle from operating a commercial motor vehicle; and</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-33-190__subsec_c__subsec_15">
                <num>(15)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>serious traffic violation means
(A) speeding 15 miles per hour or more above the posted limit;
(B) reckless or negligent driving, in violation of
AS 28.35.400
or 28.35.410 or an ordinance with substantially similar elements;
(C) violation of a provision of this title, or a regulation adopted under this title, relating to improper lane changes or following too closely, or an ordinance with substantially similar elements;
(D) violation of a law or ordinance relating to traffic control, which was determined by the court by a preponderance of the evidence to have been a factor in causing physical injury to a person;
(E) driving a commercial motor vehicle without obtaining a license to drive a commercial motor vehicle;
(F) driving a commercial motor vehicle without a license to drive a commercial motor vehicle in the driver's possession; however, if an individual provides proof to the department by the date that the individual was required to appear in court or pay any fine for that violation that the individual held a valid license to drive a commercial motor vehicle on the date the citation was issued, the driving may not be considered as a serious traffic violation under this paragraph;
(G) driving a commercial motor vehicle without the proper class of license to drive a commercial motor vehicle and any required endorsements for the specific vehicle group being operated, or for the passengers or type of cargo being transported; or
(H) driving a commercial motor vehicle in violation of
AS 28.35.161
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>