<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-37/chapter-25"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-37/chapter-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="37.25"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-37/chapter-25/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-37/chapter-25/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-37/chapter-25/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-37/chapter-25/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_37">
        <num>37</num>
        <heading>Public Finance</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_37__chp_25">
          <num>25</num>
          <heading>Appropriations</heading>
          <section eId="sec_37-25-010">
            <num>37.25.010</num>
            <heading>Unexpended balances of one-year appropriations.</heading>
            <subsection eId="37-25-010__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The unexpended balance of a one-year appropriation authorized in an appropriation bill lapses on June 30 of the fiscal year for which appropriated.  However, a valid obligation (encumbrance) existing on June 30 is automatically reappropriated for the fiscal year beginning on the succeeding July 1 if it is recorded with the Department of Administration by August 31 of the succeeding fiscal year.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-25-010__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A valid approved claim arising from a prior year for which the appropriation has lapsed shall be paid from the current year's appropriations if this claim does not exceed the balance lapsed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-25-010__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>University receipts received on or before June 30 of a fiscal year in excess of the amount expended for that year may be expended in the succeeding fiscal year if an appropriation of university receipts has been made for the succeeding fiscal year.  The amount of university receipts expended in a fiscal year may not exceed the amount of university receipts appropriated for that year.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-25-010__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The University of Alaska shall, in the report required under
AS 14.40.190
(a), report the amount of university receipts received in one year and expended in the succeeding fiscal year.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-25-010__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, university receipts has the meaning given in
AS 14.40.491
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-25-020">
            <num>37.25.020</num>
            <heading>Unexpended balances of appropriation for capital projects.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.25.020.   Unexpended balances of appropriation for capital projects.
An appropriation made for a capital project is valid for the life of the project, and the unexpended balance shall be carried forward to subsequent fiscal years if substantial, ongoing work on the project has begun within five years after the effective date of the appropriation. Between July 1 and August 31 of each fiscal year, a statement supporting the amount of the unexpended balance required to complete the projects for which the initial appropriation was made and the amount that may be lapsed shall be recorded with the Department of Administration. The office of management and budget, in coordination with the Department of Administration, shall deliver to the house and senate finance committees a report of unexpended balances of appropriations for capital projects not later than the 15th day of each regular session of the legislature.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-25-050">
            <num>37.25.050</num>
            <heading>Methods of disbursement.</heading>
            <subsection eId="37-25-050__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (b) of this section, unless federal law requires otherwise, a state agency may not disburse money unless the disbursement is made</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="37-25-050__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>by an electronic funds transfer to an account in a financial institution; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="37-25-050__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>from an account established by the state agency by contract with a financial institution under which a person uses an electronic payment card issued by the financial institution to access the money.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-25-050__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A state agency is not required to use the disbursement methods described in (a) of the section if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="37-25-050__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>another state law or federal law requires that disbursement be made by another disbursement method;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="37-25-050__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>use of the disbursement methods would cause substantial hardship to the recipient of the disbursement;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="37-25-050__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>not more than five disbursements will be made to a recipient, or, on average, to each recipient entitled to disbursement under the program for which the disbursements are made;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="37-25-050__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a vendor or grantee elects not to be paid by the disbursement methods;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="37-25-050__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the disbursement is to a state employee and
(A) is the only disbursement that the state agency will make to the employee for the employment; or
(B) it is in the best interests of the state agency or the employee to use another disbursement method to pay the employee; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="37-25-050__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>use of another disbursement method is in the best interests of the state agency.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-25-050__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner of administration shall adopt regulations to implement (b) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-25-050__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A state agency is not liable to pay a fee imposed by a recipient's financial institution for a disbursement made under (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-25-050__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="37-25-050__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>disbursement includes wages and other employment benefits;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="37-25-050__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>state agency means a department, institution, board, commission, division, authority, public corporation, committee, or other administrative unit of the executive branch of state government, including the University of Alaska.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>