<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-33/chapter-35"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-33/chapter-35"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="33.35"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-33/chapter-35/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-33/chapter-35/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-33/chapter-35/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-33/chapter-35/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_33">
        <num>33</num>
        <heading>Probation, Prisons, Pardons, and Prisoners</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_33__chp_35">
          <num>35</num>
          <heading>Agreement on Detainers</heading>
          <section eId="sec_33-35-010">
            <num>33.35.010</num>
            <heading>Agreement enacted.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-35-010__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The written notice and request for final disposition referred to in paragraph (a) of this article shall be given or sent by the prisoner to the warden, commissioner of corrections or other official having custody of the prisoner, who shall promptly forward it together with the certificate to the appropriate prosecuting official and court by registered or certified mail, return receipt requested.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-35-010__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The warden, commissioner of corrections or other official having custody of the prisoner shall promptly inform the prisoner of the source and contents of any detainer against the prisoner, and shall also inform the prisoner of the right to make a request for final disposition of the indictment, information or complaint on which the detainer is based.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-35-010__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Any request for final disposition made by a prisoner under paragraph (a) of this article shall operate as a request for final disposition of all untried indictments, informations or complaints on the basis of which detainers have been lodged against the prisoner from the state to whose prosecuting official the request for final disposition is specifically directed.  The warden, commissioner of corrections or other official having custody of the prisoner shall notify all appropriate prosecuting officers and courts in the several jurisdictions within the state to which the prisoner's request for final disposition is being sent of the proceedings being initiated by the prisoner.  Any notification sent under this paragraph shall be accompanied by copies of the prisoner's written notice, request, and the certificate.  If trial is not had on any indictment, information or complaint contemplated by this article before the return of the prisoner to the original place of imprisonment, that indictment, information or complaint is of no further force or effect, and the court shall enter an order dismissing it with prejudice.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-35-010__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A request for final disposition made by a prisoner under paragraph (a) of this article shall also be considered a waiver of extradition with respect to any charge or proceeding contemplated or included by reason of paragraph (d) of this article, and a waiver of extradition to the receiving state to serve any sentence imposed upon the prisoner there, after completion of the prisoner's term of imprisonment in the sending state.  The request for final disposition also constitutes a consent by the prisoner to the production of the prisoner's body in any court where the prisoner's presence may be required in order to effectuate the purposes of this agreement and a further consent voluntarily to be returned to the original place of imprisonment in accordance with the provisions of this agreement. Nothing in this paragraph prevents the imposition of a concurrent sentence if otherwise permitted by law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-35-010__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Escape from custody by the prisoner after the execution of the request for final disposition referred to in paragraph (a) of this article shall void the request.
Article IV   (a) The appropriate officer of the jurisdiction in which an untried indictment, information or complaint is pending is entitled to have a prisoner, against whom the officer has lodged a detainer and who is serving a term of imprisonment in any party state, made available in accordance with Article V(a) of this agreement upon presentation of a written request for temporary custody or availability to the appropriate authorities of the state in which the prisoner is incarcerated; provided that the court having jurisdiction of an indictment, information or complaint must have duly approved, recorded and transmitted the request; and provided that there shall be a period of 30 days after receipt by the appropriate authorities before the request is honored, within which period the governor of the sending state may disapprove the request for temporary custody or availability, either upon the governor's own motion or upon motion of the prisoner.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-35-010__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon receipt of the officer's written request as provided in paragraph (a) of this article, the appropriate authorities having the prisoner in custody shall furnish the officer with a certificate stating the term of commitment under which the prisoner is being held, the time already served, the time remaining to be served on the sentence, the amount of good time earned, the time of parole eligibility of the prisoner, and any decisions of the state parole agency relating to the prisoner.  Those authorities shall at the same time furnish all other officers and appropriate courts in the receiving state who have lodged detainers against the prisoner with similar certificates and with notices informing them of the request for custody or availability and of the reasons for the request.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-35-010__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In any proceeding under this article, trial shall begin within 120 days of the arrival of the prisoner in the receiving state.  However, for good cause shown in open court, the prisoner or counsel for the prisoner being present, the court having jurisdiction of the matter may grant any necessary or reasonable continuance.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-35-010__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing contained in this article may be construed to deprive a prisoner of any right that the prisoner may have to contest the legality of the prisoner's delivery as provided in paragraph (a) of this article, but the prisoner's delivery may not be opposed or denied on the ground that the executive authority of the sending state had not affirmatively consented to or ordered the delivery.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-35-010__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If trial is not had on any indictment, information or complaint contemplated by this agreement before the prisoner's return to the prisoner's original place of imprisonment under Article V(e) of this agreement, the indictment, information or complaint is not of any further force or effect, and the court shall enter an order dismissing it with prejudice.
Article V   (a) In response to a request made under Article III or Article IV of this agreement, the appropriate authority in a sending state shall offer to deliver temporary custody of a prisoner to the appropriate authority in the state where the indictment, information or complaint is pending against the prisoner in order that speedy and efficient prosecution may be had.  If the request for final disposition is made by the prisoner, the offer of temporary custody shall accompany the written notice provided for in Article III of this agreement. In the case of a federal prisoner, the appropriate authority in the receiving state is entitled to temporary custody as provided by this agreement or to the prisoner's presence in federal custody at the place of trial, whichever custodial arrangement may be approved by the custodian.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-35-010__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The officer or other representative of a state accepting an offer of temporary custody shall present the following upon demand:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-35-010__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>proper identification and evidence of the authority of the officer or other representative to act for the state into whose temporary custody the prisoner is to be given; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-35-010__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a certified copy of the indictment, information or complaint on the basis of which the detainer has been lodged and on the basis of which the request for temporary custody of the prisoner has been made.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-35-010__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the appropriate authority refuses or fails to accept temporary custody of the prisoner, or if an action on the indictment, information or complaint, on the basis of which the detainer has been lodged, is not brought to trial within the period provided in Article III or Article IV of this agreement, the appropriate court of the jurisdiction where the indictment, information or complaint has been pending shall enter an order dismissing it with prejudice, and any detainer based on it shall cease to be of any force or effect.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-35-010__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The temporary custody referred to in this agreement is only for the purpose of permitting prosecution on the charge or charges contained in one or more untried indictments, informations or complaints which form the basis of the detainer or for prosecution on any other charge arising out of the same transaction.  Except for the prisoner's attendance at court and while being transported to or from any place at which the prisoner's presence may be required, the prisoner shall be held in a suitable jail or other facility regularly used for persons awaiting prosecution.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-35-010__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>At the earliest practicable time consistent with the purposes of this agreement, the prisoner shall be returned to the sending state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-35-010__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>During the continuance of temporary custody or while the prisoner is otherwise being made available for trial as required by this agreement, time being served on the sentence shall continue to run but good time shall be earned by the prisoner only if, and to the extent that, the law and practice of the jurisdiction which imposed the sentence may allow.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-35-010__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For all purposes other than that for which temporary custody as provided in this agreement is exercised, the prisoner shall be considered to remain in the custody of and subject to the jurisdiction of the sending state.  Any escape from temporary custody may be dealt with in the same manner as an escape from the original place of imprisonment or in any other manner permitted by law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-35-010__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>From the time that a party state receives custody of a prisoner under this agreement until the prisoner is returned to the territory and custody of the sending state, the state in which the untried indictments, informations or complaints are pending or in which trial is being had shall be responsible for the prisoner and shall also pay all costs of transporting, caring for, keeping and returning the prisoner. The provisions of this paragraph govern unless the states concerned have entered into a supplementary agreement providing for a different allocation of costs and responsibilities between themselves.  Nothing in this agreement may be considered to alter or affect any internal relationship among the departments, agencies and officers of and in the government of a party state, or between a party state and its subdivisions, as to the payment of or the responsibility for costs.
Article VI   (a) In determining the duration and expiration dates of the time periods provided in Articles III and IV of this agreement, the running of those time periods shall be tolled when and for as long as the prisoner is unable to stand trial, as determined by the court having jurisdiction of the matter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-35-010__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>No provision of this agreement, and no remedy made available by this agreement, apply to a person who is adjudged to be mentally ill.
Article VII  Each state party to this agreement shall designate an officer who, acting jointly with like officers of other party states, shall adopt regulations to carry out the terms and provisions of this agreement, and who shall provide, inside and outside the state, information necessary to the effective operation of this agreement.
Article VIII  This agreement shall enter into full force and effect as to a party state when that state has enacted it into law.  A state party to this agreement may withdraw from it by enacting a statute repealing it. However, the withdrawal of any state does not affect the status of any proceedings already initiated by inmates or by state officers at the time the withdrawal takes effect, nor does it affect their rights in respect to those proceedings.
Article IX  This agreement shall be liberally construed so as to effectuate its purposes.  The provisions of this agreement shall be severable and if any phrase, clause, sentence or provision of this agreement is declared to be contrary to the constitution of any party state or of the United States or the applicability of a provision to any government, agency, person or circumstance is held invalid, the validity of the remainder of this agreement and the applicability of it to any government, agency, person or circumstance is not affected. If this agreement is held to be contrary to the constitution of any party state, the agreement shall remain in full force and effect as to the remaining states and in full force and effect as to the state affected as to all severable matters.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-35-020">
            <num>33.35.020</num>
            <heading>Appropriate court defined.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 33.35.020.   Appropriate court defined.
The phrase appropriate court in
AS 33.35.010
, with reference to the courts of this state, means the superior court.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-35-030">
            <num>33.35.030</num>
            <heading>Enforcement.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 33.35.030.   Enforcement.
All courts, departments, agencies, officers, and employees of the state and its political subdivisions shall enforce the Agreement on Detainers under
AS 33.35.010
and cooperate with one another and with other party states in enforcing the agreement and effectuating its purpose.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-35-040">
            <num>33.35.040</num>
            <heading>Central administrator and information agent.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 33.35.040.   Central administrator and information agent.
The commissioner of corrections or the designee of the commissioner of corrections is the central administrator of and information agent for the Agreement on Detainers under
AS 33.35.010
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>