<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-13"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-13"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="8.13"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-13/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-13/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-13/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-13/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_8">
        <num>8</num>
        <heading>Business and Professions</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_8__chp_13">
          <num>13</num>
          <heading>Barbers and Hairdressers</heading>
          <section eId="sec_08-13-010">
            <num>08.13.010</num>
            <heading>Creation and membership of board.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-13-010__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>There is created the Board of Barbers and Hairdressers consisting of seven members appointed by the governor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-010__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board consists of</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-010__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>one person licensed as a barber under this chapter;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-010__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>one person licensed to practice body piercing, tattooing, or permanent cosmetic coloring under this chapter;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-010__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>two persons licensed as hairdressers under this chapter, one of whom is also licensed as an esthetician under this chapter;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-010__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>one public member;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-010__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>one person licensed to practice manicuring under this chapter; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-010__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>one person licensed to practice any activity licensed under this chapter.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-13-030">
            <num>08.13.030</num>
            <heading>Powers and duties of the board.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-13-030__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board shall exercise general control over the vocations of barbering, hairdressing, hair braiding, manicuring, esthetics, body piercing, tattooing, and permanent cosmetic coloring.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-030__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-030__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>examine applicants and approve the issuance of licenses and permits to practice;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-030__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>authorize the issuance of licenses for schools of barbering, hairdressing, manicuring, and esthetics;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-030__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>develop written instructions and notices that tattooing, permanent cosmetic coloring, and body piercing shop owners and practitioners are required to give or display under
AS 08.13.215
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-030__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>enforce the provisions of this chapter, regulations adopted under this chapter, and regulations relating to barbering, hairdressing, hair braiding, manicuring, and esthetics adopted under
AS 44.46.020</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-030__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board may</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-030__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>suspend or revoke a license or permit;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-030__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>on its own motion or upon receipt of a written complaint, conduct hearings and request the
(A) Department of Commerce, Community, and Economic Development to investigate the practices of a person, shop, or school involved in the practice or teaching of barbering, hairdressing, hair braiding, manicuring, or esthetics; or
(B)  Department of Commerce, Community, and Economic Development or the Department of Environmental Conservation to investigate the practices of a person, shop, or school involved in the practice or teaching of body piercing, tattooing, or permanent cosmetic coloring;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-030__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>adopt regulations or do any act necessary to carry out the provisions of this chapter.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-13-040">
            <num>08.13.040</num>
            <heading>Meetings and examinations.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-13-040__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board shall meet as often as necessary to conduct its business. It shall conduct separate examinations covering the following fields of practice: barbering, hairdressing, advanced manicuring, and esthetics. Examinations shall be given at least twice in every year for each of these fields of practice for which applications for licensure or endorsements are pending. An applicant may take an examination in more than one field during the same testing session. The board may not require an applicant for licensure as a manicurist to take or pass an examination conducted by the board for the field of manicuring; however, nothing in this sentence prohibits the board from requiring a licensed manicurist to pass an examination to obtain an optional endorsement as an advanced manicurist under
AS 08.13.080
(f).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-040__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board may not require a person applying for a limited license to practice non-chemical barbering under
AS 08.13.100</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-040__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>to take an examination that tests the person's knowledge of chemical processes, including permanent waving, bleaching, coloring, or chemical straightening.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-13-050">
            <num>08.13.050</num>
            <heading>Records of the board.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.13.050.   Records of the board.
The Department of Commerce, Community, and Economic Development shall keep a record of the board's proceedings related to the issuance, refusal, suspension, and revocation of each license and permit. The record shall contain the name of the person to whom a license or permit is issued, the person's place of business, the date of issuance for each license and permit, and whether it is currently valid. The record shall be open to inspection by the public at all reasonable times.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-13-070">
            <num>08.13.070</num>
            <heading>License required.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-13-070__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or permitted under
AS 08.13.160
(e);</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-070__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>open or conduct a school of barbering, hairdressing, manicuring, or esthetics without a license;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-070__subsec_d__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>teach in a school of barbering, hairdressing, manicuring, or esthetics, or supervise an apprentice in barbering, hairdressing, manicuring, or esthetics without an instructor's license;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-070__subsec_d__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>operate a shop in violation of
AS 08.13.120
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-070__subsec_d__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>permit an employee or other person being supervised who is not exempted under
AS 08.13.160</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-070__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>to practice barbering, hairdressing, hair braiding, manicuring, esthetics, body piercing, tattooing, or permanent cosmetic coloring without a license, temporary permit, temporary license, or student permit;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-070__subsec_d__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>permit the use of the person's license, temporary permit, temporary license, or student permit by another person;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-070__subsec_d__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>obtain or attempt to obtain a license, temporary permit, temporary license, or student permit by fraudulent means.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-13-080">
            <num>08.13.080</num>
            <heading>Qualifications of applicants.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-13-080__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An applicant for an examination authorized under
AS 08.13.040
must</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-080__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>have successfully completed all courses that a school with a curriculum in barbering approved by the board is required to teach in order to be licensed under
AS 08.13.110
if applying for a license to practice barbering; the curriculum may be limited for non-chemical barbering under
AS 08.13.100</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-080__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>have successfully completed all courses that a school with a curriculum in hairdressing approved by the board is required to teach to be licensed under
AS 08.13.110
if applying for a license to practice hairdressing;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-080__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>have successfully completed all courses that a school with a curriculum in esthetics approved by the board is required to teach in order to be licensed under
AS 08.13.110
if applying for a license to practice esthetics;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-080__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>have served an apprenticeship under
AS 08.13.082
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-080__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>specify the field of practice in which the applicant intends to teach and have held a license to practice in the field for three years or have held a license in the field for one year and have completed 600 hours of student training as an instructor in the field of practice from a licensed school with a curriculum approved by the board if applying for a license as an instructor, except that a person licensed as an instructor in hairdressing may be an instructor in manicuring for courses that satisfy the requirements of (e) of this section, and the board may, by regulation, establish requirements for other manicuring instructors, including instructors who teach courses that satisfy requirements for an advanced manicurist endorsement; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-080__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>have completed course work and, if applicable, an apprenticeship acceptable to the board.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-080__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 12 ch 27 SLA 2015.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-080__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 12 ch 27 SLA 2015.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-080__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An applicant for a license to practice body piercing, tattooing, or permanent cosmetic coloring shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-080__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>satisfy the training requirement of
AS 08.13.082</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-080__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>by passing a written examination approved by the board, demonstrate to the board or the board's designee safety, sanitation, sterilization, aseptic, and practice techniques that indicate that the applicant has adequate knowledge of infection control practices and requirements relating to tattooing, permanent cosmetic coloring, or body piercing, as applicable; this demonstration may, at the option of the board, also include a practical examination in addition to the written examination; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-080__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>pay the appropriate fee.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-080__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An applicant for a license to practice manicuring shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-080__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>submit documentation that the applicant has completed a course of 12 hours of instruction or training approved by the board that addresses health, safety, and hygiene concerns of manicuring customers and practitioners that are relevant to the practice of manicuring from a school licensed under
AS 08.13.110
as a school of manicuring; documentation of completion of the course must include certification from the school that the applicant has passed a test given by the school covering the health, safety, and hygiene concerns of manicuring customers and practitioners that are relevant to the practice of manicuring; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-080__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>pay the appropriate fee.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-080__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An applicant for an endorsement to a license to practice manicuring or hairdressing indicating that the person is an advanced manicurist shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-080__subsec_f__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>hold, or be approved for, a current license issued under this chapter for manicuring or hairdressing;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-080__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>request the endorsement;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-080__subsec_f__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>submit documentation from a licensed school of manicuring or hairdressing certifying completion of 250 hours of instruction in manicuring that meets the requirements of
AS 08.13.110</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-080__subsec_f__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>pass an examination given by the board for advanced manicurists; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-080__subsec_f__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>pay the appropriate fee.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-080__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An applicant for a license to practice hair braiding shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-080__subsec_g__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>apply in writing on a form prescribed by the board;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-080__subsec_g__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>complete, to the satisfaction of the board, 35 hours of instruction in hair braiding, health, safety, and sanitation
(A) at an accredited school of hairdressing;
(B) at a professional association of hairdressing or hair braiding; or
(C) from an individual or school licensed under this chapter and approved by the board; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-080__subsec_g__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>pay the appropriate fee.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-13-082">
            <num>08.13.082</num>
            <heading>Apprenticeship.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-13-082__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The period of apprenticeship required to qualify an applicant for a license to practice barbering is 2,000 hours. The apprenticeship must be served in a shop approved by the board. The apprenticeship may not be completed in less than 12 months from the date of its commencement and must be completed in not more than two years from the date of its commencement. The board may set by regulation a period of apprenticeship of less than 2,000 hours for an applicant for a license to practice non-chemical barbering. The board may not require an applicant for a license to practice non-chemical barbering under
AS 08.13.100</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-082__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>to perform apprenticeship hours or practical operations relating to chemical processes, including permanent waving, bleaching, coloring, or chemical straightening.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-082__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The period of apprenticeship required to qualify an applicant for a license to practice hairdressing is 2,000 hours. The apprenticeship must be served in a shop approved by the board.  The apprenticeship may not be completed in less than one year from the date of its commencement and must be completed in not more than two years from the date of its commencement.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-082__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The period of apprenticeship required to qualify an applicant for a license to practice esthetics is 350 hours. The apprenticeship must be served in a shop approved by the board. The apprenticeship may not be completed in less than six months from the date of its commencement and must be completed in not more than one year from the date of its commencement.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-082__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The number of hours of training required to qualify an applicant for a license to practice tattooing, permanent cosmetic coloring, or body piercing shall be set by the board in regulations. The trainee must be at least 18 years of age when the training commences. The training required under this subsection</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-082__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>may only be received
(A) in a licensed shop in this state under a person who has a practitioner's license under this chapter in the field in which the trainee seeks training; or
(B) outside the state from a person approved by the board at a site approved by the board;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-082__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>must include at least 12 hours of training in safety, sanitation, sterilization, aseptic, and other practices necessary to prevent transmission of diseases and infection;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-082__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall be completed in not more than 12 months from the date of its commencement; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-082__subsec_d__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall be documented by certification from the trainer that the training was successfully completed by the trainee.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-082__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, §  12, ch. 12, SLA 2017.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-13-090">
            <num>08.13.090</num>
            <heading>Examinations and other requirements.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-13-090__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A written examination shall be given to each applicant for examination at a time and place determined by the board.  The board may delegate the power of examination to a committee of the board or a board member.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-090__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The written examination must cover subjects designated by the board and must test the applicant's knowledge of sanitary practices, safety of all procedures, and use of instruments, equipment, and chemicals permitted within the field of practice for which the applicant is seeking a license.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-090__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board may by regulation establish requirements for a practical examination for licensure.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-13-100">
            <num>08.13.100</num>
            <heading>License.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-13-100__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board shall authorize the issuance of a license for the practice of barbering, hairdressing, or esthetics to each qualified applicant who has passed an examination under
AS 08.13.090
and meets other applicable requirements under this chapter. The board shall authorize the issuance of a license for the practice of tattooing, permanent cosmetic coloring, or body piercing to each applicant who has satisfied the requirements of
AS 08.13.080
(d). The board shall authorize the issuance of a license to practice manicuring to each applicant who has satisfied the requirements of
AS 08.13.080
(e). The board shall authorize the issuance of an endorsement to a license to practice manicuring or hairdressing indicating that the person is an advanced manicurist to each applicant who has satisfied the requirements of
AS 08.13.080
(f). The board shall authorize the issuance of a license for the practice of hair braiding to each applicant who has satisfied the requirements of
AS 08.13.080
(g).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-100__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A practitioner license must state the areas of practice (barbering, non-chemical barbering, hairdressing, hair braiding, manicuring, esthetics, tattooing, permanent cosmetic coloring, or body piercing) that the practitioner is qualified to perform.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-100__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board may by regulation create areas of limited professional licensing in the field of esthetics. Any limitation must be stated on the license.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-100__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who holds a current valid license from a board of barbering, hairdressing, manicuring, or esthetics in another state or who is licensed by another state to practice hair braiding, tattooing, permanent cosmetic coloring, or body piercing is entitled to a license or endorsement under this chapter without examination or a new period of training in this state. An application must include</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-100__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>proof of a valid license issued by another licensing jurisdiction; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-100__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>proof of completed training, testing, and working experience that the board finds to meet the minimum requirements of this state.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-100__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person licensed as an instructor is considered to be licensed as a practitioner and is subject to the same requirements that a practitioner is subject to, in the same area for which the person is licensed as an instructor, except that, for purposes of setting fees under
AS 08.01.065
, the department shall consider instructors to be an occupation separate from practitioners. An instructor license shall state the areas of practice (barbering, hairdressing, manicuring, or esthetics) in which the licensee is qualified to instruct and practice.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-100__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board shall by regulation create an area of limited professional licensing in the field of barbering for non-chemical barbering that allows a person to practice barbering without the use of chemicals and chemical processes. The limitation must be stated on the license.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-13-110">
            <num>08.13.110</num>
            <heading>School license.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-13-110__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board shall adopt regulations for the licensing of schools of barbering, hairdressing, manicuring, and esthetics. The regulations must include details of the curriculum, minimum hours of instruction, physical condition of the facilities, and financial responsibility of the owner. The curriculum required for a school of hairdressing must include the curriculum required for a school of manicuring.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-110__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 12 ch 27 SLA 2015.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-110__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 12 ch 27 SLA 2015.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-110__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board shall issue a license to a school of manicuring if the school offers a curriculum of 12 hours of instruction or training approved by the board that addresses health, safety, and hygiene concerns of manicuring customers and practitioners that are relevant to the practice of manicuring. A school of manicuring may offer instruction in addition to the 12 hours required for a license, but the board may not issue a license to a school of manicuring if the school requires its students to complete more than 12 hours of the required instruction or training in health, safety, and hygiene concerns before the school will certify that the student has completed the school's manicuring course for purposes of
AS 08.13.080
(e).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-110__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A school of manicuring may seek approval from the board for a curriculum designed to qualify students for an advanced manicurist endorsement. The board shall establish the curriculum requirements applicable under this subsection through its authority under (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-13-120">
            <num>08.13.120</num>
            <heading>Shop license.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-13-120__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board shall adopt regulations for the licensing of shops. The regulations must require that a shop for tattooing, permanent cosmetic coloring, or body piercing be inspected and certified by the Department of Environmental Conservation as being in compliance with the regulations adopted under
AS 44.46.020
before a shop license may be issued under this subsection. A shop owner shall be licensed to operate a shop without examination, but, unless the shop owner is a practitioner, the shop owner may not conduct business without employing a manager who is a practitioner. This subsection does not apply to a shop for the practice of barbering, hairdressing, hair braiding, or esthetics located in a community having a population of less than 1,000 people that is not within 25 miles of a community of more than 1,000 people.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-120__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The regulations adopted under (a) of this section must include provisions under which the board may issue a temporary shop license to a person who has a license or temporary permit under this chapter to practice tattooing, permanent cosmetic coloring, or body piercing. The temporary shop license authorized under this subsection may only be issued to cover a site where the practitioner intends to hold a workshop or to demonstrate techniques as part of a convention or other special event, as defined by the board, that includes other practitioners of tattooing, permanent cosmetic coloring, or body piercing. Each practitioner of tattooing, permanent cosmetic coloring, or body piercing who holds a workshop or demonstrates techniques at a convention or special event shall have a separate temporary shop license and a license or temporary permit under this chapter to practice tattooing, permanent cosmetic coloring, or body piercing. The board shall issue a temporary shop license upon receipt of an application from a practitioner demonstrating compliance with the regulations adopted under this section and payment of the appropriate fee; however, the temporary shop license may be summarily revoked, without refunding of the fee, if the Department of Environmental Conservation determines after an inspection that the cleanliness or sanitation conditions at the site covered by the temporary license pose a clear and immediate danger to the public health or safety. A licensee may appeal a summary revocation under this subsection to the superior court.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-13-130">
            <num>08.13.130</num>
            <heading>Display of license or permit.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-13-130__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A practitioner shall display the practitioner's license in a conspicuous location in the practitioner's place of business. Each shop owner is responsible for the conspicuous display of the shop's license and the licenses of employees and individuals renting booths in the shop. A person holding a student permit, temporary license, or temporary permit shall display the permit or license in a conspicuous location in the school in which the person is enrolled or the shop in which the person works. The school or shop owner is responsible for the display of a permit or license for each enrolled student, apprentice, or temporary license holder.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-130__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A license issued to a manicurist by the department must state that the manicurist has successfully completed a course of instruction or training in health, safety, and hygiene concerns related to the practice of manicuring.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-13-140">
            <num>08.13.140</num>
            <heading>Lapsed license.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.13.140.   Lapsed license.
A lapsed license may be reinstated if the license has not been lapsed for a period of more than three years, or otherwise at the discretion of the board, and all renewal and delinquent fees for the period during which the license has been lapsed are paid.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-13-150">
            <num>08.13.150</num>
            <heading>Disciplinary sanctions and grounds for refusal of a license or permit.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.13.150.   Disciplinary sanctions and grounds for refusal of a license or permit.
The board may, in addition to the actions authorized under
AS 08.01.075
, refuse, suspend, or revoke a license, student permit, temporary license, or temporary permit for failure to comply with this chapter, with a regulation adopted under this chapter, with a regulation adopted by the Department of Environmental Conservation under
AS 44.46.020
, or with an order of the board.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-13-160">
            <num>08.13.160</num>
            <heading>Application of license requirements.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-13-160__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person holding a valid license to practice barbering under former
AS 08.12
is licensed under this chapter and may continue to practice barbering under the conditions imposed by former
AS 08.12
and the regulations adopted under former
AS 08.12
until the license expires.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-160__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person holding a valid license under former
AS 08.28
may continue to practice under the conditions imposed under former
AS 08.28
and the regulations adopted under former
AS 08.28
until the license expires.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-160__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person holding a valid license issued under former
AS 08.12
or former
AS 08.28
shall be entitled upon its expiration to a license to practice under this chapter in the field of practice for which the person was originally licensed, without meeting requirements for new licensure.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-160__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The licensing and permit provisions of this chapter do not apply to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-160__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a person practicing barbering, hairdressing, hair braiding, manicuring, or esthetics in a community having a population of less than 1,000 people that is not within 25 miles of a community of more than 1,000 people and who does not use chemicals or uses only chemicals available to the general public;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-160__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a licensed health care professional;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-160__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a person licensed by another licensing jurisdiction in a field of practice licensed by this chapter while demonstrating techniques or products to persons holding licenses or permits under this chapter;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-160__subsec_d__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a person practicing tattooing, permanent cosmetic coloring, or body piercing solely on the person's own body;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-160__subsec_d__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the practice of manicuring by a student as part of instruction in a 12-hour course approved under
AS 08.13.110</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-160__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board shall adopt regulations to permit a person licensed under this chapter to practice barbering, hairdressing, hair braiding, manicuring, or esthetics outside a licensed shop or school for limited purposes including</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-160__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>care of clients confined to an institution or health care facility;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-160__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>care of clients with limited mobility;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-160__subsec_e__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>participation in charitable events; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-160__subsec_e__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>participation in workshops or demonstrations of techniques or products.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-160__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person licensed under this chapter to practice hairdressing is considered to be licensed to practice manicuring, hair braiding, and limited esthetics under the same license.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-13-170">
            <num>08.13.170</num>
            <heading>Temporary permits.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.13.170.   Temporary permits.
The department shall issue a temporary permit to an applicant for licensing who holds a license to practice barbering, hairdressing, hair braiding, manicuring, esthetics, tattooing, permanent cosmetic coloring, or body piercing in another state. The permit is valid until the board either issues a permanent license or rejects the application. The board shall act on an application within six months.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-13-175">
            <num>08.13.175</num>
            <heading>Temporary license.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.13.175.   Temporary license.
A person who meets the requirements of
AS 08.13.080
(a)(1), (2), (3), (4), or (6) is entitled to be temporarily licensed after applying for examination under this chapter if the applicant works under the direct supervision, and within the physical presence, of a person who is licensed in the area of practice for which the applicant has applied for examination. A temporary license issued under this section is valid for 120 days and is nonrenewable. A person may not receive more than one temporary license for each area of practice licensed under this chapter. An application for a temporary license must be signed by the supervising licensee and accompanied by the temporary license fee required under
AS 08.13.185
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-13-180">
            <num>08.13.180</num>
            <heading>Student permits.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.13.180.   Student permits.
A person attending a licensed school of barbering, hairdressing, manicuring, or esthetics and a person apprenticed to a licensed instructor in a shop approved by the board or receiving training from a practitioner of tattooing, permanent cosmetic coloring, or body piercing shall obtain a student permit. A student permit to practice barbering or hairdressing is valid for two years. A student permit to practice esthetics, tattooing, permanent cosmetic coloring, or body piercing is valid for one year. A student permit may not be renewed, but, upon application, the board may issue a new permit to the same person or extend an expired permit to the date of the next scheduled examination. Credit earned under an expired student permit may be transferred to a new permit as determined by the board.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-13-183">
            <num>08.13.183</num>
            <heading>Use of title; unlicensed use prohibited.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-13-183__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person licensed to practice manicuring in the state may use the title licensed nail technician.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-183__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who uses the title licensed nail technician who is not licensed to practice manicuring under this chapter is guilty of a violation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-13-185">
            <num>08.13.185</num>
            <heading>Fees.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-13-185__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Commerce, Community, and Economic Development shall set fees under
AS 08.01.065
for initial licenses and renewals for the following:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-185__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>schools;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-185__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>school owners;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-185__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>instructor;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-185__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shop owner;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-185__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>practitioner of barbering;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-185__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>practitioner of hairdressing;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-185__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>practitioner of manicuring;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-185__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>practitioner of esthetics;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-185__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>practitioner of tattooing;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-185__subsec_a__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>practitioner of body piercing;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-185__subsec_a__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>temporary shop license;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-185__subsec_a__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>temporary permit;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-185__subsec_a__subsec_13">
                <num>(13)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>temporary license;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-185__subsec_a__subsec_14">
                <num>(14)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>student permit;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-185__subsec_a__subsec_15">
                <num>(15)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>endorsement for advanced manicuring;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-185__subsec_a__subsec_16">
                <num>(16)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>practitioner of hair braiding;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-185__subsec_a__subsec_17">
                <num>(17)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>practitioner of permanent cosmetic coloring;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-185__subsec_a__subsec_18">
                <num>(18)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>practitioner of non-chemical barbering.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-185__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall set fees under
AS 08.01.065
for examination and investigation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-13-190">
            <num>08.13.190</num>
            <heading>Failure to possess a license or permit.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-13-190__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who practices barbering, hairdressing, hair braiding, esthetics, tattooing, permanent cosmetic coloring, or body piercing, or operates a shop, or operates a school of barbering, hairdressing, or esthetics, or teaches in a school of barbering, hairdressing, or esthetics, without a license, temporary permit, temporary license, or student permit and who is not exempt under
AS 08.13.120
or under
AS 08.13.160</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-190__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>is guilty of a class B misdemeanor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-190__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who practices manicuring, operates a shop for manicuring, operates a school of manicuring, or teaches in a school of manicuring without the appropriate license, temporary permit, temporary license, or student permit and who is not exempt under
AS 08.13.120
or 08.13.160(d) is guilty of a violation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-13-195">
            <num>08.13.195</num>
            <heading>Civil penalty.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-13-195__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to any other provision of law, if a person violates
AS 08.13.070
or 08.13.217, the board may enter an order levying a civil penalty.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-195__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A civil penalty levied under this section may not exceed $5,000 for each offense. In levying a civil penalty, the board shall set the amount of the penalty imposed under this section after taking into account appropriate factors, including the seriousness of the violation, the economic benefit resulting from the violation, the history of violations, and other matters the board considers appropriate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-195__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before issuing an order under this section, the board shall provide the person written notice and the opportunity to request, within 30 days of issuance of notice by the board, a hearing on the record.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-195__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In connection with proceedings under (a) and (b) of this section, the board may issue subpoenas to compel the attendance and testimony of witnesses and the disclosure of evidence, and may request the attorney general to bring an action to enforce a subpoena.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-195__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person aggrieved by the levy of a civil penalty under this section may file an appeal with the superior court for judicial review of the penalty under
AS 44.62.560
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-195__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a person fails to pay a civil penalty within 30 days after entry of an order under (a) of this section, or if the order is stayed pending an appeal, within 10 days after the court enters a final judgment in favor of the board of an order appealed under (e) of this section, the board shall notify the attorney general. The attorney general may commence a civil action to recover the amount of the penalty.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-195__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An action to enforce an order under this section may be combined with an action for an injunction under
AS 08.01.087
.
Article 3. General Provisions.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-13-210">
            <num>08.13.210</num>
            <heading>Health and sanitary conditions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-13-210__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Health and sanitary conditions in shops and schools of</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-210__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>barbering, hairdressing, hair braiding, manicuring, and esthetics shall be supervised by the board;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-210__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>tattooing, permanent cosmetic coloring, and body piercing shall be supervised by the Department of Environmental Conservation.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-210__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Environmental Conservation shall conduct an annual inspection of each shop licensed for the practice of tattooing, permanent cosmetic coloring, or body piercing to ensure that the shop meets the department's standards of cleanliness and sanitation established under
AS 44.46.020
. If the Department of Environmental Conservation determines that the shop is not in compliance with a regulation of the department, the department shall report the violation to the board and take appropriate action under its own regulations.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-13-215">
            <num>08.13.215</num>
            <heading>Notification requirements for tattooing, permanent cosmetic coloring, and body piercing.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-13-215__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before performing a tattooing, permanent cosmetic coloring, or body piercing procedure on a client, a practitioner shall give written educational information, approved by the board, to the client.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-215__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After completing a tattooing, permanent cosmetic coloring, or body piercing procedure on a client, the practitioner shall give written aftercare instructions, approved by the board, to the client. The written instructions</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-215__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>must include advice to the client to consult a physician at the first sign of infection;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-215__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>must contain the name, address, and telephone number of the shop where the procedure was performed;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-215__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall be signed and dated by the client and the practitioner; the practitioner shall keep the original and provide a copy to the client.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-215__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The owner of a shop for tattooing, permanent cosmetic coloring, or body piercing shall prominently display</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-215__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a copy of the statement provided by the board under
AS 08.13.030</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-215__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>that advises the public of the health risks and possible consequences of tattooing, permanent cosmetic coloring, or body piercing, as applicable;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-215__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the names, addresses, and telephone numbers of the Department of Commerce, Community, and Economic Development and the Department of Environmental Conservation and a description of how a complaint about the shop or a practitioner in the shop may be filed with either entity or with the board.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-13-217">
            <num>08.13.217</num>
            <heading>Tattooing and permanent cosmetic coloring or body piercing on a minor.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-13-217__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not practice tattooing or permanent cosmetic coloring on a minor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-217__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not practice body piercing on a minor without prior written permission from the minor's parent or legal guardian and the presence of the parent or legal guardian during the body piercing procedure. The person who performs the body piercing shall keep a copy of the written permission on file for at least three years.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-217__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who with criminal negligence violates this section is guilty of a class B misdemeanor. In this subsection, criminal negligence has the meaning given in
AS 11.81.900
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-13-220">
            <num>08.13.220</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-13-220__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>cut, trim, polish, color, tint, or cleanse a natural or artificial nail;
(ii) affix material by artificial means to a natural nail for the addition to or extension of the natural nail;
(iii) cleanse, treat, or beautify the hands or feet for cosmetic purposes; or
(iv) otherwise treat the nails of the hand or foot except as provided in (B) of this paragraph;
(B) notwithstanding (A) of this paragraph, does not include</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-13-220__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>massage treatment; or
(ii) cleansing, treating, or beautifying the hands or feet solely for the treatment of disease or physical or mental ailments;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-220__subsec_i__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>non-chemical barbering means shaving, trimming, cutting, styling, or curling the beard or hair of a living person for a fee and for cosmetic purposes;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-220__subsec_i__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>permanent cosmetic coloring means tattooing for the purpose of simulating hair or makeup, such as permanent eyeliner, lip color, eyebrows, and eyeshadow;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-220__subsec_i__subsec_13">
                <num>(13)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>practitioner means a person licensed to practice barbering, non-chemical barbering, hairdressing, hair braiding, manicuring, esthetics, tattooing, permanent cosmetic coloring, or body piercing under this chapter;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-220__subsec_i__subsec_14">
                <num>(14)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shampoo person means a person who, for a fee and under the supervision of a practitioner of barbering or hairdressing, cleanses or conditions the hair of the human head with products that have no effect other than cleaning or conditioning the hair;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-220__subsec_i__subsec_15">
                <num>(15)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shop is an establishment operated for the purpose of engaging in barbering, hairdressing, hair braiding, manicuring, esthetics, tattooing, permanent cosmetic coloring, or body piercing;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-13-220__subsec_i__subsec_16">
                <num>(16)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>tattooing  means the process by which the skin is marked or colored to form indelible marks, figures, or decorative designs for nonmedical purposes by inserting or ingraining an indelible pigment into or onto the skin, microblading, or microneedling.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>