<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-34/chapter-05"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-34/chapter-05"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="34.05"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-34/chapter-05/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-34/chapter-05/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-34/chapter-05/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-34/chapter-05/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_34">
        <num>34</num>
        <heading>Property</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_34__chp_05">
          <num>05</num>
          <heading>Rental of Agricultural, Personal, and Nonresidential Property</heading>
          <section eId="sec_34-05-025">
            <num>34.05.025</num>
            <heading>Agricultural tenants.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.05.025.   Agricultural tenants.
A tenant whose lease or occupancy is for agricultural purposes and who breaches the rental agreement, or continues in possession of the premises at the expiration of the time limited in or contrary to a condition or covenant in the lease or agreement under which the tenant holds, shall be provided with a written notice specifying the breach and demanding the tenant quit the premises at least 30 days before commencement of an action for the recovery of the property.  The tenant shall have free access to the premises to cultivate and harvest crops or produce planted by the tenant before the service of the notice of the breach and demand to quit the premises.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-05-040">
            <num>34.05.040</num>
            <heading>Failure to return rental equipment.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.05.040.   Failure to return rental equipment.
A person in possession of equipment under an agreement in writing that requires the person to return the equipment to a particular place or at a particular time who refuses or wilfully neglects to return it to the place and at the time specified in the agreement in writing, or who secretes, converts, sells, or attempts to sell the equipment or any part of it is, upon conviction, punishable by imprisonment for not more than one year, or by a fine of not more than $1,000, or by both.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-05-050">
            <num>34.05.050</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.05.050.   Definitions.
In
AS 34.05.040
,
(1) equipment means any tools, machinery, implements, or appliances used for any type of purpose or service;
(2) wilfully neglects means omits, fails, or forebears, with a conscious purpose to injure, or without regard for the rights of the owner, or with indifference whether a wrong is done the owner or not.
Article 3. Illegal Activities in Premises Not Subject to Uniform Residential Landlord and Tenant Act.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-05-100">
            <num>34.05.100</num>
            <heading>Tenant responsibilities in premises not subject toAS 34.03.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-05-100__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In rented premises other than premises to which the provisions of
AS 34.03
apply, the tenant may not knowingly engage at the premises in prostitution, an illegal activity involving a place of prostitution, an illegal activity involving alcoholic beverages, an illegal activity involving gambling or promoting gambling, an illegal activity involving a controlled substance, or an illegal activity involving an imitation controlled substance, or knowingly permit others in the premises to engage in one or more of those activities at the rental premises.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-05-100__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If there is noncompliance with (a) of this section, a person may seek relief under
AS 09.50.170
 09.50.240.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-05-100__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An order of abatement entered by a court under
AS 09.50.210
against premises under this section terminates a rental agreement on the premises subject to the order of abatement.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-05-100__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-05-100__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>illegal activity involving alcoholic beverages, illegal activity involving a controlled substance, illegal activity involving an imitation controlled substance, illegal activity involving gambling or promoting gambling, illegal activity involving a place of prostitution, and prostitution have the meanings given in
AS 34.03.360
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-05-100__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>premises means a structure or the structure of which it is a part, and facilities and appurtenances in it, and grounds, areas, and facilities held out for the use of persons entitled to possession under an agreement that relates to its use.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>