<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-28/chapter-05"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-28/chapter-05"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="28.05"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-28/chapter-05/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-28/chapter-05/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-28/chapter-05/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-28/chapter-05/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_28">
        <num>28</num>
        <heading>Motor Vehicles</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_28__chp_05">
          <num>05</num>
          <heading>Administration</heading>
          <section eId="sec_28-05-011">
            <num>28.05.011</num>
            <heading>Duty of commissioners to adopt regulations.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-05-011__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner of public safety shall, unless otherwise provided by statute, adopt regulations in compliance with
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act) necessary to carry out the provisions of this title and other statutes whose administration is vested in the Department of Public Safety. The regulations must include</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-011__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>rules of the road relating to the driving, stopping, standing, parking, and other conduct of vehicles, to pedestrians, and to official traffic control devices; regulations adopted under this paragraph may not prohibit the use of an electric personal motor vehicle on a sidewalk, bike path, or vehicular way or area restricted to the use of pedestrians; limitations on regulation of electric personal motor vehicles imposed under this paragraph do not apply to a municipal ordinance regulating electric personal motor vehicles enacted to meet local requirements;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-011__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>minimum equipment for vehicles, including minimum standards of compliance to be met by manufacturers and vehicle sales and repairs businesses;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-011__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>inspection of vehicles other than commercial motor vehicles, and the removal of vehicles from areas of public use when they are found to be in a defective or unsafe condition;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-011__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>abandonment of vehicles;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-011__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>management of records of the Department of Public Safety required for that department's administration of this title and its regulations adopted under this title, including provisions for ensuring the accuracy of information contained in automated and manual information retrieval systems;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-011__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>definitions of words and phrases used in this title and in regulations adopted under this title unless otherwise provided by statute;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-011__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>certification and regulation of junk yards.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-011__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner of administration shall, unless otherwise provided by statute, adopt regulations in compliance with
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act) necessary to carry out the provisions of this title whose administration is vested in the Department of Administration. The regulations must include, but are not limited to,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-011__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>registration, titling, and transfer of vehicles;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-011__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>licensing of drivers of vehicles and procedures for obtaining limited license privileges;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-011__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>financial responsibility relating to vehicles other than commercial motor vehicles;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-011__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>management of records of the Department of Administration required for that department's administration of this title and its regulations adopted under this title, including provisions for ensuring the accuracy of information contained in automated and manual information retrieval systems;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-011__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>definitions of words and phrases used in this title and in regulations adopted under this title unless otherwise provided by statute;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-011__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>registration of motor vehicle, trailer, and semi-trailer dealers;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-011__subsec_b__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>regulations necessary to implement a commercial motor vehicle driver's licensing program; regulations adopted under this paragraph must provide for a waiver of the driver skills test for drivers with recent military commercial vehicle driving experience as allowed by federal law.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-011__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the department publishes a manual related to the safe and lawful operation of a motor vehicle, the manual must include the rights and responsibilities of drivers when encountering or being stopped by a peace officer.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-05-015">
            <num>28.05.015</num>
            <heading>Wheeled adjuncts.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.05.015.   Wheeled adjuncts.
The department shall, unless prohibited by an ordinance of a governmental subdivision of the state, allow pedestrians to use wheeled adjuncts, such as rollerblades, roller skates, and roller skis, on roadways and vehicular ways in addition to areas available for use by bicycles.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-05-021">
            <num>28.05.021</num>
            <heading>Commissioners to enter compacts and reciprocal agreements.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-05-021__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner of administration may, under terms and conditions best calculated to promote the interests of the state, enter into a compact or agreement with an authorized representative of another jurisdiction in a matter relating to driver licensing, vehicle registration, or other activity authorized under this title, the administration of which is vested in the Department of Administration. The commissioner of public safety may, under the same terms and conditions, enter into a compact or agreement with an authorized representative of another jurisdiction in a matter relating to an activity authorized under this title, the administration of which is vested in the Department of Public Safety. A compact or agreement affecting state finances or driving privileges must be approved by adoption of a concurrent resolution approved by a majority vote of each house of the legislature before it becomes effective.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-021__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 28 ch 90 SLA 1991.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-05-031">
            <num>28.05.031</num>
            <heading>Department of Public Safety to publish statutes and regulations relating to vehicles, vehicle use, and pedestrians.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-05-031__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Public Safety shall publish current state statutes and regulations relating to vehicles and their driving or movement, to drivers of vehicles, and to pedestrians. The cost of publication shall be jointly shared by that department and other state agencies that administer statutes and regulations included in the publication prescribed under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-031__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A single copy of a facsimile of the publication prescribed in (a) of this section shall be available to the public without charge at all offices of the Department of Administration that administer the statutes in this title and at all offices of the Department of Public Safety. However, a municipality may request and receive without charge a reasonable number of copies of the publication.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-05-035">
            <num>28.05.035</num>
            <heading>Approval of accident prevention courses.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.05.035.   Approval of accident prevention courses.
For the purposes of
AS 21.96.025
(a)(4), the commissioner may approve driver education courses intended to prevent motor vehicle accidents and promote safe driving practices.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-05-041">
            <num>28.05.041</num>
            <heading>Forms, applications, and oaths.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-05-041__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner of administration shall prescribe and provide suitable application forms, certificates of title and registration, driver's licenses, and all other forms necessary to carry out the provisions of this title and regulations adopted under this title, the administration of which is vested in the Department of Administration. The commissioner of public safety shall prescribe and provide suitable forms necessary to carry out the provisions of this title and regulations adopted under this title, the administration of which is vested in the Department of Public Safety, including a standard citation form that meets the requirements of
AS 12.25.175
and 12.25.200 and that is in a form necessary to identify the offender and the offense and otherwise necessary to meet the needs of the public safety and the administration of justice as required under
AS 12.25.175
and 12.25.200.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-041__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Administration shall examine and approve or disapprove any application for registration of, or certificate of title for, a vehicle, and for a driver's license and any other application made to the department. The department may make any investigation it considers necessary and may require additional information before approving an application. The department shall reject an application if it is not satisfied with the genuineness, regularity, or legality of the application, the truth of a statement contained in it, or the adequacy or sufficiency of information requested by the department. The department shall reject an application when the applicant is not entitled to issuance of the registration, title, license, or permit for which the person is applying or for any other reason required by law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-041__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner of public safety and officers and employees of the Department of Public Safety designated by that commissioner, and the commissioner of administration and officers and employees of the Department of Administration designated by that commissioner, may, for the purpose of administering this title and regulations adopted under this title, administer oaths and acknowledge signatures, and do so without charging a fee.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-05-045">
            <num>28.05.045</num>
            <heading>Voter registration.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.05.045.   Voter registration.
The administrative component of the department that administers motor vehicle and driver's license laws shall comply with
AS 15.07.055
to serve as a voter registration agency to the extent required by state and federal law, including 42 U.S.C. 1973gg (National Voter Registration Act of 1993) and this section. A state resident, who will be 18 years of age or older within 90 days, who applies in an office of the department for a driver's license, identification card issued under
AS 18.65.310
, or vehicle registration under
AS 28.10
shall at the time of application be advised by the division that the resident may also register to vote. The application submitted by the resident shall serve as an application for voter registration unless the resident fails to sign the voter registration portion of the application. The department shall forward completed voter registration forms to the division of elections. The department shall prominently display notice of the right to apply for voter registration at each place that the public may apply for a driver's license, identification card, or vehicle registration.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-05-048">
            <num>28.05.048</num>
            <heading>Sex offender registration.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.05.048.   Sex offender registration.
The department shall display notice of the registration requirements of
AS 12.63.010
at a place where the public may apply for a driver's license, identification card, or vehicle registration.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-05-051">
            <num>28.05.051</num>
            <heading>Suspended or revoked documents.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-05-051__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the department suspends or revokes a vehicle registration, certificate of registration, registration plate, permit, or certificate of title or suspends, cancels, or revokes a license, the owner or person in possession of the document shall, immediately upon receiving notice of the suspension, revocation, or cancellation, mail or deliver the registration, certificate, plate, permit, or license to the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-051__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner, officers and employees of the department designated by the commissioner, judges and employees of a court, and all peace officers, may take possession of a certificate of title, registration, or license issued by this jurisdiction that has been revoked, canceled, limited, or suspended, or is fictitious, stolen, or altered.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-05-061">
            <num>28.05.061</num>
            <heading>Records of departments and certified copies of records.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-05-061__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Administration shall file, maintain, and appropriately index records of</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-061__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>vehicle registrations under
AS 28.10.071</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-061__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p> (c);</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-061__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>stolen, converted, recovered, and unclaimed vehicles under
AS 28.10.071</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-061__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>titles and documents creating and evidencing liens or encumbrances under
AS 28.10.381
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-061__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>abandoned vehicles under
AS 28.11.030</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-061__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>driver's license and driving records under
AS 28.15.151
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-061__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>applications under
AS 28.10.262
for cancellation of a manufacturer's certificate of origin for a manufactured home;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-061__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>applications under
AS 28.10.263
for cancellation of a certificate of title to a manufactured home;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-061__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>applications under
AS 28.10.264
for confirmation of the nonapplication of
AS 28.10
to a manufactured home;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-061__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>applications under
AS 28.10.265
for a certificate of title to a severed manufactured home;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-061__subsec_a__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>manufacturer's certificates of origin accepted for cancellation by the department under
AS 28.10.262
for a manufactured home; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-061__subsec_a__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>certificates of title accepted for cancellation by the department under
AS 28.10.263
for a manufactured home.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-061__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Administration and the Department of Public Safety each may file and maintain any other records considered necessary for the respective department's administration of this title and regulations adopted by that department under it.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-061__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Records maintained by the Department of Administration or the Department of Public Safety under this title or regulations adopted under this title may be stored in any reasonable manner, including electronic data storage. The commissioner of each of those departments and officers and employees of those departments designated by the respective commissioner shall, upon request, prepare under the seal of the respective department and deliver, unless otherwise prohibited by law, a certified copy of any record of that department maintained under this title or regulations adopted under this title, charging a fee for each certified copy. A certified copy of the record stored under this section is admissible in an administrative proceeding or in a court in the same manner as the original document.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-061__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a copy of a motor vehicle record prepared or maintained by the Department of Administration is requested by the child support services agency created in
AS 25.27.010
, or the child support enforcement agency of another state, the department shall provide the requesting agency with a certified copy of the record. If information is prepared or maintained by the department in an electronic data base, the department may give the requesting agency a copy of the electronic record and a statement certifying its contents. The agency receiving information under this subsection may use the information only for child support purposes authorized under law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-061__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For cancelled manufacturer's certificates of origin, cancelled certificates of title, or applications for confirmation filed under (a)(8), (10), or (11) of this section, the department's record must state</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-061__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name of each owner of the manufactured home;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-061__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the date the manufacturer's certificate of origin or the certificate of title was accepted for cancellation if the certificate was cancelled under (a)(10) or (11) of this section; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-061__subsec_e__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the recording information for the affixation affidavit required by
AS 28.10.266
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-061__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For applications for certificates of title under (a)(9) of this section, the department's record must state the name of each owner of the manufactured home and the recording information for the severance affidavit recorded under
AS 40.17.125
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-061__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, recording information means the district where the affidavit was recorded and the date and serial numbers of the affidavit's recording in the recording district.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-05-065">
            <num>28.05.065</num>
            <heading>Access to criminal justice information.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-05-065__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of carrying out the provisions of
AS 28.05
,
AS 28.15
,
AS 28.33
, and
AS 28.35
, an employee of the department assigned to perform functions under those chapters may access criminal justice information about an adult or minor charged with or convicted of an offense.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-065__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of obtaining access to criminal justice information maintained by the Department of Public Safety under
AS 12.62
, the unit assigned motor vehicle functions in the Department of Administration is a criminal justice agency conducting a criminal justice activity.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-065__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-065__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>criminal justice activity has the meaning given in
AS 12.62.900
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-065__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>criminal justice agency has the meaning given in
AS 12.62.900
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-05-068">
            <num>28.05.068</num>
            <heading>Prohibition on data sharing.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-05-068__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the department conveys, distributes, or communicates data to be used in a database, index, pointer system, or any other system managed by an entity other than the department, including the American Association of Motor Vehicle Administrators, to comply with the requirements of P.L. 109-13, Division B (REAL ID Act of 2005), the department may not convey, distribute, or communicate to that entity any data not required to be conveyed, distributed, or communicated for the state to be certified by the United States Department of Homeland Security to be in compliance with the requirements of P.L. 109-13, Division B (REAL ID Act of 2005).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-068__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (a) of this section, the department may not convey, distribute, or communicate to a private entity any scanned or stored documents collected in order to carry out the provisions of
AS 28.15
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-068__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall take all steps available to obtain from the entity an agreement that the state need not convey, distribute, or communicate social security numbers, in whole or in part, to participate in the database, index, pointer system, or other system.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-068__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall take all steps available to work with other states, the United States Department of Homeland Security, and any multistate entities in which the state participates to secure a means of compliance with P.L. 109-13, Division B (REAL ID Act of 2005), including through an interstate compact, that does not involve the storage or sharing of social security numbers, in whole or in part, with an interstate database, index, pointer system, or other system.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-068__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the department has complied with (c) and (d) of this section and has been unable to secure a means of compliance with P.L. 109-13, Division B (REAL ID Act of 2005) that does not involve the storage or sharing of social security numbers, in whole or in part, the department shall take all steps necessary to minimize the number of digits of a social security number required to be stored or shared.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-068__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may share only the least number of digits of a person's social security number necessary to comply with federal law that requires the department to determine whether a person has been issued a driver's license in another state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-068__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, §  18 ch. 8 SLA 2017]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-05-071">
            <num>28.05.071</num>
            <heading>Change of name or address.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-05-071__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who has applied for or been issued a certificate, registration, title, license, permit, or other form under this title, and who changes the person's name or moves from the address shown on the records or forms of the Department of Administration or the Department of Public Safety, shall notify the appropriate department of the change in name or address within 30 days</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-071__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>on a form or in a format specified by the appropriate department; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-071__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in a manner prescribed in regulations adopted by the appropriate department.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-071__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person convicted of a violation of (a) of this section is guilty of an infraction punishable by a fine not to exceed $25.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-05-081">
            <num>28.05.081</num>
            <heading>Approval of vehicle equipment.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-05-081__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the commissioner has reason to believe that vehicle equipment being sold commercially in the state does not comply with the requirements of this title or regulations adopted under this title or other statutes and regulations, the commissioner may, after giving 30 days notice to the person holding the certificate of approval for the equipment in this state, conduct a hearing upon the question of compliance of the equipment.  After the hearing, the commissioner shall determine whether the equipment is in compliance.  If the equipment is not in compliance with the law, the commissioner shall give notice of that fact to the person holding the certificate of approval for the equipment in this state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-081__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If, at the end of 90 days after the notice of noncompliance given under (a) of this section, the person holding the certificate of approval for the vehicle equipment has failed to satisfy the commissioner that the equipment as sold after the 90 days is in compliance with the law, the commissioner shall suspend or revoke the approval issued for the equipment until the equipment is resubmitted to, and retested by, a testing agency approved by the commissioner and is found to be in compliance with the law.  The commissioner may, at the time of retest, purchase in the open market and submit to the testing agency one or more sets of the equipment.  If the equipment upon retest fails to comply with the law, the commissioner may refuse to renew the certificate of approval of the equipment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-081__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After January 1, 1978, a motorcycle helmet may not be manufactured or sold in this state that does not conform to standards established in regulations adopted by the commissioner. These regulations must provide for helmets that allow normal peripheral vision and hearing and minimize neck injuries to the wearer potentially caused by the helmet.  For the purposes of this section and
AS 28.05.011
(a)(2), a motorcycle helmet is considered to be vehicle equipment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-081__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, commissioner means the commissioner of public safety.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-05-091">
            <num>28.05.091</num>
            <heading>Impoundment of unlawful vehicles.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.05.091.   Impoundment of unlawful vehicles.
A motor vehicle that is driven on a highway or vehicular way or area, and that has been determined to be defective in equipment so as to be unsafe for driving, or on which the vehicle identification number has been removed, defaced, or otherwise altered, is an unlawful vehicle and may be impounded by a peace officer or an employee of the Department of Public Safety officially designated for that purpose. The owner or person in lawful possession of a vehicle that is driven on a highway or vehicular way or area and that is so defective in equipment as to be unsafe for driving shall pay the necessary costs of impounding and storing the vehicle. The impounding of a vehicle is in addition to any other penalty. Nothing in this section prevents the driving or moving of a defective vehicle in the manner directed by the peace officer or employee to a place for
(1) the correction of a defect in the equipment;
(2) dismantling or wrecking; or
(3) storage without repair.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-05-095">
            <num>28.05.095</num>
            <heading>Use of seat belts and child safety devices required.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-05-095__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (c) of this section, a person</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-095__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>16 years of age or older may not occupy a motor vehicle while being driven on a highway unless restrained by a safety belt; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-095__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>may not drive a motor vehicle on a highway unless restrained by a safety belt.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-095__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (c) of this section, a driver may not transport a child under the age of 16 in a motor vehicle unless the driver has provided the required safety device and properly secured each child as described in this subsection. A child</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-095__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>less than one year of age or a child one year of age or older who weighs less than 20 pounds shall be properly secured in a rear-facing child safety seat that meets or exceeds standards of the United States Department of Transportation and is used in accordance with the manufacturer's instructions;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-095__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>one or more years of age but less than four years of age who weighs 20 pounds or more shall be properly secured in a child restraint device that meets or exceeds the standards of the United States Department of Transportation and is used in accordance with the manufacturer's instructions;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-095__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>over four years of age but less than eight years of age who is less than 57 inches in height and weighs 20 or more pounds but less than 65 pounds shall be properly secured in a booster seat that is secured by a seat belt system or by another child passenger restraint system that meets or exceeds the standards of the United States Department of Transportation and is used in accordance with the manufacturer's instructions;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-095__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>over four years of age who exceeds the height or weight requirements in (3) of this subsection shall be properly secured in a seat belt;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-095__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>eight years of age but less than 16 years of age who does not exceed the height and weight requirements in (3) of this subsection shall be properly secured in a child safety device approved for a child of that size by the United States Department of Transportation or in a safety belt, whichever is appropriate for the particular child as determined solely by the driver.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-095__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subsections (a) and (b) of this section do not apply to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-095__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>passengers in a school bus, unless the school bus is required to be equipped with seat belts by the United States Department of Transportation, or an emergency vehicle;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-095__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a vehicle operator acting in the course of employment delivering mail or newspapers from inside the vehicle to roadside mail or newspaper boxes;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-095__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a person or class of persons exempted by regulation under
AS 28.05.096
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-095__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a person required to be restrained by safety belts under (a) or (b) of this section if the motor vehicle is not equipped with safety belts; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-095__subsec_c__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>operators or passengers of motorcycles, motor-driven cycles, off-highway vehicles, electric personal mobility vehicles, snowmobiles, and similar vehicles not designed to be operated on a highway.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-095__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not remove a safety belt from a vehicle solely to be exempted under (c)(4) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-095__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, a peace officer may not stop or detain a motor vehicle to determine compliance with (a) of this section, or issue a citation for a violation of (a) of this section, unless the peace officer has probable cause to stop or detain the motor vehicle.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-095__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In a prosecution under (a) of this section, the prosecution must prove that the peace officer stopping or detaining the vehicle personally observed the violation of (a) of this section before stopping or detaining the vehicle or otherwise had probable cause to stop or detain the vehicle.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-05-096">
            <num>28.05.096</num>
            <heading>Exemptions and alternative safety devices.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-05-096__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner of public safety may adopt regulations to exempt a person or a class of persons from the requirements of
AS 28.05.095
if the commissioner determines that the use of a safety belt or child safety device is impractical because of physical or medical conditions of the person or class of persons.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-096__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner of public safety shall specify alternative means of protection for children exempted under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-05-098">
            <num>28.05.098</num>
            <heading>Sale of child safety devices.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.05.098.   Sale of child safety devices.
A person may not sell, offer for sale, or install in any motor vehicle a child safety device that does not conform to all applicable federal standards for the device on the date of the sale, offering, or installation.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-05-099">
            <num>28.05.099</num>
            <heading>Penalty.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-05-099__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person convicted of a violation of
AS 28.05.095</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-099__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or (d) is guilty of an infraction and may be fined up to $15 or the court may waive the fine if the person convicted donates $15 to the emergency medical services entity providing services in the area in which the violation occurred.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-099__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person convicted of a violation of
AS 28.05.095</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-099__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>is guilty of an infraction, and may be fined up to $50.  The person may also be assessed demerit points as determined by regulations of the department, notwithstanding the provisions of
AS 28.15.231
(b).  A person who violates
AS 28.05.095</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-099__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>by failing to provide a child safety device or safety belt may provide a peace officer, including a village safety officer, proof of purchase or acquisition, and installation, of an approved child safety device or safety belt.  If the proof is provided within 30 days after the issuance of a citation for the infraction, the court shall dismiss the citation and no points shall be assessed under this subsection unless the person has</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-099__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>been convicted previously for violating
AS 28.05.095
by failing to provide a child safety device or safety belt;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-099__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>been cited for failure to provide a child safety device or safety belt and has forfeited the bail required by the citation; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-099__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provided proof under this subsection on a prior occasion.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-05-106">
            <num>28.05.106</num>
            <heading>Custom collector vehicle equipment.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-05-106__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A custom collector vehicle shall be equipped with</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-106__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>hydraulic service brakes on all wheels;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-106__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>sealed beam or halogen headlights;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-106__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>safety belts for all occupants;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-106__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>turn signals and turn signaling switch;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-106__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>safety glass or lexan;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-106__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>electric or vacuum windshield wiper located in front of the driver;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-106__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>standard or blue-dot taillights; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-05-106__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a parking brake that operates on at least two wheels on the same axle.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-106__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding any other provisions of this title or regulations adopted under this title, the Department of Public Safety may not require a custom collector vehicle to be equipped with a bumper, hood, or fenders.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-106__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A custom collector vehicle shall be equipped in a manner that while in motion and functional on the vehicle's four rims on a flat surface, the suspension, steering, or chassis does not contact the highway, vehicular way, or area.
Article 3. Subpoenas, Notices, and Hearings.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-05-111">
            <num>28.05.111</num>
            <heading>Subpoenas of witnesses and documents.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-05-111__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner of public safety and officers and employees of the Department of Public Safety designated by that commissioner, and the commissioner of administration and officers and employees of the Department of Administration designated by that commissioner, may, for good cause, subpoena witnesses to give testimony under oath or to give written deposition upon a matter under the jurisdiction of the appropriate department with respect to this title and regulations adopted under this title. A subpoena issued under this section may require the production of relevant books, papers, documents, records, or other tangible things designated in the subpoena.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-111__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A subpoena issued under this section shall be served at least five days before the return date, either by personal service made by a peace officer or another person who is not less than 18 years of age or by registered or certified mail.  Return acknowledgment is required to prove service by mail.  The fees for the attendance and travel of witnesses are the same as for witnesses appearing before the district court.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-111__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A subpoena issued under this section may be enforced by the district court.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-05-121">
            <num>28.05.121</num>
            <heading>Giving of notice.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.05.121.   Giving of notice.
When the Department of Public Safety or the Department of Administration is authorized or required to give notice under this title or regulations adopted under this title, unless a different method of giving notice is otherwise expressly provided, notice shall be given by a qualified person, either by personal delivery to the person to be notified or by registered or certified mail, return receipt requested, addressed to the person at the address of the person as shown in the records of the appropriate department. The giving of notice by mail is considered complete upon the return of the receipt or upon return of the notice as undeliverable, refused, or unclaimed. Proof of the giving of notice in either manner may be made by the affidavit of the person giving the notice by personal delivery or by mail, naming the person to whom the notice was given and specifying the time, place, and manner of giving the notice.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-05-131">
            <num>28.05.131</num>
            <heading>Opportunity for hearing required.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-05-131__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless otherwise specifically provided, or unless immediate action in suspending, revoking, canceling, limiting, restricting, denying, or impounding is necessary for the protection of the health, safety, or welfare of the public, the Department of Public Safety or the Department of Administration, as appropriate, shall give notice of the opportunity for an administrative hearing before a license, registration, title, permit, or privilege issued or allowed under this title or regulations adopted under this title is suspended, revoked, cancelled, limited, restricted, or denied or a vehicle is impounded by that department. If action is required under this section and prior opportunity for a hearing cannot be afforded, the appropriate department shall promptly give notice of the opportunity for a hearing as soon after the action as possible to the parties concerned.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-131__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The notice under this section must state the reasons for the proposed action of the Department of Public Safety or of the Department of Administration, and must provide for a reasonable attendance date of not less than 10 days after service of the notice. If there is no request for a hearing by the attendance date specified in the notice, the hearing is considered to have been waived.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-05-141">
            <num>28.05.141</num>
            <heading>Hearings and appeals.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-05-141__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless otherwise specifically provided, all hearings required under this title or regulations adopted under this title shall be conducted by the Department of Public Safety or the Department of Administration, as appropriate, under regulations adopted by the appropriate commissioner governing practice and procedure and consistent with due process of law. Hearings must be informal, and technical rules of evidence do not apply. A person who requests a hearing may retain an attorney. The hearing officer shall be appointed by the appropriate commissioner and may be appointed from the department conducting the hearing. A hearing officer need not be an attorney, but must be impartial and may not have participated in the decision that is under review. The hearing officer does not have to file a full opinion or make formal findings of fact or conclusions of law, but the hearing officer must state the reasons for the determination and indicate the evidence relied upon. The proceedings at the hearing shall be recorded.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-141__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A hearing ordered under (a) of this section must be held by telephone unless the hearing officer finds that a telephonic hearing would substantially prejudice the rights of the person involved in the hearing or that an in-person hearing is necessary to decide the issues to be presented in the hearing. An in-person hearing must be held at the office of the Department of Public Safety or of the Department of Administration nearest to the residence of the person involved in the hearing unless the appropriate department and the person agree that the hearing is to be held elsewhere. The appropriate department shall grant a hearing delay if the person presents good cause for the delay. If a person fails to attend or appear for the hearing at the time and place stated by the appropriate department and if a hearing delay has not been granted, the person's failure to attend or appear is considered a waiver of the hearing and the appropriate department may take appropriate action with respect to the person.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-141__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If at a hearing conducted by the Department of Administration under (a) of this section it appears that the record of the person sustains suspension, revocation, limitation, denial, or other remedial action, the hearing officer shall so order and the Department of Administration may suspend, revoke, limit, deny, or take other remedial action against that person's license, registration, or title and, if appropriate, the department shall adjust the person's point total accumulated under
AS 28.15.231
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-141__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person aggrieved by the decision of the hearing officer may, within 30 days after a decision is mailed or delivered to the person, file an appeal in superior court for judicial review of the hearing officer's decision. The judicial review shall be on the record. The court may reverse the determination of the Department of Public Safety or of the Department of Administration if the court finds that the department making the determination misinterpreted the law, acted in an arbitrary and capricious manner, or made a determination unsupported by the evidence in the record. The respective department's decision suspending, revoking, canceling, limiting, restricting, or denying a license, registration, title, permit, or privilege is stayed and does not take effect during the pendency of an appeal.
Article 4. Disposition of Certain Vehicle and Traffic Offenses.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-05-151">
            <num>28.05.151</num>
            <heading>Citations for scheduled vehicle and traffic offenses.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-05-151__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The supreme court shall determine by rule or order those motor vehicle and traffic offenses, except for offenses subject to a scheduled municipal fine, that are amenable to disposition without court appearance and shall establish a scheduled amount of bail, not to exceed fines prescribed by law, for each offense. A municipality shall determine by ordinance the municipal motor vehicle and traffic offenses that may be disposed of without court appearance and shall establish a fine schedule for each offense.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-151__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The supreme court shall establish a scheduled amount of bail allowing disposition of a citation for a violation of
AS 28.05.095
and
AS 28.35.161
that is punishable as a violation without court appearance.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-151__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The supreme court shall require as a condition of the disposition of an offense without appearance that a person charged with any offense for which a bail forfeiture amount has been adopted shall pay the surcharge prescribed in
AS 12.55.039
in addition to the bail forfeiture amount established by the supreme court. The surcharge required to be paid under this subsection shall be deposited into the general fund and accounted for under
AS 37.05.142
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-151__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The supreme court, in establishing scheduled amounts of bail under this section, and each municipality that establishes or has established a fine schedule under this section shall provide that the scheduled amount of bail or fine, as applicable, for a motor vehicle or traffic offense that is committed in a highway work zone or traffic safety corridor shall be double the amount of the bail or fine for the offense if it had not been committed in a highway work zone or traffic safety corridor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-05-151__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The supreme court, in establishing scheduled amounts of bail under this section, and each municipality that establishes or has established a fine schedule under this section may not allow for the disposition of an offense without court appearance for a person who is cited for violation of the traffic laws in connection with a motor vehicle accident if the accident resulted in the death of a person. In this subsection, traffic laws has the meaning given in
AS 28.15.261
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-05-155">
            <num>28.05.155</num>
            <heading>Court and collection costs.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.05.155.   Court and collection costs.
If a person's permanent fund dividend is attached to pay the bail or fine for an offense involving a moving motor vehicle, the court shall increase the bail or fine of that person by at least
(1) $25 for court costs; and
(2) $10 for collection costs.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>