<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-18/chapter-65"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-18/chapter-65"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="18.65"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-18/chapter-65/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-18/chapter-65/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-18/chapter-65/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-18/chapter-65/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_18">
        <num>18</num>
        <heading>Health, Safety, Housing, Human Rights, and Public Defender</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_18__chp_65">
          <num>65</num>
          <heading>Police Protection</heading>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-010">
            <num>18.65.010</num>
            <heading>Commissioner of public safety may appoint special officers.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-010__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner of public safety may appoint as special officers qualified police officers of the federal, state, or local government units or other persons with adequate police training over the age of 19 years, as the commissioner considers necessary to aid and assist the division of state troopers in the enforcement of the criminal laws of the state. Each special officer appointed serves without compensation and at the pleasure of the commissioner of public safety and appointments shall be of limited duration.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-010__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each person appointed as a special officer under this section may prevent crime, pursue and apprehend offenders, obtain legal evidence, institute criminal proceedings, execute warrants of arrest or search and seizure, or other criminal process issuing from any court of the state. A special officer may make arrests in the same manner as a member of the division of state troopers.  The authority and duties conferred by this section may be exercised in each case only within the geographical limits determined by the commissioner of public safety.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-010__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each special officer shall carry identification issued by the commissioner of public safety and shall carry firearms in the manner the commissioner of public safety requires.  Each person appointed shall take the constitutional oath of office.  Persons appointed may hold other public or private employment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-010__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 3 ch 6 SLA 1978.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-020">
            <num>18.65.020</num>
            <heading>Uniforms and equipment.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.020.   Uniforms and equipment.
The state shall provide members of the state troopers with standard uniforms, vehicles, supplies, and equipment necessary to carry out the objects and purposes of
AS 18.65.020
 18.65.110.  All of this property shall remain the property of the state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-030">
            <num>18.65.030</num>
            <heading>Establishment of stations and headquarters.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.030.   Establishment of stations and headquarters.
The commissioner of public safety shall establish stations and headquarters at the places and localities that are necessary for the enforcement of the laws. The state troopers may, with the approval of the governor, have the right to use land and buildings for the accommodation of its members, their vehicles, and equipment.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-040">
            <num>18.65.040</num>
            <heading>Service without uniform.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.040.   Service without uniform.
The commissioner of public safety may direct a member to serve without wearing a uniform.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-050">
            <num>18.65.050</num>
            <heading>Central information.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.050.   Central information.
The Department of Public Safety shall make available central information on fingerprints, handwriting, ballistics, stains, and other evidence of crime.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-080">
            <num>18.65.080</num>
            <heading>Powers and duties of department and members of state troopers.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-080__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Public Safety and each member of the state troopers is charged with the enforcement of all criminal laws of the state, and has the power of a peace officer of the state or a municipality and those powers usually and customarily exercised by peace officers.  Each member of the state troopers may prevent crime, pursue and apprehend offenders, obtain legal evidence, institute criminal proceedings, execute any lawful warrant or order of arrest, make an arrest without warrant for a violation of law committed in the presence of the state trooper, and may cooperate with other law enforcement agencies in detecting crime, apprehending criminals, and preserving law and order in the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-080__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Public Safety shall investigate an individual who applies to be employed as a village public safety officer under
AS 18.65.672
or certified as a village public safety officer under
AS 18.65.682
upon receipt of the materials listed in
AS 18.65.674
(a)(1) from a village public safety officer grant recipient to determine whether the individual has been convicted of a disqualifying crime listed in
AS 18.65.672
(a)(6).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-085">
            <num>18.65.085</num>
            <heading>Narcotic drugs and alcohol enforcement.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-085__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>There is established in the Department of Public Safety, division of state troopers, a narcotic drugs and alcohol enforcement unit for the purpose of investigating and combating the illicit sale and distribution of narcotic drugs and alcoholic beverages in the state. Enforcement of the alcoholic beverage control laws shall focus primarily on the investigation, apprehension, and conviction of persons who violate
AS 04.11.010
by selling, importing, or possessing alcoholic beverages in violation of a local option adopted by a municipality or established village under
AS 04.11.491
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-085__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner of public safety shall prepare a report concerning the activities of the narcotic drugs and alcohol enforcement unit. The commissioner shall notify the legislature on the first day of each regular session that the report is available. The report must include, but is not limited to, the number of arrests made, the kind, amount, and value of narcotic drugs and alcoholic beverages seized, the sentences received by narcotic drug and alcohol offenders, and an overall view of the narcotic drug and illicit alcohol problem in the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-085__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Public Safety may establish and administer a reward program, and provide grants to municipalities, established villages, and, at the request of a municipality or established village, to a nonprofit association that administers a village public safety officer program, for reward programs leading to the apprehension and conviction of persons who violate
AS 04.09.060
, 04.09.800, or
AS 04.11.010
by selling, importing, or possessing alcoholic beverages in violation of a local option adopted by a municipality or established village under
AS 04.11.491
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-086">
            <num>18.65.086</num>
            <heading>Investigative unit on sexually abused and criminally exploited children.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-086__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>There is established in the Department of Public Safety, division of state troopers, a special unit for the purpose of investigating cases of repeated child sexual abuse and the criminal exploitation of children.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-086__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner of public safety shall prepare, in odd-numbered years, a report concerning the activities of the special unit on repeated child sexual abuse and the criminal exploitation of children. The commissioner shall notify the legislature by the first day of each regular session in an odd-numbered year that the report is available. The report must include, but is not limited to, the number of arrests made in cases of repeated child sexual abuse and the criminal exploitation of children, the number of investigations that result in the Department of Family and Community Services taking temporary or permanent custody of the child, the sentences received by persons convicted in the state of child sexual abuse or criminal exploitation of a child, and an overall view of the problems of child sexual abuse and the criminal exploitation of children in the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-086__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-086__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>child means a person under 18 years of age at the time the alleged offense was committed by or against the person;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-086__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>criminal exploitation of children means the use of a child by an adult in a criminal manner for the personal gratification or profit of the adult;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-086__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>repeated child sexual abuse means conduct that is a criminal sexual offense against a child under
AS 11
and that is committed against the child more than once or against more than one child.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-087">
            <num>18.65.087</num>
            <heading>Central registry of sex offenders.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-087__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Public Safety shall maintain a central registry of sex offenders and child kidnappers and shall adopt regulations necessary to carry out the purposes of this section and
AS 12.63
. A post of the Alaska state troopers or a municipal police department that receives registration or change of address information under
AS 12.63.010
shall forward the information within five working days after receipt to the central registry of sex offenders and child kidnappers. Unless the sex offender or child kidnapper provides proof satisfactory to the department that the sex offender or child kidnapper is not physically present in the state or that the time limits described in
AS 12.63.010
have passed, the Department of Public Safety may enter and maintain in the registry information described in
AS 12.63.010
about a sex offender or child kidnapper that the department obtains from</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-087__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the sex offender or child kidnapper under
AS 12.63
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-087__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a post of the Alaska state troopers or a municipal police department under this subsection;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-087__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a court judgment under
AS 12.55.148
,
AS 26.05.890</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-087__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Department of Corrections under
AS 33.30.012
or 33.30.035;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-087__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Federal Bureau of Investigation or another sex offender registration agency outside this state if the information indicates that a sex offender or child kidnapper is believed to be residing or planning to reside in the state or cannot be located;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-087__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a criminal justice agency in the state or another jurisdiction;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-087__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the department's central repository under
AS 12.62
; information entered in the registry from the repository is not subject to the requirements of
AS 12.62.160</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-087__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Department of Military and Veterans' Affairs; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-087__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>another reliable source as defined in regulations adopted by the department.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-087__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Information about a sex offender or child kidnapper that is contained in the central registry, including sets of fingerprints, is confidential and not subject to public disclosure except as to the sex offender's or child kidnapper's name, aliases, address, photograph, physical description, description of motor vehicles, license numbers of motor vehicles, and vehicle identification numbers of motor vehicles, place of employment, date of birth, crime for which convicted, date of conviction, place and court of conviction, length and conditions of sentence, and a statement as to whether the offender or kidnapper is in compliance with requirements of
AS 12.63
or cannot be located.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-087__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (b) of this section, if a sex offender has been convicted in this state or another jurisdiction of a sex offense identified as incest, that offense may be disclosed under (b) of this section only as a felony sexual abuse of a minor conviction.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-087__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Public Safety</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-087__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall adopt regulations to
(A) allow a sex offender or child kidnapper to review sex offender or child kidnapper registration information that refers to that sex offender or child kidnapper, and if the sex offender or child kidnapper believes the information is inaccurate or incomplete, to request the department to correct the information; if the department finds the information is inaccurate or incomplete, the department shall correct or supplement the information;
(B) ensure the appropriate circulation to law enforcement agencies of information contained in the central registry;
(C) ensure the anonymity of members of the public who request information under this section;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-087__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall provide to the Department of Corrections and municipal police departments the forms and directions necessary to allow sex offenders and child kidnappers to comply with
AS 12.63.010
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-087__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>may adopt regulations to establish fees to be charged for registration under
AS 12.63.010
and for information requests; the fee for registration shall be based upon the actual costs of performing the registration and maintaining the central registry but may not be set at a level whereby registration is discouraged; the fee for an information request may not be greater than $10;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-087__subsec_d__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall remove from the central registry of sex offenders and child kidnappers under this section information about a sex offender or child kidnapper required to register under
AS 12.63.020</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-087__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The name, address, and other identifying information of a member of the public who makes an information request under this section is not a public record under
AS 40.25.100
 40.25.295.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-087__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When a sex offender or child kidnapper registers under
AS 12.63
, the Department of Public Safety shall make reasonable attempts to verify that the sex offender or child kidnapper is residing at the registered address. Reasonable attempts at verifying an address include sending certified mail, return receipt requested, to the offender or kidnapper at the registered address. The department shall make reasonable efforts to locate an offender or kidnapper who cannot be located at the registered address.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-087__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department, at least quarterly, shall compile a list of those persons with a duty to register under
AS 12.63.010
who have failed to register, whose addresses cannot be verified under (f) of this section, or who otherwise cannot be located. The department shall post this list on the Internet and request the public's assistance in locating these persons.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-087__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Public Safety shall provide on the Internet website that the department maintains for the central registry of sex offenders and child kidnappers information as to how members of the public using the website may access or compile the information relating to sex offenders or child kidnappers for a particular geographic area on a map. The information may direct members to mapping programs available on the Internet and to Internet websites where information contained in the registry has already been converted to a map or geographic format.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-087__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (b) of this section, the department may provide a method for, or may participate in a federal program that allows, the public to submit an electronic or messaging address or Internet identifier and receive a confirmation of whether the address or identifier has been registered by a registered sex offender or child kidnapper.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-090">
            <num>18.65.090</num>
            <heading>Department to assist other agencies.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.090.   Department to assist other agencies.
The Department of Public Safety shall assist other departments of the state, municipal, and federal governments in the enforcement of criminal laws and regulations pertaining to those departments.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-100">
            <num>18.65.100</num>
            <heading>Power to command assistance from others.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.100.   Power to command assistance from others.
The Department of Public Safety and members of the state troopers may command the assistance of any able-bodied person to aid in accomplishing the purposes of
AS 18.65.020
 18.65.110, and when called, the person, during the time assistance is required, is considered a member of the state troopers and subject to
AS 18.65.020
 18.65.110.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-110">
            <num>18.65.110</num>
            <heading>Members not to interfere with rights and property.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.110.   Members not to interfere with rights and property.
Members of the state troopers may not interfere with the rights or property of any person except in a lawful manner necessary for the prevention of crime or the capture and arrest of an offender.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-130">
            <num>18.65.130</num>
            <heading>Policy.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.130.   Policy.
The administration of criminal justice affects the health, safety, and welfare of the people of this state and requires education and training of a professional quality. It is a primary public interest that applicants meet minimum standards for employment as police officers, probation and parole officers, and correctional officers, and that criminal justice education and training be made available to police officers, probation and parole officers, and correctional officers serving in a probationary capacity and police officers, probation and parole officers, and correctional officers already in regular service. It is of secondary public interest to encourage the establishment of preliminary training programs for persons seeking to become police officers, probation and parole officers, and correctional officers. Application of standards for employment and making education and training available for municipal correctional officers is also in the public interest.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-140">
            <num>18.65.140</num>
            <heading>Creation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.140.   Creation.
There is created in the Department of Public Safety the Alaska Police Standards Council.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-150">
            <num>18.65.150</num>
            <heading>Composition of council.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.150.   Composition of council.
The council consists of the following persons:
(1) four chief administrative officers or chiefs of police of local governments;
(2) the commissioner of public safety or a designee of the commissioner;
(3) the commissioner of corrections or a designee of the commissioner;
(4) two persons, each of whom has been certified for five years or more by the council under this chapter, one of whom serves as a police officer and one of whom serves as a probation officer, parole officer, municipal correctional officer, or correctional officer;
(5) one correctional administrative officer who is employed at the level of a deputy director or higher; and
(6) four members of the public at large with at least two from the communities of 2,500 population or less.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-160">
            <num>18.65.160</num>
            <heading>Appointment.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.160.   Appointment.
The commissioner of public safety or a designee and the commissioner of corrections or a designee shall serve during each commissioner's continuance in office. Other members of the council shall be appointed by the governor for staggered terms of four years, except that a member may not serve beyond the time the member holds the office that established eligibility for appointment.  A vacancy on the council shall be filled for the remainder of a member's unexpired term in the same manner as the original appointment.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-170">
            <num>18.65.170</num>
            <heading>Chairman and vice chairman.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.170.   Chairman and vice chairman.
The council shall select its chairman and vice chairman annually.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-180">
            <num>18.65.180</num>
            <heading>Holding another office.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.180.   Holding another office.
Membership on the council does not disqualify a member from holding any other public office or employment.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-190">
            <num>18.65.190</num>
            <heading>Compensation and expenses.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.190.   Compensation and expenses.
The members of the council receive no salary, but are entitled to per diem and travel expenses authorized by law for other boards and commissions.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-200">
            <num>18.65.200</num>
            <heading>Meetings.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.200.   Meetings.
The council shall meet at least twice a year. The chairman shall set the time and place of the meeting, either on the chairman's own motion or on written request by any three members of the council.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-220">
            <num>18.65.220</num>
            <heading>Powers.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.220.   Powers.
The council has the power to
(1) adopt regulations for the administration of
AS 18.65.130
 18.65.290;
(2) establish minimum standards for employment as a police officer, probation officer, parole officer, municipal correctional officer, and correctional officer in a permanent or probationary position and certify persons to be qualified as police officers, probation officers, parole officers, municipal correctional officers, and correctional officers under
AS 18.65.130
 18.65.290;
(3) establish minimum criminal justice curriculum requirements for basic, specialized, and in-service courses and programs for schools operated by or for the state or a political subdivision of the state for the specific purpose of training police recruits, police officers, probation officers, parole officers, municipal correctional officers, and correctional officers; the curriculum requirements established under this paragraph must include training in
(A) recognizing persons with disabilities;
(B) appropriate interactions with persons with disabilities;
(C) resources available to persons with disabilities and to those interacting with persons with disabilities; and
(D) the requirements of 42 U.S.C. 12131  12165 (Title II of the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990);
(4) consult and cooperate with municipalities, agencies of the state, other governmental agencies, universities, colleges, and other institutions concerning the development of police officer, probation officer, parole officer, municipal correctional officer, and correctional officer training schools and programs of criminal justice instruction;
(5) employ an administrator and other persons necessary to carry out its duties under
AS 18.65.130
 18.65.290;
(6) investigate when there is reason to believe that a police officer, probation officer, parole officer, municipal correctional officer, or correctional officer does not meet the minimum standards for employment; in connection with the investigation the council may subpoena persons, books, records, or documents related to the investigation and require answers in writing under oath to questions asked by the council or the administrator;
(7) charge and collect a fee of $50 for processing applications for certification of police, probation, parole, municipal correctional, and correctional officers;
(8)  require a state and national criminal history record check for an applicant to a training program established in
AS 18.65.230
and for a person to be certified as a police officer under
AS 18.65.240
if that person's prospective employer does not have access to a criminal justice information system.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-225">
            <num>18.65.225</num>
            <heading>Alaska police training fund.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.225.   Alaska police training fund.
The Alaska police training fund is created in the general fund. The fund consists of appropriations made by the legislature to the fund. The legislature may appropriate to the fund the annual estimated balance in the accounts maintained under
AS 37.05.142
for money collected under
AS 12.25.195
(c),
AS 12.55.039
,
AS 28.05.151
, and
AS 29.25.074
. The legislature may make appropriations from the fund to (1) the Department of Public Safety for the Public Safety Training Academy, including Village Public Safety Officers, (2) the Alaska Police Standards Council to provide training for the law enforcement and corrections community of the state under
AS 18.65.230
, and (3) municipalities that conduct their own police training programs. Nothing in this section creates a dedicated fund.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-230">
            <num>18.65.230</num>
            <heading>Training programs; criminal history records check.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-230__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The council shall establish and maintain police training programs, probation and parole officer training programs, and correctional training programs through those agencies and institutions that the council considers appropriate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-230__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To determine a person's qualification for appointment as a police officer under
AS 18.65.240
, each person who applies for admittance to a basic program of police training established under this section shall submit to the council the person's fingerprints along with the fee established in
AS 12.62.160
unless the person's fingerprints were previously submitted by the person's prospective employer. The Department of Public Safety shall conduct a state criminal history record check and may submit the person's fingerprints to the Federal Bureau of Investigation to obtain a national criminal history record check of the person under
AS 12.62.400
for the purpose of evaluating the person's qualifications for appointment as a police officer under
AS 18.65.240
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-240">
            <num>18.65.240</num>
            <heading>Standards.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-240__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not be appointed as a police officer, except on a probationary basis, unless the person (1) has satisfactorily completed a basic program of police training approved by the council, which includes at least 12 hours of instruction regarding domestic violence and at least 12 hours of instruction regarding sexual assault, as those terms are defined in
AS 18.66.990
, (2) possesses other qualifications the council has established for the employment of police officers, including minimum age, education, physical and mental standards, citizenship, moral character, and experience, and (3) has completed cultural training supervised by an Indigenous coordinator or Indigenous entity in the state that is related to addressing the rates of missing and murdered Indigenous persons. The council shall prescribe the means of presenting evidence of fulfillment of these requirements.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-240__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subject to (d) of this section, thecouncil shall issue a certificate evidencing satisfaction of the requirements of (a) of this section to an applicant who satisfies those requirements or who satisfies the requirements of (a)(2) of this section and satisfactorily completes a program or course of instruction in another jurisdiction equivalent in content and quality to that required by the council for approved police education and training programs in this state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-240__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The council may deny or revoke the certificate of a police officer who does not meet the standards adopted under (a)(2) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-240__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The council may not issue a certificate under (b) of this section to an applicant unless the council determines that the applicant will undergo a national criminal history record check before employment as a police officer. If a prospective employer of a person seeking certification under this section does not have access to a criminal justice information system to obtain a report of criminal justice information under
AS 12.62
and a national criminal history record check, the prospective employer shall submit to the council the applicant's fingerprints along with the fee established in
AS 12.62.160
. The council or prospective employer shall submit the fingerprints to the Department of Public Safety to request a national criminal history record check of the person for the purpose of evaluating the person's qualifications for appointment as a police officer.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-242">
            <num>18.65.242</num>
            <heading>Standards for municipal correctional, correctional, probation, and parole officers.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-242__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The council shall establish qualifications for employment of persons as municipal correctional, correctional, probation, and parole officers, including</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-242__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>minimum age, physical and mental standards, citizenship, moral character, and experience; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-242__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>minimum education standards.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-242__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The council shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-242__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>prescribe the means of presenting evidence of fulfillment of the requirements set out in (a) of this section; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-242__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>issue a certificate evidencing satisfaction of the requirements of (a) of this section to an applicant who
(A) satisfies the requirements of (a)(1) of this section; and
(B) meets the minimum education standards of (a)(2) of this section by satisfactorily completing a training program for municipal correctional, correctional, probation, or parole officers established under
AS 18.65.230
, including training regarding domestic violence that contains the subjects set out in
AS 18.66.310</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-242__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In the evaluation of applicants against the mental standards developed under (a)(1) of this section, the council shall use evaluation methods that do not discriminate against applicants of different ethnic origins.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-245">
            <num>18.65.245</num>
            <heading>Denial or revocation of certificate of municipal correctional, correctional, probation, or parole officer.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.245.   Denial or revocation of certificate of municipal correctional, correctional, probation, or parole officer.
The council may
(1) deny a certificate to an applicant for a municipal correctional, correctional, probation, or parole officer certificate if the applicant does not meet the standards adopted by the council under
AS 18.65.242
(a);
(2) revoke the certificate of a municipal correctional, correctional, probation, or parole officer who, having been issued a certificate, fails to meet the standards adopted by the council under
AS 18.65.242
(a).</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-248">
            <num>18.65.248</num>
            <heading>Employment of correctional, probation, and parole officers.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-248__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not be appointed as a municipal correctional, correctional, probation, or parole officer unless the person has a valid certificate issued by the council under
AS 18.65.242
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-248__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The provisions of (a) of this section do not apply to a person employed on a probationary basis, except that employment on a probationary basis may not exceed the period authorized for probationary employment determined by the council.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-260">
            <num>18.65.260</num>
            <heading>Grants.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-260__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The council may accept donations of property, both real and personal, and grants of money from a governmental unit or public agency, or from an institution or person. All money received by the council under this section shall be deposited in the state treasury to the account of the council.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-260__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The council shall provide for and administer a funding program authorized in (a) of this section.  In the administration of the program the council shall promote the most efficient and economical program for police training, including the maximum utilization of existing facilities and programs to avoid duplication.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-270">
            <num>18.65.270</num>
            <heading>Applicability of Administrative Procedure Act.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.270.   Applicability of Administrative Procedure Act.
AS 18.65.150
 18.65.290 shall be administered in compliance with
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act).</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-280">
            <num>18.65.280</num>
            <heading>Exemptions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-280__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner and deputy commissioner of public safety and the chief administrative officers of local police departments are exempt from the requirements of
AS 18.65.240
.  However, a person appointed chief of a local police department after July 1, 1981, who performs any operational duties, shall meet the requirements of
AS 18.65.240
(a)(1).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-280__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A political subdivision with an established police training program meeting the requirements of
AS 18.65.220</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-280__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>and (3) may exclude itself from the requirements of
AS 18.65.240
by ordinance.  The exclusion has no effect on eligibility to receive federal or state grants.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-285">
            <num>18.65.285</num>
            <heading>Municipal correctional employees.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.285.   Municipal correctional employees.
A municipality that employs persons in a municipal correctional facility may, by ordinance, require that those persons meet the requirements of
AS 18.65.130
 18.65.290 that are applicable to municipal correctional officers.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-290">
            <num>18.65.290</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.290.   Definitions.
In
AS 18.65.130
  18.65.290,
(1) chief administrative officer means a chief of police or other official who is head of a police department in a political subdivision;
(2) correctional facility means a prison or jail owned, leased, or operated by the state that is designated by the commissioner of corrections for the custody, care, security, control, and discipline of prisoners;
(3) correctional officer means a person
(A) appointed by the commissioner of corrections whose primary duty under
AS 33.30
is to provide custody, care, security, control, and discipline of persons charged or convicted of offenses against the state or held under authority of state law; or
(B) employed in a correctional facility in this state whose primary duty is to provide custody, care, security, control, and discipline of persons charged or convicted of offenses or held under authority of law;
(4) council means the Alaska Police Standards Council;
(5) criminal justice information system has the meaning given in
AS 12.62.900
;
(6) municipal correctional officer means a person who is employed full-time in a municipal correctional facility whose primary duty is to provide custody, care, security, control, and discipline of persons charged or convicted of offenses or held under authority of law; and the municipality has adopted an ordinance under
AS 18.65.285
making
AS 18.65.130
  18.65.290 applicable;
(7) parole officer means a person appointed by the commissioner of corrections or employed by a correctional facility in this state to perform the duties of supervising the parole of prisoners under
AS 33.16
;
(8) police officer means
(A) an employee of the state or a municipal police department with the authority to arrest and issue citations; detain a person taken into custody until that person can be arraigned before a judge or magistrate; conduct investigations of violations of and enforce criminal laws, regulations, and traffic laws; search with or without a warrant persons, dwellings, and other forms of property for evidence of a crime; and take other action consistent with exercise of these enumerated powers when necessary to maintain the public peace;
(B) an officer or employee of the Department of Transportation and Public Facilities who is stationed at an international airport and has been designated to have the general police powers authorized under
AS 02.15.230
(a);
(C) a University of Alaska public safety officer with general police powers authorized under
AS 14.40.043
;
(9) probation officer means a person appointed by the commissioner of corrections or employed by a correctional facility in this state to perform the duties of a probation officer under
AS 33.05
.
Article 3. Identification Cards.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-310">
            <num>18.65.310</num>
            <heading>Identification cards.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-310__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon payment of a $15 fee, the department shall issue a card identical to the motor vehicle operator's license provided for in
AS 28.15.111
, except that the card shall be of a different color and shall state in bold type letters across the face of it that it is for identification purposes only. Upon request of a person and upon payment of an additional $20 fee, the department may issue an identification card under this section that is federally compliant.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-310__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may obtain an identification card provided for in (a) of this section by applying to the department on forms and in the manner prescribed by the department. The department shall include on the application for an identification card a requirement that the applicant indicate</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-310__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>that the applicant understands the options for identification cards available at the time of issuance; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-310__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the type of identification card that the applicant selects.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-310__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Any person who knowingly makes a fraudulent written statement or application for an identification card concerning age, race, sex, or other identifying characteristics as required by the department is guilty of a misdemeanor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-310__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>It is a misdemeanor for any person to possess, use, produce, or manufacture a fraudulent identification card.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-310__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>It is a misdemeanor for a person to allow an identification card issued to that person to be used by any other person.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-310__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who violates (c), (d), or (e) of this section is guilty of a misdemeanor punishable by a fine of $500 or 60 days in jail, or both.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-310__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the person applying for the identification card provided for in (a) of this section is 60 years of age or older, charge may not be made for issuance of the card.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-310__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall cancel the identification card of a person on whom a restriction has been imposed under
AS 04.16.160
unless the person's identification card contains the information required by (i) of this section. A cancellation under this subsection remains in effect only during the period of time that the person is restricted from purchasing alcoholic beverages under
AS 04.16.160
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-310__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall, to the extent it is able, mark the identification card of an applicant who is restricted from purchasing alcoholic beverages under
AS 04.16.160
in the same manner required for a driver's license under
AS 28.15.111
. A person who has received a marked identification card under this subsection may apply for an unmarked card when the period of restriction under
AS 04.16.160
has expired.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-310__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall charge a fee of $50 for issuance of a marked identification card under (i) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-310__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An identification card issued to a person under 21 years of age expires 90 days after the person reaches 21 years of age.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-310__subsec_l">
              <num>(l)</num>
              <content>
                <p>At the request of the person, the department shall provide a veteran designation and United States flag replica on an identification card identifying the person as a retired veteran, a veteran of the armed forces of the United States discharged under honorable conditions, or a Hmong veteran or Lao veteran who served in military operations in support of the United States in the Kingdom of Laos between February 28, 1961, and May 15, 1975. The department may not charge a fee solely for the designation. To receive a veteran designation, the person shall provide proof of veteran status that shows the person is retired, was discharged under honorable conditions, or is a Hmong veteran or Lao veteran. The department shall consult with the Department of Military and Veterans' Affairs to determine the proof necessary to show that a person is a Hmong veteran or Lao veteran. With the approval of the person, the department shall make available to the Department of Military and Veterans' Affairs the name and address of a person receiving a veteran designation under this subsection. Notwithstanding (a) of this section, the department may charge a fee of $5 for replacement of a valid identification card with a new identification card with a veteran designation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-310__subsec_m">
              <num>(m)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall provide a method for a person to designate voluntarily on an identification card that the person has a disability, including a cognitive, mental, neurological, or physical disability, or a combination of those disabilities. The department shall create a discreet symbol to place on the identification card of a person requesting the designation. The method must provide a means by which the person may cancel the designation. The department may not charge a fee solely for the designation. To receive the designation, the person shall provide proof of the disability from a person licensed as a physician or physician assistant under
AS 08.64
, as a naturopath under
AS 08.45
, as an advanced practice registered nurse under
AS 08.68
, or as a licensed psychologist under
AS 08.86
. Notwithstanding (a) of this section, the department may charge a fee of $5 for replacement of a valid identification card with a new identification card with a disability designation and may charge a fee of $5 for replacement of an identification card with a disability designation with a new identification card without a disability designation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-310__subsec_n">
              <num>(n)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall adopt regulations for the issuance of identification cards that are federally compliant. For identification cards that are federally compliant, the department</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-310__subsec_n__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall copy, scan, or retain only the minimum number of documents required by P.L. 109-13, Division B (REAL ID Act of 2005), or other applicable state or federal law, for issuance of an identification card that is federally compliant;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-310__subsec_n__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall destroy, regularly and as close as practicable to 15 years after the date of application unless otherwise required by another applicable state or federal law, any documents retained under (1) of this subsection; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-310__subsec_n__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>may not copy, scan, or retain in any form a document that is not required to be retained under (1) of this subsection.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-310__subsec_o">
              <num>(o)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall continue to issue identification cards that are not federally compliant. Nothing in this section or regulations adopted under this section requires a person to be issued an identification card that is federally compliant. An applicant must clearly request an identification card that is federally compliant to obtain one. The state or a municipal government may not require a person to possess or use an identification card that is federally compliant unless the person is a state or municipal employee and the duties of the person's job require the use of an identification card that is federally compliant. The state or a municipal government shall otherwise treat an identification card that is not federally compliant the same as an identification card that is federally compliant. For an identification card that is not federally compliant, the department</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-310__subsec_o__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall retain an image of the face on the identification card for not more than 15 years after the date of application; if an applicant does not receive an identification card, the department may not retain an image of the applicant's face;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-310__subsec_o__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall scan and retain only the minimum documents necessary for issuance of the identification card; the department shall destroy any documents retained one year after the identification card expires.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-310__subsec_p">
              <num>(p)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An identification card expires on the person's birthday in the eighth year following issuance of the identification card. An identification card may be renewed within one year of its expiration upon proper application and payment of the required fee. An identification card may be renewed by mail or on the department's Internet website, except that an identification card may not be renewed by mail or on the department's Internet website if the most recent renewal of the applicant's identification card was by mail or on the department's Internet website. Under regulations adopted by the department, the department may issue to a person an identification card with a duration of less than eight years if the person is authorized to stay in the United States for less than eight years or if the period of authorized stay is indefinite. The department shall issue the identification card for the period of the authorized stay. If the period of authorized stay is indefinite, the department shall issue the identification card with a validity of up to eight years.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-310__subsec_q">
              <num>(q)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall provide public information about the differences between identification cards and identification cards that are federally compliant. The department shall also provide the information to applicants for new and renewal identification cards at the time of application. At a minimum, the information must include a description of</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-310__subsec_q__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>each type of identification card;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-310__subsec_q__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the storage and sharing process for an applicant's information for an identification card and an identification card that is federally compliant; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-310__subsec_q__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the official purpose and limitations on the use of each type of identification card, including a description of the purposes for which an identification card that is federally compliant may be required and a description of alternatives to using an identification card that is federally compliant to serve those purposes.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-310__subsec_r">
              <num>(r)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, identification card that is federally compliant means an identification card issued by the state that has been certified by the United States Department of Homeland Security to be in compliance with the requirements of P.L. 109-13, Division B (REAL ID Act of 2005).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-311">
            <num>18.65.311</num>
            <heading>Anatomical gift.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-311__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall provide a method, at the time that an identification card is issued, by which the card holder may make an anatomical gift under
AS 13.52
. The method must provide a means by which the card holder may cancel the gift.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-311__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An employee of the department who processes an identification card application, other than an application received by mail, shall ask the applicant orally whether the applicant wishes to execute an anatomical gift. The department shall, by placement of posters and brochures in the office where the application is taken, and by oral advice, if requested, make known to the applicant the method by which the cardholder may make an anatomical gift under
AS 13.52
. The department shall inform each applicant for an identification card in writing that, if the applicant executes a gift under
AS 13.52
and if the gift is made with the registration, the department will transmit the information on the identification card to a donor registry created under
AS 13.50.110
. The department shall also direct the applicant to notify a procurement organization or the department under
AS 13.50.140
if the identification card is destroyed or mutilated or the gift is revoked under
AS 13.52.183
. The department shall carry out the requirements of
AS 13.50.100
 13.50.190.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-320">
            <num>18.65.320</num>
            <heading>Cancellation of identification card.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-320__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall cancel an identification card if the person receiving the card fails to give the required or correct information in the person's application.  Nothing in this section prohibits reapplication by the person or reissuance of the identification card.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-320__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person whose identification card has been cancelled shall return the card to the department.  Failure to return a cancelled card within 10 days after receiving notice of the cancellation is a violation punishable by a fine of up to $100.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-330">
            <num>18.65.330</num>
            <heading>Definition.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.330.   Definition.
In
AS 18.65.310
 18.65.330, department means the Department of Administration.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-340">
            <num>18.65.340</num>
            <heading>Disposal of firearms and ammunition by the state and municipalities.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-340__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided by (b) of this section, the state and a municipality may only dispose of forfeited, surplus, or recovered but unclaimed firearms and ammunition by</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-340__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>public sale not limited to firearms dealers;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-340__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>trade-in for credit in the purchase of a firearm;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-340__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>donation as provided by the regulations of the department or the ordinances of the municipality making the donation; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-340__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>transfer to a state or municipal law enforcement agency.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-340__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If state or federal law prohibits the sale of a particular surplus firearm under (a)(1) of this section, the department or municipality that is disposing of the surplus firearm shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-340__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>sell the surplus firearm to a firearms dealer who has the appropriate federal license to buy the surplus firearm;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-340__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>donate the surplus firearm under (a)(3) of this section; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-340__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>dismantle the surplus firearm, destroy those surplus firearm parts that cause the sale of the surplus firearm under (a)(1) of this section to be prohibited, and dispose of the other parts of the surplus firearm under (a) of this section.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-340__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a department disposes of a surplus firearm under (a)(2), (3), or (4) of this section, the department shall submit to the legislature each year during the legislature's review of the department's budget a report that lists the surplus firearms that the department has disposed of under (a)(2), (3), or (4) of this section during the previous calendar year. The report must include a description of each surplus firearm and, for each surplus firearm disposed of under</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-340__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>(a)(2) of this section, the value of the firearm purchased and the value received for the surplus firearm; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-340__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>(a)(3) or (4) or (b)(2) of this section, the identity of the governmental agency, the organization, or the individual to whom the surplus firearm was donated or transferred.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-340__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>All money collected from the disposal of surplus firearms may be used to fund gun safety education programs in the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-340__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding
AS 09.50.250
or another provision of law, the state, a municipality, and the officers, agents, and employees of the state or a municipality, are not liable to any person, including the purchaser of a surplus firearm or part of a surplus firearm, for personal injuries or damage to property as a result of the sale of a firearm or a part of a firearm under (a) of this section, unless the state or municipality conducts the sale with gross negligence or recklessness.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-340__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-340__subsec_f__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>department means a department of state government listed in
AS 44.17.005</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-340__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p> (15);</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-340__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>firearm does not include a firearm that has been used in a homicide;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-340__subsec_f__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>surplus firearm means a firearm or ammunition that is forfeited, surplus, or recovered but unclaimed.
Article 5. Security Guards.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-400">
            <num>18.65.400</num>
            <heading>License as security guard.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.400.   License as security guard.
A person may not be employed as a security guard or security guard agency until the person has obtained a license from the commissioner of public safety under
AS 18.65.400
 18.65.490.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-410">
            <num>18.65.410</num>
            <heading>Applications.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-410__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Application for a license as a security guard must be made on forms provided by the commissioner. The application must require the furnishing of information reasonably required by the commissioner to carry out the provisions of
AS 18.65.400
 18.65.490, including classifiable fingerprints and the fees required under
AS 12.62.160
for criminal justice information under
AS 12.62
and a national criminal history record check under
AS 12.62.400
to determine if the applicant has a criminal record. The application must be accompanied by a nonrefundable application fee of $50 for a security guard and $200 for a security guard agency.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-410__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon request, the commissioner shall provide a social security number provided under (a) of this section to the child support services agency created in
AS 25.27.010
, or the child support enforcement agency of another state, for child support purposes authorized under law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-420">
            <num>18.65.420</num>
            <heading>Bonding and insurance.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.420.   Bonding and insurance.
As a condition to issuance of a license, the applicant or the applicant's employer must furnish a bond or proof of a policy of insurance to protect the state and its residents from damages arising out of the acts of the licensee.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-430">
            <num>18.65.430</num>
            <heading>Duration of license.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.430.   Duration of license.
A security guard license issued under
AS 18.65.400
  18.65.490 is valid for a period of two years and may be renewed for additional two-year terms.  A renewal fee of $50 shall be paid for each renewal.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-440">
            <num>18.65.440</num>
            <heading>Revocation of license.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.440.   Revocation of license.
A security guard license issued under
AS 18.65.400
 18.65.490 is subject to revocation in accordance with
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act) for the following reasons:
(1) false statements in an application issued under
AS 18.65.400
 18.65.490;
(2) violation of a provision of
AS 18.65.400
 18.65.490 or a regulation adopted under
AS 18.65.450
;
(3) conviction of a felony or a crime involving moral turpitude while licensed;
(4) knowing impersonation of a law enforcement officer; or
(5) knowingly continuing the employment of an individual as a security guard who has been convicted of a felony or a crime involving moral turpitude, or who has impersonated a law enforcement officer while employed by the licensee.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-450">
            <num>18.65.450</num>
            <heading>Regulations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.450.   Regulations.
The commissioner shall adopt regulations necessary to implement
AS 18.65.400
 18.65.490, including provisions specifying the amount of bond or insurance required and the types of uniforms, badges, and insignia that may be used.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-460">
            <num>18.65.460</num>
            <heading>Exceptions to licensure.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.460.   Exceptions to licensure.
An employer is not required to seek licensure for the employer's employees who provide unarmed plant security on that employer's premises.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-470">
            <num>18.65.470</num>
            <heading>Firearms training.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.470.   Firearms training.
Security guards licensed under
AS 18.65.400
 18.65.490 may not be armed with a firearm for the purpose of protecting property until they have completed firearms training acceptable to the commissioner.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-480">
            <num>18.65.480</num>
            <heading>Penalty.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.480.   Penalty.
A violation of a provision of
AS 18.65.400
 18.65.490 or a regulation adopted under
AS 18.65.450
is a misdemeanor and upon conviction is punishable by imprisonment for not more than 60 days, or by a fine of not more than $1,000, or by both.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-490">
            <num>18.65.490</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.490.   Definitions.
In
AS 18.65.400
 18.65.490,
(1) commissioner means the commissioner of public safety;
(2) security guard means a person in the business of being a private watchman, providing patrol services, or providing other services designed to prevent the theft, misappropriation, or concealment of goods, money, or valuable documents;
(3) security guard agency means a person in the business of furnishing for hire private watchmen, patrol services, or other services designed to prevent the theft, misappropriation, or concealment of goods, money, or valuable documents.
Article 6. Bodyguards.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-500">
            <num>18.65.500</num>
            <heading>Use of armed bodyguards.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.500.   Use of armed bodyguards.
A person who, in this state, hires another person to guard a person in this state with arms or deadly weapons, or a person who comes into this state armed with deadly weapons for the purpose of guarding a person, without a written permit from the commissioner of public safety, is guilty of a misdemeanor and upon conviction is punishable by imprisonment for not more than 60 days, or by a fine of not more than $1,000, or by both.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-510">
            <num>18.65.510</num>
            <heading>Domestic violence and sexual assault training.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-510__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each established police training program in the state shall provide training that acquaints police officers with</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-510__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>laws relating to substantive crimes and rules of criminal procedure applicable in cases involving domestic violence and sexual assault;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-510__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>techniques for handling incidents of domestic violence and sexual assault that promote the safety of the victim and the officer and that reduce the likelihood of recurrence;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-510__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the investigation and management of cases involving domestic violence and sexual assault, including the protocols under
AS 18.68.020
, and report writing for those cases;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-510__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>organizations in the state that offer aid or shelter to victims of domestic violence and sexual assault;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-510__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>procedures applicable in the prosecution of cases involving domestic violence and sexual assault;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-510__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>orders that may be issued by or filed with a court under
AS 18.66.100
 18.66.180;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-510__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the notification to be given to victims of domestic violence under
AS 18.65.520
; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-510__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the subjects set out in
AS 18.66.310</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-510__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In providing a training program under this section, each agency or institution offering an established police training program shall consult with the Council on Domestic Violence and Sexual Assault and interested individuals and organizations providing assistance to victims of domestic violence and sexual assault.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-510__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, sexual assault has the meaning given in
AS 18.66.990
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-515">
            <num>18.65.515</num>
            <heading>Duties of peace officer in a crime involving domestic violence.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-515__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A peace officer investigating a crime involving domestic violence shall protect the victim and any member of the victim's family and prevent further violence by</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-515__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>transporting an adult victim and any member of the victim's family from the place of the offense or the place of contact, to a location within the community where the offense occurred that is a shelter, a safe home, or another location in the community requested by the victim;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-515__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>assisting the victim in removing from the residence essential items belonging to the victim, such as clothing, vehicles, medication, personal records, and legal documents;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-515__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>assisting the victim and any member of the victim's family in obtaining medical treatment necessitated by the offense, by contacting emergency medical services or by transporting the victim to a local medical facility, if available in the community where the offense occurred; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-515__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>providing notice of the rights of victims and services available to victims of domestic violence as provided in
AS 18.65.520
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-515__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a peace officer investigating a crime involving domestic violence determines that it is necessary to protect the victim or the victim's family from domestic violence or to protect the officer or the public during the investigation, the officer may (1) seize a deadly weapon in plain view of the officer, and (2) if a deadly weapon was actually possessed during or used in the domestic violence, seize all deadly weapons owned, used, possessed, or within the control of the alleged perpetrator. If the weapon is not needed as evidence in a criminal case, the law enforcement agency having custody of the weapon, within 24 hours of making the determination that the weapon is not needed as evidence in a criminal case, shall make the weapon available for pickup by the owner of the weapon during regular business hours.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-520">
            <num>18.65.520</num>
            <heading>Notification to victims of domestic violence.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-520__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A peace officer investigating a crime involving domestic violence shall orally and in writing inform the victim of the rights of victims of domestic violence and the services available to them. The notice must be in substantially the following form:
If you are the victim of domestic violence and you believe that law enforcement protection is needed for your physical safety, you have the right to request that the officer assist in providing for your safety, including asking for an emergency protective order. You may also request the officer to assist you in obtaining your essential personal belongings and locating and taking you to a safe place, including a designated meeting place or shelter, the residence of a household member or friend, or a similar place of safety. In some places in Alaska there are organizations that provide aid and shelter to victims of domestic violence. The nearest organization is located at _____________________________________. If you are in need of medical treatment, you may request that the officer assist you in obtaining medical treatment. You may obtain information about whether the prosecuting attorney will file a criminal complaint about the domestic violence. Additionally, the victim/witness assistance program of the Department of Law may be able to help you. This information is available from the district attorney's office, which is located at _____________________________________. You also have the right to file a petition in court requesting a protective order that may include any of the following provisions:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-520__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>prohibit your abuser from threatening to commit or committing further acts of domestic violence;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-520__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>prohibit your abuser from stalking, harassing, telephoning, contacting, or otherwise communicating with you, directly or indirectly;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-520__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>remove your abuser from your residence;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-520__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>order your abuser to stay away from your residence, school, place of employment, or any other specified place frequented by you or another designated household member;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-520__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>prohibit your abuser from entering your vehicle or a vehicle you occupy;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-520__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>prohibit your abuser from using or possessing a deadly weapon if the court finds your abuser was in the actual possession of or used a weapon during the commission of your abuse;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-520__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>direct your abuser to surrender any firearm owned or possessed by that person if the court finds your abuser was in the actual possession of or used a firearm during the commission of your abuse;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-520__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>request a peace officer to accompany you to your residence to ensure your safe possession of the residence, vehicle, or other items, or to ensure your safe removal of personal items from the residence;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-520__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>award temporary custody of a minor child to the petitioner and may arrange for visitation with a minor child if the safety of the child and the petitioner can be protected;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-520__subsec_a__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>grant you possession and use of a vehicle and other essential personal  items, including a pet, regardless of the ownership of those items;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-520__subsec_a__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>prohibit your abuser from consuming controlled substances;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-520__subsec_a__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>require your abuser to pay support for you, a minor child in your care, or a pet in your care if there is an independent legal obligation of your abuser to support you, the child, or the pet;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-520__subsec_a__subsec_13">
                <num>(13)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>require your abuser to reimburse you for your expenses caused by domestic violence, including medical bills, or for your costs in getting a protective order;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-520__subsec_a__subsec_14">
                <num>(14)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>order your abuser to participate in an intervention program for batterers; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-520__subsec_a__subsec_15">
                <num>(15)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>other relief the court determines to be necessary for your safety.
The forms you need to obtain a protective order are available from the nearest court. It is not necessary to have an attorney to obtain a protective order, but you may consult an attorney if you choose. If you would like help obtaining a protective order, you may contact the nearest domestic violence program located at _____________________________________. The program can also tell you about other resources available in this community for information about domestic violence, treatment of injuries, and places of safety and shelter. You may also qualify for compensation from the Violent Crimes Compensation Board. The board may be contacted at _____.  (b) If the victim of domestic violence does not understand English, the police officer shall make reasonable efforts to inform the victim of the services and rights specified in (a) of this section in a language the victim understands.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-520__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 72 ch 64 SLA 1996.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-530">
            <num>18.65.530</num>
            <heading>Mandatory arrest for crimes involving domestic violence, violation of protective orders, and violation of conditions of release.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-530__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (b) or (c) of this section, a peace officer, with or without a warrant, shall arrest a person if the officer has probable cause to believe the person has, either in or outside the presence of the officer, within the previous 12 hours,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-530__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>committed domestic violence, except an offense under
AS 11.41.100
 11.41.130, whether the crime is a felony or a misdemeanor;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-530__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>committed the crime of violating a protective order in violation of
AS 11.56.740</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-530__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>violated a condition of release imposed under
AS 12.30.016</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-530__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or (f) or 12.30.027.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-530__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a peace officer receives complaints of domestic violence from more than one person arising from the same incident, the officer shall evaluate the conduct of each person to determine who was the principal physical aggressor. If the officer determines that one person was the principal physical aggressor, the other person or persons need not be arrested. In determining whether a person is a principal physical aggressor, the officer shall consider</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-530__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>prior complaints of domestic violence;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-530__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the relative severity of the injuries inflicted on each person;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-530__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the likelihood of future injury from domestic violence to each person; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-530__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>whether one of the persons acted in defense of self or others.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-530__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A peace officer is not required to make an arrest of a person under (a) of this section if the officer has received authorization from a prosecuting attorney in the jurisdiction in which the offense under investigation arose</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-530__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>not to arrest the person; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-530__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to deliver the person to a crisis stabilization center, a crisis residential center, or an evaluation facility as provided in
AS 12.25.031</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-530__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When investigating a crime involving domestic violence, a peace officer may not threaten or suggest the possible arrest of all persons involved in the same incident in a manner that would have a tendency to discourage requests for intervention by law enforcement in incidents involving domestic violence.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-530__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to the contents of any other report, a peace officer who does not make an arrest after investigating a complaint of domestic violence, or who arrests two or more persons based on the same incident, shall describe in writing the reasons for not making an arrest or for arresting more than one person.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-530__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not bring a civil action for damages for a failure to comply with the provisions of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-530__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A peace officer who delivers a person to a crisis stabilization center, a crisis residential center, or evaluation facility under (c) of this section shall provide the peace officer's and the peace officer's employing agency's contact information to the crisis stabilization center, crisis residential center, or evaluation facility and, if the peace officer and the peace officer's employing agency are notified under
AS 12.25.031</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-530__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>of a planned release of the person, shall make reasonable efforts to inform the victim of a crime committed under (a)(1) or (2) of this section of the planned release.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-540">
            <num>18.65.540</num>
            <heading>Central registry of protective orders.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-540__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Public Safety shall maintain a central registry of protective orders issued by or filed with a court of this state under
AS 13.26.450
 13.26.460,
AS 18.65.850
 18.65.870, or
AS 18.66.100
 18.66.180. The registry must include, for each protective order, the names of the petitioner and respondent, their dates of birth, and the conditions and duration of the order. The registry shall retain a record of the protective order after it has expired.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-540__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A peace officer receiving a protective order from a court under
AS 13.26.450
, 13.26.455,
AS 18.65.850
 18.65.855, or
AS 18.66.100
 18.66.180, a modified order issued under
AS 13.26.460
,
AS 18.65.860
, or
AS 18.66.120
, or an order dismissing a protective order shall take reasonable steps to ensure that the order, modified order, or dismissal is entered into the central registry within 24 hours after being received.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-540__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A petitioner or respondent who is the subject of a protective order may request the Department of Public Safety to correct information about the order in the central registry. The person requesting the correction has the burden of proving that the information is inaccurate or incomplete. The person may appeal an adverse decision to the court under applicable court rules for appealing the decision of an administrative agency. On appeal, the appellant has the burden of showing that the department's action was an abuse of discretion. An appeal filed under this subsection may not collaterally attack a protective order, challenge the grounds upon which the order was based, or challenge the evidence submitted in support of the order.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-540__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Public Safety may adopt regulations to implement this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-540__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not bring a civil action for damages for a failure to comply with the provisions of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-590">
            <num>18.65.590</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.590.   Definitions.
In
AS 18.65.510
  18.65.590,
(1) domestic violence has the meaning given in
AS 18.66.990
;
(2) pet means a vertebrate living creature maintained for companionship or pleasure, but does not include dogs primarily owned for participation in a generally accepted mushing or pulling contest or practice or animals primarily owned for participation in rodeos or stock contests.
Article 8. Missing Persons Information Clearinghouse.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-600">
            <num>18.65.600</num>
            <heading>Missing persons information clearinghouse.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.600.   Missing persons information clearinghouse.
There is in the Department of Public Safety the missing persons information clearinghouse.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-610">
            <num>18.65.610</num>
            <heading>Duties of missing persons information clearinghouse.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-610__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The missing persons information clearinghouse is established as a central repository of information regarding missing persons.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-610__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The clearinghouse shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-610__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establish within the state a system and appropriate procedures for communication of information regarding missing persons;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-610__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>collect, maintain, and disseminate accurate and complete information on missing persons for the purpose of identifying, locating, and returning them;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-610__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide for exchange of information on missing persons within the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-610__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>cooperate with private citizens, local law enforcement agencies, and other state and federal agencies in investigations concerning missing persons;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-610__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide training and assistance to law enforcement agencies to promote effective use of the clearinghouse.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-620">
            <num>18.65.620</num>
            <heading>Duty of law enforcement agencies.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-620__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A local or state law enforcement agency shall submit to the clearinghouse all missing person reports received by the law enforcement agency that relate to a person who is not located within 48 hours after the first report concerning that person was filed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-620__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For a person under 21 years of age, a local or state law enforcement agency shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-620__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>transmit a missing person report for entry into the Alaska Public Safety Information Network and the National Crime Information Center computer system as soon as practicable, but not later than two hours after receiving the report; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-620__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>as soon as practicable, but not later than 24 hours after the agency learns that the person has been located, request that the information provided under (1) of this subsection be removed from the Alaska Public Safety Information Network and the National Crime Information Center computer system.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-630">
            <num>18.65.630</num>
            <heading>Medical and dental records of missing persons.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-630__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When a person files a report of a missing person with a law enforcement agency or with the clearinghouse, a form authorizing the release of medical and dental records to the law enforcement agency and to the clearinghouse shall be supplied to the family, next of kin, or legal guardian of the missing person. The family, next of kin, or legal guardian of the missing person may complete the release form and deliver the release form to the physician or dentist of the missing person. The physician or dentist who receives a release form signed by the family, next of kin, or legal guardian of the missing person shall release to the law enforcement agency and the clearinghouse only that information that is necessary to identify the missing person.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-630__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the family, next of kin, or legal guardian of a missing person cannot be located or does not exist, a law enforcement agency may execute a written declaration stating that an active investigation is being conducted and that medical and dental records are required for the exclusive purpose of furthering the investigation. Notwithstanding
AS 40.25.120
and
AS 17.30.155
, the declaration signed by a peace officer under this subsection is sufficient authority for the physician or dentist to release information necessary to aid in the identification of the missing person. The physician or dentist may only release that information that is necessary to identify the missing person.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-630__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Medical and dental records obtained under this section shall be provided to the clearinghouse.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-630__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When a missing person is found, the law enforcement agency and the clearinghouse shall destroy all records in their files obtained under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-640">
            <num>18.65.640</num>
            <heading>Reports upon finding a missing person.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.640.   Reports upon finding a missing person.
A person who has filed a missing person report with the clearinghouse or a law enforcement agency shall immediately notify the clearinghouse or the law enforcement agency when the location of the missing person is determined.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-650">
            <num>18.65.650</num>
            <heading>Civil penalty.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.650.   Civil penalty.
The commissioner of public safety, or a person designated by the commissioner of public safety, may file a civil complaint in the district court to enforce
AS 18.65.640
. A person who fails to comply with
AS 18.65.640
is subject to a civil fine of not more than $1,000.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-660">
            <num>18.65.660</num>
            <heading>Definition.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.660.   Definition.
In
AS 18.65.600
 18.65.660, clearinghouse means the missing persons information clearinghouse established in
AS 18.65.600
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-670">
            <num>18.65.670</num>
            <heading>Village public safety officer program.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-670__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The village public safety officer program is created in the department, with funding appropriated to the department and disbursed by the commissioner through grants made under this section. The purpose of the program is to appoint, train, supervise, support, and retain persons to serve as village public safety officers.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-670__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>With funds appropriated for that purpose, the commissioner shall provide grants to nonprofit regional corporations and Alaska Native organizations for training and employment of village public safety officers. If a nonprofit regional corporation for a village or Alaska Native organization for the village does not exist or declines a grant under this subsection, the commissioner may provide the grant to a municipality with a population of less than 10,000 willing to administer the grant for the village. If a nonprofit regional corporation or Alaska Native organization declines a grant, the commissioner shall consult with the corporation or organization before awarding the grant to a municipality.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-670__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall annually accept applications from entities described in (b) of this section for village public safety officer grants. Grant applicants may apply to employ village public safety officers in participating villages located in the applicant's region. An application must include</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-670__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a projected budget, including administrative costs;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-670__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a list of villages in which the applicant plans to employ village public safety officers; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-670__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>other information required by the commissioner.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-670__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall enter into a written agreement with a grant recipient before providing grant funding. The agreement must require the grant recipient to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-670__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>comply with state and federal law;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-670__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide a salary and benefit schedule for the village public safety officer;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-670__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>be named as the employer of the village public safety officer; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-670__subsec_d__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>maintain insurance, independently, or with the assistance of the department, that includes coverage for premiums as follows:
(A) workers' compensation insurance as required under
AS 23.30
;
(B) comprehensive general liability insurance, including professional practice insurance for police with</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-670__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>a limit not less than $1,000,000; and
(ii) the state, including an officer, employee, or agent of the state, listed as an additional named insured.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-670__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An award of grant funding, depending on the funds awarded, must provide for at least one village public safety officer for each village included in a grant agreement entered into under (d) of this section. A grant recipient may assign more than one village public safety officer to a village and request additional funding for the additional village public safety officer. The commissioner may approve the request for additional funding if the grant recipient provides justification reasonably related to the duties of a village public safety officer and other public safety needs.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-670__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A grant recipient may assign a traveling village public safety officer to serve multiple villages within the grant recipient's region.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-670__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A grant recipient shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-670__subsec_g__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>keep original financial, personnel, and other records relating to a village public safety officer for at least three years after the officer's termination of employment and, upon request, provide that information to the department;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-670__subsec_g__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide annual financial audits to the commissioner;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-670__subsec_g__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>facilitate site visits by the department to monitor village public safety officer performance and compliance with state and federal law;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-670__subsec_g__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>notify the commissioner if the grant recipient fails to comply with state or federal law;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-670__subsec_g__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>timely notify the department if a village public safety officer resigns or vacates a position; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-670__subsec_g__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>timely notify and submit a written report to the department if a village public safety officer points a firearm in the direction of another person or discharges a firearm while on duty.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-670__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner may, in consultation with grant recipients, as provided in (k) of this section, adopt regulations related to village public safety officers, including establishing minimum standards and training, physical fitness requirements, criteria for participation by a community, a municipality, an Alaska Native organization, or a corporation, and the interaction between the department and village public safety officers. If the commissioner adopts regulations regarding training for village public safety officers, the training must be consistent with the standards in
AS 18.65.676
and disability training under
AS 18.65.220</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-670__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A grant recipient may charge its federally approved indirect costs to the village public safety officer program grant if the statewide average of indirect costs does not exceed 35 percent.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-670__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner may not withhold, without reason, approval of a funding request made under a grant award. The commissioner shall timely disburse grant funds. A grant recipient may use funding for items reasonably related to public safety and village public safety officer duties under
AS 18.65.670
 18.65.688.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-670__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner and the commissioner of corrections shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-670__subsec_k__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>ensure all relations with a federally recognized tribal government that is the incorporator of a nonprofit regional corporation are conducted on a government-to-government basis;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-670__subsec_k__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>ensure the department consults with a grant recipient
(A) before implementing a policy or regulation that affects the recipient and as early as possible in the development of a new or revised policy or regulation;
(B) on the state policies and regulations the grant recipient considers necessary, as well as the substance of the policies and regulations;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-670__subsec_k__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to the extent possible, use consensual mechanisms to develop policies and regulations, including negotiated rulemaking processes;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-670__subsec_k__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>respect tribal sovereignty in consultations with grant recipients;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-670__subsec_k__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>ensure consultations with grant recipients are open and candid to enable interested parties to accurately assess potential effects; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-670__subsec_k__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>ensure the removal of procedural impediments to working directly and effectively with grant recipients on programs that affect the governmental rights of a tribe.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-670__subsec_l">
              <num>(l)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall designate an official within the department who has the primary responsibility for compliance with this section. The official shall develop and annually review departmental procedures for compliance with this section. The department shall provide to all grant recipients the results of the annual review and post the results on the Internet website of the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-672">
            <num>18.65.672</num>
            <heading>Village public safety officer qualifications.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-672__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A grant recipient may employ a person as a village public safety officer if the individual</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-672__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is at least 21 years of age;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-672__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is a citizen of the United States or a resident alien;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-672__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is of good moral character;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-672__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has obtained a high school diploma or a general education development diploma or its equivalent;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-672__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>satisfies the physical requirements established in regulation by the department;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-672__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has not been previously convicted
(A) of a felony;
(B) of a sex offense as defined in
AS 12.63.100
;
(C) of a misdemeanor crime involving domestic violence unless at least 10 years have passed since the date of the conviction, the conviction was not for an offense against an intimate partner, spouse, child, or parent, and the department grants a waiver allowing the individual to access the criminal justice information system;
(D) of a misdemeanor if less than five years have elapsed since the individual's date of conviction for the offense;
(E) two or more times of</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-672__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>misdemeanor operating a vehicle, aircraft, or watercraft while under the influence of an alcoholic beverage, inhalant, or controlled substance under
AS 28.35.030
;
(ii) misdemeanor refusal to submit to a chemical test under
AS 28.35.032
; or
(iii) a combination of the offenses in (i) and (ii) of this subparagraph;
(F) of manufacturing, transporting, or delivering an alcoholic beverage in violation of a local option under
AS 04.11
or a municipal ordinance or a controlled substance, unless at least 10 years have elapsed; or
(G) of possession of a controlled substance as defined in
AS 11.71.900
, other than marijuana, unless the individual was under 21 years of age at the time of the possession and the possession occurred more than 10 years before the date of hire;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-672__subsec_i__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has not been denied a village public safety officer certification or had a certification revoked; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-672__subsec_i__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has not been denied police officer certification, had a certificate revoked, or surrendered a certificate in this state or another jurisdiction.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-672__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A grant recipient may not use grant money to employ a village public safety officer for a period of more than 24 months unless the officer obtains a village public safety officer certificate from the department under
AS 18.65.682
. Upon written application from a grant recipient, the department may, in its discretion, extend this period up to six months to permit the officer to complete the training required under
AS 18.65.676
, if the officer is unable to do so in the first 24 months of employment because of an illness, injury, or emergency.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-672__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-672__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>good moral character means the absence of acts or conduct that would cause a reasonable person to have substantial doubts about an individual's honesty, fairness, and respect for the rights of others and for the laws of this state and the United States; for purposes of this section, a determination of lack of good moral character may be based on a consideration of all aspects of a person's character;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-672__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>previously convicted means having been convicted of a crime described in (a) of this section or a law or ordinance of another jurisdiction with elements similar to the crimes listed in (a) of this section; a conviction for which the person received a suspended entry of judgment, suspended imposition of sentence, expungement, or pardon is a conviction for purposes of this section, unless the conviction was for a misdemeanor crime committed by the individual when the individual was under 21 years of age.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-674">
            <num>18.65.674</num>
            <heading>Background investigations.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-674__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before employing an individual as a village public safety officer, a grant recipient shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-674__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>submit to the commissioner the individual's
(A) completed application and personal and medical history, on forms prepared by the department;
(B) proof of age, citizenship status, and education; and
(C) fingerprints, the fees required by the department under
AS 12.62.160
for criminal justice information and a national criminal history record check, and other information sufficient to complete a background check consisting of a fingerprint check of national criminal records and criminal records of the state or states in which the individual has resided for the past 10 years; the department shall conduct a criminal justice information and national criminal history record check under
AS 12.62
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-674__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>review the criminal justice information and national criminal history record check completed by the department; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-674__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>review the results of the individual's physical examination and physician certification.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-674__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Personnel and training information that the department or a grant recipient receives about a village public safety officer is confidential and available only for review by a grant recipient, the department, or that officer. A village public safety officer or an individual who applies for employment as a village public safety officer may not review information that another individual supplied with the understanding that the information or its source would remain confidential, unless the information serves as the basis for a decision to deny or revoke a certificate under
AS 18.65.684
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-676">
            <num>18.65.676</num>
            <heading>Training.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-676__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A village public safety officer basic training program must provide</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-676__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a physical training program that includes instruction in physical methods of arrest, use of batons, use of chemical defensive weapons, and electronic control weapons;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-676__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>instruction in
(A) the state's criminal and procedural law;
(B) the state's criminal justice system;
(C) police procedures;
(D) disabilities training described under
AS 18.65.220
(3);
(E) domestic violence and sexual assault prevention and response procedures;
(F) emergency trauma technician training;
(G) search and rescue training;
(H) rural fire protection specialist training.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-676__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An individual seeking a village public safety officer certificate under
AS 18.65.682
shall attend all sessions of the basic training required under (a) of this section, unless the director of the training program approves an absence. An individual who is absent for more than 10 percent of the total hours of instruction has not successfully completed basic training.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-676__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An individual who fails to comply with the attendance and performance requirements of the training program may be dismissed from the training. The department may not consider a dismissed individual to have successfully completed basic training.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-676__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a village public safety officer receives training that the department did not provide and the entity conducting the training provides a description of the training to the department, the department may take that training into account in determining the completion of basic training and accept other police officer or firefighter training and experience that covers the subject matter required under (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-678">
            <num>18.65.678</num>
            <heading>Firearms training.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-678__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A village public safety officer may not, except in an emergency, carry a firearm in the performance of the officer's duties until the officer has successfully completed</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-678__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a basic firearms training program that is certified by the Alaska Police Standards Council or substantially similar training as determined by the department;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-678__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a psychological examination conducted by a mental health professional; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-678__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>all annual firearm qualification requirements.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-678__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In determining the successful completion of basic firearms training, the department may consider previous training and experience that is substantially similar to the training required under (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-680">
            <num>18.65.680</num>
            <heading>Regional public safety officers.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.680.   Regional public safety officers.
The commissioner of public safety may appoint regional public safety officers to
(1) provide an expanded public safety and law enforcement presence in rural areas of the state;
(2) provide oversight and training for the village public safety officer program;
(3) administer functions relating to
(A) protecting life and property in the rural areas of the state;
(B) conducting investigations;
(C) conducting search and rescue missions;
(D) conducting local training programs in drug and alcohol awareness and prevention, water safety, and gun safety;
(4) perform other duties relating to public safety as directed by the commissioner.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-682">
            <num>18.65.682</num>
            <heading>Village public safety officer certification.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.682.   Village public safety officer certification.
The department shall issue a village public safety officer certificate to an individual who
(1) has satisfactorily completed 12 months as a full-time paid village public safety officer without a break in service longer than 90 consecutive days or nonconsecutive breaks in service totaling 120 or more days;
(2) meets the standards in
AS 18.65.672
;
(3) has successfully completed
(A) a basic training program that meets the requirements under
AS 18.65.676
; and
(B) a background information check under
AS 18.65.674
(a); and
(4) attests to the law enforcement code of ethics.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-684">
            <num>18.65.684</num>
            <heading>Denial, revocation, or lapse of certificate.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-684__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may deny an individual's application for a village public safety officer certificate or revoke a village public safety officer certificate in accordance with
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act) if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-684__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the individual knowingly makes a false statement in an application or other document required for employment or certification; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-684__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>after the date of hire, has
(A) been convicted of a</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-684__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>felony;
(ii) misdemeanor crime involving domestic violence; or
(iii) misdemeanor crime of dishonesty, a crime that resulted in serious physical injury to another person, or of operating a vehicle, aircraft, or watercraft while under the influence of an alcoholic beverage, inhalant, or controlled substance two or more times;
(B) illegally used, possessed, manufactured, transported, or delivered an alcoholic beverage in violation of a local option under
AS 04.11
or a municipal ordinance or a controlled substance; or
(C) used, sold, cultivated, transported, manufactured, or distributed marijuana.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-684__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department is not required to deny an individual's application for a certificate or revoke a certificate if the individual or holder of the certificate establishes by clear and convincing evidence that, in connection with a conviction for a misdemeanor crime involving domestic violence, the underlying conviction</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-684__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has been expunged or set aside;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-684__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is for an offense for which the officer has been pardoned; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-684__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is for an offense for which the officer has had civil rights restored that were lost upon the conviction.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-684__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The holder of a certificate shall immediately return the certificate to the department upon notification of the revocation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-684__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An individual who is denied a certificate or a holder whose certificate is revoked may appeal to the commissioner for reversal of the denial or revocation. The appeal must be received in writing within 30 days after the date of the notice of denial or revocation and must set out the reasons for the appeal. The commissioner or the commissioner's designee shall issue a written decision within 45 days after receipt of the appeal.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-684__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A certificate lapses if the holder is not employed as a full-time village public safety officer for a period of 12 consecutive months.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-684__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An individual may request reinstatement of a lapsed certificate after undergoing additional training as determined by the department and serving an additional probationary period of up to 12 months, at the discretion of the commissioner in consultation with the grant recipient. A certificate may not be reinstated if the certificate has lapsed for more than 10 years.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-686">
            <num>18.65.686</num>
            <heading>Powers and duties of village public safety officers.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.686.   Powers and duties of village public safety officers.
A village public safety officer who is certified under
AS 18.65.682
has the power of a peace officer of the state or a municipality and is charged with
(1) the protection of life and property in the state, including through
(A) fire prevention and suppression;
(B) provision of emergency medical services; and
(C) participation in and coordination of search and rescue efforts for missing or injured persons;
(2) providing pretrial, probation, and parole supervision to persons under supervision by communicating with and monitoring the activities and progress of these persons at the direction of pretrial services, probation, and parole officers;
(3) conducting investigations;
(4) enforcing
(A) the criminal laws of the state or a municipality;
(B) statutes or ordinances of the state or municipality punishable as a violation if the certified village public safety officer has completed training in that field of violation enforcement;
(5) providing local training programs on public safety; and
(6) the powers usually and customarily exercised by a peace officer.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-688">
            <num>18.65.688</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.688.   Definitions.
In
AS 18.65.670
 18.65.688,
(1) Alaska Native organization means an organization listed in
AS 47.27.070
(a);
(2) commissioner means the commissioner of public safety;
(3) crime involving domestic violence has the meaning given in
AS 18.66.990
;
(4) department means the Department of Public Safety;
(5) marijuana has the meaning given in
AS 11.71.900
;
(6) village means a community with a population less than 2,500 based on the most recent federal census.
Article 10. Permit to Carry a Concealed Handgun.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-700">
            <num>18.65.700</num>
            <heading>Permit to carry a concealed handgun.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-700__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall issue a permit to carry a concealed handgun to a person who</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-700__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>applies in person at an office of the Alaska State Troopers;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-700__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>qualifies under
AS 18.65.705
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-700__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>submits on an application form approved by the department the information required under
AS 18.65.705
and 18.65.710; the department shall post on the department's website the state laws and regulations relating to concealed handguns, which must include a concise summary of where, when, and by whom a handgun can be carried under state and federal law and shall, on request, mail a copy of the regulations and summary to an applicant or permittee;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-700__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>submits one complete set of fingerprints in the format approved by the department that is of sufficient quality so that the fingerprints may be processed; the fingerprints must be taken by a person, group, or agency approved by the department; the department shall maintain a list of persons, groups, or agencies approved to take fingerprints and shall provide the list to the public upon request; the fingerprints shall be used to obtain a report of criminal justice information under
AS 12.62
and a national criminal history record check under
AS 12.62.400
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-700__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>submits evidence of successful completion of a handgun course as provided in
AS 18.65.715
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-700__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provides one frontal view color photograph of the person taken within the preceding 30 days that includes the head and shoulders of the person and is of a size specified by the department;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-700__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shows a valid Alaska driver's license or identification card at the time of application;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-700__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>does not suffer a physical infirmity that prevents the safe handling of a handgun; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-700__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>pays the application fee required by
AS 18.65.720
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-700__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall either approve or reject an application for a permit to carry a concealed handgun under (a) of this section within 30 days of receipt of the application. If the department has not received necessary fingerprint eligibility information from another agency by the end of this 30-day period, and the applicant is otherwise eligible, the department shall issue a conditional permit to the applicant subject to immediate revocation under the procedure provided in
AS 18.65.740</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-700__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p> (c) if the fingerprint information subsequently discloses that the applicant is ineligible for a permit. The department shall notify the applicant in writing of the reason for a rejection.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-700__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person whose application is rejected under this section may appeal the rejection decision to the commissioner. A person may seek judicial review of the decision of the commissioner under
AS 44.62.560
 44.62.570.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-700__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A permit issued under (a) of this section expires on the person's birthday in the fifth year following issuance of the permit. The department may adjust the length of an initial permit so that a permit is not issued for a period of more than five years.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-700__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall issue a permit to carry a concealed handgun to an honorably retired peace officer of this state who applies for a concealed handgun permit within one year of the officer's retirement and who satisfies the requirements of this subsection. To qualify for a permit under this subsection, an honorably retired peace officer must satisfy (a)(1)  (3) and (6)  (9) of this section and, unless the honorably retired peace officer has qualified with a handgun within five years of the officer's retirement, must also satisfy (a)(5) of this section. The department may not require an honorably retired peace officer applying under this subsection to comply with (a)(4) of this section to receive a permit. The department shall issue the permit without submitting information to or receiving permit eligibility information from the Federal Bureau of Investigation. The department may adopt regulations to define an honorably retired peace officer and the evidence that must be submitted to establish eligibility under this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-705">
            <num>18.65.705</num>
            <heading>Qualifications to obtain a permit.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.705.   Qualifications to obtain a permit.
A person is qualified to receive and hold a permit to carry a concealed handgun if the person
(1) is 21 years of age or older;
(2) is eligible to own or possess a handgun under the laws of this state and under federal law;
(3) is a resident of the state and has been for the 90 days immediately preceding the application for a permit;
(4) has not been convicted of two or more class A misdemeanors of this state or similar laws of another jurisdiction within the six years immediately preceding the application;
(5) is not now in and has not in the three years immediately preceding the application been ordered by a court to complete an alcohol or substance abuse treatment program; and
(6) has successfully completed a handgun course as provided in
AS 18.65.715
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-710">
            <num>18.65.710</num>
            <heading>Application for permit to carry a concealed handgun.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-710__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The application for a permit to carry a concealed handgun must contain the following information:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-710__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the applicant's name, physical residence, mailing address, place and date of birth, physical description, including height, weight, race, hair color, and eye color, Alaska driver's license or identification card number, and the city and state of each place the applicant has resided in the five years immediately preceding the application;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-710__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a statement that the applicant qualifies under
AS 18.65.705
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-710__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a statement that the applicant has been furnished with a copy of the state laws and regulations relating to concealed handguns, has read those sections, and understands them;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-710__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a statement that the applicant desires a permit to carry a concealed handgun for a lawful purpose, which may include self-defense;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-710__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a statement by the applicant that all statements, answers, and attachments to the application are true and complete;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-710__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a conspicuous warning that an applicant who supplies a false statement, answer, or document in connection with the application that the applicant does not believe to be true may be prosecuted for unsworn falsification in the second degree and, if found guilty, may be punished for violation of a class A misdemeanor, and that, in such cases, the permit shall be revoked and the applicant may be barred from any further application for a permit; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-710__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a statement that the applicant understands that a permit eligibility investigation will be conducted as a part of the application process, that this may involve computerized records searches, and that the applicant authorizes the investigation.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-710__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An application under (a) of this section may not inquire of an applicant about, or require the submission of, information beyond that described in that subsection. As part of an application under (a) of this section, the department may not inquire of an applicant as to any firearms owned by the applicant.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-715">
            <num>18.65.715</num>
            <heading>Demonstration of competence with handguns.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-715__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An applicant for a permit to carry a concealed handgun shall provide a certificate of successful completion of a handgun course that is approved by the department. The handgun course must have been completed within the 12 months immediately preceding the application. The department shall approve a handgun course, including the personal protection course offered by the National Rifle Association, if the course tests the applicant's</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-715__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>knowledge of Alaska law relating to firearms and the use of deadly force;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-715__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>familiarity with the basic concepts of the safe and responsible use of handguns;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-715__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>knowledge of self-defense principles; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-715__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>physical competence with a handgun.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-715__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 20 ch 1 SLA 1998.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-715__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may not require a certificate of competence submitted under this section to contain any specifically identifying information, including make, model, or serial number, of a handgun with which an applicant or permittee has demonstrated competence.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-715__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall maintain a list of approved courses and shall provide the list to the public upon request.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-720">
            <num>18.65.720</num>
            <heading>Fees.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.720.   Fees.
The department shall charge a nonrefundable fee for the processing of the application for and initial issuance of a permit, renewal of a permit, or replacement of a permit. The fees shall be set by regulation and must be based on the actual costs incurred by the department. However, the fee for the processing of an application and initial issuance of a permit may not exceed $99 and the fee for renewal of a permit or replacement of a permit may not exceed $30.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-725">
            <num>18.65.725</num>
            <heading>Permit renewal.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-725__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A permittee shall apply for renewal of a permit to carry a concealed handgun within 90 days before the expiration of the permit, on a renewal form approved by the department. The renewal form must include</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-725__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>any change in the information originally submitted under
AS 18.65.710
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-725__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a statement that the person remains qualified to receive and hold a permit to carry a concealed handgun under
AS 18.65.705
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-725__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>one frontal view photograph of the person taken within the preceding 30 days that includes the head and shoulders of the person and is of a size specified by the department;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-725__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the renewal fee required under
AS 18.65.720
; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-725__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the warning listed in
AS 18.65.710</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-725__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 15 ch 94 SLA 2000.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-725__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A renewal of a permit to carry a concealed handgun submitted on or after the expiration date is subject to a late fee of $25. The department may not accept a renewal for a permit that is submitted more than 60 days after the expiration date of the permit. Nothing in this subsection prohibits the holder of an expired permit from applying for a new permit.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-725__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A renewal form under (a) of this section may not inquire of a permittee about, or require the submission of, information beyond that described in (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-725__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding
AS 18.65.705</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-725__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall mail the permittee a notice of expiration by first class mail at least 90 days before expiration of the permit.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-730">
            <num>18.65.730</num>
            <heading>Replacement of permit.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.730.   Replacement of permit.
The department may replace a permit that the permittee certifies under oath has been lost, stolen, or destroyed, provided the permittee applies in person and
(1) provides one frontal view photograph of the permittee taken within the preceding 30 days that includes the head and shoulders and is of a size specified by the department;
(2) pays the replacement fee required under
AS 18.65.720
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-735">
            <num>18.65.735</num>
            <heading>Suspension of permit.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-735__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall immediately suspend a permit to carry a concealed handgun if a permittee becomes ineligible to hold a permit under
AS 18.65.705
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-735__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person whose permit is suspended under this section shall immediately surrender the permit to the nearest peace officer. A peace officer receiving a permit under this section shall immediately forward the permit to the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-735__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall retain a permit suspended under this section until the permit is revoked or returned to the permittee.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-740">
            <num>18.65.740</num>
            <heading>Revocation of permit; appeal.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-740__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A permit to carry a concealed handgun shall be immediately revoked by the department when the permittee</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-740__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>becomes disqualified to receive and hold a permit under
AS 18.65.705
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-740__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is convicted of two class A misdemeanors of this state or similar laws of another jurisdiction within a six-year period if at least one of the convictions occurs after the application;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-740__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>knowingly supplied a false or fraudulent answer, statement, or document, or made a material misstatement or omission, in connection with an application for a permit or renewal or replacement of a permit.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-740__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person whose permit is revoked under (a) of this section shall immediately surrender the permit to the nearest peace officer. A peace officer receiving a permit under this section shall immediately forward the permit to the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-740__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person whose permit is revoked under this section may appeal the revocation decision to the commissioner. A person may seek judicial review of the decision of the commissioner under
AS 44.62.560
 44.62.570.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-740__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person whose permit is revoked may not apply for a permit until at least five years after the revocation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-745">
            <num>18.65.745</num>
            <heading>No liability for issuance of permit or for training.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-745__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The state, and its officers and employees, are not liable by virtue of having issued a permit to carry a concealed handgun for damage or harm caused by the permittee.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-745__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who provides firearm training to a person who receives a permit under
AS 18.65.700
 18.65.790 is not liable for damage or harm caused by the permittee.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-748">
            <num>18.65.748</num>
            <heading>Permit holders from other jurisdictions considered Alaska permit holders.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-748__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>for purposes of
AS 18.65.755
 18.65.765.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-755">
            <num>18.65.755</num>
            <heading>Places where permittee may not possess a concealed handgun.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-755__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A permittee may not possess a concealed handgun</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-755__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>[Repealed, § 7 ch 62 SLA 2003.]</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-755__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>anywhere a person is prohibited from possessing a handgun under state or federal law.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-755__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 20 ch 1 SLA 1998.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-755__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to any other penalty provided by law, a person who violates this section is guilty of a class B misdemeanor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-760">
            <num>18.65.760</num>
            <heading>Misuse of a permit.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-760__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The holder of a permit issued under
AS 18.65.700
 18.65.790 may not</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-760__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>alter the permit;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-760__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>allow another person to use the permit;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-760__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>possess or display a suspended or revoked permit; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-760__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>represent or display an expired permit as if the permit were valid, unless the holder has submitted a complete, timely renewal form under
AS 18.65.725
and the renewal process has been delayed due to circumstances not under the control of the applicant; this paragraph does not require a holder to return or surrender a permit upon its expiration, nor may the department require a holder to return or surrender a permit upon its expiration.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-760__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who violates (a)(1)  (3) of this section is guilty of a class A misdemeanor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-760__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who violates (a)(4) of this section is guilty of a violation and upon conviction may be punished by a fine of not more than $100.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-765">
            <num>18.65.765</num>
            <heading>Responsibilities of the permittee.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-765__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The holder of a permit issued under
AS 18.65.700
 18.65.790</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-765__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall notify the department of a change in the permittee's address within 30 days;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-765__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall immediately report a lost, stolen, or illegible permit to the department;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-765__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall immediately notify the department if the holder is no longer qualified to hold a permit under
AS 18.65.705
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-765__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who violates this section is guilty of a violation and upon conviction may be punished by a fine of not more than $100.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-770">
            <num>18.65.770</num>
            <heading>Permits, applications, and other materials not public records.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.770.   Permits, applications, and other materials not public records.
Applications, permits, and renewals are not public records under
AS 40.25.110
 40.25.125 and may only be used for law enforcement purposes.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-775">
            <num>18.65.775</num>
            <heading>Regulations; reciprocity agreements.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-775__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall adopt regulations to implement
AS 18.65.700
 18.65.790. This section does not delegate to the department the authority to regulate or restrict the issuing of permits beyond those provisions contained in
AS 18.65.700
 18.65.790.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-775__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall enter into reciprocity agreements with other states that have the legal authority to enter into such agreements so that permittees may carry concealed handguns in those other states.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-778">
            <num>18.65.778</num>
            <heading>Municipal preemption.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.778.   Municipal preemption.
A municipality may not restrict the carrying of a concealed handgun by permit under
AS 18.65.700
 18.65.790.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-790">
            <num>18.65.790</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.790.   Definitions.
In
AS 18.65.700
 18.65.790,
(1) commissioner means the commissioner of public safety;
(2) competence means the ability to place in a life size silhouette target
(A) seven out of 10 shots at seven yards;
(B) six out of 10 shots at 15 yards;
(3) concealed handgun means a firearm, that is a pistol or a revolver, and that is covered or enclosed in any manner so that an observer cannot determine that it is a handgun without removing it from that which covers or encloses it or without opening, lifting, or removing that which covers or encloses it; however, concealed handgun does not include a shotgun, rifle, or a prohibited weapon as defined under
AS 11.61.200
;
(4) department means the Department of Public Safety;
(5) permit means a permit to carry a concealed handgun issued under
AS 18.65.700
 18.65.790.
Article 11. Firearms.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-800">
            <num>18.65.800</num>
            <heading>Possession of firearms in motor vehicles.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-800__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the state, a municipality, or a person may not adopt or enforce a law, ordinance, policy, or rule that prohibits or has the effect of prohibiting an individual from possessing a firearm while that individual is within a motor vehicle or prohibiting an individual from storing a firearm that is locked in the individual's motor vehicle while the motor vehicle is otherwise legally parked in or on state or municipal property or another person's property. This section applies only to possession of a firearm by an individual who may legally possess a firearm under state and federal law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-800__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This section does not limit a person's rights or remedies under any other law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-800__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The state, a municipality, or a person is not liable for any injury or damage resulting from the storage of a firearm in the vehicle of another individual in accordance with this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-800__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (a) of this section, an employer or its agent may prohibit the possession of firearms within a secured restricted access area, as defined in
AS 29.35.145
(e)(2), in a vehicle owned, leased, or rented by the employer or its agent or in a parking lot owned or controlled by the employer within 300 feet of the secured restricted access area that does not include common areas of ingress and egress open to the general public. The employer or its agent shall post conspicuous notice of the prohibition against possession of firearms at each entrance to the restricted access area and affected parking area.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-810">
            <num>18.65.810</num>
            <heading>Execution of federal firearms forms.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-810__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The chief administrative officer of a municipal police department for a person who resides in the municipality and the head of the Alaska state troopers for a person who resides in the state but does not reside in a municipality with a police department shall execute within 30 days federal firearms forms required to be submitted by the person as a transferee of a firearm if the person is qualified under state law to possess the firearm.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-810__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, chief administrative officer has the meaning given in
AS 18.65.290
.
Article 12. Stalking and Sexual Assault Protective Orders and Notification to Stalking and Sexual Assault Victims.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-850">
            <num>18.65.850</num>
            <heading>Protective orders for stalking and sexual assault.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-850__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who reasonably believes that the person is a victim of stalking or sexual assault that is not a crime involving domestic violence may file a petition in the district or superior court for a protective order against a respondent who is alleged to have committed the stalking or sexual assault. A parent or guardian may file a petition on behalf of a minor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-850__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When a petition for a protective order is filed, the court shall schedule a hearing and provide at least 10 days' notice to the respondent of the hearing and of the respondent's right to appear and be heard, either in person or through an attorney. If the court finds by a preponderance of evidence that the respondent has committed stalking or sexual assault against the petitioner, regardless of whether the respondent appears at the hearing, the court may order any relief available under (c) of this section. The provisions of a protective order issued under this section are effective for one year unless earlier dissolved by the court.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-850__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A protective order issued under this section may</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-850__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>prohibit the respondent from threatening to commit or committing stalking or sexual assault;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-850__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>prohibit the respondent from telephoning, contacting, or otherwise communicating directly or indirectly with the petitioner or a designated household member of the petitioner specifically named by the court;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-850__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>direct the respondent to stay away from the residence, school, or place of employment of the petitioner, or any specified place frequented by the petitioner; however, the court may order the respondent to stay away from the respondent's own residence, school, or place of employment only if the respondent has been provided actual notice of the opportunity to appear and be heard on the petition;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-850__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>order other relief the court determines to be necessary to protect the petitioner or the designated household member.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-850__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the court issues a protective order under this section, the court shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-850__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>make reasonable efforts to ensure that the order is understood by the petitioner and by the respondent, if present; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-850__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>have the order delivered to the appropriate local law enforcement agency for expedited service.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-850__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A court may not deny a petition for a protective order solely because</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-850__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>there is a lapse of time between an act of sexual assault and the filing of the petition;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-850__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the stalking or act of sexual assault was the basis for a previous protective order; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-850__subsec_e__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a court previously found that the petitioner was a victim of stalking or sexual assault but declined to order relief under this section, if the petition alleges a change in circumstances since the court's previous finding.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-850__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Within 30 days before, or within 60 days after, the expiration of a protective order issued or extended under this section, a petitioner may petition the court for an extension of the protective order. The court shall schedule a hearing and provide at least 10 days' notice to the respondent of the hearing and of the respondent's right to appear and be heard, either in person or through an attorney. If the court finds that an extension of the provisions of the order is necessary to protect the petitioner from stalking or sexual assault, regardless of whether the respondent appears at the hearing, the court may extend the provisions of the order. An extension granted under this subsection is effective for one year unless earlier dissolved by court order. If the court grants an extension before the protective order expires, the extension takes effect on the day the protective order would have expired.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-855">
            <num>18.65.855</num>
            <heading>Ex parte and emergency protective orders for stalking and sexual assault.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-855__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who reasonably believes that the person is a victim of stalking or sexual assault that is not a crime involving domestic violence may file a petition under
AS 18.65.850
and request an ex parte protective order. If the court finds that the petition establishes probable cause that the crime of stalking or sexual assault has occurred, that it is necessary to protect the petitioner from further stalking or sexual assault, and that the petitioner has certified to the court in writing the efforts, if any, that have been made to provide notice to the respondent, the court shall ex parte and without notice to the respondent issue a protective order. An ex parte protective order under this section may grant the protection allowed by
AS 18.65.850
(c). An ex parte protective order expires 20 days after it is issued unless dissolved earlier by the court at the request of either the petitioner or the respondent after notice and, if requested, a hearing. If the court issues an ex parte protective order, the court shall have the order delivered to the appropriate law enforcement agency for expedited service.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-855__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A peace officer, on behalf of and with the consent of a victim of stalking or sexual assault that is not a crime involving domestic violence, may request an emergency protective order from a judicial officer. The request may be made orally or in writing based on the sworn statement of a peace officer, and in person or by telephone. If the court finds probable cause to believe that the petitioner is in immediate danger of stalking or sexual assault based on an allegation of the recent commission of stalking or sexual assault, the court ex parte shall issue an emergency protective order. An emergency protective order may grant the protection allowed by
AS 18.65.850
(c). An emergency protective order expires 72 hours after it is issued unless dissolved earlier by the court at the request of the petitioner. A peace officer who obtains an emergency protective order under this section shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-855__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>place the provisions of an oral order in writing on a form provided by the court and file the written order with the issuing court by the end of the judicial day after the order is issued;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-855__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide a copy of the order to the petitioner; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-855__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>serve a copy of the order on the respondent.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-860">
            <num>18.65.860</num>
            <heading>Modification of protective orders for stalking and sexual assault.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-860__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Either the petitioner or the respondent may request modification of a protective order issued under
AS 18.65.850
or 18.65.855(a). If a request is made for modification of</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-860__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a protective order, after notice and hearing under
AS 18.65.850
, the court shall schedule a hearing within 20 days after the date the request is made, except that, if the court finds that the request is meritless on its face, the court may deny the request without a hearing; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-860__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an ex parte protective order under
AS 18.65.855</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-860__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the court modifies a protective order under this section, the court shall issue a modified order and shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-860__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>make reasonable efforts to ensure that the order is understood by the petitioner and by the respondent, if present at the hearing; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-860__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>have the order delivered to the appropriate local law enforcement agency for expedited service.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-865">
            <num>18.65.865</num>
            <heading>Service of process; forms for petitions and orders; fees; warnings; notification; and pending civil or criminal actions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-865__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Service of process of an order issued by the court under
AS 18.65.850
 18.65.860 shall be as provided in
AS 18.66.160
for service of process of domestic violence protective orders.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-865__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Alaska Court System shall prepare forms for petitions and protective orders and instructions for their use by a person seeking a protective order under
AS 18.65.850
 18.65.860. The forms must conform to the Alaska Rules of Civil Procedure, except that information on the forms may be filled in by legible handwriting. Filing fees may not be charged in any action seeking only the relief provided in
AS 18.65.850
- 18.65.870. Each protective order form must contain the following warning in boldface type: Violation of this order may be a misdemeanor, punishable by up to one year of incarceration and a fine of up to $25,000.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-865__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Public Safety shall develop and make available to law enforcement agencies in the state a notice that details the rights of victims of stalking and sexual assault and the services available to them. The form must be similar to that provided to victims of domestic violence under
AS 18.65.520
. A peace officer investigating a stalking or sexual assault offense shall provide the form to the victim.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-865__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to other information required, a petition for a protective order must include a statement of pending civil and criminal actions involving either the petitioner or the respondent, if known. While a protective order is in effect or a petition for a protective order is pending, both the petitioner and respondent have a continuing duty to inform the court of pending civil and criminal actions involving either the petitioner or the respondent, if known.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-867">
            <num>18.65.867</num>
            <heading>Enforcement and recognition of protective orders issued in other jurisdictions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-867__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A protective order issued in another jurisdiction has the same effect and must be recognized and enforced in the same manner as a protective order issued by a court of this state if the protective order is</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-867__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>issued by a court of the United States, a court of another state or territory, a United States military tribunal, or a tribal court;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-867__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>related to stalking or sexual assault that is not a crime involving domestic violence; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-867__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>entitled to full faith and credit under 18 U.S.C. 2265.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-867__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A protective order issued in another jurisdiction that appears authentic on its face is presumed valid.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-870">
            <num>18.65.870</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.870.   Definitions.
In
AS 18.65.850
 18.65.870,
(1) crime involving domestic violence has the meaning given in
AS 18.66.990
;
(2) household member has the meaning given in
AS 18.66.990
;
(3) sexual assault has the meaning given in
AS 18.66.990
;
(4) stalking means a violation of
AS 11.41.260
or 11.41.270.
Article 13. Law Enforcement Use of Unmanned Aircraft Systems.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-900">
            <num>18.65.900</num>
            <heading>Use of unmanned aircraft systems.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.900.   Use of unmanned aircraft systems.
Except as provided in
AS 18.65.900
 18.65.909, a law enforcement agency may not use an unmanned aircraft system.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-901">
            <num>18.65.901</num>
            <heading>Operational requirements for unmanned aircraft systems.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-901__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A law enforcement agency shall adopt procedures for the use of unmanned aircraft systems. The procedures adopted under this section must require, at a minimum, that the law enforcement agency</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-901__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>obtain any authorization, permit, or certificate required by the Federal Aviation Administration to operate the unmanned aircraft system;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-901__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>allow the unmanned aircraft system to be operated only by unmanned aircraft system pilots and crew members who have been trained and certified in the operation of the unmanned aircraft system and only under the supervision of officials trained in the policies and procedures governing the use of the unmanned aircraft system;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-901__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide that the flight of an unmanned aircraft system be approved by the commissioner or deputy commissioner of public safety or the chief administrative officer of the law enforcement agency or the officer's designee;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-901__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>ensure that the flight of an unmanned aircraft system be for a public purpose;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-901__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>maintain a record of each flight, including the time, date, and purpose of the flight, and the identity of the authorizing official;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-901__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establish an auditable flight record system, including the documentation of a change in a flight time record;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-901__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establish a method for notifying the public of the operation of an unmanned aircraft system, unless notifying the public would endanger the safety of a person;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-901__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide for community involvement in the development of the policies required in this section, including the consideration of public comment.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-901__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, chief administrative officer has the meaning given in
AS 18.65.290
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-902">
            <num>18.65.902</num>
            <heading>Use of an unmanned aircraft system by a law enforcement agency.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.902.   Use of an unmanned aircraft system by a law enforcement agency.
A law enforcement agency may use an unmanned aircraft system
(1) to gather evidence in a criminal investigation
(A) under the express terms of a search warrant issued by a court; or
(B) in accordance with a judicially recognized exception to the warrant requirement; or
(2) in situations and for uses not involving a criminal investigation and not intended to lead to the production of evidence for use in a criminal investigation, if the use does not constitute an unwarranted invasion of personal privacy and is consistent with the procedures in
AS 18.65.901
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-903">
            <num>18.65.903</num>
            <heading>Retention of images.</heading>
            <subsection eId="18-65-903__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A law enforcement agency may not retain images captured by an unmanned aircraft system unless retention of the image is required</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-903__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>as part of an investigation or prosecution;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-903__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for training purposes; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="18-65-903__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>by federal or state law or by municipal ordinance.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="18-65-903__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Images that may not be retained under (a) of this section are confidential and are not public records under
AS 40.25.100
 40.25.295.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-65-909">
            <num>18.65.909</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.65.909.   Definitions.
In
AS 18.65.900
 18.65.909,
(1) law enforcement agency has the meaning given in
AS 12.36.090
;
(2) unmanned aircraft system means an unmanned aircraft that is operated without direct human intervention from inside or on the aircraft and includes the associated support equipment, control station, data links, telemetry, communications, and navigation equipment necessary to operate the unmanned aircraft;
(3) unmanned aircraft system crew member means a person other than an unmanned aircraft system pilot who is assigned to duties related to an unmanned aircraft system during flight;
(4) unmanned aircraft system pilot means a person exercising control over an unmanned aircraft system during flight.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>