<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-33/chapter-16"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-33/chapter-16"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="33.16"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-33/chapter-16/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-33/chapter-16/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-33/chapter-16/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-33/chapter-16/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_33">
        <num>33</num>
        <heading>Probation, Prisons, Pardons, and Prisoners</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_33__chp_16">
          <num>16</num>
          <heading>Parole Administration</heading>
          <section eId="sec_33-16-010">
            <num>33.16.010</num>
            <heading>Parole.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-16-010__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A prisoner who is serving a term or terms of two years or more is eligible for mandatory parole.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-010__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A prisoner who is eligible under
AS 33.16.090
may be granted discretionary parole by the board of parole.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-010__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (g) of this section, a prisoner who is not eligible for special medical or discretionary parole, or who is not released on special medical or discretionary parole, shall be released on mandatory parole for the term of good time deductions credited under
AS 33.20
, if the term or terms of imprisonment are two years or more.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-010__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A prisoner released on special medical, discretionary, or mandatory parole is subject to the conditions of parole imposed under
AS 33.16.150
. Parole may be revoked under
AS 33.16.220
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-010__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A prisoner eligible under
AS 33.16.085
may be released on special medical parole by the Parole Board.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-010__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 72 ch 1 4SSLA 2017.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-010__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A prisoner is not eligible for mandatory parole if the prisoner has been convicted of a crime under
AS 11.41.100
or 11.41.110.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-16-020">
            <num>33.16.020</num>
            <heading>Board of parole.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-16-020__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>There is in the Department of Corrections a board of parole consisting of five members appointed by the governor, subject to confirmation by a majority of members of the legislature in joint session.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-020__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Members of the board serve for staggered terms of five years and until their successors are appointed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-020__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The governor shall choose the presiding officer of the board from among the membership.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-020__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The governor shall make appointments to the board with due regard for representation on the board of the ethnic, racial, sexual, and cultural populations of the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-020__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The governor shall appoint at least one member who resides in the First Judicial District, one member who resides in the Third Judicial District, and one member who resides in either the Second or Fourth Judicial District.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-16-030">
            <num>33.16.030</num>
            <heading>Selection criteria for board members.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-16-030__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The governor shall appoint board members on the basis of their qualifications to make decisions that are compatible with the welfare of the community and of individual offenders. The governor shall appoint members who are able to consider the character and background of offenders and the circumstances under which offenses were committed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-030__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>At least one person appointed to the board must have experience in the field of criminal justice.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-030__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Officers or employees of the state may not be appointed to the board.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-16-040">
            <num>33.16.040</num>
            <heading>Compensation and expenses.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 33.16.040.   Compensation and expenses.
A board member is entitled to compensation at an amount to be set by the governor for each day the member is participating in business of the board, and is also entitled to the per diem and travel allowances provided under
AS 39.20.180
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-16-050">
            <num>33.16.050</num>
            <heading>Meetings of the board.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-16-050__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board may meet as often as it considers necessary to carry out its responsibilities, but shall meet at least four times a year.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-050__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Three members of the board constitute a quorum for the conduct of business.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-050__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except when a member of the board imposes special conditions of mandatory parole for the board under
AS 33.16.150
and except as provided in (e) of this section, decisions and orders of the board require the affirmative votes of a majority of the members present.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-050__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board may conduct meetings by the use of teleconferencing facilities.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-050__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A meeting of the board is not required for a decision or order setting special conditions of mandatory parole by a single member of the board under
AS 33.16.150</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-050__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and (e). If a prisoner or parolee who is aggrieved by the board member's decision or order applies to the full board under
AS 33.16.150</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-050__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and 33.16.160 for a change in parole conditions, the board shall meet to act on the application.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-16-060">
            <num>33.16.060</num>
            <heading>Duties of the board.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-16-060__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-060__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>serve as the parole authority for the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-060__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>consider the suitability for parole of a prisoner who is eligible for discretionary parole or special medical parole if
(A)  the prisoner had no disciplinary action imposed during incarceration; or
(B)  the prisoner had disciplinary action imposed during incarceration and the prisoner filed an application with the board for discretionary or special medical parole;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-060__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>impose parole conditions on all prisoners released under special medical, discretionary, or mandatory parole;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-060__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>under
AS 33.16.210
, discharge a person from parole when custody is no longer required;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-060__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>maintain records of the meetings and proceedings of the board;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-060__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>recommend to the governor and the legislature changes in the law administered by the board;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-060__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>recommend to the governor or the commissioner changes in the practices of the department and of other departments of the executive branch necessary to facilitate the purposes and practices of parole;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-060__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>upon request of the governor, review and recommend applicants for executive clemency; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-060__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>execute other responsibilities prescribed by law.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-060__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board shall adopt regulations under the Administrative Procedure Act (
AS 44.62
)</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-060__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establishing standards under which the suitability of a prisoner for special medical or discretionary parole shall be determined;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-060__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>providing for the supervision of parolees and for recommitment of parolees; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-060__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>governing procedures of the board.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-060__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board shall establish a program for a parolee who has conditions of parole that include not consuming controlled substances or alcoholic beverages and who has been identified as being at moderate to high risk as identified by a risk-needs assessment. The program must</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-060__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>include random testing for controlled substance and alcoholic beverage use;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-060__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>require that a parole officer file a parole violation report by the close of the next business day if a parolee
(A) fails to appear for an appointment as directed by the parole officer; or
(B) tests positive for the use of controlled substances or alcoholic beverages; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-060__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>include a means to notify the board by the close of the next business day that a parole violation report has been filed on a parolee placed in the program by the board.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-16-070">
            <num>33.16.070</num>
            <heading>Process.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 33.16.070.   Process.
The board or a member of the board may issue subpoenas and subpoenas duces tecum in the performance of board duties under
AS 33.16.060
(a).  Subpoenas issued under this section are enforceable in superior court.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-16-080">
            <num>33.16.080</num>
            <heading>Executive director.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 33.16.080.   Executive director.
The board shall hire an executive director to serve the board in the discharge of its duties. The executive director must have had training and experience in the field of criminal justice.  The executive director may employ additional staff to assist the board.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-16-085">
            <num>33.16.085</num>
            <heading>Special medical parole.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-16-085__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding a presumptive, mandatory, or mandatory minimum term or sentence a prisoner may be serving or any restriction on parole eligibility under
AS 12.55
, a prisoner who is serving a term of at least 181 days may, upon application by the prisoner or the commissioner, be released by the board on special medical parole if the board determines that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-085__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the prisoner has not been convicted of an offense under
AS 11.41.410
 11.41.425 or 11.41.434  11.41.438 and the prisoner is severely medically or cognitively disabled as certified in writing by a physician licensed under
AS 08.64
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-085__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a reasonable probability exists that
(A) the prisoner will live and remain at liberty without violating any laws or conditions imposed by the board;
(B) because of the prisoner's severe medical or cognitive disability, the prisoner will not pose a threat of harm to the public if released on parole; and
(C) release of the prisoner on parole would not diminish the seriousness of the crime;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-085__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the prisoner
(A) was not suffering from the severe medical or cognitive disability at the time the prisoner committed the offense or parole or probation violation for which the prisoner is presently incarcerated; or
(B) was suffering from the severe medical or cognitive disability at the time the prisoner committed the offense or parole or probation violation for which the prisoner is presently incarcerated and the medical or cognitive disability has progressed so that the likelihood of the prisoner's committing the same or a similar offense is low;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-085__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the care and supervision that the prisoner requires can be provided in a more medically appropriate or cost-effective manner than by the department;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-085__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the prisoner is incapacitated to an extent that incarceration does not impose significant additional restrictions on the prisoner;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-085__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the prisoner is likely to remain subject to the severe medical or cognitive disability throughout the entire period of parole or to die and there is no reasonable expectation that the prisoner's medical or cognitive disability will improve noticeably; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-085__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an appropriate discharge plan has been formulated that addresses basic life domains of the prisoner, including care coordination, housing, eligibility for public benefits, and health care, including necessary medication.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-085__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the board finds a change in circumstances or discovers new information concerning a prisoner who has been granted a special medical parole release date, the board may rescind or revise the previously granted parole release date.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-085__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board shall issue its decision to grant or deny special medical parole, or to rescind or revise the release date of a prisoner granted special medical parole, in writing and provide a basis for the decision. A copy of the decision shall be provided to the prisoner.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-16-087">
            <num>33.16.087</num>
            <heading>Rights of victims in connection with special medical parole.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-16-087__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the victim of a crime requests notice of a scheduled hearing to review or consider special medical parole for a prisoner convicted of that crime, the board shall send notice of the hearing to the victim at least 30 days before the hearing. The notice must be accompanied by a copy of the prisoner's or commissioner's application for parole submitted under
AS 33.16.085
. The copy of the application sent to the victim must include the prisoner's proposed residence and employment addresses.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-087__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A victim who requests notice under this section shall maintain a current, valid mailing address on file with the board. The board shall send the notice required by this section to the last known address of the victim. The victim's address may not be disclosed to the prisoner or the prisoner's attorney.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-087__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The victim has a right to attend meetings of the parole board in which the status of the prisoner convicted of the crime against that victim is officially considered and to comment, in writing or in person, on the proposed action of the board. Copies of any written comments shall be provided to the prisoner and the prisoner's attorney before action by the board.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-087__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board shall consider the comments presented under (c) of this section in deciding whether to release the prisoner on special medical parole.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-087__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the victim requests, the board shall make every reasonable effort to notify the victim as soon as practicable in writing of its decision to grant or deny special medical parole. The notice under this subsection must include the expected date of the prisoner's release, the geographic area in which the prisoner is required to reside, and other pertinent information concerning the prisoner's conditions of parole that may affect the victim.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-16-089">
            <num>33.16.089</num>
            <heading>Eligibility for administrative parole.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 33.16.089.   Eligibility for administrative parole.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-16-089">
            <num>33.16.089</num>
            <heading>Eligibility for administrative parole.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 33.16.089.   Eligibility for administrative parole.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-16-090">
            <num>33.16.090</num>
            <heading>Eligibility for discretionary parole and minimum terms to be served.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-16-090__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A prisoner sentenced to an active term of imprisonment of at least 181 days may, in the discretion of the board, be released on discretionary parole if the prisoner</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-090__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has served the amount of time specified under (b) of this section, except that
(A) a prisoner sentenced to one or more mandatory 99-year terms under
AS 12.55.125</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-090__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or one or more definite terms under
AS 12.55.125</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-090__subsec_l">
              <num>(l)</num>
              <content>
                <p>is not eligible for consideration for discretionary parole;
(B) a prisoner is not eligible for consideration of discretionary parole if made ineligible by order of a court under
AS 12.55.115
;
(C) a prisoner imprisoned under
AS 12.55.086
is not eligible for discretionary parole unless the actual term of imprisonment is more than one year;
(D)  a prisoner sentenced to a single sentence within or below a presumptive range set out in
AS 12.55.125
(c), (d)(2)  (4), (e)(3) and (4), or (i) who has not been allowed by the three-judge panel under
AS 12.55.175
to be considered for discretionary parole release is not eligible for consideration of discretionary parole;
(E)  a prisoner sentenced to a single sentence, including a consecutive or partially consecutive sentence, that is not eligible for a good time deduction under
AS 33.20.010
(a)(3) and that has not been allowed by the three-judge panel under
AS 12.55.175
to be considered for discretionary parole release is not eligible for consideration of discretionary parole; or</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-090__subsec_l__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is at least 60 years of age, has served at least 10 years of a sentence for one or more crimes in a single judgment, and has not been convicted of an unclassified felony or a sexual felony as defined in
AS 12.55.185
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-090__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A prisoner eligible under (a)(1) of this section who is sentenced</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-090__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to a single sentence under
AS 12.55.125</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-090__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or (b) may not be released on discretionary parole until the prisoner has served the mandatory minimum term under
AS 12.55.125</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-090__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or (b),
(A)  two-thirds of the active term of imprisonment imposed, or any term set under
AS 12.55.115
, whichever is greatest, for a conviction under
AS 11.41.100
or 11.41.110;
(B)  one-half of the active term of imprisonment imposed, or any term set under
AS 12.55.115
, whichever is greatest, for a conviction for an offense not listed in (A) of this paragraph;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-090__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to a single sentence under
AS 12.55.125</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-090__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>the prisoner has successfully completed all rehabilitation programs ordered by the three-judge panel that were made available to the prisoner; and
(ii) the prisoner would not constitute a danger to the public if released on parole;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-090__subsec_i__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to a single enhanced sentence under
AS 12.55.155</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-090__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>that is above the applicable presumptive range may not be released on discretionary parole until the prisoner has served the greater of the following:
(A) an amount of time, less good time earned under
AS 33.20.010
, equal to the upper end of the presumptive range plus one-fourth of the amount of time above the presumptive range; or
(B) any term set under
AS 12.55.115
;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-090__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to a single sentence under any other provision of law may not be released on discretionary parole until the prisoner has served at least one-fourth of the active term of imprisonment, any mandatory minimum sentence imposed under any provision of law, or any term set under
AS 12.55.115
, whichever is greatest;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-090__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to concurrent sentences may not be released on discretionary parole until the prisoner has served the greatest of
(A) any mandatory minimum sentence or sentences imposed under any provision of law;
(B) any term set under
AS 12.55.115
; or
(C) the amount of time that is required to be served under (1)  (4) or (7) of this subsection for the sentence imposed for the primary crime, had that been the only sentence imposed;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-090__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to consecutive or partially consecutive sentences may not be released on discretionary parole until the prisoner has served the greatest of
(A) the composite total of any mandatory minimum sentence or sentences imposed under any provision of law, including
AS 12.55.127
;
(B) any term set under
AS 12.55.115
; or
(C) the amount of time that is required to be served under (1)  (4) or (7) of this subsection for the sentence imposed for the primary crime, had that been the only sentence imposed, plus one-quarter of the composite total of the active term of imprisonment imposed as consecutive or partially consecutive sentences imposed for all crimes other than the primary crime;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-090__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to a single sentence under
AS 12.55.125</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-090__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>for an offense under
AS 11.71.030
(a)(2) or (9), and has not been allowed by the three-judge panel under
AS 12.55.175
to be considered for discretionary parole release, may not be released on discretionary parole until the prisoner has served one-half of the active term of imprisonment imposed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-090__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>As used in this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-090__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>active term of imprisonment has the meaning given in
AS 12.55.127
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-090__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>primary crime has the meaning given in
AS 12.55.127
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-16-100">
            <num>33.16.100</num>
            <heading>Granting of discretionary parole.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-16-100__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board may authorize the release of a prisoner who is otherwise eligible under
AS 12.55.115
and
AS 33.16.090
(a)(1) on discretionary parole if it determines a reasonable probability exists that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-100__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the prisoner will live and remain at liberty without violating any laws or conditions imposed by the board;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-100__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the prisoner's rehabilitation and reintegration into society will be furthered by release on parole;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-100__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the prisoner will not pose a threat of harm to the public if released on parole; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-100__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>release of the prisoner on parole would not diminish the seriousness of the crime.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-100__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the board finds a change in circumstances in a prisoner's preparole reports listed in
AS 33.16.110
(a), or discovers new information concerning a prisoner who has been granted a parole release date, the board may rescind or revise the previously granted parole release date. In reconsidering the release date, the procedures set out in
AS 33.16.130
shall be followed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-100__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 32 ch 2 SLA 2005.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-100__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 32 ch 2 SLA 2005.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-100__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 179 ch 36 SLA 2016.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-100__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 138 ch 4 FSSLA 2019.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-100__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When considering a prisoner for release on discretionary parole under
AS 33.16.090
(a)(2), the board may release a prisoner if, taking into consideration the prisoner's likelihood of recidivism given the prisoner's age, criminal history, behavior in prison, participation in treatment, and plans for reentering the community, a reasonable probability exists that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-100__subsec_g__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the prisoner will live and remain at liberty without violating any laws or conditions imposed by the board;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-100__subsec_g__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the prisoner's rehabilitation and reintegration into society will be furthered by release on parole;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-100__subsec_g__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the prisoner will not pose a threat of harm to the public if released on parole; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-100__subsec_g__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>release of the prisoner on parole would not diminish the seriousness of the crime.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-100__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the board considers an application for discretionary parole and denies parole because the prisoner does not meet the standards in (a) or (g) of this section, the board may make the prisoner ineligible for further consideration of discretionary parole or require that additional time be served before the prisoner is again eligible for consideration for discretionary parole.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-16-110">
            <num>33.16.110</num>
            <heading>Preparole reports.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-16-110__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In determining whether a prisoner is suitable for discretionary parole, the board shall consider the preparole reports including</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-110__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the presentence report made to the sentencing court;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-110__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the recommendations made by the sentencing court, by the prosecuting attorney, and by the defense attorney, and any statements made by the victim or the prisoner at sentencing;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-110__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the prisoner's institutional conduct history while incarcerated;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-110__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>recommendations made by the staff of the correctional facilities in which the prisoner was incarcerated;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-110__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>reports of prior crimes, juvenile histories, and previous experiences of the prisoner on parole or probation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-110__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>physical, mental, and psychiatric examinations of the prisoner;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-110__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>information submitted by the prisoner, the sentencing court, the victim of the crime, the prosecutor, or other persons having knowledge of the prisoner or the crime;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-110__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>information concerning an unjustified disparity in the sentence imposed on a prisoner in relation to other sentences imposed under similar circumstances;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-110__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the case plan created under
AS 33.30.011</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-110__subsec_a__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a reentry plan created under
AS 33.30.011</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-110__subsec_a__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>other relevant information that may be reasonably available.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-110__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board shall provide information available under (a)(3) and (a)(6) of this section when requesting comments on the discretionary parole of a prisoner from the sentencing court.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-16-120">
            <num>33.16.120</num>
            <heading>Rights of certain victims in connection with parole.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-16-120__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the victim of a crime against a person or arson in the first degree requests notice of a scheduled hearing to review or consider discretionary parole for a prisoner convicted of that crime, the board shall send notice of the hearing to the victim at least 30 days before the hearing. The notice must be accompanied by a copy of the prisoner's parole plan submitted to the board. However, the copy of the parole plan sent to the victim may not include the prisoner's confidential health information, information protected under
AS 33.16.170
, proposed residence, or employment addresses.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-120__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A victim who requests notice under this section shall maintain a current, valid mailing address on file with the board. The board shall send the notice required by this section to the last known address of the victim. The victim's address may not be disclosed to the prisoner or the prisoner's attorney.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-120__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The victim has a right to attend meetings of the parole board in which the status of the prisoner convicted of the crime against that victim is officially considered and to comment, in writing or in person, on the proposed action of the board. Copies of any written comments shall be provided to the prisoner and the prisoner's attorney before action by the board.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-120__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board shall consider the comments presented under (c) of this section in deciding whether to release the prisoner on parole.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-120__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the victim requests, the board shall make every reasonable effort to notify the victim as soon as practicable in writing of its decision to grant or deny discretionary parole or to release the prisoner under
AS 33.16.010
(c). The notice under this subsection must include the expected date of the prisoner's release, the geographic area in which the prisoner is required to reside, and other pertinent information concerning the prisoner's conditions of parole that may affect the victim.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-120__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon request of the victim, if a prisoner is released under
AS 33.16.010</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-120__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or 33.16.090, the board shall make every reasonable effort to notify the victim before the prisoner's release date. Notification under this subsection must include the expected date of the prisoner's release, the geographic area in which the prisoner is required to reside, and other pertinent information concerning the prisoner's conditions of parole that may affect the victim.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-120__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A victim of a crime involving domestic violence or of a sexual assault under
AS 11.41.410
-  11.41.427 shall be informed by the board at least 30 days in advance of a scheduled hearing to review or consider parole for a prisoner. The board shall inform the victim of any decision to grant or deny parole or to release the prisoner under
AS 33.16.010
(c). If the prisoner is to be released, the victim shall be notified of the expected date of the release, the geographic area in which the prisoner will reside, and any other information concerning conditions of parole that may affect the victim. The victim shall also be informed of any changes in the conditions of parole that may affect the victim. The board shall send the notice required to the last known address of the victim. A person may not bring a civil action for damages for a failure to comply with the provisions of this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-120__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 27 ch 13 SLA 2017.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-16-130">
            <num>33.16.130</num>
            <heading>Parole procedures.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-16-130__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A prisoner eligible for discretionary parole may apply to the board for discretionary parole. As part of the application for parole, the prisoner shall submit to the board a parole release plan that includes information concerning the prisoner's plan for employment, residence, and rehabilitation if released on parole.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-130__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before the board determines a prisoner's suitability for discretionary parole, the prisoner is entitled to a hearing before the board. The commissioner or the commissioner's designee shall furnish to the prisoner a copy of the preparole reports listed in
AS 33.16.110
(a), and the prisoner shall be permitted access to all records that the board will consider in making its decision except those that are made confidential by law. The prisoner may also respond in writing to all materials the board considers, be present at the hearing, and present evidence to the board.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-130__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the board denies parole, the board shall state the reasons for the denial, identify all of the factors considered relevant to the denial, and provide a written plan for addressing all of the factors relevant to the denial. The board may schedule a subsequent parole hearing at the time of the denial or at a later date.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-130__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board shall issue its decision in writing and provide a copy of the decision to the prisoner.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-16-140">
            <num>33.16.140</num>
            <heading>Order for parole.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-16-140__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and (b) and the date parole custody ends, shall be furnished to each prisoner released on special medical, discretionary, or mandatory parole.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-16-150">
            <num>33.16.150</num>
            <heading>Conditions of parole.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-16-150__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>As a condition of parole, a prisoner released on special medical, discretionary, or mandatory parole</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-150__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall obey all state, federal, or local laws or ordinances, and any court orders applicable to the parolee;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-150__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall make diligent efforts to maintain steady employment or meet family obligations;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-150__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall, if involved in education, counseling, training, or treatment, continue in the program unless granted permission from the parole officer assigned to the parolee to discontinue the program;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-150__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall report
(A) upon release to the parole officer assigned to the parolee;
(B) at other times, and in the manner, prescribed by the board or the parole officer assigned to the parolee that accommodate the diligent efforts of the parolee to secure and maintain steady employment or to participate in educational courses or training programs;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-150__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall reside at a stated place and not change that residence without notifying, and receiving permission from, the parole officer assigned to the parolee;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-150__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall remain within stated geographic limits unless written permission to depart from the stated limits is granted the parolee;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-150__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>may not use, possess, handle, purchase, give, distribute, or administer a controlled substance as defined in
AS 11.71.900
or under federal law or a drug for which a prescription is required under state or federal law without a prescription from a licensed medical professional to the parolee;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-150__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>may not possess or control a firearm; in this paragraph, firearm has the meaning given in
AS 11.81.900
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-150__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>may not enter into an agreement or other arrangement with a law enforcement agency or officer that will place the parolee in the position of violating a law or parole condition without the prior approval of the board;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-150__subsec_a__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>may not contact or correspond with anyone confined in a correctional facility of any type serving any term of imprisonment or a felon without the permission of the parole officer assigned to a parolee;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-150__subsec_a__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall agree to waive extradition from any state or territory of the United States and to not contest efforts to return the parolee to the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-150__subsec_a__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall provide a blood sample, an oral sample, or both, when requested by a health care professional acting on behalf of the state to provide the sample or samples, or an oral sample when requested by a juvenile or adult correctional, probation, or parole officer, or a peace officer, if the prisoner is being released after a conviction of an offense requiring the state to collect the sample or samples for the deoxyribonucleic acid identification registration system under
AS 44.41.035
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-150__subsec_a__subsec_13">
                <num>(13)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>from a conviction for a sex offense shall submit to regular periodic polygraph examinations; in this paragraph, sex offense has the meaning given in
AS 12.63.100
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-150__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board may require as a condition of special medical, discretionary, or mandatory parole, or a member of the board acting for the board under (e) of this section may require as a condition of mandatory parole, that a prisoner released on parole</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-150__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>not possess or control a defensive weapon, a deadly weapon other than an ordinary pocket knife with a blade three inches or less in length, or ammunition for a firearm, or reside in a residence where there is a firearm capable of being concealed on one's person or a prohibited weapon; in this paragraph, deadly weapon, defensive weapon, and firearm have the meanings given in
AS 11.81.900
, and prohibited weapon has the meaning given in
AS 11.61.200
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-150__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>refrain from possessing or consuming alcoholic beverages;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-150__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>submit to reasonable searches and seizures by a parole officer, or a peace officer acting under the direction of a parole officer;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-150__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>submit to appropriate medical, mental health, or controlled substance or alcohol examination, treatment, or counseling;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-150__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>submit to periodic examinations designed to detect the use of alcohol or controlled substances; the periodic examinations may include testing under the program established under
AS 33.16.060</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-150__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>make restitution ordered by the court according to a schedule established by the board;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-150__subsec_b__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>refrain from opening, maintaining, or using a checking account or charge account;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-150__subsec_b__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>refrain from entering into a contract other than a prenuptial contract or a marriage contract;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-150__subsec_b__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>refrain from operating a motor vehicle;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-150__subsec_b__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>refrain from entering an establishment where alcoholic beverages are served, sold, or otherwise dispensed;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-150__subsec_b__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>refrain from participating in any other activity or conduct reasonably related to the parolee's offense, prior record, behavior or prior behavior, current circumstances, or perceived risk to the community, or from associating with any other person that the board determines is reasonably likely to diminish the rehabilitative goals of parole, or that may endanger the public; in the case of special medical parole, for a prisoner diagnosed with a communicable disease, comply with conditions set by the board designed to prevent the transmission of the disease;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-150__subsec_b__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>refrain from traveling in the state to make diligent efforts to secure or maintain steady employment or to participate in educational courses or training programs only if the travel violates other conditions of parole.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-150__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except for a condition imposed under (b)(1) and (3)  (6) of this section, the board, or a member of the board acting for the board under (e) of this section, may generally delegate imposition of special conditions under (b) of this section to the discretion of the parole officer.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-150__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board, or a member of the board acting for the board under (e) of this section, may require a prisoner released on parole to comply with special conditions imposed under (b) of this section for any period up to the maximum term under which the prisoner is subject to the custody and jurisdiction of the board.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-150__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board may designate a member of the board to act on behalf of the board in imposing conditions of mandatory parole under (a) and (b) of this section, in delegating imposition of conditions of mandatory parole under (c) of this section, and in setting the period of compliance with the conditions of mandatory parole under (d) of this section. The decision of a member of the board under this section is the decision of the board. A prisoner or parolee aggrieved by a decision of a member of the board acting for the board under this subsection may apply to the board under
AS 33.16.160
for a change in the conditions of mandatory parole.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-150__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to other conditions of parole imposed under this section, the board may impose as a condition of special medical, discretionary, or mandatory parole for a prisoner serving a term for a crime involving domestic violence (1) any of the terms of protective orders under
AS 18.66.100
(c)(1)  (7); (2) a requirement that, at the prisoner's expense, the prisoner participate in and complete, to the satisfaction of the board, a program for the rehabilitation of perpetrators of domestic violence that meets the standards set by, and that is approved by, the department under
AS 44.28.020
(b); and (3) any other condition necessary to rehabilitate the prisoner. The board shall establish procedures for the exchange of information concerning the parolee with the victim and for responding to reports of nonattendance or noncompliance by the parolee with conditions imposed under this subsection. The board may not under this subsection require a prisoner to participate in and complete a program for the rehabilitation of perpetrators of domestic violence unless the program meets the standards set by, and is approved by, the department under
AS 44.28.020
(b).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-150__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to other conditions of parole imposed under this section for a prisoner serving a sentence for an offense where the aggravating factor provided in
AS 12.55.155
(c)(29) has been proven or admitted, the board shall impose as a condition of special medical, discretionary, and mandatory parole a requirement that the prisoner submit to electronic monitoring. Electronic monitoring under this subsection must comply with
AS 33.30.011
(a)(10) and provide for monitoring of the prisoner's location and movements by Global Positioning System technology. The board shall require a prisoner serving a period of parole with electronic monitoring as provided under this subsection to pay all or a portion of the costs of the electronic monitoring, but only if the prisoner has sufficient financial resources to pay the costs or a portion of the costs. A prisoner subject to electronic monitoring under this subsection is not entitled to a credit for time served in a correctional facility while the defendant is on parole. In this subsection, correctional facility has the meaning given in
AS 33.30.901
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-150__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to other conditions of parole imposed under this section, for a prisoner serving a sentence for an offense involving the use of alcohol or controlled substances, the board may impose, as a condition of special medical, discretionary, or mandatory parole, a requirement that the prisoner comply with a program established under
AS 33.16.060</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-150__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or
AS 47.38.020
. The board may require a prisoner serving a period of parole and complying with a program established under
AS 33.16.060</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-150__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or
AS 47.38.020
to pay all or a portion of the costs associated with the program.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-150__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to other conditions of parole imposed under this section, for a prisoner who is serving a sentence for an offense involving the use of alcohol and whom the board has ordered to refrain from possessing or consuming alcoholic beverages, the board shall require the surrender of the person's driver's license or identification card, forward the license or identification card to the department, and impose as a condition of parole that, if the parolee is eligible for a driver's license or identification card, the parolee shall apply to the department for a new license or identification card with a restriction imposed on the person under
AS 04.16.160
. The board shall notify the department of the board's order under this subsection by providing a copy of the board's order. Upon discharge from parole, the board shall notify the department of the parolee's discharge. In this subsection, department means the Department of Administration.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-16-160">
            <num>33.16.160</num>
            <heading>Change in parole conditions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-16-160__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon application of the state or the parolee, the board may change a condition of parole previously imposed under
AS 33.16.150
(b).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-160__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the proposed change in conditions of parole is more restrictive of a parolee's liberty, the parolee is entitled to notice of the proposed change, the reasons for the proposed change, a hearing before the board, and an opportunity to respond to the proposed change and to present evidence.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-160__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (a) and (b) of this section, when a parole officer determines that an emergency situation requires an immediate change in a condition of parole, or the imposition of a new condition, the parole officer may impose the change or new condition immediately, without a hearing.  The parole officer shall immediately notify the board of the imposition of the emergency change or new condition and shall provide a written report setting out the basis for the change or new condition and the nature of the emergency.  The effective period of a change in condition or imposition of a new condition under this subsection may not exceed 15 working days.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-160__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A condition of parole may be changed, a new condition of parole may be imposed, or a new or changed condition imposed under (c) of this section may be extended by a member of the board or the board's designee if, after a preliminary hearing, an emergency situation is found that requires a change in condition. The effective period of a change in condition under this subsection, the imposition of a new condition under this subsection, or the extension under this subsection of a new or changed condition imposed under (c) of this section may not exceed 90 days.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-16-170">
            <num>33.16.170</num>
            <heading>Confidentiality of records and information.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-16-170__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (b) of this section, the preparole reports listed in
AS 33.16.110
, and other information obtained and used by the board under this chapter, are confidential and may not be disclosed to anyone other than the board, the sentencing judge, the prosecuting and defense attorneys, the prisoner, the prisoner's attorney, the attorney for the board, the staff of the board, or others granted access to this information under this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-170__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (a) of this section and
AS 33.16.130
(b), in a preparole proceeding under
AS 33.16.130
the board may not disclose to the prisoner or the prisoner's attorney</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-170__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>diagnostic opinions that, if made known to the eligible prisoner, could lead to serious disruption of the prisoner's institutional program;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-170__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>portions of a document that reveal sources of information obtained upon a promise of confidentiality; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-170__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>other information that, if disclosed, may result in physical harm to any other person.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-170__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the board withholds information from a prisoner or the prisoner's attorney under (b) of this section, the board shall provide the prisoner with an excised copy of the material or summary of the material withheld containing as much specificity as the circumstances allow.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-170__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except for portions containing personal medical, mental health, or substance abuse treatment information or information that is otherwise required to be kept confidential by state or federal law, decisions of the board, orders for parole, and parole conditions imposed by the board are not confidential. The board shall post all decisions, orders of parole, and conditions imposed on a publicly available Internet website with any confidential portions redacted.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-16-180">
            <num>33.16.180</num>
            <heading>Duties of the commissioner.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-16-180__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>a process for responding to negative behavior that includes a review of previous violations and sanctions;
(ii) that enhanced sanctions for certain negative conduct are approved by the commissioner or the commissioner's designee; and
(iii) that appropriate due process protections are included in the process, including notice of negative behavior, an opportunity to dispute the accusation and the sanction, and an opportunity to request a review of the accusation and the sanction;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-180__subsec_i__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>within 30 days after sentencing of an offender, provide the victim of a crime information on the earliest dates the offender could be released on furlough, probation, or parole, including deductions or reductions for good time or other good conduct incentives, and the process for release, including contact information for the decision-making bodies; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-180__subsec_i__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>notify the board and the victim of a crime upon receiving notice that a parolee has filed a petition for a change of name under
AS 09.55.010
or
AS 25.24.165
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-16-190">
            <num>33.16.190</num>
            <heading>Authority of parole, pretrial services, and probation officers.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 33.16.190.   Authority of parole, pretrial services, and probation officers.
An officer appointed by the commissioner under
AS 33.05.020
(a),
AS 33.07
, or this chapter, may discharge duties under
AS 33.05
,
AS 33.07
, or this chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-16-200">
            <num>33.16.200</num>
            <heading>Custody of parolee.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 33.16.200.   Custody of parolee.
Except as provided in
AS 33.16.210
, the board retains custody of special medical, discretionary, and mandatory parolees until the expiration of the maximum term or terms of imprisonment to which the parolee is sentenced.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-16-210">
            <num>33.16.210</num>
            <heading>Discharge of parolee.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-16-210__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board may unconditionally discharge a parolee from the jurisdiction and custody of the board after the parolee has completed one year of parole. A discretionary parolee with a residual period of probation may, after one year of parole, be discharged by the board to immediately begin serving the residual period of probation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-210__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (a) of this section, the board may unconditionally discharge a mandatory parolee before the parolee has completed one year of parole if the parolee is serving a concurrent period of residual probation under
AS 33.20.040
(c), and the period of residual probation and the period of suspended imprisonment each equal or exceed the period of mandatory parole.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-210__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>At the discretion of a parole officer, a parole officer may recommend to the board early discharge for a parolee who</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-210__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has completed at least one year on parole;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-210__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has completed all treatment programs required as a condition of parole;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-210__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is currently in compliance with all conditions of parole for all of the cases for which the person is on parole; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-210__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has not been convicted of
(A) an unclassified felony offense under
AS 11
;
(B) a sexual felony as defined in
AS 12.55.185
; or
(C) a crime involving domestic violence as defined in
AS 18.66.990
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-16-215">
            <num>33.16.215</num>
            <heading>Sanctions for technical violations and other violations of parole.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 33.16.215.   Sanctions for technical violations and other violations of parole.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-16-215">
            <num>33.16.215</num>
            <heading>Sanctions for technical violations and other violations of parole.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 33.16.215.   Sanctions for technical violations and other violations of parole.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-16-220">
            <num>33.16.220</num>
            <heading>Revocation of parole.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-16-220__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board may revoke parole if the prisoner or parolee (1) engages in conduct in violation of
AS 33.16.150
(a), (b), or (f), or (2) has violated an order of the court to participate in or comply with the treatment plan of a rehabilitation program under
AS 12.55.015
(a)(10). Mandatory parole may be revoked before a prisoner's actual release on parole.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-220__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (e) of this section, within 15 working days after the arrest and incarceration of a parolee for violation of a condition of parole, the board or its designee shall hold a preliminary hearing. At the preliminary hearing, the board or its designee shall determine if there is probable cause to believe that the parolee violated the conditions of parole and, when probable cause exists, whether the parolee should be released pending a final revocation hearing. A finding of probable cause at a preliminary hearing in a criminal case is conclusive proof of probable cause that a parole violation occurred.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-220__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In determining whether a parole violator should be released pending a final revocation hearing, the board or its designee shall consider</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-220__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the likelihood of the parolee's appearance at a final revocation hearing;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-220__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the seriousness of the alleged violation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-220__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>whether the parolee presents a danger to the community;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-220__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>whether the parolee is likely to further violate conditions of parole; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-220__subsec_c__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>whether the parolee is on parole for a crime involving domestic violence; if the violation of the condition of parole involved an act of domestic violence, the parolee may not be released pending the final revocation hearing.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-220__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the parole violator is released pending a final revocation hearing, the board or its designee may impose additional conditions necessary to ensure the parolee's appearance at the final revocation hearing, and to prevent further violation of conditions of parole.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-220__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A preliminary hearing under (b) of this section is not required if the board holds a final revocation hearing within 20 working days after the parolee's arrest and incarceration.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-220__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a parolee has had a preliminary hearing under (b) of this section, the board shall hold a final revocation hearing not later than 120 days after a parolee's arrest, subject to restrictions arising under
AS 33.36.110
and (g) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-220__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the basis for the revocation proceeding is a criminal charge, the parolee may request, or the board upon its own motion may propose, that further proceedings on the revocation be delayed.  In making the determination to delay further proceedings, the board shall consider prejudice that may result to the parolee's and the state's interests in the pending criminal case and the parolee's decision to delay final revocation proceedings.  If good cause to proceed is found, the board shall consult with the attorney general before continuing the final revocation proceeding.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-220__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>At a final revocation hearing, a violation of a condition of parole must be established by a preponderance of the evidence.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-220__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If, after the final revocation hearing, the board finds that the parolee has violated a condition of parole imposed under
AS 33.16.150
(a), (b), or (f), or a law or ordinance, the board may revoke all or a portion of the remaining period of parole or change any condition of parole. A parolee's period of parole is tolled from the date of filing with the parole board of a violation report until the date of the final revocation hearing.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-220__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 138 ch 4 FSSLA 2019.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-16-230">
            <num>33.16.230</num>
            <heading>Waiver of hearing.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 33.16.230.   Waiver of hearing.
A prisoner or parolee may waive the right to a hearing provided under
AS 33.16.130
, 33.16.160, or 33.16.220 by submitting a written waiver to the board.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-16-240">
            <num>33.16.240</num>
            <heading>Arrest of parole violator.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-16-240__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A parolee may be arrested, with or without a warrant, for a violation of parole.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-240__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A warrant for the arrest of a parolee who is charged with a violation of parole may be issued by the board, or a member of the board, based on probable cause that a violation has occurred.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-240__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to the powers granted to a police officer under (g) of this section, a parole officer may, without a warrant, arrest a parolee for a violation of parole only if there is danger to the public, if there is a likelihood that the parolee will flee, or if the parolee committed a crime in the presence of the parole officer.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-240__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a parolee is arrested without a warrant, the parole officer shall notify the board no later than the working day immediately following the arrest.  The parole officer shall, within five working days after the arrest, provide the board with a written report setting out the alleged violation and circumstances that required immediate arrest of the parolee.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-240__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A parolee arrested for violation of parole is not entitled to bail.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-240__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Time spent in custody pending revocation proceedings shall be credited toward the unexpired term of imprisonment of the parolee; however, the time the parolee was at liberty on parole does not alter the time the parolee was sentenced to serve.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-240__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>At any time within the period of parole supervision, a police officer certified by the Alaska Police Standards Council may detain a parolee if the officer has reasonable suspicion that the person has recently violated or may imminently violate a parole condition relating to one of the topics set out in
AS 33.05.070
(d). The officer may also arrest the parolee without a warrant if the officer has probable cause to believe that the person has violated a parole condition relating to one of the topics set out in
AS 33.05.070
(d).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-240__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 138 ch 4 FSSLA 2019.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-240__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board or its designee may impose additional conditions necessary to ensure the parolee's appearance at a hearing held under
AS 33.16.220
(h).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-16-250">
            <num>33.16.250</num>
            <heading>Execution of warrant for arrest of parolee.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-16-250__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A parole officer, or a peace officer acting at the request of a parole officer, shall execute a warrant issued under
AS 33.16.240
by arresting the parolee and confining the parolee in a correctional facility designated by the commissioner.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-250__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The parole officer or peace officer shall immediately notify the board or a member of the board of an arrest under (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-16-260">
            <num>33.16.260</num>
            <heading>Designation of victims' representative.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 33.16.260.   Designation of victims' representative.
If more than one person who qualifies as a victim under
AS 12.55.185
requests notice under this chapter, the commissioner shall designate one person for purposes of receiving the notice required and exercising the rights granted by this chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-16-270">
            <num>33.16.270</num>
            <heading>Earned compliance credits.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-16-270__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall establish by regulation a program allowing parolees to earn credits for complying with the conditions of parole. The earned compliance credits reduce the period of parole. Nothing in this section prohibits the department from recommending to the board the early discharge of the parolee as provided in this chapter. At a minimum, the regulations must</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-270__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>require that a parolee earn a credit of 10 days for each 30-day period served in which the parolee complied with the conditions of parole;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-270__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>include policies and procedures for
(A) calculating and tracking credits earned by parolees;
(B) reducing the parolee's period of parole based on credits earned by the parolee and notifying a victim under
AS 33.30.013
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-270__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>require that a parolee convicted of a crime involving domestic violence complete all treatment programs required as a condition of parole before discharge based on credits earned under this section.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-16-270__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A parolee may not earn credits under (a) of this section if the parolee is on parole for</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-270__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an unclassified felony;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-270__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a sex offense as defined in
AS 12.63.100
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-270__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a felony crime against a person under
AS 11.41
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-16-270__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a crime involving domestic violence, as defined in
AS 18.66.990
, that is an offense under
AS 11.41
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-16-900">
            <num>33.16.900</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 33.16.900.   Definitions.
In this chapter,
(1) administrative sanctions and incentives means responses by a parole officer to a parolee's compliance with or violation of the conditions of parole under
AS 33.16.180
.
(2) board means the board of parole;
(3) commissioner means the commissioner of corrections;
(4) controlled substance means a drug, substance, or immediate precursor included in the schedules set out in
AS 11.71.140
  11.71.190;
(5) crime against a person has the meaning given in
AS 33.30.901
;
(6) crime involving domestic violence and domestic violence have the meanings given in
AS 18.66.990
;
(7) department means the Department of Corrections;
(8) discretionary parole means the release of a prisoner by the board before the expiration of a term, subject to conditions imposed by the board and subject to its custody and jurisdiction; discretionary parole does not include special medical parole;
(9) mandatory parole means the release of a prisoner who was sentenced to one or more terms of imprisonment of two years or more, for the period of good time credited under
AS 33.20
, subject to conditions imposed by the board and subject to its custody and jurisdiction;
(10) parolee means a prisoner, sentenced to one or more terms of imprisonment exceeding 180 days in the case of discretionary parole and of two years or more in the case of mandatory parole, released by the board or by operation of law before the expiration of the term, subject to the custody and jurisdiction of the board;
(11) prisoner means an offender confined for a violation of state law, but does not include a person confined under
AS 47
;
(12) severely medically or cognitively disabled means that a person has a medical condition, or a cognitive condition, that substantially reduces the ability to commit an offense similar to the offense for which the person was convicted or to commit an offense in violation of
AS 11.41
that is punishable as a felony, and the person is likely to
(A) remain subject to the severe medical or cognitive condition throughout the entire period of parole; or
(B) die from the medical or cognitive condition;
(13) special medical parole means the release by the board before the expiration of a term, subject to conditions imposed by the board and subject to its custody and jurisdiction, of a prisoner who is severely medically or cognitively disabled;
(14) victim has the meaning given in
AS 12.55.185
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>