<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-10/chapter-50"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-10/chapter-50"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="10.50"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-10/chapter-50/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-10/chapter-50/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-10/chapter-50/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-10/chapter-50/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_10">
        <num>10</num>
        <heading>Corporations and Associations</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_10__chp_50">
          <num>50</num>
          <heading>Alaska Revised Limited Liability Company Act</heading>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-010">
            <num>10.50.010</num>
            <heading>Authorized purposes.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.010.   Authorized purposes.
A limited liability company may be organized under this chapter for any lawful purpose, including the rendering of a professional service.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-015">
            <num>10.50.015</num>
            <heading>Compliance with other laws.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.015.   Compliance with other laws.
If an activity of a limited liability company or the purpose for which a limited liability company is organized is subject to another provision of law, the company shall also comply with the other provision of law.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-020">
            <num>10.50.020</num>
            <heading>Limited liability company name.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-020__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The name of a limited liability company stated in the company's articles of organization must contain the words limited liability company or the abbreviation L.L.C., or LLC. The word limited may be abbreviated as Ltd., and the word company may be abbreviated as Co.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-020__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The name of a city, borough, or village may be used in a limited liability company name; however, the name may not contain the word city, borough, or village or otherwise imply that the company is a municipality.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-020__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not adopt a name that contains the words limited liability company unless the person is organized under this chapter or is registered as a foreign limited liability company under this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-025">
            <num>10.50.025</num>
            <heading>Distinguishable name.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.025.   Distinguishable name.
The name of a limited liability company must be distinguishable on the records of the department from the name of any other organized entity and from a reserved or registered name. The department may adopt regulations to implement this section. In this section, organized entity and reserved or registered name have the meanings given in
AS 10.35.040
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-030">
            <num>10.50.030</num>
            <heading>Right to reserve name.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.030.   Right to reserve name.
The exclusive right to use a name may be reserved by a
(1) person intending to organize a limited liability company and to adopt the name;
(2) person intending to organize a foreign limited liability company and to register under this chapter;
(3) limited liability company, or a foreign limited liability company registered under this chapter, that intends to change its name; or
(4) foreign limited liability company that intends to register under this chapter and to adopt the name.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-035">
            <num>10.50.035</num>
            <heading>Application to reserve company name.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.035.   Application to reserve company name.
Reservation of a name under
AS 10.50.030
is made by filing an application with the department. If the department finds that the name is available for use by a limited liability company and is distinguishable on the records of the department under
AS 10.50.025
, the department shall reserve it for the exclusive use of the applicant for a period of 120 days.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-038">
            <num>10.50.038</num>
            <heading>Transfer of reserved name.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.038.   Transfer of reserved name.
The holder of a name reserved under
AS 10.50.030
may transfer the right to the exclusive use of the name to another person by filing a notice of transfer with the department, signed by the holder of the name, and specifying the name and address of the transferee.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-040">
            <num>10.50.040</num>
            <heading>Registration of company name.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.040.   Registration of company name.
A limited liability company or a foreign limited liability company may register its name if the name is distinguishable on the records of the department under
AS 10.50.025
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-043">
            <num>10.50.043</num>
            <heading>Exclusive right to use of name; use of nondistinguishable name.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.043.   Exclusive right to use of name; use of nondistinguishable name.
Organization or registration under this chapter, or registration of a name under this chapter, gives the person who has organized or registered under this chapter, or registered a name under this chapter, exclusive right to the use of the name. The person may enjoin the use of a name that is not distinguishable from the name to which the person has the exclusive right and the person has a cause of action for damages against a person who uses a name that is not distinguishable from the name to which the person has the exclusive right.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-048">
            <num>10.50.048</num>
            <heading>Procedure for registration of company name.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.048.   Procedure for registration of company name.
Registration of a name under
AS 10.50.040
is made by filing with the department
(1) a signed application for registration setting out the name of the company, the state or territory under the laws of which it is organized, the date of organization, a statement that it is conducting affairs, and a brief statement of its principal activities; and
(2) proof from the jurisdiction where the company is organized that indicates that the company is organized in that jurisdiction if the company is a foreign limited liability company.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-050">
            <num>10.50.050</num>
            <heading>Duration of name registration.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.050.   Duration of name registration.
The registration of a name under
AS 10.50.040
is effective until the close of the calendar year in which the application for registration is filed.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-053">
            <num>10.50.053</num>
            <heading>Renewal of name registration.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-053__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The registration of a name under
AS 10.50.040
may be renewed each year by</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-053__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>filing an application for renewal setting out the facts required in an original application for registration;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-053__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>filing proof of organization required for an original registration; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-053__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>paying a fee established by the department.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-053__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An application for renewal shall be filed between October 1 and December 31 in each year. The renewal extends the registration for the following calendar year.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-055">
            <num>10.50.055</num>
            <heading>Registered office and registered agent.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.055.   Registered office and registered agent.
A limited liability company shall continuously maintain in this state a registered agent and a registered office. The registered office may be the same as the office of the company. The registered agent may be either an individual resident of this state whose business office is the same as the registered office, or a domestic or foreign corporation authorized to transact business in this state whose business office is the same as the registered office.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-060">
            <num>10.50.060</num>
            <heading>Change of registered office or agent by company.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-060__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A limited liability company may change its registered office, agent, or both, by filing with the department a signed statement that includes</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-060__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name of the company;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-060__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the address of its registered office;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-060__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the address of its new registered office if the registered office is to be changed;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-060__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name of its registered agent;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-060__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name of its new registered agent if the registered agent is to be changed; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-060__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a statement that the change is authorized by the company's manager, or, if the company is not managed by a manager, by the members.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-060__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the department finds that the statement complies with this chapter, the department shall file it in the department's office. The change becomes effective when the statement is filed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-063">
            <num>10.50.063</num>
            <heading>Registered agent's change of office location or resignation.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-063__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A registered agent of a limited liability company may change the location of the agent's office from one address to another in this state. The agent may change the registered office for each company for which the person is acting as registered agent by filing in the department a statement setting out the name of the agent, the address of the agent's office before change, the address to which the office is changed, and a list of companies for which the person is the registered agent. The statement shall be executed by the registered agent in the individual name of the agent or, if the agent is a corporation, it shall be executed by its president or a vice-president. The statement shall be delivered to the department and the limited liability company and, if the department finds that the statement complies with this chapter, the department shall file it. The change becomes effective when the statement is filed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-063__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A registered agent may resign by filing a written notice and an exact copy of the notice with the department. The written notice of resignation must set out the latest address of the principal office of the company and the name, address, and title of the manager, or, if the company is managed by its members, the names and addresses of the members of the company known by the agent. The department shall immediately mail a copy of the notice to the company at its principal office. The resignation becomes effective 30 days after the filing of the written notice, unless the company sooner appoints a successor registered agent, as provided in
AS 10.50.060
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-065">
            <num>10.50.065</num>
            <heading>Service on company.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-065__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The registered agent of a limited liability company is an agent upon whom process, notice, or demand required or permitted by law to be served upon the company may be served.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-065__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a limited liability company fails to appoint or maintain a registered agent in this state, or if its registered agent cannot, with reasonable diligence, be found at the registered office, the commissioner is an agent of the company upon whom the process, notice, or demand may be served. A person may serve the commissioner under this subsection by</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-065__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>serving on the commissioner or the designee of the commissioner a copy of the process, notice, or demand, with any papers required by law to be delivered in connection with the service, and a fee established by the department by regulation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-065__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>sending to the company being served by certified mail a notice that service has been made on the commissioner under this subsection and a copy of the process, notice, or demand and accompanying papers; notice to the company shall be sent to
(A) the address of the last registered office of the company as shown by the records on file in the department; and
(B) the address, the use of which the person initiating the proceedings knows or, on the basis of reasonable inquiry, has reason to believe is most likely to result in actual notice; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-065__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>filing with the appropriate court or other body, as part of the return of service, the return receipt of mailing and an affidavit of the person initiating the proceedings that this section has been complied with.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-065__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall keep a record of processes, notices, and demands served upon the commissioner under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-065__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This section does not affect the right to serve process, notice, or demand required or permitted by law to be served upon a company in any other manner permitted.
Article 3. Organization and Operating Agreement.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-070">
            <num>10.50.070</num>
            <heading>Organizers.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.070.   Organizers.
One or more persons may organize a limited liability company by signing articles of organization and delivering the signed articles to the department for filing. A person who organizes a limited liability company may be a person who is not a member of the company when the company is organized or after the company is organized.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-075">
            <num>10.50.075</num>
            <heading>Contents of articles of organization.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.075.   Contents of articles of organization.
The articles of organization of a limited liability company must state
(1) the name of the company;
(2) the purpose for which the company is organized, which may be stated to be, or to include, the conduct of any or all lawful affairs for which a limited liability company may be organized under this chapter;
(3) the mailing address of the company's registered office and the name of the company's registered agent;
(4) if applicable, that the company will be managed by a manager; and
(5) any other provision for the regulation of the internal affairs of the company that is consistent with this chapter and the laws of this state if the persons organizing the company elect to include the provision in the articles of organization.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-078">
            <num>10.50.078</num>
            <heading>Disclosure of company activities.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.078.   Disclosure of company activities.
The organizers delivering articles of organization under
AS 10.50.070
shall deliver with the articles a separate statement of the codes from the identification codes established under
AS 10.06.870
that most closely describe the activities in which the company will initially engage.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-080">
            <num>10.50.080</num>
            <heading>Effective date of organization.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.080.   Effective date of organization.
A limited liability company is organized when the articles of organization for the company that conform to the filing requirements of this chapter are delivered to the department for filing under
AS 10.50.820
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-090">
            <num>10.50.090</num>
            <heading>Conclusive evidence of compliance.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.090.   Conclusive evidence of compliance.
A copy of the articles of organization that is stamped filed and marked with the filing date is conclusive evidence that the organizers of the limited liability company have complied with all conditions precedent required to be performed by the organizers and that the company has been organized under this chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-095">
            <num>10.50.095</num>
            <heading>Operating agreement.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.095.   Operating agreement.
The members of a limited liability company may adopt an operating agreement for the company and may amend and repeal the agreement. The articles of organization may restrict or eliminate the power of the members to adopt, amend, or repeal an operating agreement.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-100">
            <num>10.50.100</num>
            <heading>Amendment of articles.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-100__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A limited liability company may amend its articles of organization in any respect if the articles as amended contain only the provisions that are required or permitted by this chapter to be included in the original articles of organization at the time of the amendment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-100__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A limited liability company may amend its articles of organization by filing articles of amendment with the department. The articles of amendment must state the</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-100__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>name of the company;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-100__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>date the articles of organization were filed; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-100__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>amendment adopted by the company.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-105">
            <num>10.50.105</num>
            <heading>Restatement of articles.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.105.   Restatement of articles.
A limited liability company may restate its articles of organization at any time. The company shall file its restated articles with the department. The restated articles of organization must be specifically designated as restated articles in the title to the restated articles and must state, either in the title or in an introductory paragraph, the
(1) company's present and, if the name is changed, all of the company's former names; and
(2) date of the filing of the company's original articles of organization.
Article 5. Management.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-110">
            <num>10.50.110</num>
            <heading>Management generally.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-110__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as otherwise provided in the company's articles of organization, the members of a limited liability company manage the affairs and make the decisions of the company. Management by the members is subject to a provision in an operating agreement or this chapter limiting or increasing the management rights and duties of the members, including limits or increases placed on a class of members or an individual member.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-110__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a limited liability company is managed by a manager, the manager has the exclusive power to manage the affairs of the company to the extent authorized by the operating agreement.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-115">
            <num>10.50.115</num>
            <heading>Appointment, removal, and replacement of managers.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.115.   Appointment, removal, and replacement of managers.
Except as otherwise provided in an operating agreement of a limited liability company, a manager of the company may not be appointed, removed, or replaced, unless more than one-half of all of the members of the company authorize the appointment, removal, or replacement.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-120">
            <num>10.50.120</num>
            <heading>Eligibility and number of managers.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.120.   Eligibility and number of managers.
Unless otherwise provided in an operating agreement of the company, a manager of a limited liability company may be a person who is not an individual or a member of the company. A company may have more than one manager.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-125">
            <num>10.50.125</num>
            <heading>Tenure of manager.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-125__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless otherwise provided in an operating agreement of the company, a manager of a limited liability company holds office until the manager's successor is elected and qualified, unless the manager resigns or is removed earlier.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-125__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A manager may not resign as manager of a limited liability company except at the time or upon the happening of events specified in the operating agreement of the company. An operating agreement may provide that a manager does not have the right to resign as a manager of a limited liability company. Notwithstanding that an operating agreement provides that a manager does not have the right to resign as a manager of a limited liability company, a manager may resign as a manager of a limited liability company at any time by giving notice to the members and any other managers. If the resignation of a manager violates the operating agreement of the company, in addition to any remedy otherwise available under applicable law, a limited liability company may recover from the resigning manager damages for breach of the operating agreement and may offset the damages against the amount otherwise distributable to the resigning manager. If the manager was the sole manager and if, within 90 days after the resignation, the members fail to agree on the appointment of a new manager, then each member shall have a say in the management of the company that is equal to the proportion of the member's capital account in the company.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-130">
            <num>10.50.130</num>
            <heading>Limitation of member fiduciary duty.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.130.   Limitation of member fiduciary duty.
Unless otherwise provided in an operating agreement of the company, if a person is a member of a limited liability company that is managed by a manager and if the person is not a manager, the person does not have the fiduciary duty of a manager to the company or to the other members of the company when the person acts solely in the capacity of a member.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-135">
            <num>10.50.135</num>
            <heading>Duty of care.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-135__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who is a manager or a managing member of a limited liability company shall perform the duties of management in good faith, in a manner the person reasonably believes to be in the best interests of the company, and with the care, including reasonable inquiry, that an ordinarily prudent person in a like position would use under similar circumstances. Except as provided in (b) of this section, the person is entitled to rely on information, opinions, reports, or statements, including financial statements and other financial data, in each case prepared or presented by</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-135__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an employee of the company whom the person reasonably believes to be reliable and competent in the matters presented; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-135__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>counsel, public accountants, or other professionals or experts as to matters that the person reasonably believes to be within the professional's or expert's competence.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-135__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person is not acting in good faith under (a) of this section if the person has knowledge concerning the matter in question that makes reliance otherwise permitted by (a) of this section unwarranted.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-140">
            <num>10.50.140</num>
            <heading>Conflicts of interest.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-140__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A contract or other transaction between a limited liability company and a manager or managing member of a limited liability company, or between a limited liability company and a limited liability company, foreign limited liability company, corporation, firm, or association in which a manager or managing member of the company has a material financial interest, is not void or voidable because the manager or managing member or the other company, corporation, firm, or association are parties or because the manager or managing member is present at the meeting that authorizes, approves, or ratifies the contract or transaction, if the material facts as to the transaction and as to the interest of the manager or managing member are fully disclosed or known to the members and the contract or transaction is approved by the members in good faith, with the interested manager or managing member not being entitled to vote.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-140__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The fact that a manager or managing member of a limited liability company is a manager or managing member of another entity involved in the transaction does not alone constitute a material financial interest within the meaning of this section. A manager or managing member is not interested within the meaning of this section in a decision fixing the compensation of another manager or managing member as a manager or managing member of the company, notwithstanding the fact that the first manager or managing member is also receiving compensation from the company.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-140__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A contract or other transaction between a manager or managing member and a limited liability company or association of which one or more managers or managing members of the company are managers or managing members is not void or voidable because the managers or managing members are present at the meeting that authorizes, approves, or ratifies the contract or transaction, if the material facts of the transaction and the manager's or managing member's other management position are fully disclosed or known to the members and the members authorize, approve, or ratify the contract or transaction in good faith by a sufficient vote without counting the vote of the common manager or managing member or the contract or transaction is approved by the members in good faith. This subsection does not apply to contracts or transactions covered by (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-140__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing in this section affects the prohibitions or restraints imposed by
AS 45.50.562
 45.50.596.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-145">
            <num>10.50.145</num>
            <heading>Loans to managers, managing members, and employees.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-145__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A loan may not be extended by a limited liability company to an employee without authorization by the company's managers or managing members. A loan may not be extended to a manager or a managing member of a limited liability company without the approval of two-thirds of the company's members. An employee who is also a manager or managing member is considered a manager or managing member for purposes of this section. A member is not disqualified from voting on a loan to a member as a manager or managing member because of personal interest.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-145__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A loan to a manager, managing member, or employee and a loan secured by the limited liability company interests of the company may not be made unless the loan would be permissible as a distribution under
AS 10.50.290
 10.50.345. A loan under this subsection impairs the retained earnings or paid-in capital accounts to the extent of the loan.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-145__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of this section, a loan may consist of cash, securities, or personal or real property.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-145__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a limited liability company acts as a guarantor on a loan to a manager, managing member, or employee, the guarantee is treated as a loan under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-145__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A manager, managing member, or employee of an affiliated limited liability company is a manager, managing member, or employee of the lending company for purposes of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-145__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A loan is to be judged by the duties of managers and managing members to act in good faith in a manner reasonably believed to be in the best interests of the company and with the care, including reasonable inquiry, that an ordinarily prudent person in a like position would use under similar circumstances.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-148">
            <num>10.50.148</num>
            <heading>Indemnification of managers, managing members, employees, and agents; insurance.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-148__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A limited liability company may indemnify a person who was, is, or is threatened to be made a party to a completed, pending, or threatened action or proceeding, whether civil, criminal, administrative, or investigative, other than an action by or in the right of the company, by reason of the fact that the person is or was a manager, managing member, employee, or agent of the company, or is or was serving at the request of the company as a manager, managing member, employee, or agent of another limited liability company, partnership, joint venture, trust, or other enterprise. Indemnification may include reimbursement of expenses, attorney fees, judgments, fines, and amounts paid in settlement actually and reasonably incurred by the person in connection with the action or proceeding if the person acted in good faith and in a manner the person reasonably believed to be in or not opposed to the best interests of the company, and, with respect to a criminal action or proceeding, the person had no reasonable cause to believe the conduct was unlawful. The termination of an action or proceeding by judgment, order, settlement, conviction, or upon a plea of nolo contendere or its equivalent, does not create a presumption that the person did not act in good faith and in a manner which the person reasonably believed to be in or not opposed to the best interests of the company, and, with respect to a criminal action or proceeding, the person had reasonable cause to believe that the conduct was unlawful.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-148__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A limited liability company may indemnify a person who was, is, or is threatened to be made a party to a completed, pending, or threatened action by or in the right of the company to procure a judgment in its favor by reason of the fact that the person is or was a manager, managing member, employee, or agent of the company, or is or was serving at the request of the company as a manager, managing member, employee, or agent of another limited liability company, partnership, joint venture, trust, or other enterprise. Indemnification may include reimbursement for expenses and attorney fees actually and reasonably incurred by the person in connection with the defense or settlement of the action if the person acted in good faith and in a manner the person reasonably believed to be in or not opposed to the best interests of the company. Indemnification may not be made in respect of any claim, issue, or matter as to which the person has been adjudged to be liable for negligence or misconduct in the performance of the person's duty to the company except to the extent that the court in which the action was brought determines upon application that, despite the adjudication of liability, in view of all the circumstances of the case, the person is fairly and reasonably entitled to indemnity for expenses that the court considers proper.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-148__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To the extent that a manager, managing member, employee, or agent of a limited liability company has been successful on the merits or otherwise in defense of an action or proceeding referred to in (a) or (b) of this section, or in defense of a claim, issue, or matter in the action or proceeding, the manager, managing member, employee, or agent shall be indemnified against expenses and attorney fees actually and reasonably incurred in connection with the defense.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-148__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless otherwise ordered by a court, indemnification under (a) or (b) of this section may only be made by a company upon a determination that indemnification of the manager, managing member, employee, or agent is proper in the circumstances because the manager, managing member, employee, or agent has met the applicable standard of conduct set out in (a) and (b) of this section. The determination shall be made by the members.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-148__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The company may pay or reimburse the reasonable expenses incurred in defending a civil or criminal action or proceeding in advance of the final disposition in the manner provided in (d) of this section if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-148__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in the case of a manager or managing member, the manager or managing member furnishes the company with a written affirmation of a good faith belief that the standard of conduct described in
AS 10.50.135</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-148__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>has been met;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-148__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the manager, managing member, employee, or agent furnishes the company a written unlimited general undertaking, executed personally or on behalf of the individual, to repay the advance if it is ultimately determined that an applicable standard of conduct was not met; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-148__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a determination is made that the facts then known to those making the determination would not preclude indemnification under this chapter.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-148__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The indemnification provided by this section is not exclusive of any other rights to which a person seeking indemnification may be entitled. The right to indemnification continues as to a person who has ceased to be a manager, managing member, employee, or agent, and inures to the benefit of the heirs, executors, and administrators of the person.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-148__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A limited liability company may purchase and maintain insurance on behalf of a person who is or was a manager, managing member, employee, or agent of the company, or is or was serving at the request of the company as a manager, managing member, employee, or agent of another limited liability company, partnership, joint venture, trust, or other enterprise against any liability asserted against the person and incurred by the person in that capacity, or arising out of that status, whether or not the company has the power to indemnify the person against the liability under the provisions of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-150">
            <num>10.50.150</num>
            <heading>Authorization of company affairs.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-150__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless otherwise provided in an operating agreement of the company, the company's articles of organization, or by this chapter, if the company is not managed by a manager, the consent of more than one-half of all of the members of a limited liability company is required to decide the affairs of the company.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-150__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless otherwise provided in an operating agreement of the company or by this chapter, the consent of more than one-half of the number of managers of a limited liability company is required to decide the affairs of the company.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-150__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (a) and (b) of this section, and unless otherwise provided in an operating agreement of the company or in the company's articles of organization, the written consent of all of the members of a limited liability company is required to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-150__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>amend the articles of organization;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-150__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>amend an operating agreement of the company; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-150__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>authorize a manager or member to perform an act on behalf of the company that contravenes an operating agreement of the company, including an act that contravenes a provision of the operating agreement that expressly limits the purposes, affairs, or conduct of the affairs of the company.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-150__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 4 ch 52 SLA 2007.]
Article 6. Membership.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-155">
            <num>10.50.155</num>
            <heading>Membership requirements.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-155__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may become a member in a limited liability company if the person acquires a limited liability company interest</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-155__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>directly from the limited liability company
(A) in compliance with an operating agreement of the company; or
(B) with the written consent of all of the members of the company if an operating agreement of the company does not provide for acquiring an interest directly from the company; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-155__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>by assignment of the interest by a company member in compliance with
AS 10.50.165
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-155__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A limited liability company must have one or more members.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-160">
            <num>10.50.160</num>
            <heading>Effective date of admission.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.160.   Effective date of admission.
The effective date of the admission of a member to a limited liability company is the later of the date
(1) when the company is organized;
(2) established in an operating agreement of the company; or
(3) when the person's admission is reflected in the records of the company if an operating agreement of the company does not establish an effective date.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-165">
            <num>10.50.165</num>
            <heading>Authorization for assignee to become member.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-165__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless otherwise provided in an operating agreement of the company, an assignee of a limited liability company interest may not become a member unless all other members consent.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-165__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An operating agreement of the company may specify the manner for evidencing the consent required by (a) of this section. If an operating agreement does not specify the manner for evidencing the consent, the consent is evidenced by a written instrument that is dated and signed by the members.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-170">
            <num>10.50.170</num>
            <heading>Rights, powers, and liabilities of assignee who becomes a member.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-170__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An assignee who becomes a member has, to the extent assigned, the rights and powers of a member under the articles of organization, an operating agreement, and this chapter, and is subject to the restrictions and liabilities of a member under the articles of organization, an operating agreement, and this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-170__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to the liabilities imposed under (a) of this section, an assignee of a limited liability company interest who becomes a member of the company is liable for an obligation of the assignor to make a contribution under
AS 10.50.280
that is not imposed by the articles of organization, an operating agreement, or otherwise by this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-170__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (a) and (b) of this section, an assignee who becomes a member is not liable for liabilities that are unknown to the assignee when the assignee becomes a member and that cannot be determined from the written records of the company maintained under
AS 10.50.860
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-180">
            <num>10.50.180</num>
            <heading>Rights of assignor when assignee becomes a member.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.180.   Rights of assignor when assignee becomes a member.
Unless otherwise provided in an operating agreement of the company, when an assignee of a member's limited liability company interest becomes a member of the company with respect to the assignor's entire interest, the assignor ceases to be a member or to have the power to exercise the rights of a member.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-185">
            <num>10.50.185</num>
            <heading>Resignation of member.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-185__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A member may not resign from a limited liability company except at the time or upon the happening of events specified in the operating agreement of the company and in accordance with the operating agreement of the company.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-185__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding anything to the contrary under applicable law, unless an operating agreement of the company provides otherwise, a member may not resign from a limited liability company before the dissolution and winding up of the limited liability company.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-185__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the resignation of a member violates an operating agreement of the company, in addition to any remedy otherwise available under applicable law, a limited liability company may recover from the resigning member damages for breach of the operating agreement and may offset the damages against the amount otherwise distributable to the resigning member.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-185__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless otherwise provided in an operating agreement of the company and except for termination under
AS 10.50.205
, after a member resigns from a limited liability company, the rights of the former member are those of an assignee.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-205">
            <num>10.50.205</num>
            <heading>Removal of member.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-205__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person's membership in a limited liability company may not be terminated by removal except as provided by (b) or (c) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-205__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (c) of this section, a person's membership in a limited liability company terminates if the person assigns all of the person's interest in the company and if a majority of the members who have not assigned their interests in the company authorize the removal of the person as a member.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-205__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If an operating agreement of the company provides for the removal of a member with or without cause, a person's membership in a limited liability company terminates if the person is removed as a member in the manner and under the circumstances provided in the agreement.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-210">
            <num>10.50.210</num>
            <heading>Effect of death or incompetency on membership.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.210.   Effect of death or incompetency on membership.
Unless otherwise provided in an operating agreement or by the written consent of all of the members at the time, the membership of a member of a limited liability company who is an individual terminates if the member dies, or if a court of competent jurisdiction enters an order adjudicating the member incompetent to manage the member's person or property.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-215">
            <num>10.50.215</num>
            <heading>Termination of membership held by trust, trustee, or estate.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-215__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless otherwise provided in an operating agreement of the company or by the written consent of all of the members of the company at the time, the limited liability company membership held by a trust or trustee terminates when the trust terminates. In this subsection, terminates does not include the substitution of a new trustee.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-215__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless otherwise provided in an operating agreement of the company or by the written consent of all of the members of the company at the time, the limited liability company membership held by an estate terminates when the estate's entire limited liability company interest is distributed by the fiduciary of the estate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-220">
            <num>10.50.220</num>
            <heading>Termination on dissolution of member.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-220__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless otherwise provided in an operating agreement of the company or by the written consent of all of the members of the company at the time, a limited liability company membership of a member that is a separate limited liability company terminates when the member dissolves and begins to wind up its affairs.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-220__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless otherwise provided in an operating agreement of the company or by the written consent of all of the members of the company at the time, a limited liability company membership of a member that is a corporation terminates when the corporation is dissolved and 90 days lapse without reinstatement.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-225">
            <num>10.50.225</num>
            <heading>Other events terminating membership.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-225__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless otherwise provided in writing in an operating agreement of the company or authorized by the written consent of all of the members of the company at the time, a person's membership in a limited liability company terminates when the person</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-225__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>makes an assignment for the benefit of creditors;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-225__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>files a voluntary petition in bankruptcy;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-225__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is adjudicated a bankrupt or insolvent;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-225__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>files a petition or answer seeking for the person a reorganization, arrangement, composition, readjustment, liquidation, dissolution, or similar relief under law;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-225__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>files an answer or other pleading admitting or failing to contest the material allegations of a petition filed against the member in a proceeding in the nature of (1)  (4) of this subsection; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-225__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>seeks, consents to, or acquiesces in the appointment of a trustee, receiver, or liquidator of the person or of all or a substantial part of the person's property.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-225__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless otherwise provided in writing in an operating agreement of the company or consented to in writing by all of the members of the company at the time, a person's membership in a limited liability company terminates when</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-225__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a proceeding against the person seeking reorganization, arrangement, composition, readjustment, liquidation, dissolution, or similar relief is not dismissed within 120 days after the commencement of the proceeding; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-225__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an appointment, without the person's consent, of a trustee, receiver, or liquidator of the person or of all or a substantial part of the person's property is not vacated or stayed within 120 days after the appointment or after the expiration of the stay.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-225__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The members of a limited liability company may provide in writing in an operating agreement that other events terminate a membership.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-250">
            <num>10.50.250</num>
            <heading>Agency power of members and managers.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-250__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (b) and (c) of this section, a member of a limited liability company is an agent of the company for the purpose of conducting the company's affairs. A member's act, including the execution of an instrument in the name of the company, that appears to be performed in the usual and customary way of conducting business, binds the company, unless the member does not in fact have the authority to act for the company in the particular matter and the person with whom the member is dealing knows that the member does not have the authority to act for the company in the particular matter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-250__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a limited liability company is managed by a manager, a member is not, solely by reason of being a member, an agent of the company.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-250__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a limited liability company is managed by a manager, a manager is an agent of a limited liability company for the purpose of conducting its affairs, and a manager's act, including the execution of an instrument in the name of the company, that appears to be performed in the usual and customary way of conducting business binds the company, unless the manager does not in fact have the authority to act for the company in the particular matter and the person with whom the manager is dealing knows that the manager does not have the authority to act for the company in the particular matter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-250__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A limited liability company manager's or member's act that does not appear to be performed in the usual and customary way of conducting business does not bind the company, unless the act is authorized by an operating agreement of the company when the act is performed or at another time.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-250__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A limited liability company manager's or member's act that contravenes a restriction on the manager's or member's authority does not bind the company with regard to persons who know about the restriction.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-255">
            <num>10.50.255</num>
            <heading>Admissions and representations by members and managers.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-255__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (b) of this section, an admission or representation made by a member of a limited liability company about the affairs of the company is evidence against the company if the admission or representation is within the scope of the member's authority under this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-255__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a limited liability company is managed by a manager, an admission or representation made by a</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-255__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>manager about the affairs of the company is evidence against the company if the admission or representation is within the scope of the manager's authority under this chapter; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-255__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>member, acting solely in the capacity of a member, is not evidence against the company.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-260">
            <num>10.50.260</num>
            <heading>Limited liability company charged with knowledge of or notice to member or manager.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-260__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (b) and (c) of this section, and except for a fraud on the company committed by or with the consent of the member who has the knowledge or receives the notice, the following operate as notice to or knowledge of a limited liability company:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-260__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>notice given to a company member of a matter relating to the affairs of the company;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-260__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the knowledge of a company member acting in the particular matter, whether acquired while a member or known at the time of becoming a member; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-260__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the knowledge of a company member who reasonably could and should have communicated the knowledge to a member acting in the particular matter.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-260__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the company is managed by a manager, the following operate as notice to or knowledge of a limited liability company, except for a fraud on the company committed by or with the consent of the manager who has the knowledge or receives the notice:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-260__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>notice given to a manager of a matter relating to the affairs of the limited liability company;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-260__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the knowledge of the manager acting in the particular matter, acquired while a manager or known at the time of becoming a manager; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-260__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the knowledge of a company manager who reasonably could and should have communicated the knowledge to the manager acting in the particular matter.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-260__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the company is managed by a manager, notice to, or the knowledge of, a member of a limited liability company while the member is acting solely in the capacity of a member does not operate as notice to or knowledge of the company.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-265">
            <num>10.50.265</num>
            <heading>Liability of members to third parties.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.265.   Liability of members to third parties.
A person who is a member of a limited liability company or a foreign limited liability company is not liable, solely by reason of being a member, under a judgment, decree, or order of a court, or in another manner, for a liability of the company to a third party, whether the liability arises in contract, tort, or another form, or for the acts or omissions of another member, manager, agent, or employee of the company to a third party.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-275">
            <num>10.50.275</num>
            <heading>Consideration for company interests.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.275.   Consideration for company interests.
An interest in a limited liability company may be issued for property or services rendered. A member who has contributed property or services rendered may also contribute a promissory note or other obligation to contribute property or services.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-280">
            <num>10.50.280</num>
            <heading>Liability for contributions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-280__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding
AS 09.25.010
 09.25.020, a promise by a member of a limited liability company to contribute property or services to the company is not enforceable unless the promise is stated in a writing signed by the member.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-280__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless otherwise provided in an operating agreement of the company, a member of a limited liability company is liable for performing an enforceable promise made to the company to contribute property or services, even if the member is unable to perform because of death, disability, or another reason.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-280__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a member of a limited liability company does not make the member's required contribution of property or services, the member shall, at the option of the company, contribute cash equal to that portion of value of the required contribution that has not been made.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-280__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless otherwise provided in an operating agreement of the company, an assignor of a limited liability company interest is not released from the assignor's liability to the company under this section, even if the assignee becomes a member with respect to the assigned interest.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-285">
            <num>10.50.285</num>
            <heading>Compromise of contribution obligation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.285.   Compromise of contribution obligation.
Unless otherwise provided in an operating agreement of the company, the obligation of a member to make a contribution to a limited liability company may not be compromised, unless all of the other members consent to the compromise.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-290">
            <num>10.50.290</num>
            <heading>Repayment of contribution and sharing of profits and other assets.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.290.   Repayment of contribution and sharing of profits and other assets.
Subject to
AS 10.50.305
 10.50.320, and unless otherwise provided in an operating agreement of the company, a member of a limited liability company shall be repaid the member's contribution to capital and shares equally in the profits and other assets of the company remaining after all liabilities, including liabilities to members, are satisfied.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-295">
            <num>10.50.295</num>
            <heading>Interim distributions under operating agreement.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.295.   Interim distributions under operating agreement.
Subject to
AS 10.50.305
 10.50.320, if a limited liability company makes an interim distribution of its assets to its members, the company shall make the distribution to the members in the manner provided in an operating agreement of the company. The operating agreement of the company may authorize different interim distributions for different classes of members.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-300">
            <num>10.50.300</num>
            <heading>Interim distributions without operating agreement.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.300.   Interim distributions without operating agreement.
Subject to
AS 10.50.305
 10.50.320, if an operating agreement of the company does not provide for the interim distribution of the assets of the company, when a limited liability company makes an interim distribution of its assets, the interim distributions to each member of the company shall be equal.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-305">
            <num>10.50.305</num>
            <heading>Restrictions on distributions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-305__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A distribution may not be made by a limited liability company if, after giving effect to the distribution,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-305__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the company would not be able to pay its debts as they become due in the usual course of conducting its affairs; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-305__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the limited liability company's assets would be less than the sum of its liabilities plus, unless otherwise provided in an operating agreement, the amount that would be needed, if the limited liability company were to be dissolved at the time of the distribution, to satisfy the preferential rights of other members upon dissolution that are superior to the rights of the member receiving the distribution.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-305__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A limited liability company may base a determination that a distribution is not prohibited under (a) of this section on</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-305__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>financial statements prepared on the basis of accounting practices and principles that are reasonable under the circumstances; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-305__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a fair valuation or other method that is reasonable under the circumstances.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-305__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (e) of this section, the effect of a distribution in accordance with (a) of this section is measured as of the date</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-305__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the distribution is authorized if the payment occurs within 120 days after the date of authorization; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-305__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>payment is made if the payment occurs more than 120 days after the date of authorization.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-305__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the terms of an indebtedness provide that payment of principal and interest is to be made only if and to the extent that payment of a distribution to members could then be made under this section, indebtedness of a limited liability company, including indebtedness issued as a distribution, is not a liability for purposes of determinations made under (b) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-305__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If indebtedness is issued as a distribution, each payment of principal or interest on the indebtedness is treated as a distribution, and the effect of the distribution is measured on the date the payment is actually made.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-315">
            <num>10.50.315</num>
            <heading>Additional restrictions in articles or agreement.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.315.   Additional restrictions in articles or agreement.
Nothing in this chapter prohibits additional restrictions upon the purchase or redemption of a company's own limited liability company interests by provision in the articles of organization or operating agreement of the limited liability company or in another agreement entered into by the company.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-320">
            <num>10.50.320</num>
            <heading>Liability of members receiving prohibited distributions; suit against members.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-320__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A member of a limited liability company who receives a distribution prohibited by this chapter with knowledge of facts indicating the impropriety of the distribution is liable to the company for the benefit of all of the creditors or members entitled to institute an action under (b) of this section for the amount received by the member with interest at the legal rate on judgments until paid. The liability of the member under this subsection may not exceed the liabilities of the company owed to nonconsenting creditors at the time of the violation and the injury suffered by nonconsenting members.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-320__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Suit may be brought in the name of the company to enforce the liability to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-320__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>creditors arising under (a) of this section for a violation of
AS 10.50.305
against any or all members liable by any one or more creditors of the company whose debts or claims arose before the time of the distribution to members and who have not consented to the distribution, whether or not they have reduced their claims to judgment; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-320__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>members arising under (a) of this section for a violation of
AS 10.50.305
against any or all members liable by any one or more members holding preferred limited liability company interests outstanding at the time of the distribution who have not consented to the distribution, without regard to the provisions of
AS 10.50.735
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-320__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A member sued under this section may compel contribution from all other members liable under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-320__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This section does not affect the liability that a member may have under other applicable law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-330">
            <num>10.50.330</num>
            <heading>Time for interim distributions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.330.   Time for interim distributions.
A member of a limited liability company is entitled to receive interim distributions under
AS 10.50.295
 10.50.300 at the times or upon the happening of the events specified in an operating agreement of the company, or at the times determined by the members or managers under
AS 10.50.150
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-340">
            <num>10.50.340</num>
            <heading>Distribution in kind.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-340__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless otherwise provided in an operating agreement of the company, a member, regardless of the nature of the member's contribution, may not demand and receive a distribution from a limited liability company in a form other than cash.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-340__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless otherwise provided in an operating agreement of the company, a limited liability company may not compel a member of the company to accept from the company a distribution of a company asset in a form other than cash to the extent that the percentage of the asset distributed to the member exceeds the percentage that the member would have shared in a cash distribution equal to the value of the asset at the time of distribution.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-345">
            <num>10.50.345</num>
            <heading>Right to distribution.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.345.   Right to distribution.
When a member of a limited liability company is entitled to receive a distribution from the company, the member is a creditor of the company with respect to the distribution, and is entitled to all remedies available to a creditor of the company.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-348">
            <num>10.50.348</num>
            <heading>Inapplicability to winding up and dissolution.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.348.   Inapplicability to winding up and dissolution.
AS 10.50.290
 10.50.340 do not apply in a proceeding for winding up and dissolution of a limited liability company.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-350">
            <num>10.50.350</num>
            <heading>Ownership of company property.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-350__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Property transferred to or otherwise acquired by a limited liability company is the property of the company and is not the property of the members individually.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-350__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A limited liability company shall acquire, hold, and convey property, including real property, in the name of the company. If a limited liability company acquires an interest in property, the company holds the title to the interest and not the members individually.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-355">
            <num>10.50.355</num>
            <heading>Transfer of property.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-355__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (b) of this section, a limited liability company may transfer the property of the company if the company uses an instrument of transfer signed by a member of the company in the name of the company.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-355__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the company is managed by a manager,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-355__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>title to limited liability company property may be transferred by an instrument of transfer signed by a manager of the company in the name of the company; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-355__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a member, solely by reason of being a member, does not have the authority to transfer the property of the company.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-360">
            <num>10.50.360</num>
            <heading>Recovery of property.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.360.   Recovery of property.
A limited liability company may recover property transferred under
AS 10.50.355
if the company proves that the execution of the instrument of transfer did not bind the company under
AS 10.50.250
, unless the property has been transferred by the initial transferee, or by a person claiming through the initial transferee, to a subsequent transferee who gives value without having notice that the person who signed the instrument of initial transfer lacked authority to bind the company.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-370">
            <num>10.50.370</num>
            <heading>Nature of interest in company.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.370.   Nature of interest in company.
A limited liability company interest is personal property.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-375">
            <num>10.50.375</num>
            <heading>Assignment of interest in company.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-375__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may assign a limited liability company interest in whole or in part.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-375__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The assignment of a limited liability company interest entitles the assignee to receive, to the extent assigned, only the distributions to which the assignor is entitled.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-375__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The assignment of a limited liability company interest does not dissolve the company or entitle the assignee to participate in the management and affairs of the company, to become a member, or to exercise the rights of a member. Unless the assignee of the interest becomes a member with respect to the interest, the assignor continues to be a member and may exercise the rights of a member, subject to the members' right to remove the assignor under
AS 10.50.205
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-375__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless the assignee becomes a member, an assignee of a limited liability company interest is not liable as a member solely as a result of the assignment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-375__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The assignor of a limited liability company interest is not released, solely as a result of the assignment, from the assignor's liability as a member.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-375__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An operating agreement may establish terms different from those in (a)  (e) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-375__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless otherwise provided in an operating agreement of the company, the pledge of, or granting of a security interest, lien, or other encumbrance in or against, a part or all of a member's limited liability company interest is not an assignment under this section and does not terminate the membership or the rights and powers of the member.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-380">
            <num>10.50.380</num>
            <heading>Rights of judgment creditors.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-380__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a judgment creditor of a limited liability company member applies to a court of competent jurisdiction, the court may charge the member's limited liability company interest for payment of the unsatisfied amount of the judgment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-380__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To the extent a limited liability company interest is charged under (a) of this section, the judgment creditor has only the rights of an assignee of the member's interest.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-380__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This section provides the exclusive remedy that a judgment creditor of a member or a member's assignee may use to satisfy a judgment out of the judgment debtor's interest in the limited liability company. Other legal or equitable remedies, including foreclosure on the member's limited liability company interest and a court order for directions, accounts, and inquiries that the debtor member might have made, are not available to the judgment creditor attempting to satisfy a judgment out of the judgment debtor's interest in the limited liability company and may not be ordered by a court.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-380__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This section does not deprive a member of the benefit of an exemption applicable to the member's membership interest.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-380__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This section applies to limited liability companies with only one member as well as to limited liability companies with more than one member.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-385">
            <num>10.50.385</num>
            <heading>Rights of estate or legal representative of deceased or incompetent member.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.385.   Rights of estate or legal representative of deceased or incompetent member.
If a member who is an individual dies or if a court of competent jurisdiction determines the member to be incompetent to manage the member's person or property, the member's executor, administrator, guardian, conservator, or other legal representative has the rights of an assignee of the member's interest, if the member's interest has not been terminated.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-390">
            <num>10.50.390</num>
            <heading>Rights of dissolved or terminated entity.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.390.   Rights of dissolved or terminated entity.
If a member who is not an individual terminates or is dissolved, the member's legal representative or successor has the rights of an assignee of the member's interest.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-400">
            <num>10.50.400</num>
            <heading>Dissolution.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.400.   Dissolution.
A limited liability company is dissolved and its affairs shall be wound up when the first of the following occurs:
(1) at the time or on the happening of events specified for dissolution in an operating agreement of the company;
(2) all of the members of the company consent in writing; or
(3) the superior court enters a decree for judicial dissolution of the company under
AS 10.50.405
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-405">
            <num>10.50.405</num>
            <heading>Dissolution by court.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.405.   Dissolution by court.
On application by or for a member of a limited liability company, the superior court may order the company dissolved if the court determines that it is impossible for the company to carry on the purposes of the company.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-408">
            <num>10.50.408</num>
            <heading>Involuntary dissolution by commissioner.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-408__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A limited liability company may be dissolved involuntarily by the commissioner if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-408__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the company is delinquent six months in filing its biennial report or in paying a fee or a penalty;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-408__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the company has failed for 30 days to appoint and maintain a registered agent in the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-408__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the company has failed for 30 days after change of its registered office or registered agent to file in the office of the commissioner a statement of the change; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-408__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a misrepresentation of material facts has been made in the application, report, affidavit, or other document submitted under this chapter.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-408__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A limited liability company may not be dissolved under this section unless the commissioner has given the company written notice of its delinquency, failure, or misrepresentation by mail as provided by (f) of this section. If the company fails, within 60 days after the notice is sent by mail as required under this subsection, to contest the alleged delinquency, failure, or misrepresentation, it may be dissolved under (d) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-408__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If, following a hearing, the commissioner determines the presence of the delinquency, failure, or misrepresentation providing grounds for involuntary dissolution under this section, the company may appeal to the superior court. The court shall either sustain the commissioner or direct the commissioner to take action the court considers proper.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-408__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a limited liability company has given cause for involuntary dissolution and has failed to correct the neglect, omission, delinquency, or noncompliance as provided in this section, and there has not been a controlling order of the superior court, the commissioner shall dissolve the company by issuing a certificate of involuntary dissolution containing a statement that the company has been dissolved, the date, and the reason for which it was dissolved. The original certificate of dissolution shall be placed in the department files and a copy of it mailed to the company as provided by (f) of this section. Upon the issuance of the certificate of involuntary dissolution, the existence of the company ceases, except as otherwise provided in this chapter, and its name shall be available to use and may be adopted by another company on a date that is six months or later after the dissolution.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-408__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A company dissolved under this section may be reinstated within two years from the date of the certificate of involuntary dissolution if it is established to the satisfaction of the commissioner that in fact there was no cause for the dissolution, or if the delinquency, failure, or misrepresentation resulting in dissolution has been corrected and payment made of double the amount delinquent along with the amount the company would have paid had it not been dissolved during the two-year period. Reinstatement may not be authorized if the name of the company is not distinguishable upon the records of the department under
AS 10.50.025
unless the company being reinstated amends its articles of organization to change its name to conform with the provisions of this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-408__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the mailing of an item is required by (b) or (d) of this section, the commissioner shall first mail the item by certified mail to the registered office of the limited liability company at the last known address of the registered office shown on the records of the commissioner. If the item mailed to the registered office is returned to the department, the commissioner shall mail the item by first class mail to the registered agent of the limited liability company at the last known address of the registered agent shown on the records of the commissioner. If the item mailed to the registered agent is returned to the department, the commissioner shall mail the item by first class mail to the manager or the managing member of the limited liability company at the last known address for the manager or the managing member shown on the records of the commissioner. If the name and address of the manager or managing members are not shown on the records of the commissioner, the commissioner is not required to mail the notice to the manager or managing member. If the item mailed to the manager or managing member is returned to the department, the commissioner is not required to mail the item again. If the address shown on the records of the commissioner for a mailing after the initial certified mailing is not different from the address for the previous mailing, the commissioner is not required to mail the item to the same address, but shall mail the item to the next required addressee whose address is different from the address for the returned mailing, and, if none of the mailings required after a returned mailing has an address that is different from the address for the returned mailing, the commissioner is not required to mail the item again. In this subsection, item means the notice required under (b) of this section or the certificate of involuntary dissolution issued under (d) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-410">
            <num>10.50.410</num>
            <heading>Authority to wind up.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.410.   Authority to wind up.
Unless otherwise provided in an operating agreement, the affairs of a limited liability company may be wound up by the
(1) members or managers who have authority under
AS 10.50.110
to manage the company before dissolution; or
(2) superior court on the application of a member of the company or the member's legal representative or assignee if
(A) a member or manager identified in (1) of this subsection has engaged in wrongful conduct; or
(B) other cause is shown.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-415">
            <num>10.50.415</num>
            <heading>Acts of winding up.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.415.   Acts of winding up.
Unless otherwise provided in an operating agreement of the company, a person winding up the affairs of a limited liability company may, in the name of, and for and on behalf of, the company,
(1) prosecute and defend court actions;
(2) settle and close the affairs of the company;
(3) dispose of and transfer the property of the company;
(4) discharge the liabilities of the company; and
(5) distribute to the members the assets of the company.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-420">
            <num>10.50.420</num>
            <heading>Agency power of manager or member after dissolution.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-420__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (b)  (d) of this section, after dissolution of a limited liability company, a member having authority to wind up the company's affairs can bind the company by an act that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-420__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is appropriate for winding up the company's affairs or completing transactions unfinished at dissolution; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-420__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>would have bound the company if the company had not been dissolved, if the other party to the transaction does not have notice of the dissolution; in this paragraph, filing the articles of dissolution is presumed to constitute notice of the dissolution.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-420__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A member's act that is not binding on the limited liability company under (a) of this section binds the company if the act is otherwise authorized by the company.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-420__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A member's act that violates a restriction on the member's authority does not bind the member's limited liability company with regard to a person who knows about the restriction, even if the member's act would otherwise be binding under (a) of this section or is otherwise authorized.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-420__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the company is managed by a manager, a member does not have the authority to bind the company if the member is acting solely in the capacity of a member, and a manager of the company can bind the company by an act that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-420__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is appropriate for winding up the company's affairs or completing transactions unfinished at dissolution; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-420__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>would have bound the company if the company had not been dissolved if the other party to the transaction does not have notice of the dissolution; in this paragraph, filing the articles of dissolution is presumed to constitute notice of the dissolution.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-425">
            <num>10.50.425</num>
            <heading>Distribution of assets.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.425.   Distribution of assets.
Upon the winding up of a limited liability company, the assets of the company shall be distributed in the following manner and order of priority:
(1) payment, or adequate provision for payment, to creditors, including, to the extent permitted by law, members who are creditors and not covered by (2) of this section, in satisfaction of the liabilities of the company;
(2) unless otherwise provided in an operating agreement of the company, payment to members or former members in satisfaction of the company's liabilities for distributions under
AS 10.50.295
 10.50.330;
(3) unless otherwise provided in an operating agreement of the company, to members and former members in the following order of priority:
(A) for the return of their contributions; and
(B) in proportion to the members' respective rights to share in distributions from the company before dissolution.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-430">
            <num>10.50.430</num>
            <heading>Articles of dissolution.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.430.   Articles of dissolution.
After the dissolution of a limited liability company under
AS 10.50.400
, the limited liability company may file articles of dissolution with the department. The articles must state
(1) the name of the company;
(2) the date of filing of the company's articles of organization and of any amendments to the articles of organization;
(3) the reason for filing the articles of dissolution;
(4) the effective date, which must be a specific date, of the articles of dissolution if the articles of dissolution are not to be effective when filed; and
(5) other information determined appropriate by the members or managers filing the articles.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-435">
            <num>10.50.435</num>
            <heading>Known claims against dissolved limited liability company.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-435__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon dissolution, a limited liability company may dispose of the known claims against it by filing articles of dissolution under
AS 10.50.430
and following the procedures described in this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-435__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A dissolved limited liability company shall notify its known claimants in writing of the dissolution at any time after the effective date of dissolution. The written notice must</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-435__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>describe the information that must be included in the claim;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-435__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide a mailing address where the claim may be sent;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-435__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>state the deadline, which may not be fewer than 120 days after the later of the date of the written notice or the filing of articles of dissolution under
AS 10.50.430
, for the company to receive the claim; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-435__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>state that the claim is barred if it is not received by the company by the deadline.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-435__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A claim against a limited liability company is barred if a claimant</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-435__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>who was given written notice under (b) of this section does not deliver the claim to the company by the deadline; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-435__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>whose claim is rejected by the company does not begin a proceeding to enforce the claim within 90 days after the date of the rejection notice.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-435__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, claim does not include a contingent liability or a claim based on an event occurring after the effective date of dissolution.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-440">
            <num>10.50.440</num>
            <heading>Unknown claims against dissolved limited liability company.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-440__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a limited liability company publishes a newspaper notice in accordance with (b) of this section and files articles of dissolution under
AS 10.50.430
, the following claims are barred unless the claimant commences a proceeding to enforce the claim against the company within three years after the later of the publication date of the newspaper notice or the filing of the articles of dissolution:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-440__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a claim by a claimant who did not receive written notice under
AS 10.50.435
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-440__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a claim sent within the time allowed if the company does not act on the claim;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-440__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a claim that is contingent or based on an event occurring after the effective date of dissolution.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-440__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The notice published under (a) of this section shall be published once in a newspaper of general circulation in the judicial district where the company's principal office, or its registered office if it does not have a principal office in this state, is located in this state, and must</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-440__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>describe the information that must be included in a claim;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-440__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide a mailing address where the claim may be sent;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-440__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>state that a claim against the company is barred unless a proceeding to enforce the claim is begun within three years after the publication of the notice; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-440__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>request that persons with claims against the company present them in writing to the company as provided in the notice.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-440__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A claim may be enforced under this section</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-440__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>against the company to the extent of the company's undistributed assets; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-440__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if the company's assets have been distributed in liquidation, against a member of the company to the extent of the member's pro rata share of the claim or of the assets of the company distributed to the member in liquidation, whichever is less; a member's total liability for all claims under this section may not exceed the total amount of assets of the company that are distributed to the member.
Article 12. Merger, Consolidation, and Conversion.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-500">
            <num>10.50.500</num>
            <heading>Authority for merger or consolidation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.500.   Authority for merger or consolidation.
Unless otherwise provided in an operating agreement of the company, and subject to the law applicable to the other limited liability company, a limited liability company may merge or consolidate with or into a limited liability company or a foreign limited liability company.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-510">
            <num>10.50.510</num>
            <heading>Approval or abandonment of merger or consolidation.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-510__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless otherwise provided in an operating agreement of the company, a limited liability company may not approve a proposed merger or consolidation unless the merger or consolidation is approved by all of the members of the company.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-510__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A foreign limited liability company that is a party to a proposed merger or consolidation may not approve the merger or consolidation unless the merger or consolidation is approved in the manner and by the vote required by the law applicable to the foreign limited liability company.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-510__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A party to a merger or consolidation under this chapter may abandon the merger or consolidation as provided in the merger or consolidation agreement.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-515">
            <num>10.50.515</num>
            <heading>Filing of articles of merger or consolidation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.515.   Filing of articles of merger or consolidation.
The limited liability company that survives or results from a merger or consolidation under this chapter shall file with the department articles of merger or consolidation signed by each limited liability company that is a party to the merger or consolidation.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-520">
            <num>10.50.520</num>
            <heading>Contents of articles of merger or consolidation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.520.   Contents of articles of merger or consolidation.
The articles of merger or consolidation required by
AS 10.50.515
must state
(1) the name of each limited liability company that is a party to the merger or consolidation;
(2) the jurisdiction where each limited liability company that is a party to the merger or consolidation was organized;
(3) that an agreement of merger or consolidation has been approved and signed by each limited liability company that is a party to the merger or consolidation;
(4) the name of the surviving or resulting limited liability company;
(5) the future effective date, which must be a specific date, of the merger or consolidation if the merger or consolidation is not effective when the articles are filed;
(6) that the agreement of merger or consolidation is on file at an office of the surviving or resulting limited liability company and the address of the office;
(7) that a copy of the agreement of merger or consolidation will be furnished by the surviving or resulting limited liability company on request and without cost to a person holding an interest in a limited liability company that is a party to the merger or consolidation;
(8) if the surviving or resulting limited liability company is not organized under the laws of this state, a statement that the surviving or resulting limited liability company
(A) agrees that it may be served with process in this state in a proceeding to enforce an obligation of a company that is a party to the merger or consolidation and that was organized under the laws of this state, and to enforce an obligation of the surviving or resulting company;
(B) appoints the department as its agent for service of process in an enforcement proceeding under (A) of this paragraph; and
(C) the address to which a copy of the process may be mailed to the surviving or resulting company by the department.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-525">
            <num>10.50.525</num>
            <heading>Execution of articles of merger or consolidation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.525.   Execution of articles of merger or consolidation.
Articles of merger or consolidation shall be signed by a limited liability company that is a party to the merger or consolidation.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-530">
            <num>10.50.530</num>
            <heading>Equivalent to articles of dissolution.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.530.   Equivalent to articles of dissolution.
Articles of merger or consolidation constitute articles of dissolution for a limited liability company that is not the surviving or resulting limited liability company in the merger or consolidation.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-535">
            <num>10.50.535</num>
            <heading>Effective date of merger or consolidation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.535.   Effective date of merger or consolidation.
A merger or consolidation under
AS 10.50.500
 10.50.565 takes effect upon the later of the effective date of the filing of the articles of merger or consolidation or an effective date stated in the articles of merger or consolidation.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-540">
            <num>10.50.540</num>
            <heading>Use of merger or consolidation agreement to amend or adopt operating agreement.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-540__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An agreement of merger or consolidation approved under
AS 10.50.510
may amend an operating agreement of a limited liability company or adopt a new operating agreement for the company if the company is the surviving or resulting limited liability company in the merger or consolidation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-540__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An approved agreement of merger or consolidation may provide that the operating agreement of a limited liability company that is a party to the merger or consolidation, including a limited liability company organized for the purpose of consummating a merger or consolidation, is the operating agreement of a limited liability company that is the surviving or resulting limited liability company.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-540__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An amendment to an operating agreement or the adoption of a new operating agreement under this section is effective when the merger or consolidation is effective.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-540__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This subsection is not intended to limit the accomplishment of a merger or of a matter referred to in this section by other means provided for in an operating agreement or in another agreement or as otherwise permitted by law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-545">
            <num>10.50.545</num>
            <heading>General effects of merger or consolidation.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-545__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When a merger or consolidation becomes effective, the limited liability companies that are parties to a merger or consolidation agreement become a single limited liability company that, in the case of a merger, is the limited liability company named in the plan of merger as the surviving limited liability company, and, in the case of a consolidation, is the limited liability company named in the plan of consolidation as the resulting limited liability company.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-545__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When a merger or consolidation becomes effective, a limited liability company that is a party to the merger or consolidation agreement and that is not the surviving or resulting limited liability company ceases to exist.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-545__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The surviving limited liability company of a merger or the limited liability company resulting from a consolidation possesses all the rights, privileges, immunities, and powers of each limited liability company that is a party to the merger or consolidation agreement and is subject to all the restrictions, disabilities, and duties of each limited liability company that is a party to the merger or consolidation to the extent the rights, privileges, immunities, powers, franchises, restrictions, disabilities, and duties apply to the type of limited liability company that is the surviving limited liability company or the resulting limited liability company.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-550">
            <num>10.50.550</num>
            <heading>Effect of merger or consolidation on property of companies.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.550.   Effect of merger or consolidation on property of companies.
The real and personal property, the debts due, including promises to make capital contributions, other choses in action, and the other interests of the limited liability companies that are parties to a merger or consolidation belong to the surviving or resulting limited liability company without further action by the companies.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-555">
            <num>10.50.555</num>
            <heading>Effect of merger or consolidation on liabilities and proceedings.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-555__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The surviving or resulting limited liability company in a merger or consolidation is liable for the liabilities of the limited liability companies that are parties to the merger or consolidation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-555__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A claim, action, or other proceeding that exists at the time of the merger or consolidation and that is pending by or against a limited liability company that is a party to a merger or consolidation may be pursued as if the merger or consolidation had not taken place, or the surviving or resulting limited liability company may be substituted in the claim, action, or other proceeding.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-560">
            <num>10.50.560</num>
            <heading>Rights of creditors and liens.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.560.   Rights of creditors and liens.
The rights of creditors and liens on the property of a limited liability company that is a party to a merger or consolidation are not impaired by the merger or consolidation.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-565">
            <num>10.50.565</num>
            <heading>Conversion or exchange of interests at merger or consolidation.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-565__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon a merger or consolidation, the limited liability company interests that are to be converted or exchanged into interests, cash, obligations, or other property under the terms of a merger or consolidation agreement are converted as provided by the merger or consolidation agreement.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-565__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon a merger or consolidation, the former holders of interests converted under (a) of this section have the rights provided in the merger or consolidation agreement or otherwise provided by law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-580">
            <num>10.50.580</num>
            <heading>Other transactions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.580.   Other transactions.
Under
AS 10.55
(Alaska Entity Transactions Act), a limited liability company may enter into mergers, interest exchanges, conversions, and domestications that are not covered by
AS 10.50.500
 10.50.565.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-590">
            <num>10.50.590</num>
            <heading>Definition.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.590.   Definition.
In
AS 10.50.500
 10.50.590, limited liability company means a limited liability company organized under this chapter or a foreign limited liability company.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-600">
            <num>10.50.600</num>
            <heading>Governing law.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-600__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subject to the constitution of this state, the law of the state or other jurisdiction under which a foreign limited liability company is organized governs the organization and internal affairs of the company.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-600__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may not deny registration to a foreign limited liability company because of differences between the law of this state and the law of the state or other jurisdiction under which the foreign limited liability company is organized.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-605">
            <num>10.50.605</num>
            <heading>Registration required.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.605.   Registration required.
Before conducting affairs in this state, a foreign limited liability company shall register with the department. To register, the company shall deliver to the department an application for registration as a foreign limited liability company.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-610">
            <num>10.50.610</num>
            <heading>Execution of registration application.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.610.   Execution of registration application.
An application for registration filed by a foreign limited liability company under
AS 10.50.605
shall be signed by a person who is authorized by the law of the state or other jurisdiction where the company was organized to sign the application.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-615">
            <num>10.50.615</num>
            <heading>Contents of registration application.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-615__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An application for the registration of a foreign limited liability company must state</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-615__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name of the foreign limited liability company and, if different, the name the company proposes to use in this state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-615__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the state or other jurisdiction where the company was organized, and date of its organization;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-615__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name and address of the company's registered agent;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-615__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>that the department is appointed the agent of the company for service of process if the foreign limited liability company fails to appoint or maintain a registered agent under
AS 10.50.635
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-615__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the address of the office required by the state or other jurisdiction of the company's organization to be maintained in that state or other jurisdiction, or, if the state or other jurisdiction does not require an office to be maintained in that state or other jurisdiction, the principal office of the company;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-615__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the purpose the company proposes to pursue in the conduct of its affairs in this state and the codes from the identification code established under
AS 10.06.870
that most closely describe the activities in which the company will engage in this state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-615__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the names and addresses of the managers of the company, or, if the company is not managed by a manager, the names and addresses of the members of the company;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-615__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name and address of each person owning at least a five percent interest in the company and the percentage of interest owned by that person in the company; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-615__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>that the company is a foreign limited liability company.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-615__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to the information required by (a) of this section, an application must include proof from the jurisdiction where the company was organized that indicates that the company was organized in that jurisdiction.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-620">
            <num>10.50.620</num>
            <heading>Name.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.620.   Name.
The department may not file the application for registration of a foreign limited liability company unless the name of the company satisfies the requirements of
AS 10.50.020
 10.50.025. If the name under which a foreign limited liability is organized in the state or other jurisdiction of its organization does not satisfy the requirements of
AS 10.50.020
 10.50.025, the company may register under
AS 10.50.605
if the company uses an assumed name that is available to the company under this chapter and that satisfies the requirements of
AS 10.50.020
 10.50.025.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-623">
            <num>10.50.623</num>
            <heading>Change of name.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.623.   Change of name.
If a foreign limited liability company that is registered under this chapter changes its name to one under which it may not register under this chapter, the registration of the company is suspended and the company may not conduct affairs in this state until it has changed its name to a name available to it under the laws of this state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-625">
            <num>10.50.625</num>
            <heading>Amendment of registration.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.625.   Amendment of registration.
A foreign limited liability company may amend its registration by filing an amendment of registration with the department that is signed by a person who has the authority to sign it under the law of the state or other jurisdiction of the company's organization.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-630">
            <num>10.50.630</num>
            <heading>Contents of amendment of registration.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-630__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The amendment of registration filed by a foreign limited liability company must state the</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-630__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>name of the company;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-630__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>date the original application for registration was filed; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-630__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>amendment.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-630__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The application for registration may be amended in any way if the application for registration as amended contains only provisions that this chapter allows to be contained in an application for registration at the time of amendment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-635">
            <num>10.50.635</num>
            <heading>Registered office and registered agent of foreign company.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.635.   Registered office and registered agent of foreign company.
A foreign limited liability company registered under this chapter shall have and continuously maintain in the state a registered
(1) office that may be, but need not be, the same as its office in this state; and
(2) agent, who may be either an individual resident in this state whose business office is identical to the registered office, a corporation organized under
AS 10.06
, or a foreign corporation authorized to transact business in this state, that has a business office identical to the registered office.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-637">
            <num>10.50.637</num>
            <heading>Change of registered office or registered agent of foreign company.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.637.   Change of registered office or registered agent of foreign company.
A foreign limited liability company registered under this chapter may change its registered office or change its registered agent, or both, upon filing with the department a signed statement setting out
(1) the name of the company;
(2) the address of its registered office;
(3) the address of the new registered office if the address of its registered office is to be changed;
(4) the name of its registered agent;
(5) the name of its new registered agent if its registered agent is to be changed;
(6) that the address of its registered office and the address of the business office of its registered agent, as changed, will be identical; and
(7) that the change is authorized by the company.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-638">
            <num>10.50.638</num>
            <heading>Filing and effective date of change.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.638.   Filing and effective date of change.
If the department finds that the statement conforms to the provisions of this chapter, the department shall file the statement, and upon the filing, the change of address of the registered office, or the appointment of a new registered agent, or both, as the case may be, becomes effective.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-640">
            <num>10.50.640</num>
            <heading>Service on foreign company.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.640.   Service on foreign company.
The registered agent appointed by a foreign limited liability company registered under this chapter shall be an agent of the company upon whom process, notice, or demand required or permitted by law to be served upon the company may be served.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-645">
            <num>10.50.645</num>
            <heading>Service on commissioner.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.645.   Service on commissioner.
When a foreign limited liability company that is registered under this chapter, or that conducts affairs in this state without being registered under this chapter, fails to appoint or maintain a registered agent in this state, when a registered agent cannot with reasonable diligence be found at the registered office, or when the registration of a foreign company is suspended or revoked, the commissioner is an agent upon whom process, notice, or demand may be served. Service is made upon the commissioner as provided in
AS 10.50.065
(b).</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-650">
            <num>10.50.650</num>
            <heading>Revocation of registration.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-650__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The registration of a foreign limited liability company authorizing the company to conduct affairs in this state may be revoked by the commissioner if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-650__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the company fails to file its biennial report within the time established by this chapter, or fails to pay fees or penalties established by this chapter when they are due and payable;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-650__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the company fails to appoint and maintain a registered agent in this state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-650__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the company fails, after change of its registered office or registered agent, to file with the commissioner a statement of the change as required by this chapter; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-650__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a misrepresentation of a material matter has been made in an application, report, affidavit, or other document submitted under this chapter.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-650__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner may not revoke the registration of a foreign limited liability company unless the</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-650__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>commissioner has given the company at least 60 days notice by certified mail addressed to its registered agent at its registered office; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-650__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>company fails before revocation to file the report, pay the fees or penalties, file the required statement of change of registered agent or registered office, or correct the misrepresentation.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-650__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon revoking a registration, the commissioner shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-650__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>issue a certificate of revocation in duplicate;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-650__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>file one of the certificates in the commissioner's office; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-650__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>mail one of the certificates of revocation to the limited liability company at its registered office.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-650__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon the issuance of the certificate of revocation, the authority of the limited liability company to conduct affairs in this state ceases.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-653">
            <num>10.50.653</num>
            <heading>Appeal from revocation of registration.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.653.   Appeal from revocation of registration.
If the commissioner revokes the registration of a foreign limited liability company to conduct affairs in this state under this chapter, the company may appeal to the superior court. The court shall either sustain the action of the commissioner or direct the commissioner to take action the court considers proper.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-655">
            <num>10.50.655</num>
            <heading>Authority to cancel registration.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.655.   Authority to cancel registration.
A foreign limited liability company registered in this state may cancel its registration by filing an application for cancellation with the department.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-660">
            <num>10.50.660</num>
            <heading>Contents of application for cancellation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.660.   Contents of application for cancellation.
An application for cancellation filed by a foreign limited liability company must state
(1) the name of the company and the state or other jurisdiction where the company was organized;
(2) that the company is not conducting affairs in this state;
(3) that the company cancels its registration in this state;
(4) that the company revokes the authority of its registered agent for service of process in this state and consents that service of process may subsequently be made on the company by service on the commissioner for a cause of action arising in this state during the time the company was registered in this state; and
(5) an address for mailing a copy of a process to the company.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-665">
            <num>10.50.665</num>
            <heading>Form, manner, and execution of application for cancellation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.665.   Form, manner, and execution of application for cancellation.
The application for cancellation must be in the form and manner designated by the department and shall be signed on behalf of the foreign limited liability company by
(1) a person with authority to sign the application under the law of the state or other jurisdiction of its organization; or
(2) if the company is controlled by a receiver, trustee, or other court-appointed fiduciary, by the receiver, trustee, or other fiduciary.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-670">
            <num>10.50.670</num>
            <heading>Effect of cancellation of registration.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.670.   Effect of cancellation of registration.
The cancellation of a registration under this chapter does not terminate the authority of the commissioner to accept service of process on the foreign limited liability company with respect to causes of action arising out of the company's conduct of affairs in this state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-675">
            <num>10.50.675</num>
            <heading>Conducting affairs without registration.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-675__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A foreign limited liability company conducting affairs in this state may not maintain an action or other proceeding in a court of this state until it has registered in this state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-675__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The failure of a foreign limited liability company to register in this state does not</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-675__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>impair the validity of a contract or act of the company;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-675__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>affect the right of another party to a contract of the company to maintain an action or proceeding on the contract; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-675__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>prevent the company from defending an action or other proceeding in a court of this state.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-690">
            <num>10.50.690</num>
            <heading>Liability for fees and penalties.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.690.   Liability for fees and penalties.
A foreign limited liability company that conducts affairs in this state without registration is liable to the department for the following fees and penalties for the full or partial years when it conducts affairs in this state without registration:
(1) the fees that would have been imposed by this chapter on the company if the company had been registered under this chapter; or
(2) the penalties imposed by this chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-700">
            <num>10.50.700</num>
            <heading>Civil penalty.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-700__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A foreign limited liability company that conducts affairs in this state without registration is subject to a civil penalty payable to the state not to exceed $10,000 for each calendar year, including a partial year, the company conducts affairs in this state without being registered under this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-700__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The civil penalty imposed in (a) of this section may be recovered in an action brought in the superior court by the attorney general.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-710">
            <num>10.50.710</num>
            <heading>Injunctive relief.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-710__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon application to the court, if a court finds that a foreign limited liability company has conducted affairs in this state in violation of this chapter, the court may issue, in addition to imposing a civil penalty, an injunction restraining the company from conducting further affairs in this state and from further exercising the company's rights and privileges in this state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-710__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An injunction issued under (a) of this section may continue until the civil penalties, interest, and court costs assessed by the court have been paid and until the foreign limited liability company otherwise complies with this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-715">
            <num>10.50.715</num>
            <heading>Nonliability of member or manager.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.715.   Nonliability of member or manager.
A member or manager of a foreign limited liability company is not liable for the debts and obligations of the company solely because the company conducts affairs in this state without registration.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-720">
            <num>10.50.720</num>
            <heading>Transactions not constituting conducting affairs.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.720.   Transactions not constituting conducting affairs.
The activities of a foreign limited liability company that are not considered to be conducting affairs in this state for the purposes of
AS 10.50.600
 10.50.720 include
(1) maintaining, defending, or settling a court action or other proceeding or a claim;
(2) holding meetings of the members or managers of the company;
(3) maintaining bank accounts;
(4) selling through independent contractors;
(5) soliciting or procuring orders by mail, through employees, agents, or otherwise, if the orders require acceptance outside the state before becoming binding contracts;
(6) creating as borrower or lender, or acquiring, indebtedness or mortgages or other security interests in real or personal property;
(7) securing or collecting debts, or enforcing rights in property securing debts;
(8) conducting an isolated transaction that is completed within 30 days and that is not part of a course of repeated transactions of a similar nature; or
(9) conducting affairs in interstate commerce.
Article 14. Court Actions By and Against Limited Liability Companies.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-730">
            <num>10.50.730</num>
            <heading>Actions against companies.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.730.   Actions against companies.
A court action may be brought by or against a limited liability company. The court action may be brought in the name of the company.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-735">
            <num>10.50.735</num>
            <heading>Authority to sue on behalf of company.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-735__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in
AS 10.50.320
, and unless otherwise provided in an operating agreement of the company, a person may not bring a court action on behalf of a limited liability company in the name of the company unless the person is authorized under (b) or (c) or this section to bring the action.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-735__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Whether or not the company is managed by a manager, a member of a limited liability company may bring a court action on behalf of the company in the name of the company if the member is authorized to bring the action by more than one-half of all of the members of the company who are eligible to consent to the authorization, unless a larger number of the members is required under
AS 10.50.150</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-735__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>for the authorization. When determining whether the required number of members consent under
AS 10.50.150
, the total number of all members does not include a member who has an interest in the outcome of the action that is adverse to the interest of the company and the member with the adverse interest is excluded from determining the authorization.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-735__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A manager of a limited liability company may bring a court action on behalf of the company in the name of the company if the manager is authorized to bring the action by the consent required under
AS 10.50.150
of the members eligible to consent to the authorization. When determining the number of managers required to consent under
AS 10.50.150
, the number does not include a manager who has an interest in the outcome of the action that is adverse to the interest of the company and the manager with the adverse interest is excluded from determining the authorization.
Article 15. Biennial Report.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-750">
            <num>10.50.750</num>
            <heading>Biennial report required.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.750.   Biennial report required.
A limited liability company and a foreign limited liability company conducting affairs in this state shall file a biennial report within the time established by this chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-755">
            <num>10.50.755</num>
            <heading>Contents of biennial report.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.755.   Contents of biennial report.
A biennial report must set out
(1) the name of the company and the state or country where it is organized;
(2) the address of the registered office of the company in this state, and the name of its registered agent in this state at that address, and, in the case of a foreign limited liability company, the address of its principal office in the state or country where it is organized;
(3) the names and addresses of the managers of the company, or, if the company is not managed by a manager, the names and addresses of the members of the company;
(4) the name and address of each person owning at least a five percent interest in the company and the percentage of interest owned by that person in the company.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-760">
            <num>10.50.760</num>
            <heading>Filing of biennial report.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-760__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A biennial report required by
AS 10.50.750
shall be filed with the department and is due before January 2 of the filing year. A limited liability company filing articles of organization and a foreign limited liability company registering during an even-numbered year shall file the biennial report each even-numbered year. A limited liability company filing articles of organization and a foreign limited liability company registering during an odd-numbered year shall file the biennial report each odd-numbered year. The biennial report is delinquent if not filed before February 1 of each odd- or even-numbered year as provided in this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-760__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Proof to the satisfaction of the department that on or before February 1 the report was deposited in the United States mail in a sealed envelope, properly addressed with postage prepaid, is compliance with (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-760__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall file the report if it conforms to the requirements of this chapter. If the department finds that the report does not conform to the requirements of this chapter, the report shall promptly be returned to the company for necessary corrections.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-760__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon receipt of a form from the department, a limited liability company shall file a biennial report within six months after original organization.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-765">
            <num>10.50.765</num>
            <heading>Filing interim notice of change of managers or managing members.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-765__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In the event of a change of the manager of a limited liability company or of a foreign limited liability company registered under this chapter, or of a member of the company, if the members manage the company, during the first year of the biennial reporting period, the company shall file a notice of change amending the biennial report of the company before the following January 2.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-765__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The notice shall be filed with the department and shall state the name and current mailing address of the manager or member not included in the company's last filed biennial report, and the name of the person replaced and the office held.
Article 16. Miscellaneous Provisions.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-800">
            <num>10.50.800</num>
            <heading>Company certificates.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.800.   Company certificates.
An operating agreement of a limited liability company may authorize the company to issue a certificate as evidence of a limited liability company interest. An operating agreement may also authorize and provide for the assignment or transfer of the interest represented by the certificate.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-810">
            <num>10.50.810</num>
            <heading>Submission of documents to department.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.810.   Submission of documents to department.
When a document is required or allowed to be delivered to or filed with the department under this chapter, the person delivering the document shall deliver to the department the required fee, the original signed document, and an exact copy of the document.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-820">
            <num>10.50.820</num>
            <heading>Filing of documents by department.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-820__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the department determines that a document filed under this chapter conforms to the filing requirements of this chapter, the department shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-820__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>mark on the original signed document and on the exact copy the word filed and the date and time of the document's acceptance for filing;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-820__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>retain the original signed document in the department's files; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-820__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>return the exact copy to the person who filed the document or to the person's representative.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-820__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may not file a document if the requirements of this section are not met.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-830">
            <num>10.50.830</num>
            <heading>Disapproval of writing by department; appeal.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.830.   Disapproval of writing by department; appeal.
If the department fails to approve articles of organization, amendment, merger, consolidation, or dissolution, or any other document required by this chapter to be approved by the department, the department shall, within 10 days after the delivery of the document to the department, give written notice of disapproval to the person, limited liability company, or foreign limited liability company, delivering the document, and specifying the reasons for disapproval. The person or company may appeal the disapproval to the superior court.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-840">
            <num>10.50.840</num>
            <heading>Execution of documents.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-840__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless otherwise provided in this chapter, a document required by this chapter to be filed with the department by or for a limited liability company shall be signed by</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-840__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a manager of the company if the company is managed by a manager;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-840__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a member of the company if the articles of organization do not provide that the company is managed by a manager;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-840__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a person organizing the company if the company is not organized;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-50-840__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the fiduciary if the company is controlled by a receiver, trustee, or other court-appointed fiduciary.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-840__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person signing a document filed with the department under this chapter shall state beneath or opposite the signature the person's name and the capacity in which the person signs.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-840__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person signing a document filed with the department under this chapter may sign as an attorney-in-fact, but is not required to provide or file with the department a document authorizing the person to act as attorney-in-fact for the signing of a document.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-850">
            <num>10.50.850</num>
            <heading>Filing and other fees.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.850.   Filing and other fees.
The department shall charge fees established by the department by regulation adopted under
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act) for
(1) filing the original articles of organization;
(2) filing an amendment of registration;
(3) filing articles of merger or consolidation;
(4) filing articles of dissolution;
(5) issuing a document not otherwise covered by this section;
(6) furnishing a copy of a document;
(7) accepting an application for reservation of a name, or filing a notice of the transfer or cancellation of a name reservation;
(8) filing a statement of change of address for a registered office or registered agent;
(9) accepting service of a notice, demand, or process upon the department;
(10) filing the application for registration of a foreign limited liability company;
(11) registering a name, reserving a name, or renewing a name registration under this chapter; or
(12) filing another document allowed or required under this chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-860">
            <num>10.50.860</num>
            <heading>Maintenance of records.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.860.   Maintenance of records.
Unless otherwise provided in an operating agreement, a limited liability company shall keep at its main office
(1) current and past lists that state in alphabetical order the full name and last known mailing address of every member and manager of the company;
(2) a copy of the company's articles of organization and amendments to the articles, including a signed copy of a power of attorney used by a person who signed articles of amendment for the company;
(3) a copy of the company's federal, state, and local income tax returns and financial statements, if any, for the three most recent years or, if the returns and statements are not prepared, a copy of the information and statements provided to, or that should have been provided to, the members to enable the members to prepare their federal, state, and local tax returns for the three-year period;
(4) a copy of any effective operating agreement of the company, amendments to the agreement, and former operating agreements;
(5) unless contained in an operating agreement,
(A) a document stating the amount of cash contributed by a member of the company, the agreed value of other property or services contributed by a member, and when a member is to make additional contributions;
(B) a document stating the events, if any, that cause the company to be dissolved and its affairs wound up; and
(C) other documents that an operating agreement requires the company to prepare.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-870">
            <num>10.50.870</num>
            <heading>Inspection of records.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-50-870__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A limited liability company shall make its books and records of account, or certified copies of them, reasonably available for inspection and copying at its registered office or principal office in the state by a member of the company. Member inspection shall be upon written demand stating with reasonable particularity the purpose of the inspection. The inspection may be in person or by agent or attorney, at a reasonable time and for a proper purpose. Only books and records of account, minutes, and the record of members directly connected to the stated purpose of the inspection may be inspected or copied.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-870__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A manager, or, if the company is not managed by a manager, a member, who, or a limited liability company that, refuses to allow a member, or the agent or attorney of the member, to examine and make copies from its books and records of account, minutes, and record of members, for a proper purpose, is liable to the member for a penalty in the amount of 10 percent of the value of the limited liability company interests owned by the member or $5,000, whichever is greater, in addition to other damages or remedy given the member by law. It is a defense to an action for penalties under this section that the person suing has within two years sold or offered for sale a list of members of the company or any other limited liability company or has aided or abetted a person in procuring a list of members for this purpose, or has improperly used information secured through a prior examination of the books and records of account, minutes, or record of members of the company or any other limited liability company, or was not acting in good faith or for a proper purpose in making the person's demand.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-50-870__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing in this chapter impairs the power of a court, upon proof by a member of a demand properly made and for a proper purpose, to compel the production for examination by the member of the books and records of account, minutes, and record of members of a limited liability company.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-880">
            <num>10.50.880</num>
            <heading>Disclosure of information.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.880.   Disclosure of information.
The members of a limited liability company, if the articles of organization do not provide that the company is managed by a manager, or the manager of the company, if the articles of organization provide that the company is managed by a manager, shall provide, to the extent just and reasonable under the circumstances, true and full information of all matters that affect the members of a company to a member or to the legal representative of a deceased member or a member under a legal disability.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-890">
            <num>10.50.890</num>
            <heading>Waiver of notice.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.890.   Waiver of notice.
If notice is required to be given to a member or manager of a limited liability company under the provisions of this chapter or under the provisions of the articles of organization or an operating agreement of the company, a waiver of the notice in writing signed by the person entitled to notice, whether before or after the time stated for notice, is equivalent to the giving of notice.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-900">
            <num>10.50.900</num>
            <heading>Regulations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.900.   Regulations.
In addition to the regulations the department is required to adopt under this chapter, the department may adopt other regulations under
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act) to implement this chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-910">
            <num>10.50.910</num>
            <heading>Interstate application.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.910.   Interstate application.
A limited liability company that is organized and existing under this chapter may conduct its affairs and exercise the powers granted by this chapter in another jurisdiction, subject to the laws of that jurisdiction.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-990">
            <num>10.50.990</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.990.   Definitions.
In this chapter, unless the context indicates otherwise,
(1) articles of organization means the articles of organization filed under
AS 10.50.070
and the articles as amended or restated;
(2) commissioner means the commissioner of commerce, community, and economic development;
(3) consolidation means a consolidation authorized by
AS 10.50.500
;
(4) corporation means a corporation organized under the laws of this or another state, or of this or another country;
(5) department means the Department of Commerce, Community, and Economic Development;
(6) filed, unless expressly provided otherwise, means filed with the department;
(7) foreign limited liability company means an organization that is
(A) not incorporated;
(B) organized under the law of a state other than this state, or under the law of a foreign country;
(C) organized under a statute that affords to each of its members limited liability regarding the liabilities of the organization; and
(D) not required to be registered under a statute of this state other than this chapter;
(8) interim distribution means a distribution of the assets of a limited liability company to the company's members, except as provided under
AS 10.50.425
;
(9) know means to have actual knowledge or to know other facts that demonstrate bad faith in the circumstances; this definition applies also to the derivatives of know, including known, unknown, and knowledge;
(10) limited liability company or domestic limited liability company means an organization organized under this chapter;
(11) limited liability company interest means an interest in a limited liability company issued under
AS 10.50.275
;
(12) limited partnership means a limited partnership organized under
AS 32.11
or under the law of another state or a foreign country;
(13) manager means a person who manages a limited liability company, if the articles of organization provide that the company is managed by a manager;
(14) managing member means a member of a limited liability company if the company's articles of organization do not provide that the company is managed by a manager;
(15) member means a person who has been admitted to membership in a limited liability company under
AS 10.50.155
 10.50.160 and whose membership has not ended under
AS 10.50.180
 10.50.185 or 10.50.205  10.50.225;
(16) merger means a merger authorized by
AS 10.50.500
;
(17) operating agreement means a written agreement among all of the members of a limited liability company about conducting the affairs of the company;
(18) professional service has the meaning given in
AS 10.45.500
;
(19) property includes cash;
(20) state means a state, territory, or possession of the United States, and includes the District of Columbia, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, the Northern Mariana Islands, Guam, the Virgin Islands, American Samoa, and the Trust Territory of the Pacific Islands.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-50-995">
            <num>10.50.995</num>
            <heading>Short title.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.50.995.   Short title.
This chapter may be cited as the Alaska Revised Limited Liability Company Act.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>