<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-06"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-06"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="8.06"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-06/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-06/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-06/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-06/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_8">
        <num>8</num>
        <heading>Business and Professions</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_8__chp_06">
          <num>06</num>
          <heading>Acupuncture</heading>
          <section eId="sec_08-06-010">
            <num>08.06.010</num>
            <heading>Practice of acupuncture without license prohibited.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.06.010.   Practice of acupuncture without license prohibited.
A person may not practice acupuncture without a license.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-06-020">
            <num>08.06.020</num>
            <heading>Application for license.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.06.020.   Application for license.
A person desiring to practice acupuncture shall apply in writing to the department.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-06-030">
            <num>08.06.030</num>
            <heading>License to practice acupuncture.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-06-030__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person is qualified to receive a license to practice acupuncture if the person</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-06-030__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is of good moral character;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-06-030__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is at least 21 years of age;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-06-030__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>either
(A) has completed a course of study consistent with the core curriculum and guidelines of the Accreditation Commission for Acupuncture and Oriental Medicine at a school of acupuncture approved by the department; or
(B) is licensed to practice acupuncture in another jurisdiction that has acupuncture licensing requirements equivalent to those of this state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-06-030__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is qualified for certification by the National Certification Commission for Acupuncture and Oriental Medicine as a diplomate in acupuncture;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-06-030__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>does not have a disciplinary proceeding or unresolved complaint pending at the time of application; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-06-030__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has not had a license to practice acupuncture suspended or revoked in this state or in another jurisdiction.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-06-030__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall issue a license to practice acupuncture to each person who is qualified and who pays the appropriate fee.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-06-030__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each person licensed to practice acupuncture under this chapter shall display the license in a conspicuous place where the licensee practices.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-06-040">
            <num>08.06.040</num>
            <heading>Renewal of license.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.06.040.   Renewal of license.
The department may not renew a license under this chapter unless the applicant demonstrates continued competence as an acupuncturist in a manner established by the department in regulations.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-06-050">
            <num>08.06.050</num>
            <heading>Disclosure.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-06-050__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who practices acupuncture shall disclose that the person's training and practice are in acupuncture</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-06-050__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to each patient; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-06-050__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>on all material used in the practice of acupuncture and made available to patients or to the public.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-06-050__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who practices acupuncture without being covered by malpractice insurance shall disclose to each patient that the person does not have the insurance.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-06-060">
            <num>08.06.060</num>
            <heading>Restrictions on practice of acupuncture.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.06.060.   Restrictions on practice of acupuncture.
A person who practices acupuncture may not
(1) give, prescribe, or recommend in the practice a
(A) prescription drug;
(B) controlled substance;
(C) poison;
(2) engage in surgery; or
(3) use the word physician in the person's title unless the person is also licensed as a physician.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-06-070">
            <num>08.06.070</num>
            <heading>Grounds for imposition of disciplinary sanctions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.06.070.   Grounds for imposition of disciplinary sanctions.
After a hearing, the department may impose a disciplinary sanction on a person licensed under this chapter when the department finds that the licensee
(1) secured a license through deceit, fraud, or intentional misrepresentation;
(2) engaged in deceit, fraud, or intentional misrepresentation in the course of providing professional services or engaging in professional activities;
(3) advertised professional services in a false or misleading manner;
(4) has been convicted of a felony or other crime that affects the licensee's ability to continue to practice competently and safely;
(5) intentionally or negligently engaged in patient care, or permitted the performance of patient care by persons under the licensee's supervision, that does not conform to minimum professional standards regardless of whether actual injury to the patient occurred;
(6) failed to comply with this chapter, with a regulation adopted under this chapter, or with an order of the department;
(7) continued to practice after becoming unfit due to
(A) professional incompetence;
(B) failure to keep informed of current professional practices;
(C) addiction to or severe dependency on alcohol or other drugs that impairs the ability to practice safely;
(D) physical or mental disability; or
(8) engaged in lewd or immoral conduct in connection with the delivery of professional service to patients.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-06-080">
            <num>08.06.080</num>
            <heading>Exemption.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.06.080.   Exemption.
This chapter does not apply to a person who practices acupuncture under
AS 08.36
or
AS 08.64
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-06-090">
            <num>08.06.090</num>
            <heading>Penalty.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.06.090.   Penalty.
A person who violates this chapter or a regulation adopted under this chapter is guilty of a class B misdemeanor.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-06-100">
            <num>08.06.100</num>
            <heading>Regulations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.06.100.   Regulations.
The department may adopt regulations to implement this chapter, including regulations establishing
(1) standards for the practice of acupuncture;
(2) standards for continuing education and training;
(3) a code of ethics for the practice of acupuncture.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-06-190">
            <num>08.06.190</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.06.190.   Definitions.
In this chapter,
(1) acupuncture means a form of healing developed from traditional Chinese medical concepts that uses the stimulation of certain points on or near the surface of the body by the insertion of needles to prevent or modify the perception of pain or to normalize physiological functions;
(2) department means the Department of Commerce, Community, and Economic Development;
(3) practice of acupuncture means the insertion of sterile acupuncture needles and the application of moxibustion to specific areas of the human body based upon acupuncture diagnosis; the practice of acupuncture includes adjunctive therapies involving mechanical, thermal, electrical, and electromagnetic treatment and the recommendation of dietary guidelines and therapeutic exercise.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>