<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-22/chapter-10"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-22/chapter-10"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="22.10"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-22/chapter-10/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-22/chapter-10/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-22/chapter-10/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-22/chapter-10/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_22">
        <num>22</num>
        <heading>Judiciary</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_22__chp_10">
          <num>10</num>
          <heading>The Superior Court</heading>
          <section eId="sec_22-10-010">
            <num>22.10.010</num>
            <heading>Establishment of superior court.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 22.10.010.   Establishment of superior court.
There shall be one superior court for the state. The court shall consist of four districts bounded as follows:
First District: the area within election districts numbered one to six, both inclusive, as those districts are described in art. XIV of the state constitution on March 19, 1959;
Second District: the area within election districts numbered 21 to 23, both inclusive, and those areas of election districts 18 and 20 within the boundaries of the North Slope Borough, as those districts are described in art. XIV of the state constitution on March 19, 1959;
Third District: the area within election districts numbered seven to 15, both inclusive, as those districts are described in art. XIV of the state constitution on March 19, 1959, and the portion of election district 19, as that district is described in art. XIV of the state constitution on March 19, 1959, that is in the Glennallen Venue District on March 1, 2002, described as follows: Beginning at a point on the divide between the watersheds of the Tanana River and the Copper River south of the headwaters of Totschunda Creek; thence southwesterly in a straight line first crossing the Nabesna River to Mt. Allen; thence meandering on the divide mountain peak to mountain peak to a point north of Regal Mountain on the divide separating the Nabesna Glacier from the Chisana Glacier; thence westerly and northwesterly along the divide between the watersheds of the Tanana River and Copper River as it meanders from mountain peak to mountain peak back to a point on the divide south of the headwaters of the Totschunda Creek, the place of the beginning; and
Fourth District: the area within election districts numbered 16, 17, and 24, the areas of election districts numbered 18 and 20 not included in the second district, and the area of election district numbered 19 not included in the third district, as those districts are described in art. XIV of the state constitution on March 19, 1959.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_22-10-020">
            <num>22.10.020</num>
            <heading>Jurisdiction of the superior court.</heading>
            <subsection eId="22-10-020__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The superior court is the trial court of general jurisdiction, with original jurisdiction in all civil and criminal matters, including probate and guardianship of minors and incompetents. Except for a petition for a protective order under
AS 18.66.100
 18.66.180, an action that falls within the concurrent jurisdiction of the superior court and the district court may not be filed in the superior court, except as provided by rules of the supreme court.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="22-10-020__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The jurisdiction of the superior court extends over the whole of the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="22-10-020__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The superior court and its judges may issue injunctions, writs of review, mandamus, prohibition, habeas corpus, and all other writs necessary or proper to the complete exercise of its jurisdiction.  A writ of habeas corpus may be made returnable before any judge of the superior court.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="22-10-020__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The superior court has jurisdiction in all matters appealed to it from a subordinate court, or administrative agency when appeal is provided by law, and has jurisdiction over petitions for relief in administrative matters under
AS 44.62.305
. The hearings on appeal from a final order or judgment of a subordinate court or administrative agency, except an appeal under
AS 43.05.242
, shall be on the record unless the superior court, in its discretion, grants a trial de novo, in whole or in part. The hearings on appeal from a final order or judgment under
AS 43.05.242
shall be on the record.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="22-10-020__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An appeal to the superior court is a matter of right, but an appeal from a subordinate court may not be taken by the defendant in a criminal case after a plea of guilty, except on the ground that the sentence was excessive. The state's right of appeal in criminal cases is limited by the prohibitions against double jeopardy contained in the United States Constitution and the Alaska Constitution.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="22-10-020__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An appeal to the superior court may be taken on the ground that an unsuspended sentence of imprisonment exceeding 120 days was excessive and the superior court in the exercise of this jurisdiction has the power to reduce the sentence. The state may appeal a sentence on the ground that it is too lenient. When a sentence is appealed on the ground that it is too lenient, the court may not increase the sentence but may express its approval or disapproval of the sentence and its reasons in a written opinion.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="22-10-020__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In case of an actual controversy in the state, the superior court, upon the filing of an appropriate pleading, may declare the rights and legal relations of an interested party seeking the declaration, whether or not further relief is or could be sought.  The declaration has the force and effect of a final judgment or decree and is reviewable as such.  Further necessary or proper relief based on a declaratory judgment or decree may be granted, after reasonable notice and hearing, against an adverse party whose rights have been determined by the judgment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="22-10-020__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Renumbered as
AS 22.10.025
(a).]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="22-10-020__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The superior court is the court of original jurisdiction over all causes of action arising under the provisions of
AS 18.80
.  A person who is injured or aggrieved by an act, practice, or policy which is prohibited under
AS 18.80
may apply to the superior court for relief. The person aggrieved or injured may maintain an action on behalf of that person or on behalf of a class consisting of all persons who are aggrieved or injured by the act, practice, or policy giving rise to the action. In an action brought under this subsection, the court may grant relief as to any act, practice, or policy of the defendant which is prohibited by
AS 18.80
, regardless of whether each act, practice, or policy, with respect to which relief is granted, directly affects the plaintiff, so long as a class or members of a class of which the plaintiff is a member are or may be aggrieved or injured by the act, practice, or policy. The court may enjoin any act, practice, or policy which is illegal under
AS 18.80
and may order any other relief, including the payment of money, that is appropriate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_22-10-025">
            <num>22.10.025</num>
            <heading>Powers of superior court in action for divorce, separation, or child support.</heading>
            <subsection eId="22-10-025__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The superior court, in an action for divorce, separation, or child support affecting inalienable stock in a corporation organized under 43 U.S.C. 1601 et seq. (Alaska Native Claims Settlement Act), may order the stock transferred to the spouse, a child, or a guardian or custodian for a child, but may not order it sold on the open market or transferred to other persons.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="22-10-025__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The superior court, in an action for divorce, separation, or child support, may issue orders to aid in the enforcement of child support, including orders requiring an individual who owes support under an order of support to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="22-10-025__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>make payments according to an approved payment plan;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="22-10-025__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>participate in appropriate work activities if the individual is not incapacitated; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="22-10-025__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>complete and submit an application for a permanent fund dividend under
AS 43.23.015
or provide proof to the agency or the court that the individual is not eligible for a dividend in a given year.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_22-10-030">
            <num>22.10.030</num>
            <heading>Where actions are to be brought.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 22.10.030.   Where actions are to be brought.
Venue for all actions shall be set under rules adopted by the supreme court.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_22-10-040">
            <num>22.10.040</num>
            <heading>Change of venue.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 22.10.040.   Change of venue.
The superior court in which the action is pending may change the place of trial in an action from one place to another place in the same judicial district or to a designated place in another judicial district for any of the following reasons:
(1) when there is reason to believe that an impartial trial cannot be had;
(2) when the convenience of witnesses and the ends of justice would be promoted by the change;
(3) when for any cause the judge is disqualified from acting, but if the judge of another judicial district is assigned to try the action, no change of place of trial need be made;
(4) if the court finds that the defendant will be put to unnecessary expense and inconvenience, and if the court finds that the expense and inconvenience were intentionally caused, the court may assess costs against the plaintiff.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_22-10-050">
            <num>22.10.050</num>
            <heading>General powers and sessions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 22.10.050.   General powers and sessions.
The superior court shall always be open, except on judicial holidays as determined by rule of the supreme court. Injunctions, writs of prohibition, mandamus, and habeas corpus may be issued and served on holidays and nonjudicial days. The superior court is a court of record and is vested with all power and authority necessary to carry into complete execution all its judgments, decrees, and determinations in all matters within its jurisdiction according to the constitution, the laws of the state, and the common law. The superior court shall hold regular sessions in each district at the times and places as may be designated by rule or order of the supreme court.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_22-10-060">
            <num>22.10.060</num>
            <heading>Effect of adjournment.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 22.10.060.   Effect of adjournment.
An adjournment from day to day, or from time to time, is a recess in the session, and does not prevent the court from sitting at any time.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_22-10-080">
            <num>22.10.080</num>
            <heading>Process.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 22.10.080.   Process.
Process of the superior court shall be in the name of the State of Alaska, signed by the clerk of the court or the deputy clerk in the judicial district where the process is issued, dated when issued, sealed with the seal of the court, and made returnable according to rule prescribed by the supreme court.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_22-10-090">
            <num>22.10.090</num>
            <heading>Qualifications of judges.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 22.10.090.   Qualifications of judges.
A judge of the superior court shall be a citizen of the United States and of the state, a resident of the state for five years immediately preceding appointment, have been engaged for not less than five years immediately preceding appointment in the active practice of law, and at the time of appointment be licensed to practice law in the state.  The active practice of law shall be as defined for justices of the supreme court in
AS 22.05.070
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_22-10-100">
            <num>22.10.100</num>
            <heading>Vacancies.</heading>
            <subsection eId="22-10-100__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The governor shall fill a vacancy or appoint a successor to fill an impending vacancy in the office of superior court judge within 45 days after receiving nominations from the judicial council, by appointing one of two or more persons nominated by the council for each actual or impending vacancy.  An appointment to fill an impending vacancy becomes effective upon the actual occurrence of the vacancy.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="22-10-100__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The office of a superior court judge becomes vacant 90 days after the election at which the judge is rejected by a majority of those voting on the question or for which the judge fails to file a declaration of candidacy.  Upon the occurrence of (1) an actual vacancy; (2) the certification of rejection following an election; or (3) the election following failure of a judge to file a declaration of candidacy, the judicial council shall meet within 90 days and submit to the governor the names of two or more persons qualified for the judicial office; except that this 90-day period may be extended by the council with the concurrence of the supreme court.  In the event of an impending vacancy other than by reason of rejection or failure to file a declaration of candidacy, the council may meet at any time within the 90-day period immediately preceding the effective date of the vacancy and submit to the governor the names of two or more persons qualified for the judicial office.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_22-10-110">
            <num>22.10.110</num>
            <heading>Oath of office.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 22.10.110.   Oath of office.
Each superior court judge, upon entering office, shall take and subscribe to an oath of office required of all officers under the constitution and any further oath or affirmation as may be prescribed by law.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_22-10-120">
            <num>22.10.120</num>
            <heading>Number of judges.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 22.10.120.   Number of judges.
The superior court consists of 45 judges, six of whom shall be judges in the first judicial district, three of whom shall be judges in the second judicial district, 28 of whom shall be judges in the third judicial district, and eight of whom shall be judges in the fourth judicial district. At the time of submitting the names of nominees to the governor to fill a vacancy on the superior court bench, the judicial council shall also designate the district in which the appointee is to reside and serve.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_22-10-130">
            <num>22.10.130</num>
            <heading>Appointment and duties of presiding judges.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 22.10.130.   Appointment and duties of presiding judges.
The chief justice of the supreme court shall designate a presiding judge for each district.  The presiding judge shall, in addition to regular judicial duties,
(1) assign the cases pending to the judges made available within the district;
(2) supervise the judges and their court personnel in the carrying out of their official duties within the district; and
(3) expedite and keep current the business of the court within the district.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_22-10-140">
            <num>22.10.140</num>
            <heading>Chief justice may assign superior court judges.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 22.10.140.   Chief justice may assign superior court judges.
The chief justice may assign a superior court judge and that judge's court personnel for temporary duty from time to time not to exceed 90 days annually anywhere in the state except to permit completion of hearings in progress. A judge may be temporarily assigned for longer and additional periods with the consent of that judge.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_22-10-150">
            <num>22.10.150</num>
            <heading>Approval or rejection.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 22.10.150.   Approval or rejection.
Each superior court judge is subject to approval or rejection as provided in
AS 15
(Alaska Election Code). The judicial council shall conduct an evaluation of each judge before the retention election and shall provide to the public information about the judge and may provide a recommendation regarding retention or rejection. The information and any recommendation shall be made public at least 60 days before the retention election. The information shall include the judge's consideration of victims when imposing sentence on persons convicted of felony offenses where the offenses involve victims. The judicial council shall also provide the information and any recommendation to the office of the lieutenant governor in time for publication in the election pamphlet under
AS 15.58.050
. If a majority of those voting on the question rejects the candidacy of a judge, the rejected judge may not for a period of four years thereafter be appointed to fill any vacancy in the supreme court, court of appeals, superior court, or district courts of the state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_22-10-170">
            <num>22.10.170</num>
            <heading>Impeachment.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 22.10.170.   Impeachment.
A superior court judge is subject to impeachment by the legislature for malfeasance or misfeasance in the performance of official duties.  Impeachment shall originate in the senate and must be approved by two-thirds vote of its members.  The motion for impeachment must list fully the basis for the proceeding.  Trial on impeachment shall be conducted by the house of representatives.  A supreme court justice designated by the court shall preside at the trial. Concurrence of two-thirds of the members of the house is required for a judgment of impeachment.  The judgment may not extend beyond removal from office, but does not prevent proceedings in the courts on the same or related charges.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_22-10-180">
            <num>22.10.180</num>
            <heading>Restrictions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 22.10.180.   Restrictions.
A superior court judge while holding office may not practice law, nor engage in the conduct of any other profession, vocation, or business for profit or compensation, which conduct would interfere with the performance of the judicial duties of the judge, nor may a judge hold office in a political party, or hold any other office or position of profit under the United States, the state or its political subdivisions.  A superior court judge filing for another elective public office other than delegate to a constitutional convention of this state or the United States forfeits the judicial position.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_22-10-190">
            <num>22.10.190</num>
            <heading>Compensation.</heading>
            <subsection eId="22-10-190__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (d) of this section, the monthly base salary for each superior court judge is $12,730.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="22-10-190__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A salary disbursement may not be issued to a superior court judge until the judge has filed with the state officer designated to issue salary disbursements an affidavit that no matter referred to the judge for opinion or decision has been uncompleted or undecided by the judge for a period of more than six months.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="22-10-190__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to the monthly salary, each superior court judge is entitled to receive a geographic cost-of-living adjustment each year on $100,000 of the judge's annual base salary for that year, based on the location of the primary office assignment. The commissioner of administration shall calculate the geographic cost-of-living adjustment based on the geographic pay differentials established under
AS 39.27.020
(a). Retirement contributions and benefits shall be computed only on the monthly base salary not including the geographic cost-of-living adjustment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="22-10-190__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Beginning July 1, 2006, if the monthly basic salary for Step E, Range 28, of the salary schedule set out in
AS 39.27.011
increases, the monthly base salary of the judges of the superior court shall increase by the same percentage. The increase takes effect when the salary increase under
AS 39.27.011
takes effect and may be retroactive if consistent with the change to
AS 39.27.011
. The commissioner of administration shall, by regulation, establish the percentage at which the salary is increased and the increased salary amount.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>