<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-33/chapter-30"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-33/chapter-30"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="33.30"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-33/chapter-30/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-33/chapter-30/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-33/chapter-30/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-33/chapter-30/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_33">
        <num>33</num>
        <heading>Probation, Prisons, Pardons, and Prisoners</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_33__chp_30">
          <num>30</num>
          <heading>Prison Facilities and Prisoners</heading>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-011">
            <num>33.30.011</num>
            <heading>Duties of commissioner.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-30-011__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-011__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establish, maintain, operate, and control correctional facilities suitable for the custody, care, and discipline of persons charged or convicted of offenses against the state or held under authority of state law; each correctional facility operated by the state shall be established, maintained, operated, and controlled in a manner that is consistent with
AS 33.30.015
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-011__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>classify prisoners;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-011__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for persons committed to the custody of the commissioner, establish programs, including furlough programs that are reasonably calculated to (A) protect the public and the victims of crimes committed by prisoners;
(B) maintain health;
(C) create or improve occupational skills;
(D) enhance educational qualifications;
(E) support court-ordered restitution; and
(F) otherwise provide for the rehabilitation and reformation of prisoners, facilitating their reintegration into society;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-011__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide necessary
(A) medical services for prisoners in correctional facilities or who are committed by a court to the custody of the commissioner, including examinations for communicable and infectious diseases;
(B) psychological or psychiatric treatment if a physician or other health care provider, exercising ordinary skill and care at the time of observation, concludes that</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-011__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>a prisoner exhibits symptoms of a serious disease or injury that is curable or may be substantially alleviated; and
(ii) the potential for harm to the prisoner by reason of delay or denial of care is substantial; and
(C) assessment or screening of the risks and needs of offenders who may be vulnerable to harm, exploitation, or recidivism as a result of fetal alcohol syndrome, fetal alcohol spectrum disorder, or another brain-based disorder;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-011__subsec_i__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establish minimum standards for sex offender treatment programs offered to persons who are committed to the custody of the commissioner;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-011__subsec_i__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide for fingerprinting in correctional facilities in accordance with
AS 12.80.060
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-011__subsec_i__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establish a program to conduct assessments of the risks and needs of offenders sentenced to serve a term of incarceration of 90 days or more; the program must include a requirement for an assessment before a prisoner's release on parole, furlough, or electronic monitoring from a correctional facility;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-011__subsec_i__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establish a procedure that provides for each prisoner required to serve an active term of imprisonment of 90 days or more a written case plan that
(A) takes effect and is provided to the prisoner within 90 days after sentencing;
(B) is based on the results of the assessment of the prisoner's risks and needs under (7) of this subsection;
(C) includes a requirement to follow the rules of the institution;
(D) is modified when necessary for changes in classification, housing status, medical or mental health, and resource availability;
(E) includes participation in programming that addresses the needs identified in the assessment;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-011__subsec_i__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establish a program to begin reentry planning with each prisoner serving an active term of imprisonment of 90 days or more; reentry planning must begin at least 90 days before release on furlough or probation or parole; the reentry program must include
(A) a written reentry plan for each prisoner completed upon release on furlough or probation or parole that includes information on the prisoner's proposed</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-011__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>residence;
(ii) employment or alternative means of support;
(iii) treatment options;
(iv) counseling services;</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-011__subsec_v">
              <num>(v)</num>
              <content>
                <p>education or job training services;
(B) any other requirements for successful transition back to the community, including electronic monitoring or furlough for the period between a scheduled parole hearing and parole eligibility;
(C) coordination with the Department of Labor and Workforce Development to provide access, after release, to job training and employment assistance; and
(D) coordination with community reentry coalitions or other providers of reentry services if available;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-011__subsec_v__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for offenders under electronic monitoring, establish
(A) minimum standards for electronic monitoring, which may include the requirement of active, real-time monitoring using global positioning systems; and
(B) procedures for oversight and approving electronic monitoring programs and systems provided by private contractors;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-011__subsec_v__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>ensure a prisoner has a valid state identification card upon the prisoner's release; if the prisoner does not have a valid state identification card before the prisoner's release, the department shall issue the prisoner a valid state identification card under
AS 33.30.105
and pay the application fee for an identification card issued under
AS 18.65.310
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-011__subsec_v__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide to the legislature, by electronic means, by January 10 preceding the first regular session of each legislature, a report summarizing the findings and results of the program established under (7) of this subsection; the report must include
(A) the number of prisoners who were provided with written case plans under (8) of this subsection;
(B) the number of written case plans under (8) of this subsection initiated within the preceding year; and
(C) the number of written case plans under (8) of this subsection that were updated in the preceding year; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-011__subsec_v__subsec_13">
                <num>(13)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>enter into an agreement with the Department of Family and Community Services, consistent with the provisions of
AS 47.12.105
, for the detention and care of a minor who is waived into adult court under
AS 47.12.030
or 47.12.100.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-011__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, held under authority of state law includes the confinement of persons under
AS 26.05
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-012">
            <num>33.30.012</num>
            <heading>Notice of release, parole, community placement, work release placement, furlough, or escape of sex offender or child kidnapper.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-30-012__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Within 30 days before release of a sex offender or child kidnapper with a duty to register under
AS 12.63
, the commissioner shall complete the registration of the sex offender or child kidnapper if the offender or kidnapper has not previously registered. The commissioner shall take the sex offender's or child kidnapper's photograph, and determine if legible fingerprints of the sex offender or child kidnapper have been previously provided to the Department of Public Safety; if legible fingerprints for the sex offense or child kidnapping have not previously been provided to the Department of Public Safety, the commissioner shall obtain the sex offender's or child kidnapper's fingerprints in the manner required by the Department of Public Safety and shall immediately forward the fingerprints to the department. When completing the registration or taking the photograph under this subsection, the commissioner shall also send written notice of release, parole, community placement, work release placement, or furlough of a sex offender or child kidnapper to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-012__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the chief of police of the community, if any, in which the inmate will reside;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-012__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Alaska state trooper post located nearest to where the inmate will reside;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-012__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the village public safety officer of the rural community without a municipal police department or Alaska state trooper post in which the inmate will reside; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-012__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the central registry of sex offenders and child kidnappers.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-012__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If an inmate convicted of a sex offense or child kidnapping escapes from a correctional facility, the commissioner shall immediately notify the Department of Public Safety and the chief of police of the community and the Alaska state trooper post located closest to where the inmate resided immediately before the inmate's arrest and conviction.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-013">
            <num>33.30.013</num>
            <heading>Commissioner to notify victims.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-30-013__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall notify the victim if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-013__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the offender escapes from custody;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-013__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the offender is discharged from parole under
AS 33.16
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-013__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the offender is released to the community on a furlough, on an early release program, or for any other reason; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-013__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the commissioner receives notice that the offender has filed a petition for a change of name under
AS 09.55.010
or
AS 25.24.165
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-013__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner is required to give notice of a change in the status of an offender under this section only if the victim has requested notice of the change, except that the commissioner is required to give notice, mailed to the last known address of the victim, in every case of a crime involving domestic violence.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-013__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A victim who has requested notice under (b) of this section shall maintain a current, valid mailing address on file with the commissioner. The commissioner shall send the notice from the department required by this section to the victim's last known address. The victim's address may not be disclosed to the offender or the offender's attorney.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-013__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The state may not be held liable in damages for the failure of the commissioner to comply with the requirements of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-013__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>As part of the notice under this section, the commissioner shall send the victim a photograph of the offender if the victim has specifically requested in writing that a photograph be sent. The photograph must have been taken within three weeks of the offender's release or, if the offender escapes from custody, must be the most recent photograph in the commissioner's possession. The photograph is for the victim's personal use, and the victim may not make copies of the photograph for distribution to others. An offender who is released under (a) of this section shall be notified that a photograph has been sent to the victim under this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-013__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner's duty under (a)  (c) of this section to notify a victim of a change in the status of an offender is satisfied by the notice provided by an automated victim notification system established under
AS 12.61.050
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-015">
            <num>33.30.015</num>
            <heading>Living conditions for prisoners.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-30-015__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner may not</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-015__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>make per capita expenditures for food for prisoners in a state correctional facility operated by the state that exceed 90 percent of per capita expenditures for food that is available to enlisted personnel in the United States Army stationed in the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-015__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide, in a state correctional facility operated by the state,
(A) living quarters for a prisoner into which the view is obstructed; however, the commissioner is not required to renovate a facility to comply with this subparagraph if the facility is being used as a correctional facility on August 27, 1997, or if the facility was already built before being acquired by the department;
(B) equipment or facilities for publishing or broadcasting material the content of which is not subject to prior approval by the department as consistent with keeping order in the institution and prisoner discipline;
(C) cable television service other than a level of basic cable television service that is available as a substitute for services that are broadcast to the public in the community in which a correctional facility is located;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-015__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>allow a prisoner held in a state correctional facility operated by the state to
(A) possess in the prisoner's cell a cassette tape player or recorder, a video cassette recorder (VCR), or a computer or modem of any kind;
(B) view movies rated R, X, or NC-17;
(C) possess printed or photographic material that</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-015__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>is obscene as defined by the commissioner in regulation;
(ii) could reasonably be expected to incite racial, ethnic, or religious hatred that is detrimental to the security, good order, or discipline of the institution or violence;
(iii) could reasonably be expected to aid in an escape or in the theft or destruction of property;
(iv) describes procedures for brewing alcoholic beverages or for manufacturing controlled substances, weapons, or explosives; or</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-015__subsec_v">
              <num>(v)</num>
              <content>
                <p>could reasonably be expected to facilitate criminal activity or a violation of institution rules;
(D) receive instruction in person, or by broadcast medium, or engage in boxing, wrestling, judo, karate, or other martial art or in any activity that, in the commissioner's discretion, would facilitate violent behavior;
(E) possess or have access to equipment for use in the activities listed in (D) of this paragraph;
(F) possess or have access to free weights;
(G) possess in the prisoner's cell a coffee pot, hot plate, appliance or heating element for food preparation, or more than three electrical appliances of any kind;
(H) possess or appear in a state of dress, hygiene, grooming, or appearance other than as permitted as uniform or standard in the correctional facility;
(I) use a computer other than those approved by the correctional facility; the use of a computer under this subparagraph may be approved only as part of the prisoner's employment, education, or vocational training and may not be used for any other purpose;
(J) smoke or use tobacco products of any kind.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-015__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner may determine whether the provisions of (a) of this section shall apply to correctional facilities that are not operated by the state and may negotiate with a provider of services for the detention and confinement of persons held under authority of state law under contract or agreement whether the living conditions set out in (a) of this section shall apply to persons held under authority of state law at a facility operated under contract or agreement.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-015__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>On and after January 1, 1998, the commissioner may not allow a prisoner to possess a television in the prisoner's cell if the prisoner is classified as maximum custody under
AS 33.30.011
(a)(2).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-015__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner may allow a prisoner who, under
AS 33.30.011
(a)(2), has been classified as other than maximum custody to possess a television in the prisoner's cell only if the prisoner</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-015__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>either is incapable of obtaining or has attained a high school diploma or general education development diploma or the equivalent;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-015__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is actively engaged in an educational, vocational training, or employment program;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-015__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has satisfied or is on a regular and current payment schedule for all restitution orders entered by the court as part of the prisoner's sentence and, if applicable, is actively engaged in a treatment plan or counseling, psychiatric, or rehabilitation program ordered by the court or the department as part of the prisoner's sentence; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-015__subsec_d__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>pays for the expense of providing the television and, in addition to the utility service fee required by
AS 33.30.017
, pays for the expense of providing any cable television service.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-015__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall use</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-015__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>appropriate technology to screen programs received by prisoners under (d) of this section;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-015__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Alaska farm products and salmon to the greatest extent practicable for food for prisoners in a state correctional facility operated by the state.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-017">
            <num>33.30.017</num>
            <heading>Fees for utilities services for prisoners.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-30-017__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall establish a reasonable utility fee for electrical utilities that are used by prisoners who are confined in a state correctional facility.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-017__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-017__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>charge each prisoner who possesses at least one major electrical appliance the utility fee established in (a) of this section; the commissioner may deduct the utility fee monthly from the account established for a prisoner into which money due the prisoner for labor is paid; if a prisoner is indigent, the commissioner shall make the deduction from any amount credited to the indigent inmate's account;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-017__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if available from legislative appropriation, expend money deducted and collected under (1) of this subsection to offset the cost of the department's utility expenses; the commissioner shall annually report on the amounts that are collected and expended under this paragraph.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-017__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The provisions of (b) of this section do not apply to prisoners</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-017__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>who are
(A) developmentally disabled; or
(B) severely medically or cognitively disabled, as that term is defined in
AS 33.16.900
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-017__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>who are housed in a mental health unit or psychiatric unit of a state correctional facility; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-017__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>while placed in a state correctional facility awaiting classification under classification procedures for the purpose of making the appropriate assignment of the prisoner.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-021">
            <num>33.30.021</num>
            <heading>Regulations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 33.30.021.   Regulations.
The commissioner shall adopt regulations to implement this chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-025">
            <num>33.30.025</num>
            <heading>Siting of prison facilities.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 33.30.025.   Siting of prison facilities.
The commissioner shall notify each community council established by municipal charter or ordinance of the department's plans to locate a prison facility or to contract for the operation of a prison facility, community residential facility, or other rehabilitation program if the facility or proposed facility will be within one-half mile of the boundary of the area represented by a community council.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-026">
            <num>33.30.026</num>
            <heading>Procurement Code applicable to contracts.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 33.30.026.   Procurement Code applicable to contracts.
Contracting for services under this chapter is governed by
AS 36.30
(State Procurement Code).</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-028">
            <num>33.30.028</num>
            <heading>Responsibility for costs of medical care.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-30-028__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the liability for payment of the costs of medical, psychological, and psychiatric care provided or made available to a prisoner committed to the custody of the commissioner is, subject to (b) of this section, the responsibility of the prisoner and the</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-028__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>prisoner's insurer if the prisoner is insured under existing individual health insurance, group health insurance, or any prepaid medical coverage;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-028__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Department of Health if the prisoner is eligible for assistance under
AS 47.07
or
AS 47.25.120
 47.25.300;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-028__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>United States Department of Veterans Affairs if the prisoner is eligible for veterans' benefits that entitle the prisoner to reimbursement for the medical care or medical services;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-028__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>United States Public Health Service, the Indian Health Service, or any affiliated group or agency if the prisoner is a Native American and is entitled to medical care from those agencies or groups; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-028__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>parent or guardian of the prisoner if the prisoner is under the age of 18.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-028__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall require prisoners who are without resources under (a) of this section to pay the costs of medical, psychological, and psychiatric care provided to them by the department. At a minimum, the prisoner shall be required to pay a portion of the costs based upon the prisoner's ability to pay.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-028__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall apply for medical assistance under
AS 47.07
and for general relief assistance under
AS 47.25.120
 47.25.300 on behalf of a prisoner incarcerated in a correctional facility to establish medical assistance coverage or general relief assistance for the prisoner during a period of hospitalization outside of the correctional facility.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-028__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner may obtain information necessary to determine whether a prisoner incarcerated in a correctional facility is eligible for medical assistance under
AS 47.07
or public assistance under
AS 47.25
. Information obtained under this subsection may be used only for the purpose of applying for medical assistance or public assistance under (c) of this section and may not be disclosed for any other purpose without the permission of the prisoner. An employee of the commissioner who discloses a prisoner's social security number in an application for medical assistance or public assistance under this section is considered to be acting in the performance of the employee's duties or responsibilities under
AS 45.48.400
(b).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-031">
            <num>33.30.031</num>
            <heading>Contracts for confinement and care of prisoners.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-30-031__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall determine the availability of state correctional facilities suitable for the detention and confinement of persons held under authority of state law or under agreement entered into under (e) of this section. If the commissioner determines that suitable state correctional facilities are not available, the commissioner may enter into an agreement with a public or private agency to provide necessary facilities. Correctional facilities provided through agreement with a public agency for the detention and confinement of persons held under authority of state law may be in this state or in another state. Correctional facilities provided through agreement with a private agency must be located in this state unless the commissioner finds in writing that (1) there is no other reasonable alternative for detention in the state; and (2) the agreement is necessary because of health or security considerations involving a particular prisoner or class of prisoners, or because an emergency of prisoner overcrowding is imminent. The commissioner may not enter into an agreement with an agency unable to provide a degree of custody, care, and discipline similar to that required by the laws of this state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-031__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 37 ch 2 FSSLA 1992.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-031__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding
AS 36.30.300
, an agreement with a private agency to provide necessary facilities under (a) of this section must be based on competitive bids.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-031__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person employed outside the facility while confined in a privately operated correctional facility established under (a) of this section is subject to the provisions of
AS 33.30.131
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-031__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner may enter into an agreement with the United States, another state, a municipality of this state, or another state agency, to provide a correctional facility for the custody, care, and discipline of a person held under authority of the law of that jurisdiction.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-035">
            <num>33.30.035</num>
            <heading>Notice to sex offenders or child kidnappers of registration and other requirements.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 33.30.035.   Notice to sex offenders or child kidnappers of registration and other requirements.
The department shall provide written notice to a sex offender or child kidnapper of the registration, verification, and change of address requirements of
AS 12.63.010
and shall obtain a written receipt of notice from the sex offender or child kidnapper (1) at the time of the sex offender's or child kidnapper's release from a state correctional facility; (2) immediately after taking supervision of a sex offender or child kidnapper under the Interstate Corrections Compact or
AS 33.36.110
. The department shall forward the written receipt to the Department of Public Safety, along with a description of any identifying features of the offender or kidnapper, the anticipated address of the offender or kidnapper, and a statement concerning whether the offender or kidnapper has received treatment for the offender's or kidnapper's mental abnormality or personality disorder related to the sex offense or child kidnapping. In this section, sex offense and child kidnapping have the meanings given in
AS 12.63.100
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-041">
            <num>33.30.041</num>
            <heading>Lease of correctional facility to municipality.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-30-041__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the commissioner determines that it would be in the best interest of the state, the commissioner may enter into an agreement with a municipality of the state for the lease of a state correctional facility or for the use and operation of a state correctional facility for the joint benefit of the municipality and the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-041__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An agreement executed by the commissioner under (a) of this section must provide that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-041__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the state has the right to detain or confine a prisoner held under authority of law in the correctional facility;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-041__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the administrator of the correctional facility agrees to implement an order, concerning a prisoner, issued by a court of the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-041__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the administrator of the correctional facility shall comply with the law, and regulations adopted by the commissioner, relating to the custody, care, and discipline of a prisoner detained or confined in the correctional facility; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-041__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the commissioner may inspect the correctional facility at any time to determine the conditions under which a prisoner is detained or confined.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-041__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The agreement executed by the commissioner under (a) of this section may require the administrator of the correctional facility to comply with requirements that the commissioner considers necessary for the protection of the public or for the quality of care and programs for prisoners required by this chapter and regulations adopted by the commissioner.
Article 2. Commitments, Programs, and Furloughs.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-051">
            <num>33.30.051</num>
            <heading>Commitment to commissioner.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-30-051__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person convicted of an offense against the state shall be committed to the custody of the commissioner for the term of imprisonment that the court directs.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-051__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person restrained under
AS 26.05.400
or convicted of an offense by court-martial under
AS 26.05
and confined under
AS 26.05.405
shall be committed to the custody of the commissioner for the period of restraint or confinement as directed by the adjutant general.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-061">
            <num>33.30.061</num>
            <heading>Commissioner to designate facility.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-30-061__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall designate the correctional facility to which a prisoner is to be committed to serve a term of imprisonment or period of temporary commitment. The commissioner may designate a facility without regard to whether it is maintained by the state, is located within the judicial district in which the prisoner was convicted, or is located in the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-061__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner may designate an out-of-state facility under this section only if the commissioner determines that rehabilitation or treatment of the prisoner will not be substantially impaired.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-061__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner may, under
AS 33.30.065
, designate a prisoner to serve the prisoner's term of imprisonment or period of temporary commitment, or a part of the term or period, by electronic monitoring. A prisoner serving a term of imprisonment, or a period of temporary commitment, for a crime involving domestic violence is not eligible for electronic monitoring.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-061__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A prisoner serving a term of imprisonment at a private residence as required by statute when electronic monitoring is not available does not have a liberty interest in that status. The commissioner may return the prisoner to a correctional facility if the commissioner finds that the prisoner has violated the terms and conditions of the imprisonment at the private residence.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-065">
            <num>33.30.065</num>
            <heading>Service of sentence by electronic monitoring.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-30-065__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the commissioner designates a prisoner to serve the prisoner's term of imprisonment or period of temporary commitment, or a part of the term or period, by electronic monitoring, the commissioner shall direct the prisoner to serve the term or period at the prisoner's residence or other place selected by the commissioner. The electronic monitoring shall be administered by the department or by a private contractor approved by the department under
AS 33.30.011
(a)(10)(B) and shall be designed so that any attempt to remove, tamper with, or disable the monitoring equipment or to leave the place selected for the service of the term or period will result in a report or notice to the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-065__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In determining whether to designate a prisoner to serve a term of imprisonment or period of temporary commitment by electronic monitoring, the commissioner shall consider</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-065__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>safeguards to the public;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-065__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the prospects for the prisoner's rehabilitation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-065__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the availability of program and facility space;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-065__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the nature and circumstances of the offense for which the prisoner was sentenced or for which the prisoner is serving a period of temporary commitment;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-065__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the needs of the prisoner as determined by a classification committee and any recommendations made by the sentencing court;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-065__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the record of convictions of the prisoner, with particular emphasis on crimes specified in
AS 11.41
or crimes involving domestic violence;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-065__subsec_b__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the use of drugs or alcohol by the prisoner; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-065__subsec_b__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>other criteria considered appropriate by the commissioner.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-065__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A decision by the commissioner to designate a prisoner to serve a term of imprisonment or a period of temporary confinement, or a part of the term or period, by electronic monitoring does not create a liberty interest in that status for the prisoner. The prisoner may be returned to a correctional facility at the discretion of the commissioner.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-065__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner may require a prisoner designated to serve a term of imprisonment or a period of temporary confinement by electronic monitoring to pay all or a portion of the costs of the electronic monitoring, but only if the prisoner has sufficient financial resources to pay the costs or a portion of the costs.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-071">
            <num>33.30.071</num>
            <heading>Responsibility for prisoners pending commitment.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-30-071__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner is not responsible for providing custody, care, and discipline for a person detained under
AS 47.30.705
or
AS 47.37.170
unless the person is admitted into a state correctional facility.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-071__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The responsibility of the commissioner under
AS 33.30.011
begins when a prisoner is accepted into the commissioner's custody or admitted into a correctional facility.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-071__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Medical services for a prisoner who is unconscious or in immediate need of medical attention before admission to a correctional facility or commitment by a court to the custody of the commissioner of corrections shall be provided by the law enforcement agency having custody of the prisoner. The law enforcement agency may require the prisoner to compensate the agency for the cost or for a portion of the cost of medical services provided for any preexisting medical condition.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-081">
            <num>33.30.081</num>
            <heading>Transportation of prisoners.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-30-081__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner of public safety is responsible for transporting a prisoner to and from the court having jurisdiction over the prisoner and for delivering a prisoner to a correctional facility upon temporary or final commitment by a court or upon transfer of a prisoner from one correctional facility to another either inside or outside the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-081__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner of corrections shall make available return transportation to the place of arrest for a prisoner who is released from custody in a state correctional facility.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-081__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner of public safety shall make available return transportation to the place of arrest for a prisoner who is released from custody before admission to a state correctional facility.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-081__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner of corrections shall adopt regulations governing the furnishing of transportation, discharge payments, and clothing to prisoners upon release from a state correctional facility at any stage of a criminal proceeding.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-081__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (f) of this section or as necessary in a criminal action pending against the prisoner, a court may not order the transportation of a prisoner.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-081__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A court may order a prisoner who is a party or witness to a civil action or a witness to a criminal action to appear at a place other than within a correctional facility only if the court determines, after providing a reasonable opportunity for the commissioner to comment, that the prisoner's personal appearance is essential to the just disposition of the action. In making its determination, the court shall consider available alternatives to the prisoner's personal appearance including deposition and telephone testimony.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-081__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (h) of this section, the expenses associated with the transportation of a prisoner ordered under (f) of this section, including the costs of travel for the prisoner and escorting officers, and the salary and per diem costs of the escorting officers, shall be borne by the party who has requested the prisoner's appearance, and shall be paid to the commissioner of public safety before the prisoner is transported.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-081__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A prisoner who is a party to a civil action is not required to bear the full costs of a prisoner's own transportation under (g) of this section if the court determines that the prisoner is indigent. In these cases, the court may require the prisoner to bear a portion of the costs, and the commissioner of public safety shall bear the remaining costs of transporting the prisoner. If an indigent prisoner recovers a money judgment, the court may require the prisoner to bear all or part of the expenses required under (g) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-091">
            <num>33.30.091</num>
            <heading>Designation of programs.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 33.30.091.   Designation of programs.
Except as provided in
AS 33.30.111
and 33.30.161, the commissioner may assign a prisoner committed to the commissioner's custody to a program established under
AS 33.30.011
(a)(3) considering
(1) safeguards to the public;
(2) the prospects for the prisoner's rehabilitation;
(3) the availability of program and facility space;
(4) the prospect of future judicial proceedings requiring the presence of the prisoner;
(5) the nature and circumstances of the offense for which the prisoner was sentenced;
(6) the needs of the prisoner as determined by a classification committee and any recommendations made by the sentencing court;
(7) the record of convictions of the prisoner with particular emphasis on crimes specified in
AS 11.41
;
(8) the use of drugs or alcohol by the prisoner;
(9) the length of the prisoner's sentence; and
(10) other criteria considered appropriate by the commissioner, including experimental evaluation of correctional programs that are consistent with protection of the public and reformation of the prisoner.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-095">
            <num>33.30.095</num>
            <heading>Duties of commissioner before release of prisoner.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-30-095__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall establish a program to prepare a prisoner who is serving a sentence of imprisonment exceeding one year for the prisoner's discharge, release on parole or probation, or prerelease furlough under
AS 33.30.111
that begins 90 days before the date of the prisoner's discharge, release, or furlough.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-095__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The program established under (a) of this section must include</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-095__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>instruction on
(A) obtaining state identification;
(B) community resources available for housing, employment, and treatment;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-095__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an individualized reentry plan under
AS 33.30.011</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-095__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>probation and parole orientation, if appropriate; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-095__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a partnership with one or more nonprofit organizations to allow access to a prisoner before the prisoner's discharge, release, or furlough to assist the prisoner with the prisoner's application for Medicaid, social security benefits, public assistance under
AS 47.25
, and a state identification card or driver's license and provide other programs to assist the prisoner's transition into the community, promote rehabilitation, and reduce recidivism.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-101">
            <num>33.30.101</num>
            <heading>Furloughs.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-30-101__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall adopt regulations governing the granting of prerelease and short-duration furloughs to prisoners</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-101__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to obtain counseling and treatment for alcohol or drug abuse;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-101__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to secure or attend vocational training;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-101__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to obtain medical or psychiatric treatment;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-101__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to secure or engage in employment;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-101__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to attend educational institutions;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-101__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to secure a residence or make other preparations for release;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-101__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to appear before a group whose purpose is a better understanding of crime or corrections; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-101__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for any other rehabilitative purpose the commissioner determines to be in the interests of the prisoner and the public.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-101__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the commissioner determines with reasonable probability that a prisoner can live under reduced supervision without violating the law or the conditions established for the conduct of the prisoner, the commissioner may grant a furlough after considering</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-101__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the factors in
AS 33.30.091
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-101__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>violations, if any, by the prisoner of a condition of a prior furlough;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-101__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the history, if any, of institutional misconduct by the prisoner; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-101__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the best interests of the prisoner and the public.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-101__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The regulations adopted under (a) of this section may not provide for the granting of a furlough of any type to a prisoner sentenced to a mandatory 99-year term of imprisonment under
AS 12.55.125</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-101__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or a definite term of imprisonment under
AS 12.55.125</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-101__subsec_l">
              <num>(l)</num>
              <content>
                <p>unless the prisoner is at all times in the direct custody of a correctional officer while the prisoner is away from the correctional facility.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-101__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner may release on furlough a prisoner convicted of a crime involving domestic violence only under conditions that would protect the victim of domestic violence or other household member.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-105">
            <num>33.30.105</num>
            <heading>Identification cards.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-30-105__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall issue an identification card identical to the motor vehicle operator's license provided for in
AS 28.15.111
, except that the card must be a different color and shall state in bold type letters on its face that it is for identification purposes only. The department may only issue an identification card to a prisoner before the prisoner's release. The identification card must display</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-105__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a distinguishing number assigned to the identification card;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-105__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the prisoner's full name, date of birth, brief physical description, and photograph;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-105__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>either a facsimile of the signature of the prisoner or a space on which the prisoner shall write the prisoner's usual signature with pen and ink;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-105__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>physical security features designed to prevent tampering, counterfeiting, or duplication of the document for fraudulent purposes;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-105__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for a qualified prisoner who is under 21 years of age, the words UNDER 21; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-105__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a statement that the identification card is not a valid identification card for the purpose of purchasing alcoholic beverages.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-105__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An identification card may not display the prisoner's social security number and is not valid until signed by the prisoner. If facilities are not available for the taking of the photograph required under this section, the department shall endorse on the identification card the words valid without photograph.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-105__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An identification card issued under this section expires 180 days after issuance or, if issued to a person under 21 years of age, 90 days after the person reaches 21 years of age, whichever occurs first.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-105__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-105__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>knowingly make a fraudulent written statement or application for an identification card concerning age, race, sex, or other identifying characteristics as required by the department;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-105__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>possess, use, produce, or manufacture a fraudulent identification card;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-105__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>allow an identification card issued to that person to be used by another person.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-105__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who violates (d) of this section is guilty of a misdemeanor punishable by a fine of $500 or 60 days in jail, or both.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-111">
            <num>33.30.111</num>
            <heading>Prerelease furloughs.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-30-111__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Furlough programs established under
AS 33.30.101
must include prerelease furloughs designed to facilitate the reintegration of a prisoner into society.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-111__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A facility that is specifically adapted to provide a residence outside prison, including a halfway house, group home, or other placement that provides varying levels of restriction and supervision, may be used for a prisoner on a prerelease furlough.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-111__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The restrictions and supervision required for a prerelease furlough shall provide safeguards that minimize risk to the public and include, as a minimum,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-111__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>frequent contact with the prisoner by persons supervising the prisoner;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-111__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>knowledge by supervisory staff of the location of the prisoner;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-111__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>periodic reports by supervisory staff to the commissioner on the performance of the prisoner while on furlough; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-111__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a residential setting in which persons supervising a prisoner are obliged to immediately report to the commissioner any violation of a condition set for the prisoner's conduct.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-111__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding
AS 33.30.101
(b), and other eligibility criteria established by the commissioner that relate to risks to the public posed by the proposed furlough of a prisoner,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-111__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a prisoner sentenced to a definite term of imprisonment of more than one year but less than five years is not eligible for a prerelease furlough until the prisoner has served at least one-third of the sentence; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-111__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a prisoner sentenced to a definite term of imprisonment of five years or more is not eligible for a prerelease furlough until the prisoner has served at least one-third of the sentence or is within three years of the release date, whichever is later.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-111__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A prisoner may request a prerelease furlough under procedures adopted by the commissioner. If the commissioner denies a request for a prerelease furlough, the commissioner shall provide the prisoner with a written explanation of the reasons for the denial.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-111__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (g) of this section, if the commissioner considers a prisoner convicted of a crime against a person or arson in the first degree for a prerelease furlough and the victim has requested notice under
AS 33.30.013
, the commissioner shall send notice of intent to consider the prisoner for a prerelease furlough to the victim. The victim may comment in writing on the commissioner's intent to release the prisoner on a prerelease furlough status. The commissioner shall consider the victim's comments before making a final decision to release a prisoner on a prerelease furlough status. The commissioner shall make a reasonable effort to notify the victim of an intent to release the prisoner on a prerelease furlough. The notice must contain the expected date of the prisoner's release, the geographic area in which the prisoner will reside, and other pertinent information concerning the prisoner's release that may affect the victim.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-111__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the commissioner considers a prisoner convicted of a crime involving domestic violence for a prerelease furlough, the commissioner shall send notice of intent to consider the prisoner for prerelease furlough to the last known address of the victim. The victim may comment in writing on the commissioner's intention to release the prisoner on a prerelease furlough. The commissioner shall consider the victim's comments, if any, before making a final decision to release the prisoner on a prerelease furlough. The commissioner shall make a reasonable effort to notify the victim of any decision to release the prisoner on the prerelease furlough. The notice must include the expected date of the furlough and any other information concerning the furlough that may affect the victim. A person may not bring a civil action for damages for a failure to comply with the provisions of this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-121">
            <num>33.30.121</num>
            <heading>Short-duration furloughs.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-30-121__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A short-duration furlough is an authorized leave of absence from a correctional facility for a period not to exceed 12 hours at any one time, except for</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-121__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>family visitations, that may not exceed one week or occur more frequently than once in each four-month period; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-121__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>medical treatment, for which the furlough may not last longer than necessary for the treatment.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-121__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A short-duration furlough may be granted to a prisoner at any time under regulations adopted by the commissioner.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-131">
            <num>33.30.131</num>
            <heading>Prerelease or short duration furlough or correctional restitution center placement involving employment.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-30-131__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner may grant a prerelease or short-duration furlough to permit a prisoner to participate in suitable employment under conditions and at wages that represent the prevailing standard for the area. A prisoner may not participate in employment where an organized labor dispute is in progress.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-131__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless alternative arrangements are expressly approved by the commissioner, when a prisoner is employed outside a correctional facility as part of a prerelease or short-duration furlough program, or as part of serving time in a correctional restitution center under
AS 33.30.151
 33.30.181, the earnings of the prisoner shall be delivered to the commissioner. If an employer transmits the earnings to the commissioner, the employer has no liability to the prisoner for the earnings. The commissioner shall disburse the earnings of the prisoner, in an order determined appropriate, under procedures adopted by the commissioner to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-131__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>pay for the room, board, and personal expenses of the prisoner in an amount or at a rate determined by the commissioner;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-131__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>pay any restitution or fine ordered by the sentencing court;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-131__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>reimburse the state for an award made for violent crimes compensation under
AS 18.67
arising out of the criminal conduct of the prisoner;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-131__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>pay a civil judgment arising out of the criminal conduct of the prisoner; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-131__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>support the dependents of the prisoner, and to provide child support payments as required by
AS 25.27
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-131__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After making the disbursements authorized under (b) of this section, the commissioner shall retain the balance remaining in the account of the prisoner and give it to the prisoner upon release. The commissioner may permit the prisoner to draw upon a portion of this money for other purposes that the commissioner considers appropriate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-131__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Only the earnings retained by the commissioner under (c) of this section are subject to lien, attachment, garnishment, execution, or other proceedings to encumber money or property.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-141">
            <num>33.30.141</num>
            <heading>Effect of violation of furlough conditions or failure to return.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-30-141__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If, after a hearing, a prisoner on a furlough is found to have violated the conditions established for the prisoner's conduct, the commissioner may immediately require the return of the prisoner to actual confinement for a period not to exceed the balance of the term of imprisonment or initiate disciplinary proceedings authorized by regulations adopted by the commissioner or both.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-141__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The failure of a prisoner on a furlough to return to the place of confinement or residence within the time specified by those having direct supervision over the prisoner is an unlawful evasion under
AS 11.56.335
or 11.56.340.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-151">
            <num>33.30.151</num>
            <heading>Correctional restitution centers.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-30-151__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall establish correctional restitution centers in the state. The purpose of the centers is to provide certain offenders with rehabilitation through comprehensive treatment for substance abuse, cognitive behavioral disorders, and other criminal risk factors, including aftercare support, community service, and employment, while protecting the community through partial incarceration of the offender, and to create a means to provide restitution to victims of crimes.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-151__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall adopt regulations setting standards for the operation of the centers including</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-151__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>requirements that the centers be secure and in compliance with state and local safety laws;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-151__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>standards for disciplinary rules to be imposed on prisoners confined to the centers;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-151__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>standards for the granting of emergency absence to prisoners confined to the centers;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-151__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>standards for classifying prisoners to centers;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-151__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>standards for mandatory employment and participation in community service programs in each center;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-151__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>standards for periodic review of the performance of prisoners confined to the centers and quality assurance measures to ensure centers are meeting state standards and contractual obligations;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-151__subsec_b__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>standards for the provision of treatment, including substance abuse treatment, cognitive behavioral therapy, and aftercare designed to address an offender's individual criminogenic needs; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-151__subsec_b__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>standards and a process to assess an offender's risk of recidivating and the criminal risk factors and needs that reduce the risk of recidivating and ensure that
(A)  high risk offenders with moderate to high needs are a priority for acceptance into a correctional restitution center; and
(B)  centers establish internal procedures to limit the mixing of low and high risk prisoners.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-161">
            <num>33.30.161</num>
            <heading>Eligibility to serve time in a correctional restitution center.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-30-161__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner may not allow a prisoner to serve time in a correctional restitution center unless the commissioner specifically finds that the prisoner meets the eligibility requirements of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-161__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To be eligible to serve time in a correctional restitution center, the prisoner</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-161__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>must be employable or eligible to work on community service projects approved by the commissioner and agree to secure employment or participate in community service projects and obey the rules of the center;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-161__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>may not be serving a sentence for conviction of an offense
(A) involving violence or the use of force;
(B) under
AS 11.41.320
, 11.41.330, or
AS 11.56.740
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-161__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>may not have been convicted of a felony offense, in the state or another jurisdiction, involving violence or the use of force;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-161__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>may not have been convicted of an offense under
AS 11.41.410
 11.41.470 or an offense in the state or another jurisdiction having elements substantially identical to an offense under
AS 11.41.410
 11.41.470; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-161__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>may not have been sentenced to a
(A) mandatory 99-year term of imprisonment under
AS 12.55.125</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-161__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless the commissioner determines otherwise for good cause shown, a person sentenced to less than five days who is serving time in a correctional restitution center shall participate in a community service project when available.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-161__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In (b) of this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-161__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>force has the meaning given in
AS 11.81.900</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-161__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>violence or the use of force includes possession of a firearm, as defined in
AS 11.81.900</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-171">
            <num>33.30.171</num>
            <heading>Community advisory committees.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 33.30.171.   Community advisory committees.
The commissioner shall appoint a community advisory committee for each center, to consist of five members of the community in which the center is located. The committee shall act as a liaison between the community and the department regarding community concerns with the center.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-181">
            <num>33.30.181</num>
            <heading>Confinement to the center.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-30-181__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A prisoner shall be confined to the center at all times except while</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-181__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>at work and traveling to and from work;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-181__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>at and traveling to and from a community service project approved by the commissioner;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-181__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>on emergency absence;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-181__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>at and traveling to and from a job interview; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-181__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>on a furlough approved by the commissioner.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-181__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except for an emergency absence or furlough, a prisoner may not be absent from a center under this section for more than 12 hours in a 24-hour period.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-191">
            <num>33.30.191</num>
            <heading>Employment of prison inmates.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-30-191__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>It is the policy of the state that prisoners be productively employed for as many hours each day as feasible.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-191__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner may enter into contracts or cooperative agreements with any public agency for the performance of conservation projects. After June 14, 2006, the commissioner may enter into a contract with an individual or private organization or public agency for the employment of prisoners if the commissioner consults with local union organizations before contracting and ensures that the contract will not result in the displacement of employed workers, be applied in skills, crafts, or trades in which there is a surplus of available gainful labor in the locality, or impair existing contracts for services. A contract with an individual or private organization must require payment to the commissioner of at least the minimum wage required by
AS 23.10.065
for each hour worked by a prisoner. The wage required under the contract, multiplied by the total hours worked by inmates, must be paid weekly, or for another period as required by the contract.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-191__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner may direct a prisoner to participate in a type of productive employment listed in (g)(1) and (3)  (5) of this section while the prisoner is confined in a correctional facility. A prisoner who refuses to participate in productive employment inside a correctional facility when directed under this section is subject to disciplinary sanctions imposed in accordance with regulations adopted by the commissioner.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-191__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In employing prison inmates, the department shall comply with federal and state health and safety regulations, except for providing workers' compensation under
AS 23.30
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-191__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The provisions of
AS 23
do not apply to the employment of prison inmates.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-191__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Prison inmates productively employed under this section are not state employees nor do they have the rights or privileges given to state employees, including the right to participate in collective bargaining.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-191__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, productively employed includes the following kinds of employment:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-191__subsec_g__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>routine maintenance and support services essential to the operation of a correctional facility;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-191__subsec_g__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>education, including both academic and vocational;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-191__subsec_g__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>public conservation projects, including wildland fire prevention and control, forest and watershed enhancement, recreational area development, construction and maintenance of trails and campsites, fish and game enhancement, soil conservation, and forest watershed revegetation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-191__subsec_g__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>renovation, repair, or alteration of existing correctional facilities as permitted by law; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-191__subsec_g__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>other work performed inside or outside of a correctional facility under (b) of this section.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-193">
            <num>33.30.193</num>
            <heading>Standard applicable to allowing prisoners access to and use of legal reference materials and legal assistance.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 33.30.193.   Standard applicable to allowing prisoners access to and use of legal reference materials and legal assistance.
If the commissioner imposes a restriction on access to and use of legal reference materials by or legal assistance of a prisoner in a state correctional facility, a court may not enter an order giving relief to the prisoner unless the court first finds, by a preponderance of the evidence, that enforcement or application of the restriction hinders the prisoner from having access to and use of the legal reference materials or legal assistance
(1) in order to gain meaningful access to a court for the purpose of challenging
(A) the prisoner's conviction or sentence; or
(B) the conditions of the prisoner's confinement; or
(2) in circumstances in which a state court has specifically determined that a provision of the state constitution necessarily requires a prisoner to have access to and use of the legal reference materials or legal assistance.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-201">
            <num>33.30.201</num>
            <heading>Compensation of prison inmates; deductions; disbursement; liens.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-30-201__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each prisoner who is productively employed, as defined in
AS 33.30.191
(g)(1) or (3)  (5), may receive for that work compensation at a rate determined by the commissioner under this section if the money is available from legislative appropriations. Compensation established by the commissioner under this section may not exceed 50 percent of the minimum wage established in
AS 23.10.065
; however, if required to comply with a federal statute or regulation, a higher compensation may be established by the commissioner.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-201__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If compensation established under (a) of this section is 50 percent or more of the minimum wage established in
AS 23.10.065
, the commissioner may deduct the cost of confinement of the prisoner up to the statewide average cost of confinement before disbursements are made under (c) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-201__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall disburse compensation received under (a) of this section, after any deduction required by (b) of this section, in the following order of priority:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-201__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for support of the prisoner's dependents, if any;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-201__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to reimburse the state for compensation awarded under
AS 18.67
resulting from the prisoner's criminal conduct;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-201__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to pay a civil judgment resulting from the prisoner's criminal conduct;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-201__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to pay a restitution or fine of the prisoner ordered by a sentencing court;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-201__subsec_c__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for the payment of fees for the prisoner's utilities services under
AS 33.30.017
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-201__subsec_c__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for the purchase of clothing and commissary items for the prisoner's personal use.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-201__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A prisoner's compensation remaining after any deductions under (b) of this section and disbursements under (c) of this section is to be credited to the prisoner and, except as provided in (e) of this section, must be retained by the department for the primary purpose of being available to the prisoner at the time of release. The commissioner shall maintain individual prisoner accounts for those earnings. The commissioner may, however, permit the prisoner to draw on a portion of that money for other purposes that the commissioner considers appropriate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-201__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a prisoner escapes, a portion of the retained compensation of the prisoner, as determined by the commissioner, is to be forfeited. The commissioner shall deposit forfeited compensation in the general fund.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-201__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except for execution by the state under
AS 09.38.030
(f), only the prisoner compensation retained by the commissioner under (d) of this section is subject to lien, attachment, garnishment, execution, or similar procedures to encumber money or property.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-211">
            <num>33.30.211</num>
            <heading>Transmission of documents.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-30-211__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When a prisoner is admitted to a correctional facility, a copy of the commitment shall be delivered with the prisoner as evidence of the authority of the correctional facility to hold the prisoner.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-211__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When a person is sentenced to a term of imprisonment, copies of the pre-sentence report, sentencing report prepared under
AS 12.55.025
, and any other information of the probation office or of the court that may affect the person's rehabilitation shall be transmitted to the superintendent of the correctional facility in which the prisoner will be confined.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-211__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall adopt regulations providing for the security, confidentiality, and use of documents transmitted under (b) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-216">
            <num>33.30.216</num>
            <heading>Copies of records for child support purposes.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 33.30.216.   Copies of records for child support purposes.
If a copy of a record prepared or maintained by or on behalf of the commissioner for a person in the custody of the commissioner is requested by the child support services agency created in
AS 25.27.010
, or the child support enforcement agency of another state, the official custodian of the record shall provide the requesting agency with a certified copy of the record. If the record is prepared or maintained in an electronic data base, the official custodian of the record may provide the requesting agency with a copy of the electronic record and a statement certifying its contents. The agency receiving information under this section may use the information only for child support purposes authorized under law.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-221">
            <num>33.30.221</num>
            <heading>Superintendent of correctional facility may administer oaths and acknowledgments.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 33.30.221.   Superintendent of correctional facility may administer oaths and acknowledgments.
The superintendent of a correctional facility or the superintendent's assistant may administer oaths to and take acknowledgments from a prisoner, but may not request or accept compensation from a prisoner for acts performed under this section.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-231">
            <num>33.30.231</num>
            <heading>Telephone access and monitoring inside correctional institutions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-30-231__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A prisoner shall have reasonable access to a telephone except when access is suspended as punishment for conviction of a rule infraction or pending a hearing for a rule infraction involving telephone abuse.  A suspension under this subsection must be reasonable in length and may not prohibit telephone communication between the prisoner and an attorney or between the prisoner and the office of the ombudsman.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-231__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 3 ch 56 SLA 1990.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-231__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding
AS 42.20.300
and  42.20.310, in order to preserve the security and orderly administration of the correctional facility and to protect the public, the commissioner shall monitor or record the telephone conversations of prisoners. The commissioner shall post a warning by each telephone informing prisoners that calls may be monitored or recorded. The monitoring or recording may be conducted on all calls or selectively or in some other limited manner as determined by the commissioner to be appropriate. A recording of a telephone call made under this subsection shall be kept confidential, and access to the recording and its contents is limited to persons who are acting within the scope of their official duties and whose access to specific recordings has been authorized by the facility superintendent. A telephone call between an attorney and a prisoner or between the office of the ombudsman and a prisoner may not be monitored or recorded except when authorized by a court.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-231__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (a) of this section, the department may contract under
AS 36.30
for telephone services for use by a prisoner.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-241">
            <num>33.30.241</num>
            <heading>Effect of judgment of conviction on civil rights.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-30-241__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who is convicted of a felony involving moral turpitude as defined in
AS 15.80.010
is disqualified from voting in a state or municipal election until the person's unconditional discharge.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-241__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who is convicted of a felony is disqualified from serving as a juror until the person's unconditional discharge.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-241__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section unconditional discharge has the meaning given in
AS 12.55.185
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-251">
            <num>33.30.251</num>
            <heading>Disposal of abandoned personal property.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-30-251__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (b) of this section, it is the obligation of each person committed to the custody of the commissioner to provide for the appropriate disposition of all of the person's property remaining at a correctional facility within 90 days of the date of the person's release or transfer from the correction facility.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-251__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall provide for the shipment to the receiving facility of a reasonable amount of the prisoner's property, as determined by the commissioner, when the prisoner is transferred from one correctional facility to another.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-251__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A prisoner's personal property that remains at a correctional facility after 90 days from the date of the prisoner's release or transfer is considered abandoned, and shall be delivered to the Department of Administration for disposal under
AS 44.68.110
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-251__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The state is not liable for any loss or damage to personal property properly determined to be abandoned under (c) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-261">
            <num>33.30.261</num>
            <heading>Excess money as contraband.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-30-261__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A prisoner who possesses money in an amount greater than that permitted by the commissioner is subject to disciplinary sanctions under regulations adopted by the commissioner.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-261__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Money in the possession of a prisoner in an amount greater than that permitted by the commissioner is contraband. If, after a hearing under regulations adopted by the commissioner, a prisoner is found to have been in possession of contraband under this section, the contraband shall be forfeited and deposited into the general fund.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-271">
            <num>33.30.271</num>
            <heading>Forfeiture of property.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 33.30.271.   Forfeiture of property.
A conviction of a person for a crime does not work a forfeiture of property, except in cases where a forfeiture is expressly provided by law.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-281">
            <num>33.30.281</num>
            <heading>Crime against sentenced prisoner.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 33.30.281.   Crime against sentenced prisoner.
A person who commits a crime against a sentenced prisoner is punishable as if the prisoner was not sentenced and incarcerated.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-291">
            <num>33.30.291</num>
            <heading>Treaties.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 33.30.291.   Treaties.
If a treaty in effect between the United States and a foreign country provides for the transfer or exchange of prisoners sentenced to serve a term of incarceration to the country where they are citizens or nationals, the commissioner may, on behalf of the state and subject to the terms of the treaty, consent to the transfer or exchange of prisoners and take any other action necessary to initiate the participation of the state in the treaty.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-292">
            <num>33.30.292</num>
            <heading>Designation of victims' representative.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 33.30.292.   Designation of victims' representative.
If more than one person who qualifies as a victim under
AS 12.55.185
requests notice under this chapter, the commissioner shall designate one person for purposes of receiving the notice required and of exercising the rights granted by this chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-295">
            <num>33.30.295</num>
            <heading>Review of prisoner disciplinary decisions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-30-295__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A prisoner may obtain judicial review by the superior court of a final disciplinary decision by the department only if the prisoner alleges specific facts establishing a violation of the prisoner's fundamental constitutional rights that prejudiced the prisoner's right to a fair adjudication. An appeal shall be commenced by the prisoner filing a notice of appeal and other required documents in accordance with
AS 09.19
and the applicable rules of court governing administrative appeals that do not conflict with
AS 09.19
. Unless the appeal is not accepted for filing under
AS 09.19.010
or is dismissed under
AS 09.19.020
, a record of the proceedings shall be prepared by the department, consisting of the original papers and exhibits submitted in the disciplinary process and a cassette tape of the disciplinary hearing. The record shall be prepared and transmitted in accordance with the applicable rules of court governing administrative appeals.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-295__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A disciplinary decision may not be reversed</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-295__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>unless the court finds that the prisoner's fundamental constitutional rights were violated in the course of the disciplinary process, and that the violation prejudiced the prisoner's right to a fair adjudication;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-295__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>because the department failed to follow hearing requirements set out in state statutes and regulations, unless the prisoner was prejudiced by the denial of a right guaranteed by the Alaska Constitution or United States Constitution; if such prejudice is found, the court shall enter judgment as provided in (c) of this section and remand the case to the department; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-295__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>because of insufficient evidence if the record described in (a) of this section shows that the disciplinary decision was based on some evidence that could support the decision reached.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-30-295__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The court shall enter judgment setting aside or affirming the disciplinary decision without limiting or controlling the discretion vested in the department to allocate resources within the department and to control security and administration within the prison system.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-30-901">
            <num>33.30.901</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-30-901__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>under
AS 47.12.030
, 47.12.065, or 47.12.100, the minor has been charged, prosecuted, or convicted as an adult; or
(ii) under
AS 47.12.160
(e), the minor has been ordered transferred to the custody of the commissioner;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-901__subsec_i__subsec_13">
                <num>(13)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>sex offender or child kidnapper, sex offense, and child kidnapping have the meanings given in
AS 12.63.100
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-901__subsec_i__subsec_14">
                <num>(14)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>temporary commitment means detention of a person for any period under authority of state law, but does not include confinement upon conviction and judgment of a court of this state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-30-901__subsec_i__subsec_15">
                <num>(15)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>victim has the meaning given in
AS 12.55.185
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>