<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-19/chapter-25"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-19/chapter-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="19.25"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-19/chapter-25/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-19/chapter-25/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-19/chapter-25/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-19/chapter-25/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_19">
        <num>19</num>
        <heading>Highways and Ferries</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_19__chp_25">
          <num>25</num>
          <heading>Utilities, Advertising, Encroachments, and Memorials</heading>
          <section eId="sec_19-25-010">
            <num>19.25.010</num>
            <heading>Use of rights-of-way for utilities.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.25.010.   Use of rights-of-way for utilities.
A utility facility may be constructed, placed, or maintained across, along, over, under, or within a state right-of-way only in accordance with regulations adopted by the department and if authorized by a written permit issued by the department.  The department may charge a fee for a permit issued under this section.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-25-020">
            <num>19.25.020</num>
            <heading>Relocation of utilities incident to highway projects.</heading>
            <subsection eId="19-25-020__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If, incident to the construction of a highway project, the department determines and orders that a utility facility located across, along, over, under, or within a state right-of-way must be changed, relocated, or removed, the utility owning or maintaining the facility shall change, relocate, or remove it in accordance with the order.  The order must provide a reasonable time period for compliance.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-25-020__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the utility facility is not changed, relocated, or removed in accordance with the order, the facility becomes an unauthorized encroachment and may be disposed of in accordance with
AS 19.25.240
 19.25.250.  In addition, the owner of the facility shall indemnify the state for any amount for which the state may be liable to a contractor by reason of the encroachment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-25-020__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The cost of change, relocation, or removal necessitated by highway construction is a cost of highway construction to be paid in accordance with
AS 19.59.001</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="19-25-020__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>as follows:</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="19-25-020__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>by the department as a cost of highway construction, if the utility facility is installed or authorized under a utility permit or a regulation after June 11, 1986, and is installed in the location specified in the permit;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="19-25-020__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>by the department as a cost of highway construction, if the facility was installed before June 11, 1986, under a utility permit issued on or after July 1, 1960, and is in the location specified in the permit;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="19-25-020__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>by the department as a cost of highway construction, if the utility facility was installed before July 1, 1960, or before the road became part of the state highway system;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="19-25-020__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>by the department as a cost of highway construction, if the utility permit that requires the utility to pay the relocation cost was issued more than five years before the contract for the highway construction project was first advertised;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="19-25-020__subsec_c__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>by the utility in all other cases, unless the commissioner finds it is in the public interest for the cost to be paid by the department.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-25-020__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If requested by a municipality, the department shall implement this chapter by requiring to the maximum extent possible location underground of electric power transmission lines within the municipality.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-25-075">
            <num>19.25.075</num>
            <heading>Findings and intent of the people of the State of Alaska.</heading>
            <subsection eId="19-25-075__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The people of the State of Alaska find that the presence of billboards visible from Alaska's highways endangers Alaska's uniqueness and its scenic beauty.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-25-075__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>It is the intent of the people of the State of Alaska that Alaska shall forever remain free of billboards.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-25-080">
            <num>19.25.080</num>
            <heading>Purpose.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.25.080.   Purpose.
The purposes of
AS 19.25.080
 19.25.180 are
(1) to protect the public safety and the welfare of persons using the highways of the state by having outdoor advertising signs, displays, and devices along the highways controlled;
(2) to prevent unreasonable distraction of operators of motor vehicles; to prevent confusion with regard to traffic lights, signs, or signals, or other interference with the effectiveness of traffic regulations, and to promote the safety, convenience, and enjoyment of travel on, and protection of the public investment in, highways in this state; to preserve and enhance the natural scenic beauty or aesthetic features of the highways and adjacent areas; and to attract tourists;
(3) to regulate outdoor advertising signs, displays, and devices in areas adjacent to the rights-of-way of the interstate, primary, and secondary systems within this state in accordance with this chapter and the regulations adopted under this chapter;
(4) to provide that outdoor advertising signs, displays, and devices that are not in conformity with the requirements of this chapter are a public nuisance;
(5) to provide a statutory basis for regulation of outdoor advertising signs, displays, and devices consistent with the public policy declared by the Congress relating to areas within and adjacent to the right-of-way of a highway of the interstate, primary, or secondary systems.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-25-090">
            <num>19.25.090</num>
            <heading>Outdoor advertising prohibited.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.25.090.   Outdoor advertising prohibited.
Except as provided in
AS 19.25.105
, all outdoor advertising is prohibited.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-25-105">
            <num>19.25.105</num>
            <heading>Limitations of outdoor advertising signs, displays, and devices.</heading>
            <subsection eId="19-25-105__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Outdoor advertising may not be erected or maintained within 660 feet of the nearest edge of the right-of-way and visible from the main-traveled way of the interstate, primary, or secondary highways in this state except the following:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="19-25-105__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>directional and other official signs and notices which include, but are not limited to, signs and notices pertaining to natural wonders, scenic and historic attractions, which are required or authorized by law, and which shall conform to federal standards for interstate and primary systems;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="19-25-105__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>signs, displays, and devices advertising the sale or lease of property upon which they are located or advertising activities conducted on the property;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="19-25-105__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>signs determined by the state, subject to concurrence of the United States Department of Transportation, to be landmark signs, including signs on farm structures or natural surfaces of historic or artistic significance, the preservation of which would be consistent with the provisions of this chapter;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="19-25-105__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>directional signs and notices pertaining to schools;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="19-25-105__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>advertising on bus benches or bus shelters, and adjacent trash receptacles, if the state determines that the advertising conforms to local, state, and federal standards for interstate and primary highways.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-25-105__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 21 ch 94 SLA 1980.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-25-105__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Outdoor advertising may not be erected or maintained beyond 660 feet of the nearest edge of the right-of-way of the main traveled way of the interstate, primary, or secondary highways in this state with the purpose of their message being read from that travel way except those outdoor advertising signs, displays, or devices allowed under (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-25-105__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Outdoor advertising may not be erected or maintained within the right-of-way of an interstate, primary, or secondary highway except that outdoor advertising</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="19-25-105__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>on bus benches and bus shelters, and adjacent trash receptacles, located within the right-of-way under the authority of a permit issued under
AS 19.25.200
is allowed if the bus benches or bus shelters are located within a borough or unified municipality and the buses that stop at that location operate during the entire year; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="19-25-105__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>present in the right-of-way on January 1, 2005, may remain, subject only to removals required by federal highway funding requirements imposed on the state by federal law, until or unless an encroachment permit for the outdoor advertising is denied under
AS 19.25.200</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-25-105__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 4 1998 Ballot Measure No. 5.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-25-130">
            <num>19.25.130</num>
            <heading>Penalty for violation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.25.130.   Penalty for violation.
A person who violates
AS 19.25.080
 19.25.180, or a regulation adopted under
AS 19.25.080
 19.25.180, is guilty of a misdemeanor and upon conviction is punishable by a fine of not less than $50 nor more than $5,000.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-25-140">
            <num>19.25.140</num>
            <heading>Compensation for removal of advertising.</heading>
            <subsection eId="19-25-140__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department is authorized to acquire by purchase, gift, or condemnation all advertising devices and any property rights pertaining to them when the advertising devices are required to be removed under
AS 19.25.150
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-25-140__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Damages resulting from a taking in eminent domain shall be ascertained in the manner provided by law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-25-150">
            <num>19.25.150</num>
            <heading>Unlawful advertising.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.25.150.   Unlawful advertising.
An advertising sign, display, or device that violates the provisions of
AS 19.25.080
 19.25.180 is a public nuisance. The department shall give 30 days' notice, by certified mail, to the owner of the land on which the advertising sign, display, or device is located, ordering its removal if it is prohibited by
AS 19.25.080
 19.25.180 or ordering the owner to cause it to conform to regulations if it is authorized by
AS 19.25.080
 19.25.180. If the owner of the property fails to comply within 30 days as required in the notice, the department shall remove the outdoor advertising sign, display, or device at the expense of the owner of the land or the person who erected it.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-25-160">
            <num>19.25.160</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.25.160.   Definitions.
In
AS 19.25.080
 19.25.180,
(1) billboards means any signboards, signs, displays, notices, or forms of outdoor advertising that do not strictly comply with the provisions of
AS 19.25.075
 19.25.180, or with any permit or permits issued pursuant to
AS 19.25.075
 19.25.180;
(2) interstate system means that portion of the National System of Interstate and Defense Highways located in this state, as officially designated, or as may hereafter be so designated, by the commissioner, and approved by the secretary of transportation (or by the secretary of commerce before the effective date of the transfer of functions under Public Law 89-670 (80 Stat. 931)), under the provisions of 23 U.S.C.;
(3) outdoor advertising includes any outdoor sign, display, or device used to advertise, attract attention, or inform and which is visible to a person on the main-traveled way of a highway of the interstate, primary, or secondary systems in this state, whether by printing, writing, painting, picture, light, drawing, or whether by the use of figures or objects, or a combination of these, or any other thing designed, intended, or used to advertise, inform, or attract attention;
(4) primary system or secondary system means that portion of connected main highways, as officially designated, or as may hereafter be so designated, by the commissioner, and approved by the secretary of transportation (or by the secretary of commerce before the effective date of the transfer of functions under Public Law 89-670 (80 Stat. 931)), under the provisions of 23 U.S.C.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-25-170">
            <num>19.25.170</num>
            <heading>Agreements with the United States; regulations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.25.170.   Agreements with the United States; regulations.
The department is authorized to enter into agreements in conformity with the provisions of this title with the United States Secretary of Transportation as provided by 23 U.S.C. relating to the control of outdoor advertising signs, displays, and devices in areas adjacent to interstate and primary systems and to take action in the name of the state to comply with the terms of the agreements, and to adopt required regulations.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-25-180">
            <num>19.25.180</num>
            <heading>Applicability of municipal enactments.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.25.180.   Applicability of municipal enactments.
Notwithstanding
AS 19.25.080
 19.25.180, a municipality may enact ordinances that regulate outdoor advertising in a way that is more restrictive than the provisions of
AS 19.25.080
 19.25.180.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-25-200">
            <num>19.25.200</num>
            <heading>Encroachment permits; liability.</heading>
            <subsection eId="19-25-200__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An encroachment may be constructed, placed, changed, or maintained across or along a highway, but only in accordance with regulations adopted by the department. An encroachment may not be constructed, placed, maintained, or changed until it is authorized by a written permit issued by the department, unless the department provides otherwise by regulation. The department may charge a fee for a permit issued under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-25-200__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The provisions under (a) of this section do not apply to a mailbox or a newspaper box attached to a mailbox.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-25-200__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon receipt of an application, the department shall issue an encroachment permit to a private person, a government agency acting in a business capacity, or an owner or lessee of land contiguous to the right-of-way for an encroachment that, on January 1, 2005, was present within the right-of-way of an interstate, primary, or secondary highway and is not authorized by a written encroachment permit if the department finds that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="19-25-200__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the encroachment does not pose a risk to the traveling public, and the integrity and safety of the highway is not compromised;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="19-25-200__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the applicant has demonstrated the encroachment was erected with the good faith belief it was lawful to erect and maintain the encroachment in its location;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="19-25-200__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the denial of the encroachment permit would pose a hardship on the person, agency, owner, or lessee who applies for the permit;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="19-25-200__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the issuance of an encroachment permit will not cause a break in access control for the highway;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="19-25-200__subsec_c__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the land will not be necessary for a highway construction project during the initial term of the permit; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="19-25-200__subsec_c__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>issuance of a permit is consistent with federal requirements regarding encroachments on federal-aid highways.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-25-200__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may not remove an encroachment present within the right-of-way of an interstate, primary, or secondary highway on January 1, 2005, unless the owner, occupant, or person in possession of the encroachment, or any other person causing or permitting the encroachment to exist, receives the notice provided under
AS 19.25.230
and is informed of the application process for an encroachment permit under (c) of this section. The department may charge a fee, not to exceed $100, for an encroachment permit issued under (c) of this section. An encroachment permit issued under (c) of this section may contain reasonable conditions to protect the traveling public, the safety and integrity of a highway's design, and the public interest.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-25-200__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The land area described in an encroachment permit may not be used to meet minimum requirements for a contiguous land use under applicable municipal land use standards or under applicable regulations adopted by the Department of Environmental Conservation. The use of land contiguous to the land area described in the permit must satisfy the applicable municipal land use standards and applicable regulations adopted by the Department of Environmental Conservation without regard to the land area described in the permit.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-25-200__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The issuance of an encroachment permit under
AS 19.25.200
 19.25.250 does not entitle the owner, occupant, or person in possession of the encroachment or any other person to a payment of compensation or of relocation benefits under
AS 34.60
if the encroachment permit is revoked or not renewed or if the encroachment must be changed, relocated, or removed under
AS 19.25.200
 19.25.250.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-25-200__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The state is not liable for damage to, or damage or injury resulting from the presence of, an encroachment in the right-of-way of a state highway.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-25-210">
            <num>19.25.210</num>
            <heading>Relocation or removal of encroachment.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.25.210.   Relocation or removal of encroachment.
If, incidental to the construction or maintenance of a state highway, the department determines and orders that an encroachment previously authorized by written permit must be changed, relocated, or removed, the owner of the encroachment shall change, relocate, or remove it at no expense to the state, except as provided in
AS 19.25.020
, within a reasonable time set by the department.  If the owner does not change, relocate, or remove an encroachment within the time set by the department, the encroachment shall be considered an unauthorized encroachment and subject to the provisions of
AS 19.25.220
 19.25.250.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-25-220">
            <num>19.25.220</num>
            <heading>Unauthorized encroachments.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.25.220.   Unauthorized encroachments.
If an unauthorized encroachment exists in, on, under, or over a state highway, the department may require the removal of the encroachment in the manner provided in
AS 19.25.230
 19.25.250.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-25-230">
            <num>19.25.230</num>
            <heading>Notice of removal.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.25.230.   Notice of removal.
Except as otherwise provided in
AS 19.25.200
, 19.25.210, and 19.25.240, notice shall be given the owner, occupant, or person in possession of the encroachment, or to any other person causing or permitting the encroachment to exist, by serving upon any of them a notice demanding the removal of the encroachment.  The notice must describe the encroachment complained of with reasonable certainty as to its character and location.  Service of the notice may be made by certified mail.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-25-240">
            <num>19.25.240</num>
            <heading>Summary removal.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.25.240.   Summary removal.
The department may at any time remove from a state highway or road an encroachment that obstructs or prevents the use of the highway or road by the public.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-25-250">
            <num>19.25.250</num>
            <heading>Removal after noncompliance; removal expense.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.25.250.   Removal after noncompliance; removal expense.
After a failure of the owner of an encroachment to comply with a notice or demand of the department under the provisions of
AS 19.25.200
, 19.25.210 and 19.25.230, the department may remove, or cause to be removed, the encroachment, and the owner of the encroachment shall pay to the department
(1) the expenses of the removal of the encroachment;
(2) all costs and expenses paid by the state as a result of a claim or claims filed against the state by third parties for damages due to delays because the encroachment was not changed, removed, or relocated according to the order of the department; and
(3) costs and expenses of suit.
Article 4. Roadside Memorials.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-25-260">
            <num>19.25.260</num>
            <heading>Roadside memorials permitted.</heading>
            <subsection eId="19-25-260__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding
AS 19.25.090
, 19.25.105, and 19.25.200, a person may, for a period of not more than two years, place in the right-of-way but outside of the traveled way of a state highway a temporary memorial for a decedent who died as a result of a traffic accident, or other incident in the right-of-way, at or reasonably near the site where the memorial is located.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-25-260__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A memorial must not interfere with the use of the highway, with other uses of the right-of-way, with the visibility of directional and other official signs and notices, or with highway safety, construction, or maintenance.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-25-260__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The person who places a memorial in the right-of-way of a state highway shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="19-25-260__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>post the person's contact information on the memorial;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="19-25-260__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>inform the department of the location within seven days of placement of the memorial; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="19-25-260__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide the person's contact information to the department.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-25-260__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not place a political or commercial message on a memorial.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-25-260__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not place reflective material or another item on a memorial if that material or item would be distracting to drivers and other users of the right-of-way.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-25-260__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The state is not liable for damage to, or damage or injury resulting from the presence of, a memorial in the right-of-way of a state highway.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-25-260__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, memorial means decorations, flags, flowers, and other lightweight objects or ornamentation commonly used at funerals or at gravesides as a tribute to a decedent.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-25-270">
            <num>19.25.270</num>
            <heading>Relocation or removal of memorial.</heading>
            <subsection eId="19-25-270__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If, incidental to the construction or maintenance of a state highway, the department determines that a memorial authorized by
AS 19.25.260
must be changed, relocated, or removed, the person who placed the memorial within the right-of-way shall change, relocate, or remove the memorial at no expense to the state within a reasonable time set by the department. If the owner does not change, relocate, or remove a memorial within the time set by the department, the memorial is an unauthorized encroachment and subject to the provisions of
AS 19.25.230
 19.25.250.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-25-270__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a memorial in the right-of-way of a state highway does not comply with the requirements of
AS 19.25.260
, the memorial is an unauthorized encroachment. The department may require removal of the encroachment in the manner provided in
AS 19.25.230
 19.25.250.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>