<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-25/chapter-27"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-25/chapter-27"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="25.27"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-25/chapter-27/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-25/chapter-27/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-25/chapter-27/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-25/chapter-27/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_25">
        <num>25</num>
        <heading>Marital and Domestic Relations</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_25__chp_27">
          <num>27</num>
          <heading>Child Support Services Agency</heading>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-010">
            <num>25.27.010</num>
            <heading>Creation of child support services agency.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.27.010.   Creation of child support services agency.
There is created in the Department of Revenue the child support services agency.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-020">
            <num>25.27.020</num>
            <heading>Duties and responsibilities of the agency.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-27-020__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The agency shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-020__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>seek enforcement of child support orders of the state in other jurisdictions and shall obtain, enforce, and administer the orders in this state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-020__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>adopt regulations to carry out the purposes of this chapter and
AS 25.25
, including regulations that establish
(A) procedures for hearings conducted under
AS 25.27.170
and for administrative enforcement of support orders;
(B) subject to
AS 25.27.025
and to federal law, a uniform rate of interest on arrearages of support that shall be charged the obligor upon notice if child support payments are 10 or more days overdue or if payment is made by a check backed by insufficient funds; however, an obligor may not be charged interest on late payment of a child support obligation, other than a payment on arrearages, if the obligor is</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-020__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>employed and income is being withheld from the obligor's wages under an income withholding order;
(ii) receiving unemployment compensation and child support obligations are being withheld from the obligor's unemployment payments under
AS 23.20.401
; or
(iii) receiving compensation for disabilities under
AS 23.30
and child support obligations are being withheld from the obligor's compensation payments;
(C) procedures for establishing and disestablishing paternity under
AS 25.27.165
and 25.27.166, including procedures for hearings; and
(D) procedures under which the agency shall enter into contracts or agreements with financial institutions, including brokerage houses, insurance companies, and other companies providing individual investment, transaction, or deposit accounts, doing business in the state to develop and operate an automated data match system as required by 42 U.S.C. 666(a)(17); the agency may pay a reasonable fee to a financial institution for conducting a data match under a contract or agreement under this subparagraph; the fee may not exceed the actual costs incurred by the financial institution for conducting the data match;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-020__subsec_i__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>administer and enforce
AS 25.25
(Uniform Interstate Family Support Act);</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-020__subsec_i__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establish, enforce, and administer child support obligations administratively under this chapter;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-020__subsec_i__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>administer the state plan required under 42 U.S.C. 651  669 (Title IV-D, Social Security Act) as amended;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-020__subsec_i__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>disburse support payments collected by the agency to the obligee, together with interest charged under (2)(B) of this subsection;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-020__subsec_i__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establish and enforce administratively under this chapter, or through the superior courts of the state, child support orders from other jurisdictions pertaining to obligors within the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-020__subsec_i__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>enforce and administer spousal support orders if a spousal support obligation has been established with respect to the spouse and if the support obligation established with respect to the child of that spouse is also being administered;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-020__subsec_i__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>obtain a medical support order that meets the requirements of
AS 25.27.060</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-020__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and 25.27.063;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-020__subsec_c__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>act on behalf of the Department of Health in the enforcement of
AS 47.07.025</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-020__subsec_c__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establish or disestablish, administratively under
AS 25.27.165
 25.27.166 or through court action, the paternity of a child;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-020__subsec_c__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>promptly provide to the Bureau of Vital Statistics, in a format approved by the bureau, any final agency decision administratively establishing or disestablishing the paternity of a child born in this state; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-020__subsec_c__subsec_13">
                <num>(13)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>act as the central registry for all child support orders and exchange information as required by federal law.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-020__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In determining the amount of money an obligor must pay to satisfy the obligor's immediate duty of support, the agency shall consider all payments made by the obligor directly to the obligee or to the obligee's custodian before the time the obligor is ordered to make payments through the agency. After the obligor is ordered to make payments through the agency, the agency may not consider direct payments made to the obligee or the obligee's custodian unless the obligor provides clear and convincing evidence of the payment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-020__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If admitted to the practice of law in the state, the director of the agency, or the director's designee, shall sign a complaint or other pleadings on behalf of the agency in an action to establish or enforce a support obligation under this chapter in which the agency is not represented by the attorney general.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-020__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The agency may issue an administrative order or request a court order that requires an individual in arrears under an order of support for a child who is receiving assistance under
AS 47.07
, or under
AS 47.25.310
 47.25.420 or a successor program, or for a child whose parent, guardian, or designee of the parent or guardian has applied for aid from the agency under
AS 25.27.100
, to make payments according to an approved payment plan or, if the individual is not incapacitated, to participate in appropriate work activities.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-020__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To the extent required by federal law and as necessary for locating individuals for child support purposes, the agency, the child support enforcement agency of another state, or the federal government is entitled to have access to information used by the Department of Public Safety or a successor agency to locate an individual for purposes relating to motor vehicles or law enforcement.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-020__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The agency shall, by regulation, establish procedures and standards for the forgiveness of an arrearage owed to the state under
AS 25.27.120
. The agency may forgive arrears under this section, with the approval of the commissioner and without the approval of the Department of Law, if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-020__subsec_f__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the obligor
(A) has or obtains employment for which income withholding is initiated under
AS 25.27.250
within 60 days after the date the obligor is approved for the forgiveness program;
(B) enrolls in and successfully completes an employment training program approved by the agency and obtains employment for which income withholding is initiated under
AS 25.27.250
within 30 days after completion of the employment training program; or
(C) enters into an agreement with the agency for alternative payment procedures if the agency determines that there are unusual circumstances justifying a waiver of income withholding;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-020__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the obligor is in compliance with additional requirements and limitations imposed by the agency by regulation to assure that forgiveness of the arrearage is in the best interest of the child and of the state; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-020__subsec_f__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the obligor makes monthly payments pursuant to a payment agreement approved by the agency; if the obligor misses more than two monthly payments in a calendar year or more than two consecutive payments without approval of the agency for good cause, the obligor is not eligible to continue in the arrears forgiveness program under this section.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-020__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>During each year in which an obligor complies with the requirements for the forgiveness of an arrearage under (f) of this section and any regulations adopted by the agency under that subsection, the agency may forgive up to 20 percent of the total arrearage owed to the state under
AS 25.27.120
, including any interest owed on that debt. For purposes of determining the amount of the forgiveness, the arrears shall be calculated as of the date the obligor is approved for participation in the forgiveness program.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-020__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The agency may establish by regulation requirements and limitations on eligibility in addition to those stated in (f) and (g) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-022">
            <num>25.27.022</num>
            <heading>Establishment and enforcement requests from other states.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-27-022__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The agency may act, under the laws of this state, upon requests from similar state agencies in other states that operate child support enforcement programs under 42 U.S.C. 651  669 (Title IV-D Social Security Act) to establish or disestablish paternity and to establish and enforce against obligors within this state support obligations determined in other states.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-022__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except for requests for assistance made under (c) of this section or
AS 25.25.501
, requests from child support enforcement agencies in other states shall be made by application containing the information that this state's agency requires and including written authorization from the requesting state agency and the obligee for this state's agency to initiate necessary action.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-022__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Requests from a child support agency of another state for assistance in enforcing support orders through high-volume automated administrative enforcement may be made by electronic or other means and must include the information required by 42 U.S.C. 666(a)(14).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-022__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An employer receiving an income withholding order from a child support agency of another state shall comply with the choice of law provisions of
AS 25.25.502
(d), 25.25.503, and 42 U.S.C. 666(b)(6)(A)(i)(V).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-025">
            <num>25.27.025</num>
            <heading>Rate of interest.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.27.025.   Rate of interest.
The rate of interest imposed under
AS 25.27.020
(a)(2)(B) shall be six percent a year or a lesser rate that is the maximum rate of interest permitted to be imposed under federal law.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-030">
            <num>25.27.030</num>
            <heading>Establishment of fund.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.27.030.   Establishment of fund.
There is established in the state general fund a continuing, revolving, reserve account to receive collections and make the authorized disbursements of the agency.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-040">
            <num>25.27.040</num>
            <heading>Determination of paternity.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-27-040__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The agency may appear on behalf of minor children or their mother or legal custodian or the state and initiate efforts to have the paternity of children born out of wedlock determined by the court. When the agency is a party to a court action in which paternity is contested, it shall request and pay for genetic testing and procedures under
AS 25.20.050</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-040__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and may recover the costs of the testing as provided in
AS 25.20.050
(f).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-040__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The agency may not attempt to establish paternity in any case</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-040__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>involving incest or forcible rape, unless the mother of the child is legally competent and requests the establishment of paternity; in this paragraph, forcible rape means sexual assault in the first degree under
AS 11.41.410
or a conviction under a law or ordinance from another jurisdiction with similar elements; forcible rape includes adjudications of delinquency for acts with elements similar to
AS 11.41.410
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-040__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>when legal proceedings for adoption are pending; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-040__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>when it would not be in the best interests of the children or the state.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-040__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the agency is a party in a court action in which paternity is contested, the agency shall move for a default judgment in a case that meets the conditions specified in
AS 25.20.050
(g).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-045">
            <num>25.27.045</num>
            <heading>Determination of support obligation.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-27-045__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or (b).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-050">
            <num>25.27.050</num>
            <heading>Legal assistance.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.27.050.   Legal assistance.
The agency shall contract with the Department of Law to provide needed legal services.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-060">
            <num>25.27.060</num>
            <heading>Order of support.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-27-060__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless otherwise provided under
AS 25.24.910
or
AS 25.27.061
, an order of support establishes a relationship by which the custodian of the child is the administrator for the purposes of administering child support on behalf of the child. The court shall carefully consider the need for support, the ability of both parents to meet such support obligations, the extent to which the parents supported the child before divorce, and the economic ability of the parents to pay after separation and divorce. The court shall also consider the effect on the support obligation of a change in custodian. The need of the child for support shall be considered regardless of the sex of the parent awarded custody of the child.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-060__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 21 ch 126 SLA 1977.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-060__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In a court or administrative proceeding where the support of a minor child is at issue, the court or agency, as applicable, may order either parent or both parents to pay the amount necessary for support, maintenance, nurture, and education of the child. Regardless of whether a support order for periodic payments is issued, the court or agency shall issue a medical support order, a cash medical support order, or both. The medical support order shall require health care insurance coverage for the child if health care insurance coverage is available to either parent or both parents for the child at a reasonable cost. The court or agency shall consider whether the child is eligible for services through the Indian Health Service or other insurance coverage before ordering either parent or both parents to provide health care coverage through insurance, cash medical support, or other means or a combination of insurance, cash medical support, or other means. The court or agency shall allocate equally the cost of health care insurance for the child between the parents unless there is good cause to allocate the costs unequally. If the obligor has the duty to make periodic payments for non-medical child support, the obligor's periodic payments shall be decreased by the amount of the other parent's portion of payments for health insurance ordered by the court or agency and actually paid by the obligor. If the obligor has a duty to make periodic payments for non-medical child support, the periodic payments shall be increased by the obligor's portion of payments for health insurance if the other parent is ordered to and actually does obtain and pay for insurance. The court or agency shall allocate equally between the parents the cost of reasonable health care expenses not covered by private insurance unless there is good cause to allocate the costs unequally. One parent shall reimburse the other parent for the first parent's share of the uncovered expenses paid by the parent wit</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-060__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An order for prospective child support may be modified or revoked under
AS 25.24.170
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-061">
            <num>25.27.061</num>
            <heading>Payment of support to 18-year-olds.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.27.061.   Payment of support to 18-year-olds.
A judgment, court order, or order of the agency under this chapter that provides for child support to be paid for the care of an unmarried 18-year-old child who is actively pursuing a high school diploma or an equivalent level of technical or vocational training while living as a dependent with a parent, guardian, or designee of the parent or guardian, may provide for the support to be paid directly to the child upon terms and conditions considered appropriate by the court or agency.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-062">
            <num>25.27.062</num>
            <heading>Income withholding order for support.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-27-062__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless the court or agency is establishing only a medical support order, a judgment, court order, or order of the agency under this chapter providing for support must contain an income withholding order. Except as provided in (m) of this section, the income withholding order must provide for immediate income withholding if the support order is</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-062__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>being enforced by the agency and was issued or modified on or after July 8, 1994; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-062__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>not being enforced by the agency and was issued on or after July 8, 1994.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-062__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An income withholding order must direct the obligor, the obligor's employer, future employer, and any person, political subdivision, or department of the state to withhold money due or to be due the obligor and pay the money to the agency, in an amount determined under (i) of this section. A court that issues a support order on or after July 8, 1994 shall send a copy of the order to the agency.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-062__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Income withholding under a support order that does not require immediate withholding may be initiated under
AS 25.27.150
if the support order is being enforced by the agency, or under (d) of this section if the support order is not being enforced by the agency, if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-062__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the obligor requests withholding;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-062__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the payments that the obligor has failed to make within 30 days of the monthly due date specified in the support order are equal to or greater than the support payable for one month; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-062__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the obligee requests withholding and
(A) the agency approves the request because all or part of the monthly payment of the obligor has been more than 10 days overdue more than one time in the preceding 12 months or there is reason to believe that the obligor might withdraw assets to avoid payment of support; in this paragraph, 10 days overdue means occurring 10 days after the monthly due date specified in a support order; or
(B) the court approves the request for good cause.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-062__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Income withholding under a support order that does not require immediate income withholding and that is not being enforced by the agency may be initiated either by filing a motion with the court and complying with applicable court rules or, if there is a child support arrearage, by making a written request to the agency for immediate income withholding under
AS 25.27.150
. Application to the agency under this subsection may not, by itself, be construed as a request for other services of the agency. If immediate withholding under this subsection is sought through a motion to the court, the court shall order the beginning of income withholding under this subsection if the court finds that any of the grounds in (c)(1), (2), or (3)(B) of this section is satisfied. It is not a defense to a motion based on (c)(2) of this section that less than one full month's payment is past due by 30 days if at least one full month's payment was past due by 30 days on the date the motion was filed. Notice to the obligor of income withholding ordered under this subsection must be given in a manner that complies with court rules. In this subsection, past due by 30 days means unpaid 30 days after the monthly due date specified in the support order.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-062__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The agency or the person who obtains an income withholding order under this chapter shall immediately send a copy of the income withholding order, a copy of the relevant provisions of
AS 25.27.260
and this section, and an explanation of the effect of the statutes to persons who may owe money to an obligor. These items may be served by certified mail, return receipt requested, or they may be served personally by a process server, except that the agency alternatively may send the items by electronic means. An income withholding order made under this chapter is binding upon a person, employer, political subdivision, or department of the state immediately upon receipt of a copy of the income withholding order. A person receiving an income withholding order shall immediately begin withholding the specified amount from the obligor's earnings. The amount withheld shall be sent to the agency within seven business days after the date the amount would otherwise have been paid or credited to the obligor. An employer may, for each payment made under an order, deduct $5 from other wages or salary owed to the obligor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-062__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An employer may not discharge, discipline, or refuse to employ an obligor on the basis of an income withholding order issued under this chapter. If an employer discharges, disciplines, or refuses to employ an obligor because of an income withholding obligation, the court, after notice and hearing, may order reinstatement or restitution to the obligor, or both. A person who violates this subsection or a regulation adopted to implement it, is liable for a civil penalty of not more than $1,000.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-062__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An income withholding order under this chapter has priority over all other attachments, executions, garnishments, or other legal process brought under state law against the same property unless otherwise ordered by the court. An income withholding order is not limited to the wages of an obligor but may include all money owed to the obligor not otherwise exempt by law. Exemptions under
AS 09.38
do not apply to income withholdings under this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-062__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The court may order payment of all court costs that resulted from an income withholding proceeding under this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-062__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An employer shall, to the extent permitted under 15 U.S.C. 1673(b), withhold the current support obligation from an obligor's wages, including the obligor's share, if any, of the premium for health coverage required to be withheld under
AS 25.27.063
(c)(4). An employer shall withhold additional income, to the extent permitted under 15 U.S.C. 1673(b), from an obligor's wages for any support arrearage.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-062__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An employer may combine into a single payment to the agency amounts withheld from more than one obligor if the employer specifies the portion of the payment attributable to each obligor and complies with the time deadlines set out in (e) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-062__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An employer who is withholding income of an obligor under an order that provides that the withheld income shall be paid to the agency shall notify the agency promptly when the obligor gives or receives notice of termination of employment and provide to the agency the obligor's last known home address and the name and address of the obligor's new employer, if known. The employer shall keep a record of the order to withhold income from the obligor for three years after the employer notifies the agency that the obligor has terminated employment. If, within that three-year period, the obligor is reemployed by the former employer, the employer shall immediately implement the order against the obligor's earnings unless the employer has received notice from the agency that the order is no longer applicable to the obligor. If the obligor is reemployed by the former employer after that three-year period, the employer is not required to implement a withholding order against the obligor's earnings until the employer receives a new order to withhold the obligor's income under this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-062__subsec_l">
              <num>(l)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless modified or terminated by the agency or the court, an order to withhold income under this chapter remains in effect, except as provided in (k) of this section, until the support order is satisfied. The agency or court may not terminate or modify an income withholding order solely on the ground that the obligor has paid all arrearages. Upon satisfaction of a support order, if the order is</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-062__subsec_l__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>being enforced by the agency, the agency shall, within 15 working days, notify all persons served by the agency with the income withholding order that withholding is no longer required; if the agency receives money from an obligor under an income withholding order after the underlying support order has been satisfied and the agency was enforcing the support order at the time it became satisfied, the agency shall immediately return the overpayment to the obligor; if the agency fails to return an overpayment as required under this paragraph, the state is liable to the obligor for the amount of the overpayment, plus interest at the rate of six percent a year, and a person to whom the agency erroneously disbursed the overpayment is liable to the state for the amount disbursed, plus interest at the rate of six percent a year;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-062__subsec_l__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>not being enforced by the agency, the obligor shall file a motion in court requesting termination of the withholding order and serve the motion on the obligee; the court shall enter an order terminating the withholding order if the court determines that the support order has been satisfied; the obligor may deliver a copy of the termination order to persons who were served with the income withholding order; when a termination order is entered, the obligee shall, upon request of the obligor, notify the obligor of all persons who have been served with the income withholding order by the obligee.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-062__subsec_m">
              <num>(m)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An income withholding order described in (a)(1)  (2) of this section is not subject to immediate withholding if the support order is</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-062__subsec_m__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>being enforced by the agency and the obligor agrees to keep the agency informed of the obligor's current employer and the availability of employment-related health insurance coverage for the children covered by the support order until the support order is satisfied and
(A) the agency has entered into its record a written agreement between the obligor and the obligee that provides for an alternative arrangement and income withholding has not been terminated previously and subsequently initiated; the agency must also be a party to an agreement under this paragraph if support has been assigned to the state; or
(B) the obligor or obligee demonstrates and the agency, in compliance with applicable federal law, finds good cause not to require immediate income withholding because it would not be in the best interests of the child and, in a case involving the modification of a support order, the obligor has made voluntary support payments under a court or agency order and has not been in arrears in an amount equal to the support payable for one month; in this paragraph, in arrears means failing to make a support payment within 30 days of the monthly due date specified in the order;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-062__subsec_m__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>not being enforced by the agency and the obligor agrees to keep the obligee informed of the obligor's current employer and the availability of employment-related health insurance coverage for the children covered by the support order until the support order is satisfied and
(A) the court finds that (i) a written agreement exists between the obligor and the obligee that provides for an alternative arrangement and (ii) income withholding has not been terminated previously and subsequently initiated; the agency must also be a party to an agreement under this paragraph if support has been assigned to the state; or
(B) the obligor or obligee demonstrates, and the court, in compliance with applicable federal law, finds good cause not to require immediate income withholding because it would not be in the best interests of the child and, in a case involving the modification of a support order, the obligor has made voluntary support payments under a court or agency order and has not been in arrears in an amount equal to the support payable for one month; in this paragraph, in arrears means failing to make a support payment within 30 days of the monthly due date specified in the order; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-062__subsec_m__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an order that involves an obligor who is receiving social security or other disability compensation that includes regular payments to the children who are the subjects of the support order, except to the extent that the payments to the children do not equal the child support due each month.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-062__subsec_n">
              <num>(n)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In calculating the amount of child support to be withheld under an income withholding order, the agency shall give credit to the obligor for the cost to the obligor of medical and dental insurance for the children and educational payments for the children to the extent that the insurance coverage and educational payments are required in the applicable child support order and are actually paid for by the obligor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-063">
            <num>25.27.063</num>
            <heading>Medical support order.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-27-063__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 23 ch 106 SLA 2000.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-063__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a parent who is required to provide health care coverage under a medical support order is eligible for family health coverage through an employer, the court or agency issuing the medical support order shall send a copy of the medical support order to the employer. If the agency has notice that the parent has changed or will be changing employment and is or will be eligible for family health coverage through the new employer, the agency shall send a copy of the medical support order to the new employer.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-063__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An employer who receives a copy of a medical support order under (b) of this section</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-063__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall allow the employee named in the order to enroll the child under the family coverage without regard to restrictions relating to enrollment periods if the child is otherwise eligible and is not already enrolled under the family coverage;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-063__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall, if the employee fails to apply for enrollment of a child under (1) of this subsection, enroll the child under the employee's family coverage upon application by the child's other parent or custodian, the child support services agency, or the Department of Health;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-063__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>may not disenroll or eliminate coverage of the child while the employee is still employed by the employer unless the employer has eliminated family health coverage for all of its employees or has received written evidence that
(A) the employee is no longer required by court order or administrative order to provide the child's insurance coverage; or
(B) the child is or will be enrolled in comparable health coverage through another insurer that will take effect not later than the effective date of the disenrollment or elimination of coverage; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-063__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall withhold from the employee's compensation the employee's share, if any, of premiums for health coverage to the extent permitted under 15 U.S.C. 1673(b) (Consumer Credit Protection Act) and pay the withheld amount to the appropriate insurer; if federal regulations allow the employer to withhold less than the employee's share of the insurance premium, the employer may withhold the lesser amount and pay it to the appropriate insurer.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-065">
            <num>25.27.065</num>
            <heading>Waiver of child support.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-27-065__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A custodian of a child, including a custodial parent, owes a duty to that child to ensure that child support is paid by a noncustodial parent who is obligated to pay it.  An agreement to waive past or future child support, made between an obligor and a person who is entitled to receive support on behalf of an obligee, is not enforceable unless</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-065__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the agreement is put in writing at the time the agreement is made; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-065__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the agreement is signed at the time it is made by both the obligor and the person acting for the obligee.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-065__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the right to receive child support has been assigned to a governmental entity, an agreement under (a) of this section that has not been adopted as an administrative order of the agency is not effective during a period when the obligee is receiving assistance under
AS 47.27
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-065__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In a separation, dissolution, or divorce proceeding, a court may not accept a waiver of support by a custodial parent without proof that the custodial parent can support the needs of the child adequately.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-070">
            <num>25.27.070</num>
            <heading>Order to assign wages for support.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-27-070__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In a proceeding in which the court has ordered either or both parents to pay for the support of a child, the court may, on its own motion or motion of a party or the agency on behalf of a party, after notice and an opportunity for hearing, order either parent or both parents to assign to the custodian of the child that portion of salary or wages of either parent due them currently and in the future sufficient to pay the amount ordered by the court for the support, maintenance, nurture, and education of the child.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-070__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The order of assignment is binding upon an employer upon service of a copy of the order upon the employer and until further order of the court.  The employer may, for each payment made under the order, deduct $1 from other wages or salary owed to the employee.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-070__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The assignment made under court order has priority as against an attachment, execution, or other assignment unless otherwise ordered by the court.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-070__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An employer may not terminate an employee's employment because wages of the employee are subject to an order under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-075">
            <num>25.27.075</num>
            <heading>Employment information.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-27-075__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An employer doing business in the state shall report to the agency the hiring, rehiring, or return to work of each employee. The report shall be made within the time limits set out in (b) of this section. The report must contain the name, address, and social security number of the newly hired employee, the name and address of the employer, and the identifying number assigned to the employer by the United States Department of the Treasury, Internal Revenue Service. Violation of this subsection does not give rise to a private cause of action.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-075__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An employer required to report under (a) of this section shall use the following procedures to make the report:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-075__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if the report is submitted magnetically or electronically, the report shall be made in a format mutually agreed upon by the employer and the agency; an employer reporting under this paragraph shall make two transmissions a month, not less than 12 days nor more than 16 days apart; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-075__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if the report is not submitted magnetically or electronically, the report shall be made on a United States Department of the Treasury, Internal Revenue Service, W-4 form or, at the option of the employer, on an equivalent form; an employer reporting under this paragraph shall make the report to the agency not later than 20 days after the date of the hiring, rehiring, or return to work of the employee; the report shall be transmitted by the employer by first class mail.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-075__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An employer that does business in this state and that has employees in at least one other state is not required to comply with (a) of this section if, in compliance with the laws of that state, the employer</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-075__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>submits timely magnetic or electronic reports of hires, rehires, or returns to work to the state directory of new hires of another state in which the employer has employees; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-075__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has provided written notification of its election under this subsection to the United States Secretary of Health and Human Services.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-075__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to reporting under (a) of this section, an employer of an obligor shall promptly provide to the agency, or the child support enforcement agency of another state, information requested regarding the obligor's compensation, employment, wages or salary, and occupation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-075__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An employer may charge $1 to each employee who is reported to the agency under this section to cover the cost of the reporting.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-075__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to other sanctions available under the law, an employer that violates this section is liable for a civil penalty for each failure to meet the requirements of this section of not more than</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-075__subsec_f__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>$10 for each employee who is newly hired, rehired, or newly returned to work; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-075__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>$100 if the failure is the result of a conspiracy between the employee and the employer not to supply the required report or to supply a false or incomplete report concerning an employee.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-075__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-075__subsec_g__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>employee has the meaning given in 26 U.S.C. 3401(c); employee does not include an employee of a federal or state agency performing intelligence or counterintelligence functions if the head of that agency has determined that reporting under this section on the employee could endanger the safety of the employee or compromise an ongoing investigation or intelligence mission;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-075__subsec_g__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>employer has the meaning given in 26 U.S.C. 3401(d); employer includes a governmental entity and a labor organization;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-075__subsec_g__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>labor organization has the meaning given in 29 U.S.C. 152; labor organization includes an entity that is used by the labor organization and another employer to carry out hiring or other requirements described in 29 U.S.C. 158(f)(3) in accordance with an agreement between the labor organization and the other employer.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-080">
            <num>25.27.080</num>
            <heading>Enforcement of support orders.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-27-080__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A court order requiring payment of child support shall be modified to order payments be made to the agency upon application.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-080__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The agency on behalf of the custodian or the state shall take all necessary action permitted by law to enforce child support orders, including petitioning the court for orders to aid in the enforcement of child support.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-080__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The determination or enforcement of a duty of support is unaffected by any interference by the custodian of the child with rights of custody or visitation granted by a court.  When the agency appears on behalf of a child in an action seeking to establish or enforce support, the court may not adjudicate custody, visitation, or property rights in the same action.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-080__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An order of arrest may not be issued in the enforcement of child support unless the court has reason to believe that the obligor may flee the jurisdiction or unless the obligor has been ordered to appear in the action and has failed to do so.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-085">
            <num>25.27.085</num>
            <heading>Subpoenas.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-27-085__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The agency may subpoena persons, books, records, and documents to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-085__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>obtain any financial or other information needed to establish, modify, or enforce a child support order;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-085__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>determine the paternity of a child under
AS 25.27.165
; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-085__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>disestablish the paternity of a child under
AS 25.27.166
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-085__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An administrative subpoena issued under this section shall be served in the manner provided for service of liens under
AS 25.27.240
. Proof of service may be completed according to Rule 5, Alaska Rules of Civil Procedure.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-085__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who is issued an administrative subpoena shall be provided an opportunity to refuse to comply with it for good cause by filing a request for a conference with the agency in this state in the manner and within the time specified in regulations adopted by the agency. Good cause shall be limited to mistake in identity of the person or to a prohibition under law to release such information.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-085__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After a conference requested under (c) of this section, the agency shall issue an order on the request relating to good cause. If the person continues to refuse to comply with the administrative subpoena, the agency in this state shall issue an order to impose a civil penalty of $10 for each day of noncompliance with the subpoena.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-085__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An order imposing a civil penalty under this section is a final administrative decision and may be appealed under
AS 25.27.210
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-085__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This section does not limit the ability of the agency to make other lawful requests for information.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-085__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a person fails to comply with a subpoena issued under this section, the agency may apply to the court for an order to compel obedience by proceedings for contempt as if the subpoena had been issued by a court.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-086">
            <num>25.27.086</num>
            <heading>Subpoenas issued by agency of another state.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-27-086__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the child support enforcement agency of another state issues a subpoena regarding persons, books, records, or documents in this state, the subpoena must be complied with as if it were issued by this state's child support services agency if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-086__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the subpoena is for obtaining
(A) financial or other information needed to establish, modify, or enforce a support order; or
(B) information needed to determine or disestablish the paternity of a child under the laws of the state in which the subpoena was issued; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-086__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the issuing agency complied with
AS 25.27.085</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-086__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The procedures in or adopted under
AS 25.27.085</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-086__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and (d) apply to a person who is issued a subpoena described in (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-086__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The child support services agency of this state shall enforce a subpoena described in (a) of this section and shall provide the opportunity for conference and issue any order under
AS 25.27.085</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-086__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and (d) on behalf of the issuing agency.
AS 25.27.085</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-086__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>applies to an order under this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-086__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The penalties provided in
AS 25.27.085
apply regarding a subpoena described in (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-086__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing in this section limits the ability of a child support enforcement agency of another state to make other lawful requests for information in this state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-095">
            <num>25.27.095</num>
            <heading>Agency exempt from execution.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.27.095.   Agency exempt from execution.
Execution may not issue against money held in the fund established under
AS 25.27.030
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-100">
            <num>25.27.100</num>
            <heading>All persons may use agency.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-27-100__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The agency shall provide aid to any person due child support under the laws of this state upon application. The agency may, by regulation, impose a fee for services provided under this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-100__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 148 ch 87 SLA 1997.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-103">
            <num>25.27.103</num>
            <heading>Payments to agency.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.27.103.   Payments to agency.
An obligor shall make child support payments to the agency if the agency is enforcing a duty of child support under
AS 25.25
or this chapter. The agency shall disburse that portion of a payment that exceeds the amount of money necessary to satisfy the obligor's immediate duty of support in accordance with state and federal requirements. The agency may characterize a support payment physically received by the agency through wage withholding during the last five business days of the month as having been received on the first day of the next calendar month if the agency determines that the payment was made in the course of regular wage withholding intended for the next calendar month. The agency shall credit money disbursed under this section toward satisfaction of the obligor's duty of support.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-105">
            <num>25.27.105</num>
            <heading>Audit of collections.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.27.105.   Audit of collections.
Within 30 working days after receipt of a written request from an obligor, the obligor's legal representative, the obligee, or the obligee's legal representative, the agency shall provide an audit of all child support payments made by the obligor and received by the agency. The audit shall include the date and amount of each payment, the name of the obligee, and the total amount of arrearages of support past due and amount of unpaid penalties and interest imposed under
AS 25.27.020
(a)(2)(B). The agency is required to provide only one audit each year for each obligee and obligor under this section.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-107">
            <num>25.27.107</num>
            <heading>Certification of arrears.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.27.107.   Certification of arrears.
Within 30 days after receipt of a written request from an obligee or an obligee's personal representative, the agency shall provide the obligee with a document that certifies whether or not the obligor was, at the end of the most recent calendar year,
(1) in arrears under the support order in an amount more than four times the monthly obligation under the order in cases where a payment schedule has not been established for payment of continuing support and accumulated arrears under the support order; or
(2) in arrears under a payment schedule in an amount more than four times the monthly obligation under the payment schedule if a payment schedule has been established for payment of continuing support and accumulated arrears under the support order.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-120">
            <num>25.27.120</num>
            <heading>Obligor liable for public assistance furnished obligee.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-27-120__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An obligor is liable to the state in the amount of assistance granted under
AS 47.07
and
AS 47.27
to a child to whom the obligor owes a duty of support except that, if a support order has been entered, the liability of the obligor for assistance granted under
AS 47.27
may not exceed the amount of support provided for in the support order, and, if a medical order of support has been entered, the liability of the obligor for assistance granted under
AS 47.07
may not exceed the amount of support provided for in the medical order of support.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-120__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An obligor is liable to the state in the amount of the cost incurred if the state is maintaining a child to whom the obligor owes a duty of support in a foster home or institution, except that if a support order has been entered, or an agreement for payment of that cost executed between the obligor and the state, the liability of the obligor may not exceed the amount provided in the support order or agreement.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-120__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Within 30 days after the agency knows the identity and address of an obligor who resides in the state and who is liable to the state under this section, the agency shall send written notification by certified mail to the obligor and the obligee of the obligor's accruing liability and that the obligor shall make child support payments to the agency. The notice required under this subsection must be in clear, concise, and easily readable language. The notice may accompany other communications by the agency.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-120__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the agency fails to comply with (c) of this section, interest does not accrue on the liability to the state unless a support order or medical support order, as applicable, has been entered.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-120__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The agency's failure to comply with (c) of this section does not bar an action by the state to recover amounts owed by the obligor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-125">
            <num>25.27.125</num>
            <heading>Accounting and disposition of federal receipts and agency collections.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-27-125__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Federal incentive payments received by the state under 42 U.S.C. 658 shall be deposited in the general fund and the commissioner of administration shall separately account for the payments. The annual estimated balance in the account may be used by the legislature to make appropriations to the Department of Revenue to carry out the purposes of
AS 25.27.020
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-125__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The annual estimated balance in the account maintained by the commissioner of administration under
AS 37.05.142
may be used by the legislature to make appropriations to carry out the purposes of
AS 47.14.100
 47.14.130 and
AS 47.27
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-130">
            <num>25.27.130</num>
            <heading>Subrogation of state.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-27-130__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the obligor is liable to the state under
AS 25.27.120</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-130__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or (b), the state is subrogated to the rights of the obligee to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-130__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>bring an action in the superior court seeking an order of support;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-130__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>proceed under
AS 25.27.160
 25.27.270 to establish a duty of support; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-130__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>enforce by execution, in accordance with
AS 25.27.230
 25.27.270, or otherwise, a support order entered in favor of the obligee.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-130__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To establish or enforce an order of support, including, if applicable, a medical support order, based on the subrogation of the state, the agency is not limited to the amount of assistance being granted to the child.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-130__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The recovery of any amount for which the obligor is liable that exceeds the total assistance granted under
AS 47.07
and
AS 47.27
shall be paid to the obligee.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-130__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (f) of this section, if the obligee is not receiving assistance under
AS 47.07
or
AS 47.27
at the time the state recovers money in an action under this section, the recovery of any amount for which the obligor is liable shall be distributed to the obligee for support payments, including medical support payments, that have become due and unpaid since the termination of assistance under
AS 47.07
or
AS 47.27
under a support order in favor of the obligee.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-130__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After payment to the obligee under (d) of this section, the state may retain an amount not to exceed the total unreimbursed assistance paid on behalf of the obligee under
AS 47.07
or
AS 47.27
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-130__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (d) of this section, the state shall, if required under federal law or regulations, distribute amounts recovered through offset of the obligor's federal tax refund as past due support with first distribution to the state for unpaid support assigned to the state under
AS 47.07.025
and
AS 47.27.040
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-135">
            <num>25.27.135</num>
            <heading>Limitation on actions to establish child support obligation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.27.135.   Limitation on actions to establish child support obligation.
If the same causes of action concerning a duty of child support are pending concurrently in court and before the agency, the second action filed may be abated upon the motion of a party or the agency. The court or the agency may award full costs and attorney fees to the party prevailing on the abatement motion.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-140">
            <num>25.27.140</num>
            <heading>Authority and procedures to administratively establish and enforce support obligation.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-27-140__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a support order has not been entered, the agency may establish paternity and a duty of support, which may include periodic payments of support, a medical support order, or both, utilizing the procedures prescribed in
AS 25.27.160
 25.27.220 and may enforce a duty of support utilizing the procedure prescribed in
AS 25.27.230
 25.27.270. Action under this subsection may be undertaken upon application of an obligee, or at the agency's own discretion if the obligor is liable to the state under
AS 25.27.120</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-140__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or (b).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-140__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a support order has been entered, the agency may enforce the support order utilizing the procedures prescribed in
AS 25.27.062
, 25.27.150, and 25.27.230  25.27.270.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-140__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless the agency is establishing only a medical support order, a decision of the agency determining a duty of support shall include an income withholding order as provided under
AS 25.27.062
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-150">
            <num>25.27.150</num>
            <heading>Initiation of administrative enforcement of orders; required notice.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-27-150__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If an arrearage occurs under a support order being enforced by the agency for which immediate income withholding is not required under
AS 25.27.062</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-150__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or an application is made to the agency for withholding under
AS 25.27.062
(d), the agency may execute an income withholding order without prior notice to the obligor. At the time of execution, the agency shall serve a notice of income withholding on the obligor. Notice under this subsection shall be served upon the obligor by certified mail to the obligor's last known address, and service is complete when the notice is properly addressed, certified, and mailed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-150__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The notice must state the amount of the overdue support that is owed, if any, and the amount of income that will be withheld.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-150__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The notice shall inform the obligor that income withholding has been ordered and of the procedures to follow if the obligor wishes to contest withholding on the grounds that the withholding is improper due to a mistake of fact. The notice must also inform the obligor of the information that was provided to the employer in the document that ordered the withholding.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-150__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the obligor requests a hearing, it shall be conducted under the department's regulations for informal conferences and shall be held within 15 days of the date of the request. The hearing may only be held to determine if there is a mistake of fact that makes the income withholding order improper because the amount of current or overdue support is incorrect, the identity of the obligor is inaccurate, or, for initiated withholding based on
AS 25.27.062
(c)(3)(A), the alleged facts regarding overdue payments or potential withdrawal of assets are incorrect. The order is not subject to any other legal defenses. It is not a defense to an income withholding order issued under
AS 25.27.062
(c)(2) that less than one full month's payment is past due if at least one full month's payment was past due on the date notice was served under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-150__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The conference officer shall inform the obligor of the informal conference decision either at the informal conference hearing or within 15 days after the hearing.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-150__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the conference officer determines that withholding will continue, the obligor may request a formal hearing as provided in the department's regulations.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-160">
            <num>25.27.160</num>
            <heading>Initiation of administrative action to establish support duty; required notice.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-27-160__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An action to establish a duty of support authorized under
AS 25.27.140</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-160__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>is initiated by the agency serving on the alleged obligor a notice and finding of financial responsibility. The notice and finding served under this subsection shall be served personally or by registered, certified, or insured mail, return receipt requested, for restricted delivery only to the person to whom the notice and finding is directed or to the person authorized under federal regulation to receive that person's restricted delivery mail.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-160__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (c) of this section, the notice and finding of financial responsibility served under (a) of this section must state</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-160__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the sum or periodic payments for which the alleged obligor is found to be responsible under this chapter;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-160__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name of the alleged obligee and the obligee's custodian;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-160__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>that the alleged obligor may appear and show cause in a hearing held by the agency why the finding is incorrect, should not be finally ordered, and should be modified or rescinded, because
(A) no duty of support is owed; or
(B) the amount of support found to be owed is incorrect;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-160__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>that, if the person served with the notice and finding of financial responsibility does not request a hearing within 30 days, the property and income of the person will be subject to execution under
AS 25.27.062
and 25.27.230  25.27.270 in the amounts stated in the finding without further notice or hearing.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-160__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the agency is establishing only medical support, the notice and finding of financial responsibility must state</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-160__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>that health care insurance shall be provided for the child to whom the duty of support is owed if health care insurance is available to the alleged obligor at a reasonable cost and that the alleged obligor and the other parent shall share equally the cost of the health care insurance and the costs of reasonable health care expenses not covered by insurance;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-160__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the sum of periodic payments of cash medical support for which either parent or both parents are found to be responsible under this chapter;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-160__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name of the alleged obligee and the obligee's custodian;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-160__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>that the alleged obligor may appear and show cause in a hearing held by the agency why the finding is incorrect, should not be finally ordered, and should be modified or rescinded, because
(A) no duty of support is owed;
(B) health care insurance for the child is not available to the alleged obligor at a reasonable cost;
(C) adequate health care is available to the child through the Indian Health Service or other insurance coverage; or
(D) there is good cause to allocate the costs of health insurance, cash medical support, or uninsured health care expenses unequally between the parents;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-160__subsec_c__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>that, if the person served with the notice under this subsection does not request a hearing within 30 days, a copy of the medical support order will be sent to the person's employer under
AS 25.27.063</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-160__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>without further notice or hearing for inclusion of the child in family health coverage if it is available through the person's employer.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-165">
            <num>25.27.165</num>
            <heading>Determination of paternity in an administrative proceeding.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-27-165__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon application from a mother, custodian, putative father, or legal custodian of a child, or from a state, the agency may institute administrative proceedings to determine the paternity of a child born out of wedlock.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-165__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In order to initiate a paternity proceeding administratively, the agency shall serve a mother and putative father, as appropriate, with a notice of paternity and financial responsibility. The notice shall be served personally as set out in Rule 4(d), Alaska Rules of Civil Procedure, or by registered, certified, or insured mail, return receipt requested, for restricted delivery only to the person to whom the notice is directed or to the person authorized under federal law to receive that person's restricted delivery mail. The notice must be accompanied by</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-165__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an administrative order requiring that the mother, child, and putative father submit to genetic testing to be arranged by the agency and stating that a party may provide information to show good cause not to order the testing;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-165__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an administrative order requiring the putative father to provide financial information, as defined by the agency in regulation, within 30 days after service of the notice; all financial information provided to the agency under an order under this paragraph shall be held confidential by the agency, according to any applicable regulations; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-165__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a notice of right to informal conference, to be held within 20 days after receipt of an admission of paternity or service upon the parties of genetic test results.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-165__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person served with a notice of paternity and financial responsibility and accompanying orders under (b) of this section shall file a response, admitting or denying paternity and providing the required financial information, within 30 days after the date of service of the notice of paternity and financial responsibility. If the putative father admits paternity, the agency shall issue, within 20 days after the admission of paternity, a decision establishing paternity. If the putative father denies paternity, the putative father shall submit to genetic testing, as provided in (b) of this section, within 45 days after the date of service of the notice of paternity and financial responsibility. If the putative father fails to file a response or fails to comply with an accompanying order within the time and in the manner required in this subsection, the agency may issue a decision by default establishing paternity and financial responsibility, except that, if the proceeding was instituted at the request of the putative father, the agency shall dismiss the proceeding without prejudice.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-165__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon receipt of genetic test results, the agency shall serve on the putative father notice of the test results and of the date for the informal conference. Service of the notice shall be made by first class mail. If the genetic test results are negative under the standard set in
AS 25.20.050
(d), the agency shall issue a finding of nonpaternity within 20 days after the agency's receipt of the test results. If the genetic test results are positive under the standard set in
AS 25.20.050
(d), the agency shall issue an informal conference decision within 20 days after the agency's receipt of the test results. Upon request and advance payment by a party, the agency shall order additional genetic tests. If the second genetic test results contradict the first genetic test results, the agency shall provide copies of the second genetic test results to the parties and conduct another informal conference. The agency shall issue the second informal conference decision within 20 days after the agency's receipt of the second genetic test results.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-165__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the agency issues a decision establishing paternity under (d) of this section, the putative father is entitled to a formal hearing if a written request for hearing is served on the agency by certified mail, return receipt requested, within 30 days after the date of service of the agency's decision.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-165__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a request for a formal hearing is made under (e) of this section, an execution under
AS 25.27.062
and 25.27.230  25.27.270 may not be stayed unless the putative father posts security or a bond in the amount of child support that would have been due under the informal conference decision pending the decision on the formal hearing. If no request for a formal hearing is made under (e) of this section, the informal conference decision establishing paternity is final.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-165__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a request for a formal hearing is made under (e) of this section, the hearing officer shall consider the evidence applying the standards set in
AS 25.20.050
(d).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-165__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a putative father who requests a formal hearing under (e) of this section fails to appear at the formal hearing, the hearing officer shall enter a final decision establishing paternity.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-165__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The agency may recover any costs it pays for genetic tests required by this section from the putative father unless the testing establishes that the individual is not the father, except that costs may not be recovered from a person who is a recipient of cash assistance or self-sufficiency services under
AS 47.27
(Alaska temporary assistance program). For purposes of this subsection, a person who receives a diversion payment and self-sufficiency services under
AS 47.27.026
is not considered to be a recipient of cash assistance or self-sufficiency services under
AS 47.27
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-165__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A decision establishing paternity or an admission of paternity under this section must include the social security numbers, if ascertainable, of the father, mother, and the child.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-165__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding any other provision of this section, if the agency determines, after considering the best interests of the child, that good cause exists not to order genetic testing under this section, it shall, without ordering the genetic testing and as the agency determines appropriate in the best interests of the child,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-165__subsec_k__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>end the administrative proceedings under this section without making a determination of paternity; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-165__subsec_k__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>after a hearing provided for under regulations adopted by the agency, enter a final decision regarding paternity.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-166">
            <num>25.27.166</num>
            <heading>Disestablishment of paternity.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-27-166__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The agency shall, by regulation, establish procedures and standards for the disestablishment of paternity of a child whose paternity was established in this state other than by court order if the paternity was not established by</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-166__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>genetic test results that met the standard set out in
AS 25.20.050</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-166__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>at the time the test was performed; or</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-166__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an acknowledgment of paternity under
AS 25.20.050
or an admission of paternity under
AS 25.27.165
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-166__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The agency's standards and procedures under (a) of this section must</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-166__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>allow a person to petition the agency to disestablish paternity only once per child;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-166__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>allow a petition to disestablish paternity to be brought only within three years after the child's birth or three years after the petitioner knew or should have known of the father's putative paternity of the child, whichever is later; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-166__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide standards and notice and hearing procedures that are equivalent to those used for establishment of paternity under
AS 25.27.165
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-166__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The agency shall disestablish paternity under this section if genetic test results are negative under the standard set out in
AS 25.20.050</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-166__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and if the other standards established in its regulations are met.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-166__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a decision under this section disestablishes paternity, the petitioner's child support obligation or liability for public assistance under
AS 25.27.120
is modified retroactively to extinguish arrearages for child support and accrued liability for public assistance based on the alleged paternity that is disestablished under this section. This subsection may be implemented only to the extent not prohibited by federal law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-166__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The costs of genetic testing under this section shall be assessed against the petitioner if paternity is not disestablished. If paternity is disestablished under this section, the costs of genetic testing shall be assessed against</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-166__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the individual to whom the petitioner paid or owed child support payments for the child for whom paternity was disestablished; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-166__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the agency if there is no individual who meets the description in (1) of this subsection.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-167">
            <num>25.27.167</num>
            <heading>Contempt of order for genetic testing.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-27-167__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a person who is located in this state fails to comply with an order for genetic testing issued by the agency in this state, or the tribunal of another state, the agency in this state may certify the facts to the superior court of this state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-167__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon certification under (a) of this section, the court shall issue an order directing the person to appear and show cause why the person should not be punished for contempt. The order and a copy of the certified statement shall be served on the person in the manner required for service of court orders to show cause.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-167__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After service under (b) of this section, the court has jurisdiction of the matter brought under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-167__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The law of this state applicable to contempt of a court order applies to a proceeding for contempt of an order for genetic testing brought under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-170">
            <num>25.27.170</num>
            <heading>Hearings in administrative action to establish support duty.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-27-170__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person served with a notice and finding of financial responsibility is entitled to a hearing if a request in writing for a hearing is served on the agency by registered mail, return receipt requested, within 30 days of the date of service of the notice of financial responsibility.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-170__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a request for a formal hearing under (a) of this section is made, the execution under
AS 25.27.062
and 25.27.230  25.27.270 may not be stayed unless the obligor posts security or a bond in the amount of child support that would have been due under the finding of financial responsibility pending the decision on the hearing. If no request for a hearing is made, the finding of responsibility is final at the expiration of the 30-day period.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-170__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a hearing is requested, it shall be held within 30 days of the date of service of the request for hearing on the agency.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-170__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (g) of this section, the hearing officer shall determine the amount of periodic payments necessary to satisfy the past, present, and future liability of the alleged obligor under
AS 25.27.120
, if any, and under any duty of support imposable under the law. The amount of periodic payments determined under this subsection is not limited by the amount of any public assistance payment made to or for the benefit of the child.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-170__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The hearing officer shall consider the following in making a determination under (d) of this section:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-170__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the needs of the alleged obligee, disregarding the income or assets of the custodian of the alleged obligee;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-170__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the amount of the alleged obligor's liability to the state under
AS 25.27.120
if any;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-170__subsec_e__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the intent of the legislature that children be supported as much as possible by their natural parents;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-170__subsec_e__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the ability of the alleged obligor to pay.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-170__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (g) of this section, if the alleged obligor requesting the hearing fails to appear at the hearing, the hearing officer shall enter a decision declaring the property and income of the alleged obligor subject to execution under
AS 25.27.062
and 25.27.230  25.27.270 in the amounts stated in the notice and finding of financial responsibility.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-170__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the agency is establishing only a medical support order, the hearing officer shall enter a decision about the parents' respective responsibilities for the child's health care expenses that complies with the requirements of
AS 25.27.060
(c).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-180">
            <num>25.27.180</num>
            <heading>Administrative findings and decision.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-27-180__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Within 20 days after the date of the hearing, the hearing officer shall adopt findings and a decision determining whether paternity is established and whether a duty of support exists, and, if a duty of support is found, the decision must specify</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-180__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>unless a medical support order only is being established, the amount of periodic payments or sum for which the alleged obligor is found to be responsible; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-180__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the parents' respective responsibilities for the costs of the child's health care; this medical support order must be in compliance with
AS 25.27.060</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-180__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Liability to the state under
AS 25.27.120
is limited to the amount for which the obligor is found to be responsible under (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-180__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A decision regarding support rendered under (a) of this section is modified to the extent that a subsequent order, judgment, or decree of a superior court is inconsistent with the decision entered under (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-190">
            <num>25.27.190</num>
            <heading>Modification of administrative finding or decision.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-27-190__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless a support order has been entered by a court and except as provided in
AS 25.25
, the obligor, or the obligee or the obligee's custodian, may petition the agency or its designee for a modification of the administrative finding or decision of responsibility previously entered with regard to future periodic support payments. In addition, the agency may initiate a modification and grant a hearing under (c)  (e) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-190__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The agency shall grant a hearing upon a petition made under (a) of this section if affidavits submitted with the petition make a showing of good cause and material change in circumstances sufficient to justify action under (e) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-190__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a hearing is granted, the agency shall serve a notice of hearing together with a copy of any petition and affidavits submitted on the obligee or the obligee's custodian and the obligor personally or by registered, certified, or insured mail, return receipt requested, for restricted delivery only to the person to whom the notice is directed or to the person authorized under federal regulation to receive that person's restricted delivery mail.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-190__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A hearing shall be set not less than 15 nor more than 30 days from the date of mailing of notice of hearing, unless extended for good cause.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-190__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Modification or termination of future periodic support payments may be ordered upon a showing of good cause and material change in circumstances. The adoption or enactment of guidelines or a significant amendment to guidelines for determining child support is a material change in circumstances, if the guidelines are relevant to the petition. As necessary to comply with 42 U.S.C. 666, a periodic modification of child support may be made without a showing of a material change in circumstances if the child support order being modified on the periodic basis has not been modified or adjusted during the three years preceding the periodic modification.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-193">
            <num>25.27.193</num>
            <heading>Periodic review or adjustment of support orders.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.27.193.   Periodic review or adjustment of support orders.
As necessary to comply with 42 U.S.C. 666, the agency, by regulation, shall provide procedures and standards for the modification, through a three-year cycle of review or adjustment, of a support order. Regulations adopted under this section must include procedures for periodic notice of the right to request review, procedures for hearings, and standards for adjustments regarding future periodic support payments. A modification under this section may be made without a showing of a material change in circumstances.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-194">
            <num>25.27.194</num>
            <heading>Processing time for modification of support orders.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.27.194.   Processing time for modification of support orders.
The agency shall use its best efforts to process modifications of support orders under
AS 25.27.190
and 25.27.193 in a manner that will result in the same average processing time for modifications that increase obligors' responsibilities as for modifications that decrease obligors' responsibilities.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-195">
            <num>25.27.195</num>
            <heading>Relief from administrative order.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-27-195__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A clerical mistake in an administrative order issued by the agency or an error arising from an oversight or omission by the agency may be corrected by the agency at any time.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-195__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The agency may, at any time, vacate an administrative support order issued by the agency under
AS 25.27.160
that was based on a default amount rather than on the obligor's actual ability to pay.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-195__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before an order may be corrected or vacated under (a) or (b) of this section, the agency must send notice of the intended action to the obligor and the custodian and provide an adequate opportunity for the obligor and custodian to be heard on the issue.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-195__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If an order is vacated under (b) of this section, the agency may at the same time issue a new order establishing a support amount, based on information about the obligor's income or on the Alaska average wage standard, for periods of time covered by the previous order. Upon issuance of the new order, the agency may adjust the obligor's account to reflect the support amounts established in the new order. In no case may the agency adjust the obligor's account below zero.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-200">
            <num>25.27.200</num>
            <heading>Use of standards in administrative determinations of support amounts.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.27.200.   Use of standards in administrative determinations of support amounts.
In making its findings under
AS 25.27.160
and in establishing and modifying amounts of periodic support payments under
AS 25.27.180
and 25.27.190, the agency shall consider the standards adopted by regulation under
AS 25.27.020
and any standards for determination of support payments used by the superior court of the district of residence of the obligor.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-210">
            <num>25.27.210</num>
            <heading>Judicial review of administrative decisions and actions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-27-210__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Judicial review by the superior court of a final administrative decision establishing or disestablishing paternity and establishing or modifying a duty of support or amounts of support due may be obtained by filing a notice of appeal in accordance with the applicable rules of court governing appeals in civil matters. A notice of appeal shall be filed within 30 days after the decision.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-210__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The complete record of the proceedings, or the parts of it that the appellant designates, shall be prepared by the agency.  A copy shall be delivered to all parties participating in the appeal.  The original shall be filed in the superior court within 30 days after the appellant pays the estimated cost of preparing the complete or designated record or files a corporate surety bond equal to the estimated cost.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-210__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The complete record includes</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-210__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the notice and finding of financial responsibility, the notice of paternity and financial responsibility, or the notice of and petition for an action disestablishing paternity, as applicable;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-210__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the request for a hearing;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-210__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the decision of the hearing officer;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-210__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the exhibits admitted or rejected;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-210__subsec_c__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the written evidence;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-210__subsec_c__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>all other documents in the case, including decisions of the agency.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-210__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon order of the superior court, appeals may be taken on the original record or parts of it.  The record may be typewritten or duplicated by any standard process.  Analogous rules of court governing appeals in civil matters shall be followed when this chapter is silent, and when not in conflict with this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-210__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The superior court may enjoin agency action in excess of constitutional or statutory authority at any stage of an agency proceeding.  If agency action is unlawfully or unreasonably withheld, the superior court may compel the agency to initiate action.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-220">
            <num>25.27.220</num>
            <heading>Procedure in judicial reviews.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-27-220__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An appeal shall be heard by the superior court sitting without a jury.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-220__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Inquiry in an appeal extends to the following questions: (1) whether the agency has proceeded without or in excess of jurisdiction; (2) whether there was a fair hearing; and (3) whether there was a prejudicial abuse of discretion.  Abuse of discretion is established if the agency has not proceeded in the manner required by law, the order or decision is not supported by the findings, or the findings are not supported by the evidence.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-220__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The court may exercise its independent judgment on the evidence.  If it is claimed that the findings are not supported by the evidence, abuse of discretion is established if the court determines that the findings are not supported by</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-220__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the weight of the evidence; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-220__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>substantial evidence in the light of the whole record.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-220__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The court may augment the agency record in whole or in part, or hold a hearing de novo.  If the court finds that there is relevant evidence which, in the exercise of reasonable diligence, could not have been produced or which was improperly excluded at the hearing, the court may</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-220__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>enter judgment as provided in (e) of this section and remand the case to be reconsidered in the light of that evidence; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-220__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>admit the evidence at the appellate hearing without remanding the case.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-220__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The court shall enter judgment setting aside, modifying, remanding, or affirming the decision, without limiting or controlling in any way the discretion legally vested in the agency.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-220__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The court in which proceedings under this section are started may stay the operation of the decision until</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-220__subsec_f__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the court enters judgment;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-220__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a notice of further appeal from the judgment is filed; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-220__subsec_f__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the time for filing the notice of appeal expires.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-220__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A stay may not be imposed or continued if the court is satisfied that it is against the public interest.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-220__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If further appeal is taken, the supreme court may, in its discretion, stay the superior court judgment or agency order.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-225">
            <num>25.27.225</num>
            <heading>Support payment obligations as judgments.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.27.225.   Support payment obligations as judgments.
A support order ordering a noncustodial parent obligor to make periodic support payments to the custodian of a child is a judgment that becomes vested when each payment becomes due and unpaid.  The custodian of the child, or the agency on behalf of that person, may take legal action under
AS 25.27.226
to establish a judgment for support payments ordered by a court of this state that are delinquent.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-226">
            <num>25.27.226</num>
            <heading>Collection of past due support.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.27.226.   Collection of past due support.
To collect the payment due, the custodian of a child, or the agency on behalf of that person, shall file with the court (1) a motion requesting establishment of a judgment; (2) an affidavit that states that one or more payments of support are 30 or more days past due and that specifies the amounts past due and the dates they became past due; and (3) notice of the obligor's right to respond. Service on the obligor must be in the manner provided in
AS 25.27.265
.  The child's custodian, or the agency on behalf of the custodian, shall file with the court proof of service of the petition, affidavit, and notice.  The obligor shall respond no later than 15 days after service by filing an affidavit with the court.  If the obligor's affidavit states that the obligor has paid any of the amounts claimed to be delinquent, describes in detail the method of payment or offers any other defense to the petition, then the obligor is entitled to a hearing.  After the hearing, if any, the court shall enter a judgment for the amount of money owed.  If the obligor does not file an affidavit under this section, the court shall enter a default judgment against the obligor.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-227">
            <num>25.27.227</num>
            <heading>Nature of remedies.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.27.227.   Nature of remedies.
AS 25.27.225
and 25.27.226 provide remedies in addition to and not as a substitute for any other remedies available to the parties.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-228">
            <num>25.27.228</num>
            <heading>Court costs.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.27.228.   Court costs.
The court may order an obligor to pay all court costs involved in a proceeding resulting in a court order described in
AS 25.27.225
, and in a proceeding under
AS 25.27.226
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-230">
            <num>25.27.230</num>
            <heading>Assertion, recording, and effect of lien.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-27-230__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The agency shall assert a lien upon the real or personal property of the obligor in the amount of the obligor's liability if an arrearage occurs under a support order being enforced by the agency.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-230__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A lien recorded under this section has no effect against earnings, or bank deposits or balances, unless it states the amount of the obligor's liability under this chapter and unless the lien is served in accordance with
AS 25.27.240
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-230__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The lien shall attach to all real and personal property of the obligor and be effective on the date of recording of the lien with the recorder of the recording district in which the property attached is located. A lien against earnings shall attach and be effective upon filing with the recorder of the recording district in which the employer does business or maintains an office or agent for the purpose of doing business. A lien filed at the offices of the Commercial Fisheries Entry Commission in Juneau against a limited entry permit issued under
AS 16.43
is considered to have been filed against the permit in all recording districts in which the permit holder uses the permit.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-230__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Whenever a lien has been recorded under this section and there is in the possession of any person, political subdivision, or department of the state having actual notice of the lien any property that may be subject to the lien, that property may not be paid over, released, sold, transferred, encumbered, or conveyed unless</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-230__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a written release or waiver signed by a representative of the agency has been delivered to the person, political subdivision, or department of the state; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-230__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a decision has been made in a hearing held under
AS 25.27.170
or by a superior court ordering release of the lien on the grounds that no debt exists or that the debt has been satisfied.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-230__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A lien arising in another state under the child support laws of that state shall be given full faith and credit in this state. The lien may be asserted in this state upon the real or personal property of the obligor in the amount of the obligor's liability by complying with the requirements of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-230__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A lien recorded under this section is a judgment lien and may be enforced by execution under
AS 09.35
in the full amount of the obligor's liability at the time of execution.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-240">
            <num>25.27.240</num>
            <heading>Service of lien.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-27-240__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The agency of this state or another state, or a party or other entity seeking to enforce a child support obligation, may, at any time after recording of a lien recorded under
AS 25.27.230
, serve a copy of the lien upon any person, political subdivision, or department of the state possessing earnings, or deposits or balances held in any bank account of any nature that are due, owing, or belonging to the obligor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-240__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A lien recorded under
AS 25.27.230
shall be served upon a person, political subdivision, or department of the state personally or by registered, certified, or insured mail, return receipt requested.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-244">
            <num>25.27.244</num>
            <heading>Adverse action against delinquent obligor's occupational license.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-27-244__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The agency shall compile and maintain a list of obligors who are not in substantial compliance with a support order or payment schedule negotiated under (g)(1) of this section. The agency may not include an obligor on the list unless the agency has sent to the obligor, at the obligor's most recent address on file with the agency, written notice of the arrearages at least 60 days before placement on the list. The list must include the names, social security numbers, dates of birth, and last known addresses of the persons. The list shall be updated by the agency on a monthly basis.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-244__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The agency shall, on a monthly basis, provide a copy of the list to each licensing entity through a computer readable magnetic medium. A licensing entity subject to this section shall implement procedures to accept and process the list. Notwithstanding any other law to the contrary, a licensing entity may not issue or renew a license for a person on the list except as provided in this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-244__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Promptly after receiving an application from an applicant and before issuing or renewing a license, a licensing entity, other than one issuing commercial crewmember fishing licenses, shall determine whether the applicant is on the most recent list provided by the agency. If the applicant is on the list, the licensing entity shall immediately serve notice under (e) of this section of the licensing entity's intent to withhold issuance or renewal of the license. The notice shall be considered given when delivered personally to the applicant or deposited in the United States mail addressed to the applicant's last known mailing address on file with the licensing entity.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-244__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Other than for a commercial crewmember fishing license, a licensing entity shall issue a temporary license valid for a period of 150 days to an applicant whose name is on the list if the applicant is otherwise eligible for a license. The temporary license may not be extended. Only one temporary license may be issued during a regular license term and its validity shall coincide with the first 150 days of that license term. A license for the full or remainder of the license term may be issued or renewed only upon compliance with this section. If a license or application is denied under this section, money paid by the applicant or licensee shall be refunded by the licensing entity after retention of the temporary license fee, if any.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-244__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notices for use under (c) and (r) of this section shall be developed by each licensing entity under guidelines provided by the agency and are subject to approval by the agency. The notice must include the address and telephone number of the agency and shall emphasize the necessity of obtaining a release from the agency as a condition for the issuance or renewal of a license. The notice must inform an applicant whose license is governed by (d) of this section that the licensing entity shall issue a temporary license for 150 calendar days under (d) of this section if the applicant is otherwise eligible and that, upon expiration of that time period, the license will be denied unless the licensing entity has received a release from the agency. The agency shall also develop a form that the applicant may use to request a review by the agency. A copy of this form shall be included with each notice sent under (c) or (r) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-244__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The agency shall establish review procedures consistent with this section to allow an applicant to have the underlying arrearages and relevant defenses investigated, to provide an applicant information on the process of obtaining a modification of a support order, or to provide an applicant assistance in the establishment of a payment schedule on arrearages if the circumstances warrant.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-244__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the applicant wishes to challenge being included on the list, the applicant shall submit to the agency a written request for review within 30 days after receiving the notice under (c) or (r) of this section by using the form developed under (e) of this section. Within 30 days after receiving a written request for review, the agency shall inform the applicant in writing of the agency's findings. The agency shall immediately send a release to the appropriate licensing entity and the applicant if any of the following conditions is met:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-244__subsec_g__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the applicant is found to be in substantial compliance with each support order applicable to the applicant or has negotiated an agreement with the agency for a payment schedule on arrearages and is in substantial compliance with the negotiated agreement; if the applicant fails to be in substantial compliance with an agreement negotiated under this paragraph, the agency shall send to the appropriate licensing entity a revocation of any release previously sent to the entity for that applicant;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-244__subsec_g__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the applicant has submitted a timely request for review to the agency, but the agency will be unable to complete the review and send notice of findings to the applicant in sufficient time for the applicant to file a timely request for judicial relief within the 150-day period during which the applicant's temporary license is valid under (d) of this section; this paragraph applies only if the delay in completing the review process is not the result of the applicant's failure to act in a reasonable, timely, and diligent manner upon receiving notice from the licensing entity that the applicant's name is on the list;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-244__subsec_g__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the applicant has, within 30 days after receiving the agency's findings following a request for review under (2) of this subsection, filed and served a request for judicial relief under this section, but a resolution of that relief will not be made within the 150-day period of the temporary license under (d) of this section; this paragraph applies only if the delay in completing the judicial relief process is not the result of the applicant's failure to act in a reasonable, timely, and diligent manner upon receiving the agency's notice of findings; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-244__subsec_g__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the applicant has obtained a judicial finding of substantial compliance.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-244__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An applicant is required to act with diligence in responding to notices from the licensing entity and the agency with the recognition that the temporary license granted under (d) of this section will lapse after 150 days and that the agency and, where appropriate, the court must have time to act within that 150-day period. An applicant's delay in acting, without good cause, that directly results in the inability of the agency to complete a review of the applicant's request or the court to hear the request for judicial relief within the required period does not constitute the diligence required under this section that would justify the issuance of a release.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-244__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as otherwise provided in this section, the agency may not issue a release if the applicant is not in substantial compliance with the order for support or with an agreement negotiated under (g)(1) of this section. The agency shall notify the applicant in writing that the applicant may request any or all of the following: (1) judicial relief from the agency's decision not to issue a release or the agency's decision to revoke a release under (g)(1) of this section; (2) a judicial determination of substantial compliance; (3) a modification of the support order. The notice must also contain the name and address of the court in which the applicant may file the request for relief and inform the applicant that the applicant's name shall remain on the list if the applicant does not request judicial relief within 30 days after receiving the notice. The applicant shall comply with all statutes and rules of court implementing this section. This section does not limit an applicant's authority under other law to request an order to show cause or notice of motion to modify a support order or to fix a payment schedule on arrearages accruing under a support order or to obtain a court finding of substantial compliance with a support order or a court finding of compliance with subpoenas and warrants described in (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-244__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A request for judicial relief from the agency's decision must state the grounds on which relief is requested, and the judicial action shall be limited to those stated grounds. Judicial relief under this subsection is not an appeal and shall be governed by court rules adopted to implement this section. Unless otherwise provided by court rule, the court shall hold an evidentiary hearing within 20 calendar days after the filing of service on the opposing party. The court's decision shall be limited to a determination of each of the following issues, as applicable:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-244__subsec_j__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>whether there is a support order or a payment schedule on arrearages;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-244__subsec_j__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>whether the petitioner is the obligor covered by the support order; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-244__subsec_j__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>whether the obligor is in substantial compliance with the support order or payment schedule.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-244__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the court finds that the person requesting relief is in substantial compliance with the support order or payment schedule, the agency shall immediately send a release under (g) of this section to the appropriate licensing entity and the applicant.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-244__subsec_l">
              <num>(l)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If an applicant is in substantial compliance with a support order or payment schedule, the agency shall mail to the applicant and the appropriate licensing entity a release stating that the applicant is in substantial compliance. The receipt of a release shall serve to notify the applicant and the licensing entity that, for the purposes of this section, the applicant is in substantial compliance with the support order or payment schedule unless the agency, under (a) of this section, certifies subsequent to the issuance of a release that the applicant is once again not in substantial compliance with a support order or payment schedule.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-244__subsec_m">
              <num>(m)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The agency may enter into interagency agreements with the state agencies that have responsibility for the administration of licensing entities as necessary to implement this section to the extent that it is cost effective to implement the interagency agreements. The agreements shall provide for the receipt by the other state agencies and licensing entities of federal money to cover that portion of costs allowable in federal law and regulation and incurred by the state agencies and licensing entities in implementing this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-244__subsec_n">
              <num>(n)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the licensing entities subject to this section shall assess a fee for issuance of a temporary license under this section. The licensing entity shall set the amount of the fee so that the fees collected under this section, to the extent reasonable, cover the costs of implementing and administering this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-244__subsec_o">
              <num>(o)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The process described in (g) of this section is the sole administrative remedy for contesting the issuance to the applicant of a temporary license or the denial of a license under this section. The procedures specified in
AS 44.62.330
 44.62.630 do not apply to the denial or failure to issue or renew a license under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-244__subsec_p">
              <num>(p)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The agency and licensing entities, as appropriate, shall adopt regulations necessary to implement this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-244__subsec_q">
              <num>(q)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding any provision of
AS 16
, a commercial crewmember fishing license described in (s)(2)(A)(xvi) of this section issued to an individual whose name is on the list is void and invalid, and the individual is subject to criminal sanctions for conducting the activities for which such a license is required. The licensing entity for commercial crewmember fishing licenses shall print a notice on commercial crewmember fishing license forms stating the provisions of this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-244__subsec_r">
              <num>(r)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After receiving information, including information from a licensing agent appointed under
AS 16.05.380
, that a commercial crewmember fishing license has been issued to an applicant, the licensing entity for the license shall promptly determine whether the applicant was, at the time the applicant obtained the license, on the most recent list provided by the agency under (b) of this section. If the applicant was on that list, the licensing entity shall immediately serve notice under (e) of this section that the license is void and invalid and that, notwithstanding the limitation of (d) of this section, the applicant can request the licensing entity to issue a temporary license under this section. A notice under this subsection is considered given when delivered personally to the applicant or deposited in the United States mail addressed to the applicant's last known mailing address on file with the licensing entity.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-244__subsec_s">
              <num>(s)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-244__subsec_s__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>applicant means a person applying for issuance or renewal of a license;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-244__subsec_s__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>license
(A) means, except as provided in (B) of this paragraph, a license, certificate, permit, registration, or other authorization that, at the time of issuance, will be valid for more than 150 days and that may be acquired from a state agency to perform an occupation, including the following:</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-244__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>license relating to boxing or wrestling under
AS 05.10
;
(ii) authorization to perform an occupation regulated under
AS 08
;
(iii) teacher certificate under
AS 14.20
;
(iv) authorization under
AS 18.08
to perform emergency medical services;</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-244__subsec_v">
              <num>(v)</num>
              <content>
                <p>asbestos worker certification under
AS 18.31
;
(vi) boiler operator's license under
AS 18.60.395
;
(vii) certificate of fitness under
AS 18.62
;
(viii) hazardous painting certification under
AS 18.63
;
(ix) security guard license under
AS 18.65.400
 18.65.490;</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-244__subsec_x">
              <num>(x)</num>
              <content>
                <p>license relating to insurance under
AS 21.27
;
(xi) employment agency permit under
AS 23.15.330
 23.15.520;
(xii) registration as a broker-dealer, an agent, an investment adviser, or an investment adviser representative under
AS 45.56.300
 45.56.350;
(xiii) certification as a pesticide applicator under
AS 46.03.320
;
(xiv) certification as a storage tank worker or contractor under
AS 46.03.375
;
(xv) certification as a water and wastewater works operator under
AS 46.30
;
(xvi) commercial crewmember fishing license under
AS 16.05.480
other than an entry permit or interim-use permit under
AS 16.43
;
(xvii) fish transporter permit under
AS 16.05.671
.
(B) does not include</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-244__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>a vessel license issued under
AS 16.05.490
or 16.05.530;
(ii) a business license issued under
AS 43.70
;
(iii) an entry permit or interim-use permit issued under
AS 16.43
; or
(iv) a driver's license issued under
AS 28.15
;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-244__subsec_i__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>licensee means a person holding a license or applying to renew a license;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-244__subsec_i__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>licensing entity means the state agency that issues or renews a license; in the case of a license issued or renewed by the Department of Commerce, Community, and Economic Development after an applicant's qualifications are determined by another agency, licensing entity means the department;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-244__subsec_i__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>list means the list of obligors and other persons compiled and maintained under (a) of this section;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-244__subsec_i__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>substantial compliance regarding a support order or payment schedule means that, with respect to periodic payments required under a support order or a negotiated payment schedule under (g) of this section, whichever is applicable, the obligor has
(A) no arrearage;
(B) an arrearage in an amount that is not more than four times the monthly obligation under the support order or payment schedule; or
(C) been determined by a court to be making the best efforts possible under the obligor's circumstances to have no arrearages under any support order that requires periodic payments or under a negotiated payment schedule relating to child support.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-246">
            <num>25.27.246</num>
            <heading>Adverse action against delinquent obligor's driver's license.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-27-246__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The agency shall compile and maintain a list of obligors who have a driver's license, and either (1) are not in substantial compliance with a support order, or (2) whose names are required to be placed on the list under (p)(2) of this section. The agency may not include an obligor on the list unless the agency has sent to the obligor, at the obligor's most recent address on file with the agency, written notice of the arrearages at least 60 days before placement on the list. The list must include the names, social security numbers, dates of birth, and last known addresses of the persons. The list shall be updated by the agency on a monthly basis.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-246__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The agency shall serve notice under (d) of this section to each person on the list that the person's driver's license will be suspended in 150 days, and will not be reissued or renewed the next time it is applied for if the person's name is on the list at the time of the subsequent application, unless the licensee receives a release from the agency. The notice shall be considered given when delivered personally to the person or deposited in the United States mail addressed to the person's last known mailing address on file with the agency.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-246__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the licensee fails to obtain a release during the 150-day period following notice under (b) and (d) of this section or if the agency revokes a release of a person's license under (n) or (o) of this section, the agency shall notify the department that the licensee's driver's license should be suspended and further renewals or applications should be denied until the agency sends the department a release for the licensee. Upon receiving the agency's notice under this subsection, the department shall suspend the licensee's driver's license and may not issue or renew a driver's license for the licensee until the department receives a release to do so from the agency. If a license is suspended or an application is denied under this section, money paid by the applicant or licensee may not be refunded by the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-246__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The notice under (b) of this section must include the address and telephone number of the agency and shall emphasize the necessity of obtaining a release from the agency as a condition for avoiding suspension or denial of the person's driver's license. The notice must also inform the licensee that, if a license is suspended or an application is denied under this section, money paid by the licensee will not be refunded by the department. The agency shall also develop a form that the licensee may use to request a review by the agency. A copy of this form shall be included with each notice sent under (b) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-246__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The agency shall establish review procedures consistent with this section to allow a licensee to have the underlying arrearages and relevant defenses investigated, to provide a licensee with information on the process of obtaining a modification of a support order, or to provide a licensee with assistance in the establishment of a payment schedule on arrearages if the circumstances warrant.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-246__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a licensee wishes to challenge being included on the list, the licensee shall submit to the agency a written request for review within 30 days after the notice under (b) of this section was personally delivered or postmarked by using the form developed under (d) of this section. Within 30 days after receiving a written request for review, the agency shall inform the licensee in writing of the agency's findings. The agency shall immediately send a release to the department and the licensee if any of the following conditions is met:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-246__subsec_f__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the licensee is found to be in substantial compliance with each support order applicable to the licensee or has negotiated an agreement with the agency for a payment schedule on arrearages and is in substantial compliance with the negotiated agreement;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-246__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the licensee has submitted a timely request for review to the agency, but the agency will be unable to complete the review and send notice of findings to the licensee in sufficient time for the licensee to file a timely request for judicial relief within the 150-day period before the licensee's license will be suspended under (c) of this section; this paragraph applies only if the delay in completing the review process is not the result of the licensee's failure to act in a reasonable, timely, and diligent manner upon receiving notice from the agency that the licensee's driver's license will be suspended in 150 days;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-246__subsec_f__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the licensee has, within 30 days after receiving the agency's findings following a request for review under (2) of this subsection, filed and served a request for judicial relief under this section, but a resolution of that relief will not be made within the 150-day period before license suspension under (c) of this section; this paragraph applies only if the delay in completing the judicial relief process is not the result of the licensee's failure to act in a reasonable, timely, and diligent manner upon receiving the agency's notice of findings; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-246__subsec_f__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the licensee has obtained a judicial finding of substantial compliance.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-246__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A licensee is required to act with diligence in responding to notices from the agency with the recognition that the person's driver's license will be suspended after 150 days or that a subsequent license will not be issued and that the agency and, where appropriate, the court must have time to act within that 150-day period or before the subsequent license is needed, as applicable. A licensee's delay in acting, without good cause, that directly results in the inability of the agency to complete a review of the licensee's request or the court to hear the request for judicial relief within the required period does not constitute the diligence required under this section that would justify the issuance of a release.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-246__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the agency refuses to release the license under (f) of this section or the agency revokes a release under (n) or (o) of this section, the agency shall notify the licensee in writing that the licensee may request any or all of the following: (1) judicial relief from the agency's decision not to issue a release or the agency's decision to revoke a release under (n) or (o) of this section; (2) a judicial determination of substantial compliance; (3) a modification of the support order. The notice must also contain the name and address of the court in which the licensee may file the request for relief. The licensee shall comply with all statutes and rules of court implementing this section. This section does not limit a licensee's authority under other law to request an order to show cause or notice of motion to modify a support order or to fix a payment schedule on arrearages accruing under a support order or to obtain a court finding of substantial compliance with a support order.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-246__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A request for judicial relief from the agency's decision not to issue a release under (f) of this section or from the agency's decision to revoke a release under (n) or (o) of this section must state the grounds on which relief is requested, and the judicial action shall be limited to those stated grounds. Judicial relief under this subsection is not an appeal and shall be governed by court rules adopted to implement this section. Unless otherwise provided by court rule, the court shall hold an evidentiary hearing within 20 calendar days after the filing of service on the opposing party. The court's decision shall be limited to a determination of each of the following issues, as applicable:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-246__subsec_i__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>whether there is a support order or a payment schedule on arrearages;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-246__subsec_i__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>whether the petitioner is the obligor covered by the support order; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-246__subsec_i__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>whether the obligor is in substantial compliance with the support order or payment schedule.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-246__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the court finds that the person requesting relief is in substantial compliance with the support order or payment schedule, the agency shall immediately send a release under (f) of this section to the department and the licensee.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-246__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a licensee is in substantial compliance with a support order or payment schedule, the agency shall mail to the licensee and the department a release stating that the licensee is in substantial compliance. The receipt of a release shall serve to notify the licensee and the department that, for the purposes of this section, the licensee is in substantial compliance with the support order or payment schedule unless the agency</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-246__subsec_k__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>under (a) of this section, certifies subsequent to the issuance of a release that the licensee is once again not in substantial compliance with a support order; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-246__subsec_k__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>under (n), (o), or (p) of this section, revokes a release because the licensee is not in substantial compliance with a payment schedule negotiated under this section.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-246__subsec_l">
              <num>(l)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The process described in (f) of this section is the sole administrative remedy for contesting the suspension or the denial of a driver's license under this section. The procedures specified in
AS 28
or
AS 44.62.330
 44.62.630 do not apply to the suspension or failure to issue or renew a license under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-246__subsec_m">
              <num>(m)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The agency and department, as appropriate, shall adopt regulations necessary to implement this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-246__subsec_n">
              <num>(n)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the agency releases a license under (f)(2) or (3) of this section because the review could not be completed within the 150-day period, the review process, including any request for judicial relief, may be completed after the 150-day period. If, at the completion of the review process, the licensee is found not to be in substantial compliance with each support order applicable to the licensee and has not entered into a payment schedule under this section, the agency shall send to the department a revocation of the release previously sent to the department for that licensee. The agency shall send notice of the revocation to the licensee as provided in (h) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-246__subsec_o">
              <num>(o)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (p) of this section, if the licensee fails to be in substantial compliance with a payment schedule negotiated under this section, the agency shall send to the department a revocation of any release previously sent to the department for that licensee. The agency shall send notice of the revocation to the licensee as provided in (h) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-246__subsec_p">
              <num>(p)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a licensee fails to be in substantial compliance with a payment schedule negotiated under this section but paid the monthly obligation under the payment schedule for at least two years immediately after the schedule was negotiated, the agency shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-246__subsec_p__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>revoke the release previously granted to the licensee under this section and notify the department and licensee that the release has been revoked; the licensee may not challenge the revocation of this release; upon receiving the agency's notice under this paragraph, the department may not suspend the licensee's driver's license or refuse to issue or renew a driver's license for the licensee unless the department subsequently receives a new notice to do so from the agency under (c) of this section;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-246__subsec_p__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>initiate new proceedings against the licensee under this section by placing the licensee's name on the list compiled under (a) of this section after following the procedures required under (a) of this section;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-246__subsec_p__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>follow the procedures of this section with respect to the licensee as if it were the first time that the licensee's name had been placed on the list compiled under (a) of this section, except that the agency may either negotiate a new payment schedule under (f)(1) of this section or seek to enforce the previously negotiated payment schedule.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-246__subsec_q">
              <num>(q)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-246__subsec_q__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>department means the Department of Administration;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-246__subsec_q__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>driver's license or license means a driver's license, as defined in
AS 28.90.990
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-246__subsec_q__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>licensee means a person holding or requesting a driver's license;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-246__subsec_q__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>list means the list of obligors and other persons compiled and maintained under (a) of this section;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-246__subsec_q__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>substantial compliance regarding a support order or payment schedule means that, with respect to periodic payments required under a support order or a negotiated payment schedule under (f) of this section, whichever is applicable, the obligor has
(A) no arrearage;
(B) an arrearage in an amount that is not more than four times the monthly obligation under the support order or payment schedule; or
(C) been determined by a court to be making the best efforts possible under the obligor's circumstances to have no arrearages under any support order that requires periodic payments or under a negotiated payment schedule relating to child support.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-250">
            <num>25.27.250</num>
            <heading>Order to withhold and deliver.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-27-250__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Without prior notice to the obligor, the agency may issue to any person, including an entity, political subdivision, or state agency, an order to withhold and deliver property under this section; the order may be issued</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-250__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>immediately upon issuance of an income withholding order that provides for immediate income withholding under
AS 25.27.062</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-250__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>immediately after an arrearage occurs under a support order described in
AS 25.27.150</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-250__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>at the expiration of 30 days after the date of service of a notice and finding of financial responsibility under
AS 25.27.160
; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-250__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>at the expiration of 30 days after service of a decision establishing paternity and financial responsibility under
AS 25.27.165
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-250__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>All real or personal property belonging to the obligor is subject to an order to withhold and deliver, including, but not limited to, earnings that are due, owing, or belonging to the debtor. In calculating the amount to be withheld and delivered under an order issued under this section, the agency shall give credit to the obligor for the cost to the obligor of medical and dental insurance for the children and educational payments for the children to the extent that the insurance coverage and educational payments are required in the applicable child support order and are actually paid for by the obligor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-250__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The agency may issue an order to withhold and deliver when it has reason to believe that there is in the possession of a person, political subdivision, or department of the state property that is due, owing, or belonging to the obligor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-250__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The order to withhold and deliver shall be served upon the person, political subdivision, or department of the state possessing the property electronically or in the manner provided for service of liens under
AS 25.27.240
. The order must state the amount of the obligor's liability and must state in summary the terms of
AS 25.27.260
and 25.27.270.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-250__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Any person, political subdivision, or department of the state served with an order to withhold and deliver is required to make true answers to inquiries contained in the order under oath and in writing within 14 days after service of the order, and is further required to answer all inquiries subsequently put.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-250__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a person, political subdivision, or department of the state upon whom service of an order to withhold and deliver has been made possesses property due, owing, or belonging to the obligor, that person, subdivision, or department shall withhold the property immediately upon receipt of the order and shall deliver the property to the agency (1) if the property is earnings of an employee who is subject to a child support order being enforced by the agency, within seven business days after the amount would, but for this section, have been paid or credited to the employee; or (2) in the case of all other property, within 14 business days after the date of service of the order. The agency shall hold property delivered under this subsection in trust for application against the liability of the obligor under
AS 25.27.062
, 25.27.120, or 25.27.160 or for return, without interest, depending on final determination of liability or nonliability under this chapter. The agency may accept a good and sufficient bond to secure payment of past, present, and future support conditioned upon final determination of liability in lieu of requiring delivery of property under this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-250__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Delivery to the agency of the money or other property due, owing, or belonging to the obligor shall satisfy the requirement of the order to withhold and deliver.  Delivery of money due and owing to the obligor under any contract of employment, express or implied, or held by any person, political subdivision, or department of the state, and subject to withdrawal by the obligor, shall be delivered by remittance payable to the order of the agency.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-250__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 148(a) ch 87 SLA 1997.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-250__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An order to withhold and deliver under this section has priority over all other attachments, executions, garnishments, or other legal process brought under state law against the same property unless otherwise ordered by the court. Exemptions under
AS 09.38
do not apply to proceedings to enforce the payment of child support under
AS 25.27.230
 25.27.270; however, net disposable earnings are exempt from execution as provided in 15 U.S.C. 1673(b).  In this subsection, net disposable earnings has the meaning given in 15 U.S.C. 1672.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-250__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person, political subdivision, or department that fails to comply with an order to withhold and deliver served under this subsection is subject to penalties under
AS 25.27.260
. A person, political subdivision, or department may, for each payment made under an order to withhold and deliver, deduct $5 from other wages or salary owed to the obligor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-253">
            <num>25.27.253</num>
            <heading>Earnings subject to an order or lien.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-27-253__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person, political subdivision, or department of the state shall withhold the earnings of the obligor subject to an order or lien at each succeeding interval of payment until the entire amount of the debt stated in the order to withhold and deliver has been withheld.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-253__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An order to withhold and deliver issued to the Department of Revenue remains in effect throughout the calendar year in which it is served.  That order applies to any tax refund or other disbursements to which the obligor is entitled even if the tax refund or disbursement is issued more than 30 days after service of the order.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-255">
            <num>25.27.255</num>
            <heading>Disposition of payments under income withholding orders.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-27-255__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The agency shall pay to the obligee all money recovered by the agency from the obligor under an income withholding order except for court costs and money assigned to the agency under
AS 25.27.120
 25.27.130. However, if there is more than one income withholding order under this chapter against an obligor, the agency shall allocate amounts available for withholding in a manner that gives priority to current support up to the limits imposed under 15 U.S.C. 1673(b) (sec. 303(b), Consumer Credit Protection Act). Notwithstanding the priority given to current support, the agency shall establish procedures for allocation of support among obligees so that in no case will the allocation result in a withholding order for one obligee not being implemented.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-255__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 34 ch 7 FSSLA 1994.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-255__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 34 ch 7 FSSLA 1994.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-260">
            <num>25.27.260</num>
            <heading>Civil liability upon failure to comply with an order or lien.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-27-260__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a person, political subdivision, or department of the state (1) fails to make an answer to an order to withhold and deliver within the time prescribed in
AS 25.27.250
; (2) fails or refuses to deliver property in accordance with an order issued under
AS 25.27.250
; (3) pays over, releases, sells, transfers, or conveys real property subject to a lien recorded under
AS 25.27.230
to or for the benefit of the obligor or any other person; (4) fails or refuses to surrender upon demand property attached; or (5) intentionally fails or refuses to honor an assignment of wages or an income withholding order under
AS 25.27.062
that was served by the agency through personal service by a process server or through certified mail, return receipt requested, the person, political subdivision, or department of the state is liable to the agency in an amount equal to 100 percent of the amount constituting the basis of the lien, order to withhold and deliver, attachment, or withholding of wages or income, together with costs, interest, and reasonable attorney fees.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-260__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person, political subdivision, or department of the state that intentionally fails or refuses to honor a properly served income withholding order under
AS 25.27.062
that is not being enforced by the agency is liable to the obligee in an amount equal to 100 percent of the amount ordered to be withheld together with costs, interest, and reasonable attorney fees.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-265">
            <num>25.27.265</num>
            <heading>Method of service; notification of change of address.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-27-265__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as otherwise provided under this chapter, when a notice, paper, or other document is required by this chapter to be given or served upon a person by the agency, the notice, paper, or other document may be served as required by Rule 5, Alaska Rules of Civil Procedure or any other method permitted by law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-265__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each party to a paternity or child support proceeding shall file with the tribunal and inform the agency of the party's name, location, social security number, residential and mailing addresses, telephone number, and driver's license number, as well as the name, address, and telephone number of any employer of the party. If a change in this information occurs, the party shall immediately notify the tribunal and the agency and provide updated information.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-265__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (a) of this section, if a tribunal finds that the agency has made diligent efforts to give or serve a notice, paper, or other document required by this chapter, the tribunal may order that service in any subsequent child support enforcement effort by the agency may be given upon the party by sending the document by first class mail to the party's most recent mailing address on file with the agency.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-270">
            <num>25.27.270</num>
            <heading>Judicial relief from administrative execution.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.27.270.   Judicial relief from administrative execution.
Any person against whose property a lien has been recorded under
AS 25.27.230
or an order to withhold and deliver served in accordance with
AS 25.27.250
may apply for relief to the superior court.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-273">
            <num>25.27.273</num>
            <heading>Reporting of payment information concerning delinquent obligors.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-27-273__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The agency may provide to credit bureaus or lending institutions of any kind information about delinquent support owed by obligors. The information provided must consist solely of the payment history of the obligor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-273__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon an obligor's payment of delinquent support, the agency shall immediately notify all credit bureaus and lending institutions that were furnished information about the obligor under (a) of this section that the obligor is no longer delinquent.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-275">
            <num>25.27.275</num>
            <heading>Nondisclosure of information in exceptional circumstances.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.27.275.   Nondisclosure of information in exceptional circumstances.
Upon a finding, which may be made ex parte, that the health, safety, or liberty of a party or child would be unreasonably put at risk by the disclosure of identifying information, or if an existing order so provides, a tribunal shall order that the address of the party or child or other identifying information not be disclosed in a pleading or other document filed in a proceeding under this chapter. A person aggrieved by an order of nondisclosure issued under this section that is based on an ex parte finding is entitled on request to a formal hearing, within 30 days of when the order was issued, at which the person may contest the order.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-278">
            <num>25.27.278</num>
            <heading>Payments not disbursed.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.27.278.   Payments not disbursed.
Support payments collected and held by the agency for seven years without disbursal shall be returned to the obligor.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-279">
            <num>25.27.279</num>
            <heading>Voiding of fraudulent transfers made to avoid payment of child support.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.27.279.   Voiding of fraudulent transfers made to avoid payment of child support.
In addition to the rights provided in
AS 09.25.060
, if a transfer of personal or real property is made by an obligor without immediate delivery and the actual continuing change of possession of the property transferred, the transfer of the property is presumed prima facie to be fraud against creditors for child support of the obligor who transferred the property and subsequent purchasers in good faith and for valuable consideration during the time the property remains in the possession of the obligor who made the transfer, except that retention of possession in good faith and current course of trade by a merchant seller for a commercially reasonable time after the sale or identification is not fraudulent. Nothing contained in this section supersedes the provisions of
AS 45.01

AS 45.08
,
AS 45.12
,
AS 45.14
, and
AS 45.29
(Uniform Commercial Code).</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-280">
            <num>25.27.280</num>
            <heading>Severability: Alternative when method of notification held invalid.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.27.280.   Severability: Alternative when method of notification held invalid.
If any provision of this chapter or the application of it to any person or circumstance is held invalid, the invalidity shall not affect other provisions or applications of this chapter which can be given effect without the invalid provision or application, and to this end the provisions of this chapter are severable.  If any method of notification provided for in this chapter is held invalid, service as provided for by the laws of the state for service of process in a civil action shall be substituted for the method held invalid.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-300">
            <num>25.27.300</num>
            <heading>Requests pertaining to remarriage.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 25.27.300.   Requests pertaining to remarriage.
The agency shall, at the request of a person who is an obligor under a support order enforced by the agency that includes support for a parent with whom a child is living or at the request of a child support enforcement agency of another jurisdiction that is enforcing a support order that includes support for a parent with whom a child is living, request the Bureau of Vital Statistics to disclose to the agency whether the parent has remarried in the state after a specified date if the support order provides that the support for the parent is payable only until the parent remarries. The agency may disclose to the obligor or other child support enforcement agency, as applicable, the information provided by the bureau.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-320">
            <num>25.27.320</num>
            <heading>Interest on agency return of certain overpayments.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-27-320__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the agency disburses money to an obligor because the agency made an error and mistakenly required the obligor to overpay under a support order enforced by the agency, the agency shall include interest with the disbursement at the rate of six percent a year. The interest accrues from the date the payment at issue was received by the agency, regardless of when the payment is determined to be an overpayment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-320__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The provisions of (a) of this section do not apply to situations where the agency is ordered by a court to return money to an obligor based on the obligor's being the prevailing party in a court action.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_25-27-900">
            <num>25.27.900</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="25-27-900__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and 25.27.063;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-900__subsec_c__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>earnings includes income from any form of periodic payment due to an individual, regardless of source; the gain derived from the investment of capital, from labor, or from a combination of investment and labor; and the interest on any of this income; in this paragraph, periodic payment includes wages, salaries, commissions, bonuses, workers' compensation, disability benefits, and payments under a pension or retirement program;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-900__subsec_c__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>employer means an individual or entity within the meaning given that term in 26 U.S.C. 3401(d); employer includes a governmental entity or a labor organization;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-900__subsec_c__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>high-volume automated administrative enforcement means the use of automatic data processing to search various state data bases, including license records, employment service data, and state new-hire registries, to determine whether information is available regarding a parent who owes a child support obligation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-900__subsec_c__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>obligee means a person to whom a duty of support is owed;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-900__subsec_c__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>obligor means a person owing a duty of support;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-900__subsec_c__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>support order means any judgment, decree, or order that is issued by a tribunal for the support and maintenance of a child or of a parent with whom the child is living; support order includes a judgment, decree, or order
(A) on behalf of a child who has reached the age of majority if the judgment, decree, or order was lawfully issued; and
(B) for any or all of the following:</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-900__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>monetary support, including arrearages;
(ii) payment of health care costs or maintenance of health insurance;
(iii) payment of cash medical support;
(iv) reimbursement of related costs;</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="25-27-900__subsec_v">
              <num>(v)</num>
              <content>
                <p>payment of attorney fees and legal costs and other fees; or
(vi) penalty, interest, and other relief as required by a tribunal;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="25-27-900__subsec_v__subsec_13">
                <num>(13)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>tribunal means a court, administrative agency, or quasi-judicial entity authorized to establish, enforce, or modify support orders or to determine parentage.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>