<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-41/chapter-08"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-41/chapter-08"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="41.08"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-41/chapter-08/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-41/chapter-08/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-41/chapter-08/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-41/chapter-08/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_41">
        <num>41</num>
        <heading>Public Resources</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_41__chp_08">
          <num>08</num>
          <heading>Geological and Geophysical Surveys</heading>
          <section eId="sec_41-08-010">
            <num>41.08.010</num>
            <heading>Division of geological and geophysical surveys.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.08.010.   Division of geological and geophysical surveys.
There is established in the department a division of geological and geophysical surveys under the direction of the state geologist.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-08-015">
            <num>41.08.015</num>
            <heading>State geologist.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.08.015.   State geologist.
The commissioner shall appoint the state geologist, who must be qualified by education and experience to direct the activities of the division.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-08-017">
            <num>41.08.017</num>
            <heading>Hydrological and seismic hazard data declared to be of public interest.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-08-017__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Systematic collection, recording, evaluation, and distribution of data on the quantity, location, and quality of water of the state in the ground, on the surface of the ground, or along the coasts, are in the public interest and necessary to the orderly domestic and industrial development of the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-08-017__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Systematic collection, evaluation, archival, and distribution of geologic data and information on earthquakes, volcanic eruptions, and engineering geology and identification of potential seismic, volcanic, and other geological hazards throughout the state are in the public interest and necessary to orderly, safely, and cost-effective development in the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-08-020">
            <num>41.08.020</num>
            <heading>Powers and duties.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-08-020__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The state geologist shall conduct geological and geophysical surveys to determine the potential of Alaskan land for production of metals, minerals, fuels, and geothermal resources; the locations and supplies of groundwater and construction materials; the potential geologic hazards to buildings, roads, bridges, and other installations and structures; and shall conduct such other surveys and investigations as will advance knowledge of the geology of the state. With the approval of the commissioner, the state geologist may acquire, by gift or purchase, geological and geophysical reports, surveys, and similar information.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-08-020__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition, the division of geological and geophysical surveys shall:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="41-08-020__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>collect, record, evaluate, and distribute data on the quantity, quality, and location of underground, surface, and coastal water of the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-08-020__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>publish or have published data on the water of the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-08-020__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>require the filing with it of the results and findings of surveys of water quality, quantity, and location;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-08-020__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>require of water well contractors, the filing with it of basic water and aquifer data normally obtained, including but not limited to well location, estimated elevation, well driller's logs, pumping tests and flow measurements, and water quality determinations;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-08-020__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>accept and spend funds for the purposes of this section,
AS 41.08.017
, and 41.08.035 and enter into agreements with individuals, public or private agencies, communities, private industry, state agencies, and agencies of the federal government;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-08-020__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>collect, evaluate, and distribute geologic data on seismic events and engineering geology of the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-08-020__subsec_b__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>identify potential seismic hazards that might affect development in the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-08-020__subsec_b__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>inform public officials and industry about potential seismic hazards that might affect development in the state.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-08-030">
            <num>41.08.030</num>
            <heading>Printing and distribution of reports.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.08.030.   Printing and distribution of reports.
The state geologist shall print and publish an annual report and other special and topical reports and maps as may be desirable for the benefit of the state, including the printing or reprinting of reports and maps made by other persons or agencies, where authorization to do so is obtained.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-08-035">
            <num>41.08.035</num>
            <heading>Regulations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.08.035.   Regulations.
The department may adopt regulations relating to and providing for the systematic collection, recording, and distribution of data on the water of the state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-08-040">
            <num>41.08.040</num>
            <heading>Cooperation with other agencies.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.08.040.   Cooperation with other agencies.
The state geologist, with the consent of the commissioner, may enter into cooperative agreements with federal, state, and local governmental agencies to perform geological and geophysical surveys, studies, investigations, and services.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-08-045">
            <num>41.08.045</num>
            <heading>Fees for facilities, equipment, products, and services.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-08-045__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (c) of this section, the division of geological and geophysical surveys may charge and collect a fee for facilities, equipment, products, or services that the division offers, including</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="41-08-045__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>rental of space for confidential sample storage;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-08-045__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>rental of sample viewing facilities;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-08-045__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>retrieval, cutting, splitting, processing, or sampling of geological materials;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-08-045__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>use of equipment, including microscopes; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-08-045__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>analyses, maps, reports, data, or products authorized by the division.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-08-045__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The division of geological and geophysical surveys shall establish fees that may be charged and collected under (a) of this section by regulation. Before setting the fees, the division shall consider, at public hearings, the</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="41-08-045__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>cost to the state of operating the facility or providing the service or equipment;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-08-045__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>normal fees charged for similar facilities, equipment, or services by governmental and nongovernmental entities;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-08-045__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>cost of administering a fee collection program for the facility, equipment, or service; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="41-08-045__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>public interest.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-08-045__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The division shall waive fees under this section for a student who uses facilities, equipment, products, or services for educational purposes.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-08-045__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Fees collected under this section shall be separately accounted for under
AS 37.05.142
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>