<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-30"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-30"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="14.30"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-30/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-30/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-30/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-30/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_14">
        <num>14</num>
        <heading>Education, Libraries, and Museums</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_14__chp_30">
          <num>30</num>
          <heading>Pupils and Educational Programs for Pupils</heading>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-010">
            <num>14.30.010</num>
            <heading>When attendance compulsory.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-30-010__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Every child between seven and 16 years of age shall attend school at the public school in the district in which the child resides during each school term.  Every parent, guardian or other person having the responsibility for or control of a child between seven and 16 years of age shall maintain the child in attendance at a public school in the district in which the child resides during the entire school term, except as provided in (b) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-010__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This section does not apply if a child</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-010__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is provided an academic education comparable to that offered by the public schools in the area, either by
(A) attendance at a private school in which the teachers are certificated according to
AS 14.20.020
;
(B) tutoring by personnel certificated according to
AS 14.20.020
; or
(C) attendance at an educational program operated in compliance with
AS 14.45.100
 14.45.200 by a religious or other private school;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-010__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>attends a school operated by the federal government;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-010__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has a physical or mental condition that a competent medical authority determines will make attendance impractical;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-010__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is in the custody of a court or law enforcement authorities;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-010__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is temporarily ill or injured;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-010__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has been suspended or expelled under
AS 14.03.160
or suspended or denied admittance under
AS 14.30.045
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-010__subsec_b__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>resides more than two miles from either a public school or a route on which transportation is provided by the school authorities, except that this paragraph does not apply if the child resides within two miles of a federal or private school that the child is eligible and able to attend;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-010__subsec_b__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is excused by action of the school board of the district at a regular meeting or by the district superintendent subject to approval by the school board of the district at the next regular meeting;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-010__subsec_b__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has completed the 12th grade;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-010__subsec_b__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is enrolled in
(A) a state boarding school established under
AS 14.16
; or
(B) a full-time program of correspondence study approved by the department; in those school districts providing an approved correspondence study program, a student may be enrolled either in the district correspondence program or in the centralized correspondence study program;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-010__subsec_b__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is equally well-served by an educational experience approved by the school board as serving the child's educational interests despite an absence from school, and the request for excuse is made in writing by the child's parents or guardian and approved by the principal or administrator of the school that the child attends;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-010__subsec_b__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is being educated in the child's home by a parent or legal guardian.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-010__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a parent, legal guardian, or other person having the responsibility for or control of the child elects to enroll a child who is six years of age in first grade at a public school, after enrollment, the child is subject to the provisions of (a) and (b) of this section. If the parent or guardian of a child who is six years of age and is enrolled in first grade at a public school determines, within 60 days after the child is enrolled, that the best interests of the child are not being served by enrollment in the first grade, the child may be withdrawn from school, and the provisions of (a) and (b) of this section do not apply to the child until the child is seven years of age.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-020">
            <num>14.30.020</num>
            <heading>Violations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.30.020.   Violations.
A person who knowingly fails to comply with
AS 14.30.010
is guilty of a violation. Each five days of unlawful absence under
AS 14.30.010
is a separate violation.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-030">
            <num>14.30.030</num>
            <heading>Prevention and reduction of truancy.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.30.030.   Prevention and reduction of truancy.
The governing body of a school district, including a regional educational attendance area, shall establish procedures to prevent and reduce truancy.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-045">
            <num>14.30.045</num>
            <heading>Grounds for suspension or denial of admission.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.30.045.   Grounds for suspension or denial of admission.
A school age child may be suspended from or denied admission to the public school that the child is otherwise entitled to attend only for the following causes:
(1) continued wilful disobedience or open and persistent defiance of reasonable school authority;
(2) behavior that is inimicable to the welfare, safety, or morals of other pupils or a person employed or volunteering at the school;
(3) a physical or mental condition that in the opinion of a competent medical authority will render the child unable to reasonably benefit from the programs available;
(4) a physical or mental condition that in the opinion of a competent medical authority will cause the attendance of the child to be inimicable to the welfare of other pupils;
(5) conviction of a felony that the governing body of the district determines will cause the attendance of the child to be inimicable to the welfare or education of other pupils.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-047">
            <num>14.30.047</num>
            <heading>Admission or readmission when cause no longer exists.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-30-047__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A child who has been suspended from or denied admittance to a school under
AS 14.30.045</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-047__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>or (4) shall be permitted to attend school when the child is obviously recovered or presents to the governing body a statement in writing from a competent medical authority that the child is no longer afflicted with, or suffering from, the physical or mental condition to the extent that it is a cause for suspension or denial of admission under
AS 14.30.045</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-047__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>or (4).</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-047__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A child who has been suspended from or denied admittance to a school for any other cause provided by
AS 14.30.045
shall be permitted to attend school when it reasonably appears that the cause has been remedied.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-060">
            <num>14.30.060</num>
            <heading>Purpose ofAS 14.30.070 14.30.110. [Repealed, § 59 ch 98 SLA 1966.]</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.30.060.   Purpose of
AS 14.30.070
 14.30.110. [Repealed, § 59 ch 98 SLA 1966.]</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-065">
            <num>14.30.065</num>
            <heading>Supervision.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.30.065.   Supervision.
The program of physical examination and immunizations prescribed by
AS 14.30.065
 14.30.127 shall be under the general supervision and in accordance with regulations of the Department of Health.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-070">
            <num>14.30.070</num>
            <heading>Physical examination required.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-30-070__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, §§ 25, 29 ch 2 SSSLA 2015.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-070__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Health may require the district to conduct physical examinations that it considers necessary, and may reimburse the district for the examinations on the basis and to the extent the commissioner of health prescribes by regulation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-070__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Examinations shall be made by a competent physician or, within the scope of chiropractic practice, by a chiropractor, except that if the services of a physician or chiropractor cannot be obtained or if authorized by the commissioner of health examinations may be made by a nurse.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-075">
            <num>14.30.075</num>
            <heading>Physical examinations for teachers.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-30-075__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A school district may require physical examinations of teachers as a condition of employment. A school district is not required to pay the cost of physical examinations for teachers. This section does not affect the coverage of any health insurance benefits that a school district provides to teachers.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-075__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, school district has the meaning given in
AS 14.30.350
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-125">
            <num>14.30.125</num>
            <heading>Immunization.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.30.125.   Immunization.
If in the judgment of the commissioner of health it is necessary for the welfare of the children or the general public in an area, the governing body of the school district shall require the children attending school in that area to be immunized against the diseases the commissioner of health may specify.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-127">
            <num>14.30.127</num>
            <heading>Vision and hearing screening examinations.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-30-127__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A vision and hearing screening examination shall be given to each child attending school in the state. The examination shall be made when the child enters school or as soon thereafter as is practicable, and at regular intervals specified by regulation by the governing body of the district.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-127__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Health shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-127__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>set standards for the performance of vision and hearing screening;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-127__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>train and certify public health nurses and school district employees to conduct hearing and vision screening tests;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-127__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>assist with referral and follow-up of children needing professional examination or treatment; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-127__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>assist with maintenance and repair of screening equipment.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-141">
            <num>14.30.141</num>
            <heading>Self-administration and documentation of medication.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-30-141__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A public school shall permit the self-administration of medication by a pupil for asthma or anaphylaxis if, during the current school year, the pupil's parent or guardian provides the school</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-141__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>written authorization for the self-administration of the medication;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-141__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>written certification from the pupil's health care provider that the pupil
(A) has asthma or a condition that may lead to anaphylaxis;
(B) has received instruction in the proper method of self-administration of the medication; and
(C) has demonstrated to the health care provider the skill level necessary to use the medication and any device that is necessary to administer the medication as prescribed;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-141__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a release of liability for the school and its employees or agents for injury arising from the self-administration or storage of the medication;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-141__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an agreement to indemnify and hold harmless the school and its employees or agents for any claims arising out the self-administration or storage of the medication;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-141__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a written treatment plan for the pupil that is signed by the pupil's health care provider for managing asthma or anaphylaxis episodes, a list and dosage of medications needed during school hours, and permission for and instruction on storage of the medication at school; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-141__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>any other documentation required by the school that is consistent with this section.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-141__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The public school shall provide written notification to the pupil's parent or guardian of the school's absence of liability related to the self-administration of medication under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-141__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A pupil who is permitted to self-administer medication under this section shall be permitted to carry and to store with the school nurse or other designated school official an inhaler or autoinjectable epinephrine, or both, at all times.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-141__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a student uses the student's prescribed medication in a manner other than as prescribed, disciplinary action according to school codes may be imposed upon the student. The imposed disciplinary action may not limit or restrict the student's immediate access to the student's prescribed medication.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-141__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, health care provider means a licensed physician, advanced practice registered nurse, physician assistant, village health aide, or pharmacist operating within the scope of the health care provider's authority.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-142">
            <num>14.30.142</num>
            <heading>Concussions in student athletes: prevention and reporting.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-30-142__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The governing body of a school district shall consult with the Alaska School Activities Association to develop and publish guidelines and other information to educate coaches, student athletes, and parents of student athletes regarding the nature and risks of concussions. Guidelines developed under this section must include a description of the risks of return to play and standards for return to play, including the procedures required under (c) and (d) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-142__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A school shall annually provide to a student and the parent or guardian of a student who is under 18 years of age written information on the nature and risks of concussions. A student may not participate in school athletic activities unless the student and the parent or guardian of a student who is under 18 years of age have signed a verification of receipt of the information required under this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-142__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A student who is suspected of having sustained a concussion during a practice or game shall be immediately removed from the practice or game.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-142__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A student who has been removed from participation in a practice or game for suspicion of concussion may not return to participation in practice or game play until the student has been evaluated and cleared for participation in writing by an athletic trainer or other qualified person who has received training, as verified in writing or electronically by the qualified person, in the evaluation and management of concussions. In this subsection, qualified person means either a</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-142__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>health care provider who is licensed in the state or exempt from licensure under state law; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-142__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>person who is acting at the direction and under the supervision of a physician who is licensed in the state or exempt from licensure under
AS 08.64.370
(1), (2), (4), or (6).</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-142__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who conducts an evaluation under (d) of this section and who is not paid for conducting the evaluation may not be held liable for civil damages resulting from an act or omission during the evaluation, except that the person may be held liable for reckless or intentional misconduct and for gross negligence.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-143">
            <num>14.30.143</num>
            <heading>Concussions in student athletes: school district immunity.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-30-143__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A school district may not be held liable for an injury to or the death of a person caused by a concussion and resulting from the action or inaction of a person employed by or under contract with a nonprofit youth organization if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-143__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the action or inaction occurred during the delivery of services by the district or organization in compliance with
AS 14.30.142
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-143__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the organization is under contract with the district to provide the services; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-143__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>before the provision of services, the organization provided to the district written verification of
(A) a valid insurance policy covering the injury or death in an amount not less than $50,000 for each person and $100,000 for each incident;
(B) compliance with the protocol for prevention and reporting of concussions required in
AS 14.30.142
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-143__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This section may not be construed to impair or modify the ability of a person to recover damages for harm caused by the negligent or reckless actions of an employee or contractor of a school district or by the existence of a condition, equipment, program, or structure known by the school district or organization to be unsafe.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-143__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, youth organization means a public or private entity qualified to do business in the state that provides a program or service to persons under 19 years of age.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-145">
            <num>14.30.145</num>
            <heading>Opioid overdose drugs.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-30-145__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each school district shall ensure that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-145__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a person trained to administer an opioid overdose drug is on site
(A) when the main school building of each school in the school district is open to students or staff, including periods when the school building is open before and after school hours and during weekend activities; and
(B) during each school-sponsored event conducted on school grounds;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-145__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the main school building of each school in the school district has at least two doses of an opioid overdose drug available on site; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-145__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>at least one dose of an opioid overdose drug is available during a school-sponsored event conducted on school grounds.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-145__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Health shall provide each school district with the opioid overdose drug required under this section. The commissioner of health shall develop and provide to each school district a short training video about how and when to administer an opioid overdose drug.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-145__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A school district, school, or individual is not liable for civil damages for an injury to another individual resulting from a failure to possess or maintain an opioid overdose drug under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-145__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-145__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>main school building means the building on school grounds where most of the students of the school are educated during regular school hours and the principal, nurse, and other administrative staff of the school are located;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-145__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>opioid overdose drug has the meaning given in
AS 17.20.085</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-145__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>school district means a borough school district, a city school district, a regional educational attendance area, and a state boarding school;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-145__subsec_d__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>school grounds means a building, structure, athletic playing field, playground, parking area, or land contained within the real property boundary line of a school in a school district.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-171">
            <num>14.30.171</num>
            <heading>Prohibited actions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-30-171__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in
AS 14.30.172
 14.30.176, school personnel may not, unless otherwise authorized by law or a specific policy adopted by a governing body of a school district,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-171__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>recommend to a parent or guardian that a child take or continue to take a psychotropic drug as a condition for attending a public school;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-171__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>require that a child take or continue to take a psychotropic drug as a condition for attending a public school, except when, in the opinion of the child's treating physician,
(A) the medication is necessary for the mental health of the child; or
(B) the child poses a risk of harm to self or others without the medication;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-171__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>conduct a psychiatric evaluation of a child;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-171__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>recommend a specific licensed physician, psychologist, or other health specialist to a parent or guardian for a child; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-171__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>recommend that a parent or guardian seek or use for a child
(A) a psychotropic medication; or
(B) a psychiatric or psychological treatment.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-171__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>As used in this section, school personnel means persons employed by a public school or school district to work in a public school, except for a person who holds a special services type C certificate issued under
AS 14.20
that qualifies the person to be employed to provide related services to students, as described in regulations adopted by the board.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-172">
            <num>14.30.172</num>
            <heading>Communication not prohibited.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-30-172__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing in
AS 14.30.171
may be construed to prohibit school personnel from</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-172__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>consulting or sharing classroom-based observations with parents or guardians regarding a student's academic and functional performance, behavior in the classroom or school, or the need for evaluation for special education or related services as long as school personnel do not make an assertion or recommendation that violates
AS 14.30.171
; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-172__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>exercising their authority relating to the placement within the school or readmission of a child who may be or has been suspended or expelled for a violation of a school disciplinary and safety program adopted under
AS 14.03.160
,
AS 14.30.045
, or
AS 14.33.110
 14.33.140.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-172__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing in
AS 14.30.171
may be construed to prevent teachers or other school personnel from complying with the requirements of
AS 47.17.020</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-172__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or (b) or from filing a report to authorities if a child poses a serious and imminent risk to the child's or another person's safety.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-174">
            <num>14.30.174</num>
            <heading>Compliance with federal education law.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-30-174__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding
AS 14.30.171
(a)(3) and (5), a behavioral or mental health professional working within a public school system may, in compliance with federal education law or applicable state law,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-174__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>recommend, but not require, a psychiatric or behavioral health evaluation of a child; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-174__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>recommend, but not require, psychiatric, psychological, or behavioral treatment for a child.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-174__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-174__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>behavioral health professional means a person who has a master's degree in psychology, social work, counseling, or a related field with specialization or experience in working with children experiencing behavioral, physical, and emotional disabilities, and is working within the scope of the person's training and experience;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-174__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>federal education law means 20 U.S.C. 1400  1482 (Individuals with Disabilities Education Act), 20 U.S.C. 7101  7143 (Safe and Drug-Free Schools and Communities Act of 1994), 29 U.S.C. 794 (nondiscrimination under federal grants and programs), and 42 U.S.C. 12101  12213 (equal opportunity for individuals with disabilities);</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-174__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>mental health professional has the meaning given in
AS 47.30.915
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-176">
            <num>14.30.176</num>
            <heading>List of community resources.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-30-176__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding
AS 14.30.171
(a)(4), a school district may make available to an interested parent or guardian a list of community resources, including mental health services if the list conspicuously states the following: This list is provided as a resource to you. The school neither recommends nor requires that you use this list or any of the services provided by individuals or entities on the list. It is for you to decide what services, if any, to use and from whom you wish to obtain them.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-176__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A list provided under (a) of this section must include the name, specialty, and credential of each mental health service provider listed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-177">
            <num>14.30.177</num>
            <heading>Violations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.30.177.   Violations.
Each school board shall adopt a policy that provides that an employee violating
AS 14.30.171
 14.30.176 may be subject to disciplinary action.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-179">
            <num>14.30.179</num>
            <heading>Definition.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.30.179.   Definition.
In
AS 14.30.171
 14.30.179, public school means a school operated by publicly elected or appointed school officials in which the program and activities are under the control of those officials and that is supported by public funds.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-180">
            <num>14.30.180</num>
            <heading>Purpose.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.30.180.   Purpose.
It is the purpose of
AS 14.30.180
 14.30.350 to
(1) provide an appropriate public education for each child with a disability in the state who is at least three years of age but less than 22 years of age;
(2) allow procedures and actions necessary to comply with the requirements of federal law, including 20 U.S.C. 1400  1482 (Individuals with Disabilities Education Act).</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-186">
            <num>14.30.186</num>
            <heading>Coverage; regulations.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-30-186__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Special education and related services shall be provided by</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-186__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a borough or city school district for a child with a disability residing within the district;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-186__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the board of a regional educational attendance area operating a school in the area for a child with a disability residing in the area served by the school;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-186__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the borough, city school district, or regional educational attendance area in which a treatment institution, as that term is defined in
AS 47.14.990
, juvenile detention facility or juvenile treatment facility, as those terms are defined in
AS 47.12.990
, or a correctional facility is located for a child with a disability placed at the facility;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-186__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a state boarding school established under
AS 14.16
for a child with a disability enrolled at a state boarding school; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-186__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a school district that provides a statewide correspondence study program for a child with a disability who is enrolled in the program.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-186__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 41 ch 67 SLA 2001.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-186__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 19 ch 147 SLA 1984.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-186__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 19 ch 147 SLA 1984.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-186__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the parent of a child with a disability elects to educate the child as allowed under
AS 14.30.010
(b), the child may not be compelled to receive the special education and related services provided under
AS 14.30.180
 14.30.350.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-186__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall, by regulation, establish standards for the allocation of financial responsibilities and the coordination of the provision of special education and related services among the educational agencies listed in (a) of this section when more than one educational agency is responsible for providing those services.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-191">
            <num>14.30.191</num>
            <heading>Educational evaluation and placement.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-30-191__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A school district shall obtain the written informed consent of the child's parent before an initial evaluation or placement of a child with a disability in a program of special education and related services.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-191__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After initial placement in a program of special education and related services and not less than once every three years for as long as the child is assigned to the program, a child with a disability shall receive an educational evaluation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-191__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before a school district initiates or refuses a change in the placement or educational program of a child with a disability, the district shall notify the child's parent.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-191__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon completion of an evaluation or reevaluation under this section, the school district shall provide to the parent of each child evaluated under this section an opportunity to participate in the determination of the</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-191__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>child's eligibility for special education and related services; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-191__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>educational placement of the child if the child is determined to be eligible for special education and related services.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-191__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A parent may obtain an independent educational evaluation by choosing a person from a list provided by the district or by choosing a person by agreement between the parent and the school district, at the expense of the school district, if the parent disagrees with an evaluation obtained by the school district. The school district may initiate a hearing to show that its evaluation is appropriate. If the hearing officer determines that the evaluation is appropriate, the school district may not be required to pay for the independent educational evaluation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-191__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the parent obtains an independent educational evaluation at private expense, the results of the evaluation</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-191__subsec_f__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>must be considered by the school district in a decision made with respect to the provision of an appropriate public education to the child;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-191__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>may be presented as evidence at a hearing regarding the child.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-191__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a hearing officer requests an independent educational evaluation as part of a hearing, the school district shall pay for the evaluation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-191__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A school district shall provide written notice of its decision under this section to the parent of the child. The notice must include a description of the procedural safeguards available to the parent and child under federal law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-191__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, hearing means a due process hearing under
AS 14.30.193
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-193">
            <num>14.30.193</num>
            <heading>Due process hearing.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-30-193__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A school district or a parent of a child with a disability may request a due process hearing on any issue related to identification, evaluation, or educational placement of the child, or the provision of a free, appropriate, public education to the child. A request is made by providing written notice to the other party to the hearing. A parent shall make a request for a due process hearing under this section not later than 12 months after the date that the school district provides the parent with written notice of the decision with which the parent disagrees. A school district shall make its request for a due process hearing in accordance with the time limit established by the department by regulation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-193__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a due process hearing is requested by either a school district or a parent, the school district shall contact the department to request appointment of a hearing officer. The department shall select a hearing officer through a random selection process, from a list maintained by the department under (g) of this section. Within five working days after receipt of the request, the department shall provide to the school district and the parent a notice of appointment, including the name and a statement of qualifications, of the hearing officer that the department determines is available to conduct the hearing.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-193__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The school district and the parent each have the right to reject, without stating a reason, one hearing officer appointed under this section. The rejecting party shall notify the department of that rejection in writing within five days after receipt of the department's notice of appointment. If a hearing officer is rejected under this subsection, the department shall, within five working days after receipt of the written rejection, provide a notice of appointment, including the name and a statement of qualifications, of another hearing officer that the department determines is available to conduct the hearing. Each appointment is subject to a right of rejection under this subsection by a party who has not previously rejected an appointment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-193__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After a hearing officer is appointed and the time for rejection under (c) of this section has expired, the hearing officer shall immediately inform the parent and the school district of the availability of the mediation process provided under
AS 14.30.194
and encourage use of that process to attempt to resolve the disagreement between the parent and the school district. If the mediation process does not result in settlement of all of the issues, the hearing officer shall conduct a hearing in conformance with the requirements of federal law, including 34 C.F.R. 300.511  513. After the hearing is completed, the hearing officer shall issue a written decision that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-193__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>upholds the school district's decision; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-193__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>overturns the school district's decision with specific instructions for modification of the identification, evaluation, educational placement, or provision of the education program by the district.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-193__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A hearing officer's decision under this section is final and binding on the school district and parent unless appealed under (f) of this section. Notwithstanding a decision by the hearing officer, a child may not be evaluated, placed, transferred, or compelled to receive special education or related services from the school district until the period for filing an appeal under (f) of this section has expired or, if an appeal is filed, until the appellate review process has been completed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-193__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A hearing officer's decision under this section is a final administrative order, subject to appeal to the superior court for review in the manner provided under
AS 44.62.560
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-193__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall maintain a list of qualified hearing officers and shall provide for qualification of hearing officers through a training program that is open to all individuals who meet the criteria set by the department by regulation. The list of qualified hearing officers shall be maintained as a public record.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-193__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of this section, a student with a disability aged 18  21 has the same rights and obligations under this section as a parent of a child with a disability.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-194">
            <num>14.30.194</num>
            <heading>Mediation.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-30-194__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall, by regulation, establish and implement a voluntary mediation process in conformance with the requirements of federal law, including 34 C.F.R. 300.506. The department shall encourage the use of mediation for settlement of disputes under
AS 14.30.180
 14.30.350.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-194__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-194__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>maintain a list of individuals who are qualified mediators knowledgeable in the federal and state statutes and regulations relating to the provision of special education and related services; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-194__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide for qualification of mediators through a training program that is open to all individuals who meet the criteria set by the department by regulation.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-231">
            <num>14.30.231</num>
            <heading>Advisory panel.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.30.231.   Advisory panel.
The Governor's Council on Disabilities and Special Education established under
AS 44.29.600
shall serve as the state advisory panel, the function of which is to provide information and guidance for the development of appropriate programs of special education and related services for children with disabilities.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-235">
            <num>14.30.235</num>
            <heading>Withdrawal of consent.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.30.235.   Withdrawal of consent.
If under a provision of this chapter the consent of the parent is required, the parent may withdraw the parent's consent.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-250">
            <num>14.30.250</num>
            <heading>Teacher qualifications.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.30.250.   Teacher qualifications.
A person may not be employed as a teacher of children with disabilities unless that person possesses a valid teacher certificate and, in addition, the training that the department requires by regulation.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-255">
            <num>14.30.255</num>
            <heading>Administrator qualifications.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.30.255.   Administrator qualifications.
A person may not be employed as an administrator of a program of special education and related services unless that person possesses a valid administrative certificate and, in addition, such training as the department may require by regulation.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-270">
            <num>14.30.270</num>
            <heading>Substitutes.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.30.270.   Substitutes.
AS 14.30.250
does not prohibit the employment of a person, otherwise qualified to serve as a substitute teacher, to serve as a substitute teacher of children with disabilities.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-272">
            <num>14.30.272</num>
            <heading>Procedural safeguards.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-30-272__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A school district shall inform the parent of a child with a disability of the right</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-272__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to review the child's educational record;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-272__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to review evaluation tests and procedures;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-272__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to refuse to permit evaluation or a change in the child's educational placement;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-272__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to be informed of the results of evaluation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-272__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to obtain an independent evaluation by choosing a person from a list provided by the school district or by choosing a person by agreement between the parent and school district;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-272__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to request a due process hearing;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-272__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to appeal a hearing officer's decision; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-272__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to give consent or deny access to others to the child's educational record.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-272__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall establish, by regulation, impartial procedures for a school district to follow for due process hearings to comply with requirements necessary to participate in federal grant-in-aid programs, including 20 U.S.C. 1400  1482 (Individuals with Disabilities Education Act).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-274">
            <num>14.30.274</num>
            <heading>Identification of children with disabilities.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.30.274.   Identification of children with disabilities.
Each school district shall establish and implement written procedures to ensure that all children with disabilities under the age of 22 for whom the agency is responsible under
AS 14.30.186
to provide special education and related services are identified and located for the purpose of establishing their need for special education and related services.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-276">
            <num>14.30.276</num>
            <heading>Least restrictive environment.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.30.276.   Least restrictive environment.
Each school district shall ensure that, to the maximum extent appropriate, children with disabilities, including children in public or private institutions or other care facilities, are educated with children who are not children with disabilities and that special classes, separate schooling, or other removal of children with disabilities from the regular educational environment occurs only when the nature or severity of the child's disability is such that education in regular classes with the use of supplementary aids and services cannot be achieved satisfactorily.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-278">
            <num>14.30.278</num>
            <heading>Individualized education program; transition services.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-30-278__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A school district shall develop an individualized education program for special education and related services for each eligible child with a disability. The plan must be completed not later than 30 days after the determination of the child's eligibility. Each individualized education program shall be developed and periodically reviewed and revised as necessary in conformance with federal requirements, including 34 C.F.R. 300.320  328.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-278__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When providing transition services as defined in 20 U.S.C. 1401(34) to a child with a disability who is over 15 years of age as part of a program of special education and related services under
AS 14.30.180
 14.30.350, a school district's primary objective and preferred outcome is to help the child become gainfully employed in an integrated workplace where individuals with disabilities work with and alongside of individuals without disabilities, or become enrolled in postsecondary education.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-278__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, gainfully employed means employed full time or part time within one year of leaving high school.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-285">
            <num>14.30.285</num>
            <heading>Transfers of children with disabilities.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-30-285__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall institute a statewide program for the education of children with disabilities to ensure that whenever possible children are educated in the state at locations in or near their resident school district.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-285__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An identified child with a disability may be sent to an educational program or residential school outside the child's community or school district if the child resides in a community or school district where an appropriate educational program cannot reasonably be made available and if the school district determines that provision of special education and related services in another educational program or residential school is appropriate. If the school district approves the enrollment of a child with a disability in another educational program or residential school outside the child's community or school district and the child is enrolled, the child's education expenses shall be paid as follows:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-285__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>except as otherwise provided by (2) of this subsection, the sending district shall pay all costs associated with the transfer;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-285__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the department may provide financial assistance to the school district for a child's education provided for in (1) of this subsection under regulations adopted by the department.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-285__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 19 ch 147 SLA 1984.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-285__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For the purposes of this section a child's education expenses are limited to the actual cost of necessary care, transportation, and special education and related services, including room and board.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-285__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The educational assessment of a child with a disability that indicates that the educational program that is locally available is inappropriate for the needs of the child must conform to the standards set out in
AS 14.30.191
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-285__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A school district shall obtain informed consent of the child's parent before a child may be transferred to a school outside the district in which the child resides.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-285__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The withholding of informed consent by a parent for the transfer of a child with a disability under this section does not relieve a school district of the obligation to provide special education and related services to the child.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-285__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall make available to school districts an electronic system for managing student information and tracking records relating to individualized education programs for children with disabilities. The system must, to the extent permitted by federal law, allow school districts to transfer special education records for a student when the student transfers to a different school district. If the governing body of a school district elects to use the system selected by the department, the department shall provide the school district with the system, including any software necessary to implement the system, at no charge to the school district. The department may not require a school district to use the system selected by the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-305">
            <num>14.30.305</num>
            <heading>State support of programs for children hospitalized or confined to their homes.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.30.305.   State support of programs for children hospitalized or confined to their homes.
A child who is hospitalized or confined to home and who receives at least 10 hours of special education and related services per week may be counted as a pupil in average daily membership when computing state support under the public school funding program.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-325">
            <num>14.30.325</num>
            <heading>Surrogate parents.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-30-325__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall by regulation provide for the appointment of surrogate parents to represent a child with a disability in matters relating to the provision of an appropriate public education.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-325__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A surrogate parent is not liable for civil damages as a result of an act or omission committed in the surrogate parent's official capacity, except that a surrogate parent may be liable for civil damages as a result of gross negligence or intentional misconduct.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-335">
            <num>14.30.335</num>
            <heading>Eligibility for federal funds.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.30.335.   Eligibility for federal funds.
Notwithstanding any other provision of
AS 14.30.180
 14.30.350, the department may do all things necessary to qualify for federal funds that are available to the state for the education of children with disabilities.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-340">
            <num>14.30.340</num>
            <heading>Provision of special education in a private school, home, or hospital setting.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-30-340__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a parent of a child with a disability enrolls the child in a private school, including a religious school, at the parent's expense or teaches the child at home, the school district in which the child resides shall make special education and related services available in conformance with federal requirements, including 34 C.F.R. 300.130  148. A parent teaching the parent's child at home may refuse special education and related services for the child.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-340__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a physician certifies in writing, and if the child's individualized education program under
AS 14.30.278
provides that a child's bodily, mental, or emotional condition does not permit attendance at a school and the child's parents do not elect to teach the child at home as permitted under
AS 14.30.010
(b), the school district in which the child is located shall enroll the child in public school and provide the child with special education and related services in conformance with the child's individualized education program at the child's home or at a medical treatment facility.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-347">
            <num>14.30.347</num>
            <heading>Transportation of children with disabilities.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.30.347.   Transportation of children with disabilities.
When transportation is required to be provided as a related service, a child with a disability shall be transported with children who are not children with disabilities if the district provides transportation to children in the district, except when the nature of the physical or mental disability is such that it is in the best interest of the child with a disability, as provided in the child's individualized education program, that the child be transported separately. State reimbursement for transportation of children with disabilities shall be as provided for transportation of all other pupils except that eligibility for reimbursement is not subject to restriction based on the minimum distance between the school and the residence of the child with a disability.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-350">
            <num>14.30.350</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.30.350.   Definitions.
In
AS 14.30.180
  14.30.350,
(1) appropriate education means personalized instruction with sufficient support services to permit a child to benefit educationally from the instruction;
(2) child with a disability means a child with one or more of the following:
(A) intellectual disability;
(B) learning disabilities;
(C) emotional disturbance;
(D) deafness;
(E) deaf-blindness;
(F) hearing impairment;
(G) orthopedic impairment;
(H) other health impairment;
(I) speech or language impairment;
(J) visual impairment;
(K) multiple disabilities;
(L) early childhood development delay;
(M) autism;
(N) traumatic brain injury;
(O) developmental disability;
(3) due process hearing means a hearing conducted under
AS 14.30.193
;
(4) educational records means those files, documents, records, and other material that contain information directly related to a student and are maintained by a school district or a person acting for a school district; the term educational records does not include the personnel records of the school district, maintained in the normal course of business, that relate exclusively to a person's capacity as an employee, or other records as designated by the department in regulation;
(5) informed consent means that
(A) a child's parent has been fully informed, in the parent's native language or other mode of communication, of all information relevant to the activity for which consent is sought;
(B) the parent understands and agrees in writing to the carrying out of the activity for which the parent's consent is sought;
(C) the consent describes that activity and lists any records that will be released and to whom; and
(D) the parent understands that the granting of consent is voluntary on the part of the parent and may be revoked at any time;
(6) parent means a
(A) child's natural or adoptive parent;
(B) child's guardian, but not the state if the child is in the legal custody of the state;
(C) person who is acting in the place of a child's natural or adoptive parent, such as a grandparent or stepparent with whom the child lives, or a person who is legally responsible for the child's welfare; and
(D) child's surrogate parent who has been appointed under
AS 14.30.325
;
(7) related services means services described in 34 C.F.R. 300.34;
(8) school district means a borough school district, a city school district, a regional educational attendance area, a state boarding school, and the state centralized correspondence study program;
(9) special education means an educational program described in 34 C.F.R. 300.39.
Article 6. Education for Gifted Children.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-352">
            <num>14.30.352</num>
            <heading>Programs for gifted children.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-30-352__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Every school district shall establish educational services for gifted children that provide for student identification, student eligibility, student learning plans, and parental and student participation, including an appropriate review process, consistent with regulations adopted by the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-352__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>State reimbursement for transportation of gifted children shall be as provided for transportation of all other pupils, except that eligibility for reimbursement is not limited to transportation between the child's residence and the school, but shall also include transportation between a school and another location of instruction as routinely required by the gifted education program of the district.
Article 7 Sexual Abuse and Sexual Assault Awareness and Prevention</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-355">
            <num>14.30.355</num>
            <heading>Sexual abuse and sexual assault awareness and prevention.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-30-355__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The governing body of each school district shall adopt and implement a policy, establish a training program for employees and students, and provide parent notices relating to sexual abuse and sexual assault awareness and prevention for students enrolled in grades kindergarten through 12.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-355__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The policy, training, and notices adopted under this section must include</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-355__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>age-appropriate information;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-355__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>warning signs of sexual abuse of a child;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-355__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>referral and resource information;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-355__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>available student counseling and educational support;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-355__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>methods for increasing teacher, student, and parent awareness of issues regarding sexual abuse of children;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-355__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>actions that a child may take to prevent and report sexual abuse or sexual assault; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-355__subsec_b__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a procedure allowing a student to be excused from participating in training or from receiving notices under this section at the written request of a parent or guardian of the student, or of the student if the student is emancipated or 18 years of age or older.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-355__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The training required for teachers under this section may be provided as a part of the continuing education required under
AS 18.66.310
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-355__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-355__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>school district has the meaning given in
AS 14.30.350
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-355__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>sexual abuse or sexual assault has the meaning given to sexual abuse in
AS 47.10.990
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-356">
            <num>14.30.356</num>
            <heading>Teen dating violence and abuse awareness and prevention program; training and notices.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-30-356__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department, in consultation with school districts, shall develop and approve a program relating to teen dating violence and abuse awareness and prevention for grades seven through 12. The program must</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-356__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>include training for employees and students;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-356__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide parent notices; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-356__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>be reviewed periodically by a qualified individual or committee for consistency with generally accepted standards for a teen dating violence and abuse awareness and prevention program.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-356__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The training, notices, and instruction adopted under this section must include</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-356__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>age-appropriate information;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-356__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the warning signs of dating violence and abusive behavior;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-356__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>characteristics of healthy relationships;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-356__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>measures to prevent and stop dating violence and abuse;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-356__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>community resources available to victims of dating violence and abuse; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-356__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a procedure allowing a student to be excused from participating in training or from receiving notices under this section at the written request of a parent or guardian of the student, or of the student if the student is emancipated or 18 years of age or older.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-356__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The training required for teachers under this section may be provided as a part of the continuing education required under
AS 18.66.310
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-356__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-356__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>dating violence and abuse means a pattern of behavior in which one person threatens to use, or actually uses, physical, sexual, verbal, emotional, or psychological abuse to control the person's dating partner;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-356__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>school district has the meaning given in
AS 14.30.350
.
Article 8. Health, Safety, and Physical Education.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-360">
            <num>14.30.360</num>
            <heading>Health education curriculum; physical activity guidelines.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-30-360__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each district in the state public school system shall be encouraged to initiate and conduct a program in health education for kindergarten through grade 12. The program should include instruction in physical health and personal safety including alcohol and drug abuse education, cardiopulmonary resuscitation (CPR), early cancer prevention and detection, dental health, family health including infant care, environmental health, the identification and prevention of child abuse, child abduction, neglect, sexual abuse, and domestic violence, and appropriate use of health services.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-360__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The state board shall establish guidelines for a health and personal safety education program. Personal safety guidelines shall be developed in consultation with the Council on Domestic Violence and Sexual Assault. Upon request, the Department of Education and Early Development, the Department of Health, and the Council on Domestic Violence and Sexual Assault shall provide technical assistance to school districts in the development of personal safety curricula. A school health education specialist position shall be established and funded in the department to coordinate the program statewide. Adequate funds to enable curriculum and resource development, adequate consultation to school districts, and a program of teacher training in health and personal safety education shall be provided.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-360__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to the health education program encouraged under (a) of this section, a school district shall establish guidelines for schools in the district to provide opportunities during each full school day for students in grades kindergarten through eight for a minimum of 90 percent of the daily amount of physical activity recommended for children and adolescents in the physical activity guidelines by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, United States Department of Health and Human Services. The time provided for physical activity under this subsection may include physical education classes and opportunities for unstructured physical activity, such as recess. A school district shall adopt guidelines under this subsection that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-360__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>allow a student to be excused from the physical activity opportunities if the student is unable to participate for a medical reason; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-360__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide an exemption from the physical activity opportunities under this subsection for health and safety reasons, such as inclement weather.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-360__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, district has the meaning given in
AS 14.17.990
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-361">
            <num>14.30.361</num>
            <heading>Sex education, human reproductive education, and human sexuality education.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-30-361__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may only teach a class or program in sex education, human reproduction education, or human sexuality education if the person</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-361__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>possesses a valid teacher certificate issued under
AS 14.20
and is employed under a contract with the school; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-361__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is supervised by a person who meets the requirements under (1) of this subsection.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-361__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before curriculum, literature, or materials related to sex education, human reproduction education, or human sexuality education may be used in a class or program or distributed in a school, the curriculum, literature, or materials must be</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-361__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>approved by the school board; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-361__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>available for parents to review.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-361__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before a person teaches a class or program under (a)(2) of this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-361__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the person must be approved by the school board; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-361__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the person's credentials must be available for parents to review.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-361__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The requirements under (a) of this section do not apply to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-361__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>sexual abuse and sexual assault awareness and prevention training required under
AS 14.30.355
; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-361__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>dating violence and abuse awareness and prevention training required under
AS 14.30.356
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-362">
            <num>14.30.362</num>
            <heading>Suicide awareness and prevention training.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-30-362__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A school district and the department shall provide youth suicide awareness and prevention training approved by the commissioner to each teacher, administrator, counselor, and specialist who is employed by the district or department to provide services to students in a public school in the state at no cost to the teacher, administrator, counselor, or specialist.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-362__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall approve youth suicide awareness and prevention training provided under this section if the training meets standards for professional continuing education credit in the state and is periodically reviewed by a qualified person or committee for consistency with generally accepted principles of youth suicide awareness and prevention. The training may be offered through videoconferencing or an individual program of study of designated materials.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-362__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not bring a civil action for damages against the state or a school district, or an officer, agent, or employee of the state or a school district, for a death, personal injury, or property damage that results from an act or omission in performing or failing to perform activities or duties authorized under this section. This subsection does not apply to a civil action for damages as a result of intentional misconduct with complete disregard for the safety and property of others.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-362__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The training under this section shall be provided according to the schedule adopted by the governing body of a school district.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-362__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The training provided or the failure to provide training under this section may not be construed to impose a specific duty of care on any person.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-365">
            <num>14.30.365</num>
            <heading>Interscholastic activities; eligibility.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-30-365__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A full-time student who is eligible under (b) of this section who is enrolled in grades nine through 12 in an alternative education program that is located in the state and that does not offer interscholastic activities is eligible to participate in any interscholastic activities program available in a public school</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-365__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>that, based on the residence of the parent or legal guardian, the student would be eligible to attend were the student not enrolled in an alternative education program; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-365__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>at which the student requests to participate, if
(A) the student shows good cause; and
(B) the governing body of the school approves.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-365__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A student is eligible to participate in interscholastic activities under this section if the student</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-365__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is otherwise eligible to participate in interscholastic activities under requirements established by the school, the school district, and the statewide interscholastic activities governing body;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-365__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provides documentation, including academic transcripts, proof of full-time enrollment, and applicable disciplinary records, and, if required for participation in an activity by the school, requested medical records, to the school providing the interscholastic activities program; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-365__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>claims the same school for interscholastic activities eligibility purposes during a school year.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-365__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-365__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>alternative education program means a public secondary school that provides a nontraditional education program, including the Alaska Military Youth Academy; a public vocational, remedial, or theme-based program; a home school program that is accredited by a recognized accrediting body; a charter school authorized under
AS 14.03.250
 14.03.290; and a statewide correspondence school that enrolls students who reside outside of the district in which the student resides and provides less than three hours a week of scheduled face-to-face student interactions in the same location with a teacher who is certified under
AS 14.20.020
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-365__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>district has the meaning given in
AS 14.17.990
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-365__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>full-time student means a student who
(A) is enrolled in not less than five classes in grades nine through 11 and not less than four classes in grade 12; and
(B) is on track to graduate from secondary school in not more than four years of attendance in secondary school;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-365__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>interscholastic activities means preparation for and participation in events or competitions involving another school when the preparation or participation
(A) is sanctioned or supported by the statewide interscholastic activities governing body;
(B) is conducted outside of the regular school curriculum; and
(C) does not involve participation in student government at a school;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-365__subsec_c__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>located in the state means that the alternative education program is accessed by a student who is located in the state and provides for all instructional hours to take place at a site in the state.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-370">
            <num>14.30.370</num>
            <heading>Evaluation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.30.370.   Evaluation.
Health education programs conducted under
AS 14.30.360
shall be evaluated by the department in the same manner as other curriculum programs are evaluated, except that the evaluation shall also include changes in the health status of the pupils as determined by physical and dental examinations conducted under
AS 14.30.070
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-380">
            <num>14.30.380</num>
            <heading>Environmental education.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.30.380.   Environmental education.
The board shall encourage each school board to initiate and conduct a program of environmental education for kindergarten through grade 12. The program should include, but is not limited to, education regarding the need to balance resource development with environmental safeguards, the dependence of the state on resource development, and the opportunity for pollution prevention, waste reduction, and recycling. A school board may implement environmental education as a part of regular classroom studies.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-400">
            <num>14.30.400</num>
            <heading>Bilingual-bicultural education.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.30.400.   Bilingual-bicultural education.
City or borough district school boards and regional educational attendance area boards shall provide a bilingual-bicultural education program for each school in a city or borough school district or regional educational attendance area that is attended by at least eight pupils of limited English-speaking ability and whose primary language is other than English.  A bilingual-bicultural education program shall be provided under a plan of service that has been developed in accordance with regulations adopted by the department.  Nothing in this section precludes a bilingual-bicultural education program from being provided for less than eight pupils in a school.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-410">
            <num>14.30.410</num>
            <heading>Bilingual-bicultural education funds.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-30-410__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 12 ch 42 SLA 1997.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-410__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall adopt regulations for the determination of entitlement and the distribution of bilingual-bicultural funds to city and borough school districts and regional educational attendance areas.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-420">
            <num>14.30.420</num>
            <heading>Native language education.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-30-420__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A school board shall establish a local Native language curriculum advisory board for each school in the district in which a majority of the students are Alaska Natives, and any school district with Alaska Native students may establish a local Native language curriculum advisory board for each school with Alaska Native students in their district. If the local Native language curriculum advisory board recommends the establishment of a Native language education curriculum for a school, the school board may initiate and conduct a Native language education curriculum within grades kindergarten through 12 at that school. The program, if established, must include Native languages traditionally spoken in the community in which the school is located. Each school board conducting a program of Native language education shall implement the program as a part of regular classroom studies and shall use</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-420__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>instructors who are certified under
AS 14.20.020
or 14.20.025; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-420__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to the maximum extent possible
(A) instructors and instructional materials available through the University of Alaska; and
(B) audio-visual, computer, and satellite technology.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-420__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-420__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>district has the meaning given in
AS 14.17.990
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-420__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Native means a person of one-fourth degree or more Alaskan Indian, Eskimo, or Aleut blood.
Article 11. Adventure-Based Education.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-500">
            <num>14.30.500</num>
            <heading>Adventure-based education program.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-30-500__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>transportation,
(ii) community services systems,
(iii) community problem solving.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-600">
            <num>14.30.600</num>
            <heading>Agency established.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.30.600.   Agency established.
There is established, as a public organization, the special education service agency.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-610">
            <num>14.30.610</num>
            <heading>Governing board.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.30.610.   Governing board.
The agency shall be governed by the Governor's Council on Disabilities and Special Education (
AS 44.29.600
).</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-620">
            <num>14.30.620</num>
            <heading>Employees.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.30.620.   Employees.
Employees of the agency are not in the state service and are not subject to
AS 39.25
(State Personnel Act). However, employees of the agency shall be members of either the Teachers' Retirement System (
AS 14.25
) or the Public Employees' Retirement System (
AS 39.35
).</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-630">
            <num>14.30.630</num>
            <heading>Powers and duties.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-30-630__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The agency may</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-630__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>receive and expend public and private funds to carry out the purposes of the agency;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-630__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>contract with the department and other public or private agencies for the provision of special education or related services;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-630__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>do whatever is necessary to carry out the purposes of
AS 14.30.600
 14.30.660.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-630__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The agency shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-630__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide special education services including
(A) itinerant outreach services to students who are deaf, deaf-blind, intellectually disabled, developmentally disabled, hearing impaired, blind and visually impaired, orthopedically disabled, health-impaired in other ways, and severely emotionally disturbed, and to students with multiple disabilities;
(B) special education instructional support and training of local school district special education personnel; and
(C) other services appropriate to special education needs;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-630__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide for an annual audit of the agency;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-630__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide the department with a two-year plan of operation including a description of the services to be offered by the agency, the method by which the services will be evaluated, information on the number of students and school district personnel to be served, a schedule of funds available to the agency from all sources, and other information that may be required by the department by regulation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-630__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>present an annual budget to the department.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-640">
            <num>14.30.640</num>
            <heading>Eligibility for service.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.30.640.   Eligibility for service.
The services of the agency shall be available to school districts that serve children whose special education needs occur infrequently, who require specialized services not normally available in the school district, and who cannot be easily served by local school district personnel because of the low number of students in the district in need of the particular service. The agency may provide services to a child with a disability, as that term is defined in
AS 14.30.350
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-650">
            <num>14.30.650</num>
            <heading>Funding.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.30.650.   Funding.
Each fiscal year, the department shall allocate to the agency not less than $23.13 times the number of students in the state in average daily membership in the preceding fiscal year as determined under
AS 14.17.600
. Money to carry out the provisions of this section may be appropriated annually by the legislature. If amounts are insufficient to meet the allocation authorized under this section for a fiscal year, the allocation shall be reduced pro rata.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-660">
            <num>14.30.660</num>
            <heading>Definition.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.30.660.   Definition.
In
AS 14.30.600
 14.30.660, unless the context otherwise requires, agency means the special education service agency.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-700">
            <num>14.30.700</num>
            <heading>Records of missing children.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.30.700.   Records of missing children.
Upon notification by the Department of Public Safety of a child's disappearance, a school or school district in which the child is currently or was previously enrolled shall flag the school record of that child in a manner that, when a copy or information regarding the record is requested, the school or school district shall be alerted to the fact that the record is that of a missing child. The school or school district shall immediately report to the Department of Public Safety a request regarding flagged records, including any knowledge as to the whereabouts of the child. Upon notification by the Department of Public Safety that the person who was listed as a missing child has been found, the school or school district shall remove the flag from the person's record.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-710">
            <num>14.30.710</num>
            <heading>Required records upon transfer.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.30.710.   Required records upon transfer.
Within 14 days after enrolling a child as a transfer student from this or another state in an elementary or secondary school, the school or school district shall request directly from the child's previous school a certified copy of the child's record. An elementary or secondary school or a school district in this state requested to forward a copy of a transferring child's record to another school shall comply with the request within 10 days after receiving the request unless the record has been flagged under
AS 14.30.700
. Upon receipt of a request for a record that has been flagged, the school or school district shall immediately notify the Department of Public Safety. Unless directed to do so by the Department of Public Safety, a school or a school district may not forward a copy of a flagged record. In this section, record includes information about the child's commission of an offense that is punishable as a felony or that involved the use of a deadly weapon, as that term is defined in
AS 11.81.900
(b).</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-720">
            <num>14.30.720</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.30.720.   Definitions.
In
AS 14.30.700
 14.30.720,
(1) child means a person under 18 years of age;
(2) school district means a municipal school district or a regional educational attendance area.
Article 14. Alaska Military Youth Academy.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-745">
            <num>14.30.745</num>
            <heading>Provision of student information to academy.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-30-745__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (b) of this section, on or before January 15 and July 15 of each year, a school district shall provide to the director of the Alaska Military Youth Academy, operated by the Department of Military and Veterans' Affairs for the purpose of educating and training youth, a biannual report containing the name, last known address, and dates of attendance of a student who</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-745__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is at least 15 years of age but less than 19 years of age;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-745__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>was enrolled but is no longer enrolled in a school in the district;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-745__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has not provided school transfer or graduation information to a school in the district; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-745__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has not received a high school diploma or general educational development certificate.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-745__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>At the beginning of each school year, a school district shall provide a written notice to the parent or guardian of the student, or, if the student is at least 18 years of age, to the student, of the disclosure of the information under (a) of this section and provide an opportunity for objection to the disclosure.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-745__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The official to whom the information in (a) of this section is provided shall certify in writing to the school district providing the information that the information will not be disclosed to any other party except as necessary to recruit and retain students.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-745__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, district has the meaning given in
AS 14.17.990
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-760">
            <num>14.30.760</num>
            <heading>Statewide screening and support.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-30-760__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To implement the district reading intervention services established under
AS 14.30.765
, the department shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-760__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>adopt a statewide screening tool to administer to students in grades kindergarten through three to identify students with reading deficiencies, including students with characteristics of dyslexia; the screening tool must evaluate
(A) phonemic awareness, letter naming fluency, letter sound fluency, and letter word sound fluency of students in kindergarten;
(B) letter word sound fluency and oral reading fluency of students in grade one;
(C) vocabulary and oral reading fluency of students in grades two and three;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-760__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>support teachers of grades kindergarten through three by
(A) administering the statewide screening tool three times each school year, once in the fall, once in the winter, and once in the spring, to all students in grades kindergarten through three, with the exception of students who demonstrate sufficient reading skills on the first screening of the school year;
(B) providing methods to monitor student progress;
(C) providing targeted instruction based on student needs as determined by the results of the screening tool; and
(D) providing additional assistance as determined by the department;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-760__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide training to school district staff related to using the results of the statewide screening tool and understanding evidence-based reading interventions, including explicit and systematic instruction in phonemic awareness, phonics, vocabulary development, reading fluency, oral language skills, and reading comprehension;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-760__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>require that districts identify the early education programs attended by students and report to the department the average score on each performance screening tool by students in grades kindergarten through three who
(A) attended a state-approved early education program;
(B) attended a head start program;
(C) attended a private early education program;
(D) did not attend an early education program;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-760__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establish a process that allows the commissioner to waive, upon request, use of the statewide screening tool required under this subsection by a school district if the school district has adopted an evidence-based reading screening tool and the screening tool is approved by the department;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-760__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>review, approve, and assist districts developing alternative standardized reading screening tools in any language for use by school districts.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-760__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In adopting a statewide screening tool under (a)(1) of this section, the department shall consider the following factors:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-760__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the amount of time needed to administer the screening with the intention of minimizing effects on instructional time;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-760__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the time frame for reporting screening results to teachers, administrators, and parents or guardians;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-760__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the integration of the screening with student instruction and department support;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-760__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>recommendations from a task force, working group, or committee created by law and charged with studying issues related to reading proficiency and reading deficiencies; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-760__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>whether the screening tool is culturally responsive.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-765">
            <num>14.30.765</num>
            <heading>Reading intervention services and strategies; progression.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-30-765__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each school district shall offer intensive reading intervention services to students in grades kindergarten through three who exhibit a reading deficiency to assist students in achieving reading proficiency at or above grade level by the end of grade three. The district shall provide the intensive reading intervention services in addition to the core reading instruction that is provided to all students in the general education classroom. The intensive reading intervention services must, to the extent practicable,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>be provided by a district reading teacher, or paraprofessional under the supervision of a reading teacher, to all students in grades kindergarten through three who are determined to have a reading deficiency based on the statewide screening tool adopted under
AS 14.30.760</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide explicit and systematic instruction in phonemic awareness, phonics, vocabulary development, reading fluency, oral language skills, and reading comprehension, as necessary;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>use evidence-based reading intervention methods that have shown proven results in accelerating student reading achievement within a single school year;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>include instruction with detailed explanations, extensive opportunities for guided practice, and opportunities for error correction and feedback;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>incorporate daily targeted small group reading instruction based on student needs, either in person or online;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>monitor the reading progress of each student's reading skills throughout the school year and adjust instruction according to student needs;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>be implemented during regular school hours through any available method, including in person or through online delivery by teachers or specialty reading coaches;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>be implemented outside of regular school hours, as directed in the student's individual reading improvement plan under (b) of this section, for a student who scores at the lowest achievement level on the statewide screening tool;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>be reviewed based on a department-approved response to intervention or multi-tiered system support models, addressing additional support and services needed to remedy identified needs; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_a__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>support reading intervention at home by parents or guardians by offering a list of adult literacy resources and organizations, providing opportunities for parent or guardian participation in training workshops, and encouraging regular parent or guardian-guided home reading activities.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-765__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to the reading intervention services provided under (a) of this section, a school district shall provide an individual reading improvement plan for each student in grades kindergarten through three who is determined to have a reading deficiency based on the statewide screening tool. An individual reading improvement plan developed under this section must</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>be implemented not later than 30 days after identification of the reading deficiency;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>be created by the student's reading teacher in consultation with the school principal, the student's parent or guardian, and other pertinent district staff;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>describe the evidence-based reading intervention services the student will receive to achieve and demonstrate sufficient reading skills;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide reading intervention services outside of regular school hours for a student who scores at the lowest achievement level on the statewide screening tool consistent with (a)(8) of this section;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>include a process for monitoring progress and adjusting the plan based on student needs;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide to the student's parent or guardian at least 10 reading progress updates each school year;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_b__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>be culturally responsive; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_b__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>support the student reading at home with a parent or guardian by offering a list of adult literacy resources and organizations, providing opportunities for parent or guardian participation in training workshops, and encouraging regular parent or guardian-guided home reading activities.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-765__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If at any time during the school year a student in grades kindergarten through three demonstrates a reading deficiency, the district or school shall notify the student's parent or guardian. The initial notification must</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>be provided to the student's parent or guardian not later than 15 days after identification of the reading deficiency;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>state that the district identified the student as having a reading deficiency and that a reading improvement plan will be developed under (b) of this section;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>describe current services that the district is providing to the student;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>describe the proposed evidence-based reading intervention and supplemental instructional services and supports that the district will provide to the student to improve the identified area of reading deficiency;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_c__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>explain that the district or school will inform the parent or guardian orally or in writing, as selected by the parent or guardian, of the student's progress toward grade level reading as outlined in the student's individual reading improvement plan;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_c__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>identify strategies for the parent or guardian to use at home to help the student succeed in reading;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_c__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>explain that if the student has a reading deficiency at the end of the school year and is in grades kindergarten through two, the student's progression may be delayed unless the student has previously not progressed to the next grade;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_c__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>explain that a student in grade three should demonstrate sufficient reading skills to progress to grade four under (e) of this section, unless the student receives a waiver under (f) of this section or has previously not progressed to the next grade;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_c__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>explain the process and deadline to request a waiver under (f) of this section; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_c__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>identify mid-year progression as an option for students who do not progress to the next grade.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-765__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If it is determined, based on a statewide screening administered in the spring, that a student in grades kindergarten through two has a reading deficiency, the student's teacher and other pertinent district staff shall notify and attempt to meet with the student's parent or guardian to explain that the student will not be able to maintain adequate academic progress at the next grade level. School staff shall work with the parent or guardian to schedule a date, time, and place for the meeting, to be held not later than 45 days before the end of the school year. Following that meeting, the parent or guardian shall determine whether the student will progress to the next grade. If no parent or guardian attends the meeting or if the parent or guardian does not determine whether the student will progress to the next grade, the superintendent or the superintendent's designee shall, after considering the student's best interest and whether the student has previously not progressed to the next grade, determine whether the student will progress to the next grade.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-765__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A student in grade three should demonstrate sufficient reading skills to progress to grade four. A student demonstrates sufficient reading skills to progress to grade four by</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>scoring at grade level or higher on the statewide screening tool or on the statewide summative assessment;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>achieving an acceptable score on an alternative standardized reading screening as determined and approved by the department; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_e__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>demonstrating mastery of reading standards through a student reading portfolio based on criteria established by the department.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-765__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If it is determined, based on a statewide screening administered in the spring, that a student in grade three has a reading deficiency, and the student does not demonstrate sufficient reading skills to progress to grade four under (e) of this section, the student's teacher and other pertinent district staff shall notify and attempt to meet with the student's parent or guardian to explain that the student is not prepared to progress to grade four. School staff shall work with the parent or guardian to schedule a date, time, and place for the meeting, to be held not later than 45 days before the end of the school year. Following that meeting, the parent or guardian may decide that the student will not progress to grade four or decide to progress the student to grade four by signing a waiver developed by the department acknowledging that the student is not prepared and agreeing that the student will participate in an additional 20 hours of individual reading improvement plan intervention services during the summer before the student enters grade four. If no parent or guardian attends the meeting or if the parent or guardian does not determine whether the student will progress to the next grade, the superintendent or the superintendent's designee shall, after considering the student's best interests and whether the student has previously not progressed to the next grade, determine whether the student will progress to grade four.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-765__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A superintendent or superintendent's designee may exempt a student from delayed progression when progression is in the student's best interests. When determining if progression is in a student's best interests, the superintendent or superintendent's designee shall consider whether</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_g__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the student has received intensive reading intervention services for two or more years and still demonstrates a reading deficiency;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_g__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the student's primary language is a language other than English; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_g__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the student has a disability and has an individualized education plan under
AS 14.30.278
or a plan under 29 U.S.C. 794.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-765__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If no parent or guardian attends the meeting, and a superintendent or superintendent's designee decides that a student in grades kindergarten through three will not progress to the next grade under (d) or (f) of this section, the district or school in which the student is enrolled shall provide immediate oral and written notification to the student's parent or guardian. The written notification must explain that the parent or guardian may reschedule the meeting provided under (d) or (f) of this section and that during a meeting</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_h__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for a student in grades kindergarten through two, the parent or guardian may decide to progress the student; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_h__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for a student in grade three, the parent or guardian may decide to progress the student to grade four by signing a waiver under (f) of this section.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-765__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For a student who does not progress to the next grade under (d) or (f) of this section, or who progresses to the next grade with a waiver under (f) of this section, the district in which the student is enrolled shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_i__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>review the student's individual reading improvement plan;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_i__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide intensive reading intervention services to improve the area of reading deficiency using effective instructional strategies to accelerate student progress;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_i__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide additional services and support to improve the student's identified area of reading deficiency, including
(A) a transitional instructional setting that is designed to produce learning gains;
(B) supplemental tutoring offered by a person with specialized reading training;
(C) an increase in time dedicated to the reading instruction methods described in (a)(3)  (5) of this section, including more extensive opportunities for guided practice and error correction and feedback;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_i__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>develop a plan for reading at home outlined in an agreement with the student's parent or guardian, including parent or guardian participation in training workshops and regular parent or guardian-guided home reading activities.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-765__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For a student who does not progress to grade one, grade two, or grade three under (d) of this section, the district in which the student is enrolled shall, upon request by the student's parent or guardian, develop a plan for the student's mid-year progression.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-765__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A school district shall adopt a policy providing for mid-year progression of a student who does not progress to grade four under (f) of this section if the student</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_k__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>demonstrates sufficient reading skills to progress to grade four on the fall or winter statewide screening; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_k__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>meets additional requirements determined by the district, including satisfactory achievement in other subject areas.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-765__subsec_l">
              <num>(l)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A district shall, for the remainder of the academic year, and, if necessary, for additional school years, continue to implement an individual reading improvement plan for a student promoted mid-year under (j) or (k) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-765__subsec_m">
              <num>(m)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless a parent or guardian decides that a student will not progress to the next grade under (d) or (f) of this section, a district or school may not delay the student's progression under this section if the student previously did not progress to the next grade.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-765__subsec_n">
              <num>(n)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, reading teacher means a teacher who</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_n__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>holds a valid teacher certificate under
AS 14.20
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_n__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has demonstrated effectiveness in instructing students to read at or above grade level as measured by student reading performance data and in teacher performance evaluations; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-765__subsec_n__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>meets the requirements established by the state Board of Education and Early Development in regulation.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-770">
            <num>14.30.770</num>
            <heading>Department reading program.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-30-770__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall establish a reading program to provide direct support for and intervention in intensive reading intervention services annually in the lowest-performing 25 percent of schools serving students in grades kindergarten through three as determined under
AS 14.03.123
. The department shall determine how many schools may be adequately served by the department's reading specialists and select schools from the lowest-performing 25 percent of schools to participate in the reading program. A school participating in the reading program that remains in the lowest-performing 25 percent of schools as determined under
AS 14.03.123
may apply to participate in the reading program again in the following school year. State funding provided to participating schools for implementation of the reading program is in addition to the amount of funding provided under
AS 14.17
. In conducting the program, the department shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-770__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>use the accountability system established in
AS 14.03.123
to identify low performing schools;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-770__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establish an application process for school districts to apply to participate in the program;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-770__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>select low performing schools from the schools that apply to participate in the program;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-770__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>employ and assign reading specialists to direct the implementation of the intensive reading intervention services established under
AS 14.30.765
by
(A) modeling effective instructional strategies for teachers by working regularly with students as a class, in small groups, or individually;
(B) coaching and mentoring teachers and staff in reading instruction with an emphasis on prioritizing time in a manner that has the greatest positive effects on student achievement;
(C) training teachers in data analysis and using data to differentiate instruction;
(D) leading and supporting reading leadership teams; and
(E) reporting on school and student performance to the department;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-770__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establish a reporting process for each reading specialist to submit updates to the department on implementation of the program;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-770__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>work with reading specialists to create specific improvement goals for each school selected, including measures of interim progress;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-770__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>select and purchase additional reading material for each school selected to supplement the intensive reading intervention services;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-770__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>pay travel and associated costs for a reading specialist to attend relevant training sessions identified by or hosted by the department;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-770__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>periodically review staff development programs for their effectiveness in developing reading skills and, after consultation with school districts and experts, recommend to the board for approval staff development programs that
(A) have been proven to assess and accelerate student progress toward reaching reading competency;
(B) provide explicit and systematic skill development in the areas of phonemic awareness, phonics, vocabulary development, reading fluency, oral language skills, and reading comprehension;
(C) are evidence-based and reliable;
(D) provide initial and ongoing analysis of student progress toward reaching reading competency; and
(E) include texts on core academic content to assist students in maintaining or meeting grade-appropriate proficiency in academic subjects in addition to reading.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-770__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A school selected to participate in the reading program established under this section shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-770__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>ensure that a reading specialist assigned to the school is not required to perform functions that divert from the duties the department has assigned to the reading specialist;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-770__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>coordinate with the reading specialist or specialists to redesign the school's daily schedule to dedicate time to reading program activities, including intensive reading intervention services identified in a written agreement between the school and the department;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-770__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>present on the reading program established under this section and the intensive reading intervention services established under
AS 14.30.765
at a public meeting; the presentation must include
(A) the data the department used to identify the school as eligible for the reading program;
(B) a detailed overview of the reading program and intensive reading intervention services;
(C) a timeline for implementing the intensive reading intervention services and meeting reading improvement goals; and
(D) the implications of the program for students, families, and educators;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-770__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide notice of the public meeting required under (3) of this subsection to the parent or guardian of each student at least seven days before the date of the meeting;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-770__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>present an annual update on the school's implementation of the reading program and intensive reading intervention services at a public meeting with notice provided to the parent or guardian of each student at least seven days before the date of the meeting;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-770__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>create partnerships between the school, the families of students, and the community that focus on promoting reading and increasing the amount of time that students spend reading.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-770__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall publish on the department's Internet website and make available to the public</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-770__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a completed application from each school selected to participate in the reading program; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-770__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the reading program and intensive reading intervention services implemented by each school selected to participate.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-770__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may employ a person as a reading specialist under this section if the person</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-770__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>holds a valid teacher certificate issued under
AS 14.20
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-770__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has completed an approved graduate program at an approved institution of higher education and
(A) has completed a supervised practicum or internship as a reading specialist; or
(B) has at least three years of full-time, demonstrated classroom teaching experience where reading instruction was a primary responsibility;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-770__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is knowledgeable about and demonstrates competency in reading instruction, including
(A) an understanding of phonemic awareness, phonics, vocabulary development, reading fluency, oral language skills, and reading comprehension;
(B) knowledge of and experience in implementing effective reading instruction strategies and intervention methods;
(C) experience in designing and implementing a school-wide response to an intervention program or multi-tiered system support model;
(D) an understanding of and experience in reading screenings and data analyses that inform instruction;
(E) knowledge of dyslexia and other learning disorders that affect reading achievement;
(F) knowledge of and an ability to effectively articulate the methods, issues, and resources involved in support of student instruction to a wide variety of audiences, including staff, parents, and students whose primary language is other than English; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-770__subsec_d__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>meets other reading instruction coursework requirements established by the department in regulation, including coursework in Indigenous language learning and culturally responsive education established in regulation by the department in collaboration with indigenous language stakeholders.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-775">
            <num>14.30.775</num>
            <heading>Regulation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.30.775.   Regulation.
The department shall, by regulation, define dyslexia for the purposes of
AS 14.30.760
 14.30.780. The department shall consider the meaning of dyslexia given by the International Dyslexia Association when adopting the definition by regulation.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-780">
            <num>14.30.780</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.30.780.   Definitions.
In
AS 14.30.760
 14.30.780,
(1) district has the meaning given in
AS 14.17.990
;
(2) evidence-based reading intervention means an intervention based on reliable, trustworthy, and valid evidence that has a demonstrated record of success in adequately increasing a student's reading competency in the areas of phonemic awareness, phonics, vocabulary development, reading fluency, oral language skills, and reading comprehension.
Article 16. Virtual Education.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-30-800">
            <num>14.30.800</num>
            <heading>Virtual education consortium.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-30-800__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall, in cooperation with school districts, establish a virtual education consortium for the purpose of making virtual education and professional development resources available to students and teachers in the state. The department shall establish standards for consortium resources. The consortium shall create and maintain a database of virtual education courses for students, training in virtual instruction for teachers, and professional development courses for teachers of students throughout the state if the coursework curriculum meets the state standards established by the department. The database must be accessible to all school districts that participate in the consortium.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-800__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For teachers delivering or facilitating virtual coursework to students through the consortium database, the consortium shall provide training and professional development on virtual instruction methods and the differences between virtual instruction and instruction offered in a classroom. A teacher may not provide instruction through a course for students that is in the database unless</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-800__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the teacher has completed the training or professional development provided by the consortium; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-800__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the consortium determines that the teacher's previous experience has prepared the teacher to provide virtual instruction and the teacher demonstrates the skills necessary to provide virtual instruction.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-800__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The consortium shall employ a reading specialist available to school districts to provide virtual intensive reading intervention services. The duties of the reading specialist include</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-800__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>modeling effective instructional strategies for teachers by working regularly with students as a class, in small groups, or individually;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-800__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>coaching and mentoring teachers and staff in reading instruction with an emphasis on prioritizing time in a manner that has the greatest positive effects on student achievement;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-800__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>training teachers in data analysis and using data to differentiate instruction;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-800__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>leading and supporting reading leadership teams; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-30-800__subsec_c__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>reporting on school and student performance to the department.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-800__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may require a school district that participates in the consortium to pay a fee to the consortium. If the department requires a fee, the department shall establish the fee in regulations, based on a recommendation made by the consortium, and may adjust the fee annually as necessary. The fees must approximately equal the consortium's prorated administrative costs related to reviewing and approving courses and maintaining the database.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-800__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A school district that provides a course included in the database may charge a fee to the school district in which a student who takes the course is enrolled. The department shall establish the fee in regulations.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-800__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The consortium may require, as a condition of participation, that school districts that provide courses or have students participating in courses included in the database under (a) of this section adopt the same school term and class schedule for all or part of a school day. The school term must meet the requirements of
AS 14.03.030
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-30-800__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, virtual education or virtual instruction means instruction delivered through telecommunications or another digital or electronic method.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>