<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-35"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-35"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="14.35"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-35/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-35/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-35/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-35/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_14">
        <num>14</num>
        <heading>Education, Libraries, and Museums</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_14__chp_35">
          <num>35</num>
          <heading>Vocational Education</heading>
          <section eId="sec_14-35-010">
            <num>14.35.010</num>
            <heading>Acceptance of Act of Congress for vocational education.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.35.010.   Acceptance of Act of Congress for vocational education.
The State of Alaska accepts together with the benefits of all respective funds appropriated thereunder, all of the provisions of the Act of Congress approved February 23, 1917, Public Law 347, 64th Congress, entitled: An Act to provide for the promotion of vocational education; to provide for cooperation with the states in the promotion of such education in agriculture, home economics and trades and industries; to provide for the cooperation of the states in the preparation of teachers of vocational subjects; and to appropriate money and regulate its expenditures, and Acts amending or supplementing it.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-35-020">
            <num>14.35.020</num>
            <heading>Duties of state Board of Education and Early Development.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-35-020__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The state Board of Education and Early Development serves as the state board for the purposes of any of the Acts described in
AS 14.35.010
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-35-020__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When required by any of the Acts described in
AS 14.35.010
, the board shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-35-020__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>prepare, submit, and supervise the administration of the plans for vocational education;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-35-020__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>select a state director of vocational education;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-35-020__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establish the minimum qualifications for teachers, supervisors, or directors;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-35-020__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>determine the prorated basis on which money shall be available for the salary and necessary travel expenses of the state director of vocational education;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-35-020__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>consider the advice of the Alaska Workforce Investment Board established by
AS 23.15.550
regarding employment training needs and advise that board in the development of vocational education programs.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-35-020__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing in this section shall be construed to repeal or modify any existing statute.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-35-025">
            <num>14.35.025</num>
            <heading>Duties of the Department of Education and Early Development.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.35.025.   Duties of the Department of Education and Early Development.
When required by any of the Acts described in
AS 14.35.010
, the department shall
(1) cooperate with the appropriate federal agency in the administration of the Act;
(2) do everything necessary to entitle the state to receive money available according to the Act;
(3) represent the state in all matters related to the administration of the Act;
(4) expend and disburse money received according to the Act;
(5) designate the districts, schools, departments, or classes to participate in the benefits of money received according to the Act.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-35-030">
            <num>14.35.030</num>
            <heading>Commissioner of administration as custodian of federal funds.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.35.030.   Commissioner of administration as custodian of federal funds.
The commissioner of administration is designated custodian of appropriations made under any of the Acts described in
AS 14.35.010
.  The commissioner of administration shall receive and provide for the proper custody and disbursement of all money paid to the state according to any of the Acts.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>