<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-11/chapter-81"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-11/chapter-81"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="11.81"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-11/chapter-81/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-11/chapter-81/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-11/chapter-81/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-11/chapter-81/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_11">
        <num>11</num>
        <heading>Criminal Law</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_11__chp_81">
          <num>81</num>
          <heading>General Provisions</heading>
          <section eId="sec_11-81-100">
            <num>11.81.100</num>
            <heading>General purposes.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 11.81.100.   General purposes.
The general purposes of this title are to
(1) proscribe conduct that unjustifiably and inexcusably causes or threatens substantial harm to individual or public interests;
(2) give fair warning of the nature of the conduct constituting an offense;
(3) define the act or omission and accompanying culpable mental state that constitute each offense and limit the condemnation of conduct as criminal when it is without fault; and
(4) differentiate on reasonable grounds between serious and minor offenses.
Article 2. Applicability of Criminal Statutes.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_11-81-200">
            <num>11.81.200</num>
            <heading>Effect of amendment or repeal of criminal statutes.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 11.81.200.   Effect of amendment or repeal of criminal statutes.
When all or part of a criminal statute is amended or repealed, the criminal statute or part of it so amended or repealed remains in force for the purpose of authorizing the accusation, prosecution, conviction, and punishment of a person who violated the statute or part of it before the effective date of the amending or repealing Act, unless otherwise specified in the amending or repealing Act.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_11-81-210">
            <num>11.81.210</num>
            <heading>Limitation on applicability.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 11.81.210.   Limitation on applicability.
This title does not bar, suspend, or otherwise affect any right to or liability for damages, penalty, forfeiture, or other remedy authorized by law to be recovered or enforced in a civil action, regardless of whether the conduct involved in the proceeding constitutes an offense defined in this title.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_11-81-220">
            <num>11.81.220</num>
            <heading>All offenses defined by statute.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 11.81.220.   All offenses defined by statute.
No conduct constitutes an offense unless it is made an offense
(1) by this title;
(2) by a statute outside this title; or
(3) by a regulation authorized by and lawfully adopted under a statute.
Article 3. Classification of Offenses.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_11-81-250">
            <num>11.81.250</num>
            <heading>Classification of offenses.</heading>
            <subsection eId="11-81-250__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of sentencing under
AS 12.55
, all offenses defined in this title, except murder in the first and second degree, attempted murder in the first degree, solicitation to commit murder in the first degree, conspiracy to commit murder in the first degree, murder of an unborn child, sexual assault in the first degree, sexual abuse of a minor in the first degree, misconduct involving a controlled substance in the first degree, sex trafficking in the first degree under
AS 11.66.110
(a)(2), and kidnapping, are classified on the basis of their seriousness, according to the type of injury characteristically caused or risked by commission of the offense and the culpability of the offender. Except for murder in the first and second degree, attempted murder in the first degree, solicitation to commit murder in the first degree, conspiracy to commit murder in the first degree, murder of an unborn child, sexual assault in the first degree, sexual abuse of a minor in the first degree, misconduct involving a controlled substance in the first degree, sex trafficking in the first degree under
AS 11.66.110
(a)(2), and kidnapping, the offenses in this title are classified into the following categories:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-250__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>class A felonies, which characteristically involve conduct resulting in serious physical injury or a substantial risk of serious physical injury to a person;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-250__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>class B felonies, which characteristically involve conduct resulting in less severe violence against a person than class A felonies, aggravated offenses against property interests, or aggravated offenses against public administration or order;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-250__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>class C felonies, which characteristically involve conduct serious enough to deserve felony classification but not serious enough to be classified as A or B felonies;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-250__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>class A misdemeanors, which characteristically involve less severe violence against a person, less serious offenses against property interests, less serious offenses against public administration or order, or less serious offenses against public health and decency than felonies;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-250__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>class B misdemeanors, which characteristically involve a minor risk of physical injury to a person, minor offenses against property interests, minor offenses against public administration or order, or minor offenses against public health and decency;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-250__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>violations, which characteristically involve conduct inappropriate to an orderly society but which do not denote criminality in their commission.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="11-81-250__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The classification of each felony defined in this title, except murder in the first and second degree, attempted murder in the first degree, solicitation to commit murder in the first degree, conspiracy to commit murder in the first degree, murder of an unborn child, sexual assault in the first degree, sexual abuse of a minor in the first degree, misconduct involving a controlled substance in the first degree, sex trafficking in the first degree under
AS 11.66.110
(a)(2), and kidnapping, is designated in the section defining it. A felony under the law of this state defined outside this title for which no penalty is specifically provided is a class C felony.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="11-81-250__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The classification of each misdemeanor defined in this title is designated in the section defining it.  A misdemeanor under Alaska law defined outside this title for which no penalty is provided is a class A misdemeanor.
Article 4. General Principles of Justification.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_11-81-300">
            <num>11.81.300</num>
            <heading>Justification: Defense.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 11.81.300.   Justification: Defense.
Except as otherwise specified in this title, justification as provided in
AS 11.81.320
 11.81.430 is a defense.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_11-81-320">
            <num>11.81.320</num>
            <heading>Justification: Necessity.</heading>
            <subsection eId="11-81-320__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Conduct which would otherwise be an offense is justified by reason of necessity to the extent permitted by common law when</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-320__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>neither this title nor any other statute defining the offense provides exemptions or defenses dealing with the justification of necessity in the specific situation involved; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-320__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a legislative intent to exclude the justification of necessity does not otherwise plainly appear.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="11-81-320__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The justification specified in (a) of this section is an affirmative defense.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_11-81-330">
            <num>11.81.330</num>
            <heading>Justification: Use of nondeadly force in defense of self.</heading>
            <subsection eId="11-81-330__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person is justified in using nondeadly force upon another when and to the extent the person reasonably believes it is necessary for self-defense against what the person reasonably believes to be the use of unlawful force by the other person, unless</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-330__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the person used the force in mutual combat not authorized by law;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-330__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the person claiming self-defense provoked the other's conduct with intent to cause physical injury to the other;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-330__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the person claiming self-defense was the initial aggressor; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-330__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the force used was the result of using a deadly weapon or dangerous instrument the person claiming self-defense possessed while
(A) acting alone or with others to further a felony criminal objective of the person or one or more other persons;
(B) a participant in a felony transaction or purported transaction or in immediate flight from a felony transaction or purported transaction in violation of
AS 11.71
; or
(C) acting alone or with others in revenge for, retaliation for, or response to actual or perceived conduct by a rival or perceived rival, or a member or perceived member of a rival group, if the person using deadly force, or the group on whose behalf the person is acting, has a history or reputation for violence among civilians.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="11-81-330__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who is not justified in using force in self-defense in the circumstances listed in (a)(1)  (3) of this section is justified in using force in self-defense if that person has withdrawn from the encounter and effectively communicated the withdrawal to the other person, but the other person persists in continuing the incident by the use of unlawful force.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_11-81-335">
            <num>11.81.335</num>
            <heading>Justification: Use of deadly force in defense of self.</heading>
            <subsection eId="11-81-335__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (b) of this section, a person who is justified in using nondeadly force in self-defense under
AS 11.81.330
may use deadly force in self-defense upon another person when and to the extent the person reasonably believes the use of deadly force is necessary for self-defense against</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-335__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>death;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-335__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>serious physical injury;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-335__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>kidnapping, except for what is described as custodial interference in the first degree in
AS 11.41.320
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-335__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>sexual assault in the first degree;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-335__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>sexual assault in the second degree;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-335__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>sexual abuse of a minor in the first degree; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-335__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>robbery in any degree.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="11-81-335__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not use deadly force under this section if the person knows that, with complete personal safety and with complete safety as to others being defended, the person can avoid the necessity of using deadly force by leaving the area of the encounter, except there is no duty to leave the area if the person is</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-335__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>on premises
(A) that the person owns or leases;
(B) where the person resides, temporarily or permanently; or
(C) as a guest or express or implied agent of the owner, lessor, or resident;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-335__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a peace officer acting within the scope and authority of the officer's employment or a person assisting a peace officer under
AS 11.81.380
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-335__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in a building where the person works in the ordinary course of the person's employment;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-335__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>protecting a child or a member of the person's household; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-335__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in any other place where the person has a right to be.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_11-81-340">
            <num>11.81.340</num>
            <heading>Justification: Use of force in defense of a third person.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 11.81.340.   Justification: Use of force in defense of a third person.
A person is justified in using force upon another when and to the extent the person reasonably believes it is necessary to defend a third person when, under the circumstances as the person claiming defense of another reasonably believes them to be, the third person would be justified under
AS 11.81.330
or 11.81.335 in using that degree of force for self-defense.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_11-81-350">
            <num>11.81.350</num>
            <heading>Justification: Use of force in defense of property and premises.</heading>
            <subsection eId="11-81-350__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may use nondeadly force upon another when and to the extent the person reasonably believes it is necessary to terminate what the person reasonably believes to be the commission or attempted commission by the other of an unlawful taking or damaging of property or services.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="11-81-350__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may use deadly force upon another when and to the extent the person reasonably believes it necessary to terminate what the person reasonably believes to be the commission or attempted commission of arson upon a dwelling or occupied building.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="11-81-350__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person in possession or control of any premises, or a guest or an express or implied agent of that person, may use</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-350__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>nondeadly force upon another when and to the extent the person reasonably believes it is necessary to terminate what the person reasonably believes to be the commission or attempted commission by the other of criminal trespass in any degree upon the premises;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-350__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>deadly force upon another when and to the extent the person reasonably believes it is necessary to terminate what the person reasonably believes to be a burglary in any degree occurring in an occupied dwelling or building.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="11-81-350__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 7 ch 68 SLA 2006.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="11-81-350__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-350__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in a vehicle, or forcibly removed from a vehicle, may use deadly force upon another when and to the extent the person reasonably believes it is necessary to terminate what the person reasonably believes to be a carjacking of that vehicle at or about the time the vehicle is carjacked;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-350__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>outside of a vehicle may use deadly force upon another when and to the extent the person reasonably believes it is necessary to terminate what the person reasonably believes to be the theft of that vehicle when another person, other than the perceived offender, is inside of the vehicle; this paragraph does not apply to a person outside of a vehicle who is involved in a dispute with a person inside of the vehicle who is a household member of that person; in this paragraph, household member has the meaning given in
AS 18.66.990
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="11-81-350__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person justified in using force under this section does not have a duty to leave or attempt to leave the area of the encounter before using force.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="11-81-350__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In (e) of this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-350__subsec_g__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>carjacking means a robbery involving the taking or attempted taking of a vehicle from a person in possession of the vehicle;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-350__subsec_g__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>vehicle means a motor vehicle as defined in
AS 28.90.990
, an aircraft, or a watercraft.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_11-81-370">
            <num>11.81.370</num>
            <heading>Justification: Use of force by a peace officer in making an arrest or terminating an escape.</heading>
            <subsection eId="11-81-370__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to using force justified under other sections of this chapter, a peace officer may use nondeadly force and may threaten to use deadly force when and to the extent the officer reasonably believes it necessary to make an arrest, to terminate an escape or attempted escape from custody, or to make a lawful stop.  The officer may use deadly force only when and to the extent the officer reasonably believes the use of deadly force is necessary to make the arrest or terminate the escape or attempted escape from custody of a person the officer reasonably believes</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-370__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has committed or attempted to commit a felony which involved the use of force against a person;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-370__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has escaped or is attempting to escape from custody while in possession of a firearm on or about the person; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-370__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>may otherwise endanger life or inflict serious physical injury unless arrested without delay.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="11-81-370__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The use of force in making an arrest or stop is not justified under this section unless the peace officer reasonably believes the arrest or stop is lawful.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="11-81-370__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing in this section prohibits or restricts a peace officer in preparing to use or threatening to use a dangerous instrument.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_11-81-380">
            <num>11.81.380</num>
            <heading>Justification: Use of force by private person assisting an arrest or terminating an escape.</heading>
            <subsection eId="11-81-380__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (b) of this section, a person who has been directed by another who that person reasonably believes to be a peace officer to assist in making an arrest or terminating or preventing an escape may use nondeadly force when and to the extent the person reasonably believes it necessary to carry out the peace officer's direction. A person may use deadly force under this section only when the person reasonably believes it necessary to carry out the peace officer's direction to use deadly force.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="11-81-380__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The use of force under (a) of this section is not justified if the person believes that the peace officer is not justified in using that degree of force under the circumstances.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_11-81-390">
            <num>11.81.390</num>
            <heading>Use of force by a private person in making arrest or terminating an escape.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 11.81.390.   Use of force by a private person in making arrest or terminating an escape.
In addition to using force justified under other sections of this chapter, a person, acting as a private person, may use nondeadly force to make the arrest or terminate the escape or attempted escape from custody of a person who the private person reasonably believes has committed a misdemeanor in the private person's presence or a felony when and to the extent the private person reasonably believes it necessary to make that arrest or terminate that escape or attempted escape from custody.  A private person may use deadly force under this section only when and to the extent the private person reasonably believes the use of deadly force is necessary to make the arrest or terminate the escape or attempted escape from custody of another who the private person reasonably believes
(1) has committed or attempted to commit a felony which involved the use of force against a person; or
(2) has escaped or is attempting to escape from custody while in possession of a firearm on or about the person.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_11-81-400">
            <num>11.81.400</num>
            <heading>Justification: Use of force in resisting or interfering with arrest.</heading>
            <subsection eId="11-81-400__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not use force to resist personal arrest or interfere with the arrest of another by a peace officer who is known by the person, or reasonably appears, to be a peace officer, whether the arrest is lawful or unlawful, unless</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-400__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the force used by the peace officer exceeds that allowed under
AS 11.81.370
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-400__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>[Repealed, § 1 ch 63 SLA 1982.]</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="11-81-400__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The use of force justified under this section in resisting arrest or interfering with the arrest of another may not exceed the use of force justified under
AS 11.81.330
or 11.81.335.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="11-81-400__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 1 ch 63 SLA 1982.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="11-81-400__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 1 ch 63 SLA 1982.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_11-81-410">
            <num>11.81.410</num>
            <heading>Justification: Use of force by guards.</heading>
            <subsection eId="11-81-410__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to using force justified under other sections of this chapter, a guard or peace officer employed in a correctional facility may, if authorized by regulations adopted by the Department of Corrections, use nondeadly force upon another person when and to the extent reasonably necessary and appropriate to maintain order.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="11-81-410__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (c) of this section, a guard or peace officer employed in a correctional facility or a peace officer in the immediate vicinity of a correctional facility at the time of an escape from the facility may use deadly force when and to the extent the guard or peace officer reasonably believes it necessary to terminate the escape or attempted escape of a prisoner from the correctional facility.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="11-81-410__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The use of deadly force under (b) of this section is not justified if the guard or peace officer knows that the prisoner was under official detention in the correctional facility on a charge of a misdemeanor and does not believe that the prisoner is armed with a firearm, in which event only nondeadly force may be used.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_11-81-420">
            <num>11.81.420</num>
            <heading>Justification: Performance of public duty.</heading>
            <subsection eId="11-81-420__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless inconsistent with
AS 11.81.320
 11.81.410, conduct which would otherwise constitute an offense is justified when it is required or authorized by law or by a judicial decree, judgment, or order.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="11-81-420__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The justification afforded by this section also applies when</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-420__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the person reasonably believes the conduct to be required or authorized by a decree, judgment, or order of a court of competent jurisdiction or in the lawful execution of legal process, notwithstanding lack of jurisdiction of the court or defect in the legal process; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-420__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the person reasonably believes the conduct to be required or authorized to assist a peace officer in the performance of the officer's duties, notwithstanding that the officer exceeded the officer's authority.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_11-81-430">
            <num>11.81.430</num>
            <heading>Justification: Use of force, special relationships.</heading>
            <subsection eId="11-81-430__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The use of force on another person that would otherwise constitute an offense is justified under any of the following circumstances:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-430__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>When and to the extent reasonably necessary and appropriate to promote the welfare of the child or incompetent person, a parent, guardian, or other person entrusted with the care and supervision of a child under 18 years of age or an incompetent person may use reasonable and appropriate nondeadly force on that child or incompetent person.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-430__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>When and to the extent reasonably necessary and appropriate to maintain order and when the use of force is consistent with the welfare of the students, a teacher may, if authorized by school regulations and the principal of the school, use reasonable and appropriate nondeadly force on a student. If authorized by school regulations and the principal of the school, a teacher may use nondeadly force under this paragraph in any situation in which the teacher is responsible for the supervision of students. A teacher employed by a school board, including a regional educational attendance area school board, may use nondeadly force under this paragraph only if the school regulations authorizing the use of force have been adopted by the school board.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-430__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>When and to the extent reasonably necessary and appropriate to maintain order, a person responsible for the maintenance of order in a common carrier of passengers, or a person acting under that person's direction, may use reasonable and appropriate nondeadly force.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-430__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>When and to the extent reasonably necessary to prevent a suicide, a person who reasonably believes that another is imminently about to commit suicide may use reasonable and appropriate nondeadly force on that person.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-430__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A licensed physician, licensed mobile intensive care paramedic, or registered or advanced practice registered nurse; or a person acting under the direction of a licensed physician, licensed mobile intensive care paramedic, or registered or advanced practice registered nurse; or any person who renders emergency care at the scene of an emergency, may use reasonable and appropriate nondeadly force for the purpose of administering a recognized and lawful form of treatment that is reasonably adapted to promoting the physical or mental health of the patient if
(A) the treatment is administered with the consent of the patient or, if the patient is a child under 18 years of age or an incompetent person, with the consent of the parent, guardian, or other person entrusted with care and supervision of the child or incompetent person; or
(B) the treatment is administered in an emergency if the person administering the treatment reasonably believes that no one competent to consent can be consulted under the circumstances and that a reasonable person, wishing to safeguard the welfare of the patient, would consent.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="11-81-430__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who raises a defense under (a)(1) of this section and claims that the person upon whom force was used was an incompetent person has the burden of establishing by a preponderance of the evidence that, at the time force was used, the person upon whom the force was used was an incompetent person.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_11-81-440">
            <num>11.81.440</num>
            <heading>Duress.</heading>
            <subsection eId="11-81-440__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In any prosecution for an offense, it is an affirmative defense that the defendant engaged in the proscribed conduct because the defendant was coerced to do so by the use of unlawful force upon the defendant or a third person, which force a reasonable person in the defendant's situation would have been unable to resist.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="11-81-440__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The defense of duress is not available when one recklessly places oneself in a situation in which it is probable that one will be subject to duress.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_11-81-450">
            <num>11.81.450</num>
            <heading>Entrapment.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 11.81.450.   Entrapment.
In any prosecution for an offense, it is an affirmative defense that, in order to obtain evidence of the commission of an offense, a public law enforcement official or a person working in cooperation with the official induced the defendant to commit the offense by persuasion or inducement as would be effective to persuade an average person, other than one who is ready and willing, to commit the offense.  Inducement or persuasion which would induce only a person engaged in an habitual course of unlawful conduct for gain or profit does not constitute entrapment.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_11-81-500">
            <num>11.81.500</num>
            <heading>No prosecution for safe surrender of infant.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 11.81.500.   No prosecution for safe surrender of infant.
A parent may not be criminally prosecuted for surrendering a child of the parent if the child
(1) is an infant who is less than 21 days of age;
(2) is surrendered in the manner described in
AS 47.10.013
(c); and
(3) is not the subject of a court order affecting custody of the child.
Article 6. General Principles of Criminal Liability.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_11-81-600">
            <num>11.81.600</num>
            <heading>General requirements of culpability.</heading>
            <subsection eId="11-81-600__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The minimal requirement for criminal liability is the performance by a person of conduct that includes a voluntary act or the omission to perform an act that the person is capable of performing.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="11-81-600__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person is not guilty of an offense unless the person acts with a culpable mental state, except that no culpable mental state must be proved</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-600__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if the description of the offense does not specify a culpable mental state and the offense is
(A) a violation; or
(B) designated as one of strict liability; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-600__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if a legislative intent to dispense with the culpable mental state requirement is present.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_11-81-610">
            <num>11.81.610</num>
            <heading>Construction of statutes with respect to culpability.</heading>
            <subsection eId="11-81-610__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 44 ch 102 SLA 1980.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="11-81-610__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in
AS 11.81.600
(b), if a provision of law defining an offense does not prescribe a culpable mental state, the culpable mental state that must be proved with respect to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-610__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>conduct is knowingly; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-610__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a circumstance or a result is recklessly.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="11-81-610__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When a provision of law provides that criminal negligence suffices to establish an element of an offense, that element is also established if a person acts intentionally, knowingly, or recklessly.  If acting recklessly suffices to establish an element, that element also is established if a person acts intentionally or knowingly.  If acting knowingly suffices to establish an element, that element is also established if a person acts intentionally.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_11-81-615">
            <num>11.81.615</num>
            <heading>Offenses defined by age or value.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 11.81.615.   Offenses defined by age or value.
Whenever a provision of law defining an offense requires a determination of the age of the victim or the value of property or services, it is not a defense to the lowest class of offense established by the evidence that the age of the victim is less than the age which would make the offense a higher class of offense or that the value of the property or services exceeds the value which would make the offense a higher class of offense, and a person may be charged and convicted accordingly.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_11-81-620">
            <num>11.81.620</num>
            <heading>Effect of ignorance or mistake upon liability.</heading>
            <subsection eId="11-81-620__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Knowledge, recklessness, or criminal negligence as to whether conduct constitutes an offense, or knowledge, recklessness, or criminal negligence as to the existence, meaning, or application of the provision of law defining an offense, is not an element of an offense unless the provision of law clearly so provides.  Use of the phrase intent to commit a crime, intent to promote or facilitate the commission of a crime, or like terminology in a provision of law does not require that the defendant act with a culpable mental state as to the criminality of the conduct that is the object of the defendant's intent.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="11-81-620__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person is not relieved of criminal liability for conduct because the person engages in the conduct under a mistaken belief of fact, unless</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-620__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the factual mistake is a reasonable one that negates the culpable mental state required for the commission of the offense;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-620__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the provision of law defining the offense or a related provision of law expressly provides that the factual mistake constitutes a defense or exemption; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-620__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the factual mistake is a reasonable one that supports a defense of justification as provided in
AS 11.81.320
 11.81.430.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_11-81-630">
            <num>11.81.630</num>
            <heading>Intoxication as a defense.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 11.81.630.   Intoxication as a defense.
Voluntary intoxication is not a defense to a prosecution for an offense, but evidence that the defendant was intoxicated may be offered whenever it is relevant to negate an element of the offense that requires that the defendant intentionally cause a result.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_11-81-640">
            <num>11.81.640</num>
            <heading>Application ofAS 11.81.600 11.81.630.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 11.81.640.   Application of
AS 11.81.600
 11.81.630.
AS 11.81.600
 11.81.630 apply only to this title.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_11-81-900">
            <num>11.81.900</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="11-81-900__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of this title, unless the context requires otherwise,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a person acts intentionally with respect to a result described by a provision of law defining an offense when the person's conscious objective is to cause that result; when intentionally causing a particular result is an element of an offense, that intent need not be the person's only objective;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a person acts knowingly with respect to conduct or to a circumstance described by a provision of law defining an offense when the person is aware that the conduct is of that nature or that the circumstance exists; when knowledge of the existence of a particular fact is an element of an offense, that knowledge is established if a person is aware of a substantial probability of its existence, unless the person actually believes it does not exist; a person who is unaware of conduct or a circumstance of which the person would have been aware had that person not been intoxicated acts knowingly with respect to that conduct or circumstance;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a person acts recklessly with respect to a result or to a circumstance described by a provision of law defining an offense when the person is aware of and consciously disregards a substantial and unjustifiable risk that the result will occur or that the circumstance exists; the risk must be of such a nature and degree that disregard of it constitutes a gross deviation from the standard of conduct that a reasonable person would observe in the situation; a person who is unaware of a risk of which the person would have been aware had that person not been intoxicated acts recklessly with respect to that risk;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a person acts with criminal negligence with respect to a result or to a circumstance described by a provision of law defining an offense when the person fails to perceive a substantial and unjustifiable risk that the result will occur or that the circumstance exists; the risk must be of such a nature and degree that the failure to perceive it constitutes a gross deviation from the standard of care that a reasonable person would observe in the situation.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="11-81-900__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this title, unless otherwise specified or unless the context requires otherwise,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>access device means a card, credit card, plate, code, account number, algorithm, or identification number, including a social security number, electronic serial number, or password, that is capable of being used, alone or in conjunction with another access device or identification document, to obtain property or services, or that can be used to initiate a transfer of property;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>affirmative defense means that
(A) some evidence must be admitted which places in issue the defense; and
(B) the defendant has the burden of establishing the defense by a preponderance of the evidence;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>animal means a vertebrate living creature not a human being, but does not include fish;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>benefit means a present or future gain or advantage to the beneficiary or to a third person pursuant to the desire or consent of the beneficiary;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>building, in addition to its usual meaning, includes any propelled vehicle or structure adapted for overnight accommodation of persons or for carrying on business; when a building consists of separate units, including apartment units, offices, or rented rooms, each unit is considered a separate building;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>cannabis has the meaning ascribed to it in
AS 11.71.900
(11), (12), and (15);</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_b__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>commercial sexual act means a sexual act for which anything of value is given or received by any person;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_b__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>conduct means an act or omission and its accompanying mental state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_b__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>controlled substance has the meaning ascribed to it in
AS 11.71.900
(5);</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_b__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>correctional facility means premises, or a portion of premises, used for the confinement of persons under official detention;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_b__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>credit card means any instrument or device, whether known as a credit card, credit plate, courtesy card, or identification card or by any other name, issued with or without fee by an issuer for the use of the cardholder in obtaining property or services on credit;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_b__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>crime means an offense for which a sentence of imprisonment is authorized; a crime is either a felony or a misdemeanor;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_b__subsec_13">
                <num>(13)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>crime involving domestic violence has the meaning given in
AS 18.66.990
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_b__subsec_14">
                <num>(14)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>criminal street gang means a group of three or more persons
(A) who have in common a name or identifying sign, symbol, tattoo or other physical marking, style of dress, or use of hand signs; and
(B) who, individually, jointly, or in combination, have committed or attempted to commit, within the preceding three years, for the benefit of, at the direction of, or in association with the group, two or more offenses under any of, or any combination of, the following:</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="11-81-900__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>AS 11.41
;
(ii)
AS 11.46
; or
(iii) a felony offense;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_15">
                <num>(15)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>culpable mental state means intentionally, knowingly, recklessly, or with criminal negligence, as those terms are defined in (a) of this section;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_16">
                <num>(16)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>dangerous instrument means
(A) any deadly weapon or anything that, under the circumstances in which it is used, attempted to be used, or threatened to be used, is capable of causing death or serious physical injury; or
(B) hands, other body parts, or other objects when used to impede normal breathing or circulation of blood by applying pressure on the throat or neck or obstructing the nose or mouth;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_17">
                <num>(17)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>deadly force means force that the person uses with the intent of causing, or uses under circumstances that the person knows create a substantial risk of causing, death or serious physical injury; deadly force includes intentionally discharging or pointing a firearm in the direction of another person or in the direction in which another person is believed to be and intentionally placing another person in fear of imminent serious physical injury by means of a dangerous instrument;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_18">
                <num>(18)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>deadly weapon means any firearm, or anything designed for and capable of causing death or serious physical injury, including a knife, an axe, a club, metal knuckles, or an explosive;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_19">
                <num>(19)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>deception means to knowingly
(A) create or confirm another's false impression that the defendant does not believe to be true, including false impressions as to law or value and false impressions as to intention or other state of mind;
(B) fail to correct another's false impression that the defendant previously has created or confirmed;
(C) prevent another from acquiring information pertinent to the disposition of the property or service involved;
(D) sell or otherwise transfer or encumber property and fail to disclose a lien, adverse claim, or other legal impediment to the enjoyment of the property, whether or not that impediment is a matter of official record; or
(E) promise performance that the defendant does not intend to perform or knows will not be performed;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_20">
                <num>(20)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>defense, other than an affirmative defense, means that
(A) some evidence must be admitted which places in issue the defense; and
(B) the state then has the burden of disproving the existence of the defense beyond a reasonable doubt;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_21">
                <num>(21)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>defensive weapon means an electric stun gun, or a device to dispense mace or a similar chemical agent, that is not designed to cause death or serious physical injury;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_22">
                <num>(22)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>drug has the meaning ascribed to it in
AS 11.71.900
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_23">
                <num>(23)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>dwelling means a building that is designed for use or is used as a person's permanent or temporary home or place of lodging;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_24">
                <num>(24)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>electronic smoking product
(A) means</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="11-81-900__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>any product containing or delivering nicotine or any other substance intended for human consumption that can be used by a person through inhalation of vapor or aerosol from the product, of any size or shape, whether the product is manufactured, distributed, marketed, or sold as an e-cigarette, e-cigar, e-pipe, e-hookah, vape pen, or any other product name or descriptor; or
(ii) a component, solution, alternative tobacco product, e-liquid, e-juice, vapor product, flavoring, or other related product of an electronic cigarette, electronic cigar, electronic cigarillo, electronic pipe, or other similar device of any size or shape used for, or to assist with, aerosolizing and inhaling chemical substances that may cause an adverse effect on human health;
(B) does not include marijuana as defined in
AS 11.71.900
;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_25">
                <num>(25)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>explosive means a chemical compound, mixture, or device that is commonly used or intended for the purpose of producing a chemical reaction resulting in a substantially instantaneous release of gas and heat, including dynamite, blasting powder, nitroglycerin, blasting caps, and nitrojelly, but excluding consumer fireworks and display fireworks as designated in a regulation adopted under
AS 18.72.011</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_26">
                <num>(26)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>felony means a crime for which a sentence of imprisonment for a term of more than one year is authorized;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_27">
                <num>(27)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>fiduciary means a trustee, guardian, executor, administrator, receiver, or any other person carrying on functions of trust on behalf of another person or organization;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_28">
                <num>(28)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>firearm means a weapon, including a pistol, revolver, rifle, or shotgun, whether loaded or unloaded, operable or inoperable, designed for discharging a shot capable of causing death or serious physical injury;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_29">
                <num>(29)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>force means any bodily impact, restraint, or confinement or the threat of imminent bodily impact, restraint, or confinement, force includes deadly and nondeadly force;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_30">
                <num>(30)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>government means the United States, any state or any municipality or other political subdivision within the United States or its territories; any department, agency, or subdivision of any of the foregoing; an agency carrying out the functions of government; or any corporation or agency formed under interstate compact or international treaty;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_31">
                <num>(31)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>gravity knife means any knife that has a blade that opens or releases a blade from its handle or sheath by the force of gravity or by the application of centrifugal force; gravity knife does not include a knife that has a spring, detent, or other mechanism designed to create a bias toward closure that requires a person to apply exertion to the blade by hand, wrist, or arm to overcome the bias toward closure and open or release the blade;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_32">
                <num>(32)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>highway means a public road, road right-of-way, street, alley, bridge, walk, trail, tunnel, path, or similar or related facility, as well as ferries and similar or related facilities;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_33">
                <num>(33)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>identification document means a paper, instrument, or other article used to establish the identity of a person; identification document includes a social security card, driver's license, non-driver's identification, birth certificate, passport, employee identification, or hunting or fishing license;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_34">
                <num>(34)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>includes means includes but is not limited to;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_35">
                <num>(35)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>incompetent person means a person who is impaired by reason of mental illness or mental deficiency to the extent that the person lacks sufficient understanding or capacity to make or communicate responsible decisions concerning that person;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_36">
                <num>(36)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>intoxicated means intoxicated from the use of a drug or alcohol;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_37">
                <num>(37)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>law includes statutes and regulations;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_38">
                <num>(38)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>leased includes rented;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_39">
                <num>(39)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>metal knuckles means a device that consists of finger rings or guards made of a hard substance and designed, made, or adapted for inflicting serious physical injury or death by striking a person;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_40">
                <num>(40)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>misdemeanor means a crime for which a sentence of imprisonment for a term of more than one year may not be imposed;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_41">
                <num>(41)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>nondeadly force means force other than deadly force;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_42">
                <num>(42)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>offense means conduct for which a sentence of imprisonment or fine is authorized; an offense is either a crime or a violation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_43">
                <num>(43)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>official detention means custody, arrest, surrender in lieu of arrest, or actual or constructive restraint under an order of a court in a criminal or juvenile proceeding, other than an order of conditional bail release;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_44">
                <num>(44)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>official proceeding means a proceeding heard before a legislative, judicial, administrative, or other governmental body or official authorized to hear evidence under oath;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_45">
                <num>(45)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>omission means a failure to perform an act for which a duty of performance is imposed by law;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_46">
                <num>(46)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>organization means a legal entity, including a corporation, company, association, firm, partnership, joint stock company, foundation, institution, government, society, union, club, church, or any other group of persons organized for any purpose;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_47">
                <num>(47)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>peace officer means a public servant vested by law with a duty to maintain public order or to make arrests, whether the duty extends to all offenses or is limited to a specific class of offenses or offenders;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_48">
                <num>(48)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>person means a natural person and, when appropriate, an organization, government, or governmental instrumentality;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_49">
                <num>(49)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>physical injury means a physical pain or an impairment of physical condition;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_50">
                <num>(50)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>police dog means a dog used in police work under the control of a peace officer;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_51">
                <num>(51)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>possess means having physical possession or the exercise of dominion or control over property;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_52">
                <num>(52)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>premises means real property and any building;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_53">
                <num>(53)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>propelled vehicle means a device upon which or by which a person or property is or may be transported, and which is self-propelled, including automobiles, vessels, airplanes, motorcycles, snow machines, all-terrain vehicles, sailboats, and construction equipment;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_54">
                <num>(54)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>property means an article, substance, or thing of value, including money, tangible and intangible personal property including data or information stored in a computer program, system, or network, real property, an access device, a domestic pet or livestock regardless of value, choses-in-action, and evidence of debt or of contract; a commodity of a public utility such as gas, electricity, steam, or water constitutes property, but the supplying of such a commodity to premises from an outside source by means of wires, pipes, conduits, or other equipment is considered a rendition of a service rather than a sale or delivery of property;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_55">
                <num>(55)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>public place means a place to which the public or a substantial group of persons has access and includes highways, transportation facilities, schools, places of amusement or business, parks, playgrounds, prisons, and hallways, lobbies, and other portions of apartment houses and hotels not constituting rooms or apartments designed for actual residence;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_56">
                <num>(56)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>public record means a document, paper, book, letter, drawing, map, plat, photo, photographic file, motion picture, film, microfilm, microphotograph, exhibit, magnetic or paper tape, punched card or other document of any other material, regardless of physical form or characteristic, developed or received under law or in connection with the transaction of official business and preserved or appropriate for preservation by any agency, municipality, or any body subject to the open meeting provision of
AS 44.62.310
, as evidence of the organization, function, policies, decisions, procedures, operations, or other activities of the state or municipality or because of the informational value in it; it also includes staff manuals and instructions to staff that affect the public;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_57">
                <num>(57)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>public servant means each of the following, whether compensated or not, but does not include jurors or witnesses:
(A) an officer or employee of the state, a municipality or other political subdivision of the state, or a governmental instrumentality of the state, including legislators, members of the judiciary, and peace officers;
(B) a person acting as an advisor, consultant, or assistant at the request of, the direction of, or under contract with the state, a municipality or other political subdivision of the state, or another governmental instrumentality; in this subparagraph person includes an employee of the person;
(C) a person who serves as a member of the board or commission created by statute or by legislative, judicial, or administrative action by the state, a municipality or other political subdivision of the state, or a governmental instrumentality;
(D) a person nominated, elected, appointed, employed, or designated to act in a capacity defined in (A)  (C) of this paragraph, but who does not occupy the position;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_58">
                <num>(58)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a renunciation is not voluntary and complete if it is substantially motivated, in whole or in part, by
(A) a belief that circumstances exist which increase the probability of detection or apprehension of the defendant or another participant in the criminal enterprise, or which render more difficult the accomplishment of the criminal purpose; or
(B) a decision to postpone the criminal conduct until another time or to transfer the criminal effort to another victim or another but similar objective;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_59">
                <num>(59)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>semen means fluid produced in the male reproductive organs, which may include spermatozoa.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_60">
                <num>(60)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>serious physical injury means
(A) physical injury caused by an act performed under circumstances that create a substantial risk of death; or
(B) physical injury that causes serious and protracted disfigurement, protracted impairment of health, protracted loss or impairment of the function of a body member or organ, or that unlawfully terminates a pregnancy;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_61">
                <num>(61)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>services includes labor, professional services, transportation, telephone or other communications service, entertainment, including cable, subscription, or pay television or other telecommunications service, the supplying of food, lodging, or other accommodations in hotels, restaurants, or elsewhere, admission to exhibitions, the use of a computer, computer time, a computer system, a computer program, a computer network, or any part of a computer system or network, and the supplying of equipment for use;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_62">
                <num>(62)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>sexual act means sexual penetration or sexual contact;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_63">
                <num>(63)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>sexual contact means
(A) the defendant's</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="11-81-900__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>knowingly touching, directly or through clothing, the victim's genitals, anus, or female breast;
(ii) knowingly causing the victim to touch, directly or through clothing, the defendant's or victim's genitals, anus, or female breast; or
(iii)  knowingly causing the victim to come into contact with semen;
(B) but sexual contact does not include acts</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="11-81-900__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>that may reasonably be construed to be normal caretaker responsibilities for a child, interactions with a child, or affection for a child;
(ii) performed for the purpose of administering a recognized and lawful form of treatment that is reasonably adapted to promoting the physical or mental health of the person being treated; or
(iii) that are a necessary part of a search of a person committed to the custody of the Department of Corrections or the Department of Family and Community Services;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_64">
                <num>(64)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>sexual penetration
(A) means genital intercourse, cunnilingus, fellatio, anal intercourse, or an intrusion, however slight, of an object or any part of a person's body into the genital or anal opening of another person's body; each party to any of the acts described in this subparagraph is considered to be engaged in sexual penetration;
(B) does not include acts</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="11-81-900__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>performed for the purpose of administering a recognized and lawful form of treatment that is reasonably adapted to promoting the physical health of the person being treated; or
(ii) that are a necessary part of a search of a person committed to the custody of the Department of Corrections or the Department of Family and Community Services;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_65">
                <num>(65)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>solicits includes commands;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_66">
                <num>(66)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>switchblade means any knife that has a blade that folds, closes, or retracts into the handle or sheath that opens automatically by pressure applied to a button or other device located on the handle or sheath; switchblade does not include a knife that has a spring, detent, or other mechanism designed to create a bias toward closure that requires exertion applied to the blade by hand, wrist, or arm to overcome the bias toward closure and open the blade;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_67">
                <num>(67)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>threat means a menace, however communicated, to engage in conduct described in
AS 11.41.520</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_68">
                <num>(68)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>unborn child means a member of the species Homo sapiens, at any stage of development, who is carried in the womb;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_69">
                <num>(69)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>violation is a noncriminal offense punishable only by a fine, but not by imprisonment or other penalty; conviction of a violation does not give rise to any disability or legal disadvantage based on conviction of a crime; a person charged with a violation is not entitled
(A) to a trial by jury; or
(B) to have a public defender or other counsel appointed at public expense to represent the person;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="11-81-900__subsec_i__subsec_70">
                <num>(70)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>voluntary act means a bodily movement performed consciously as a result of effort and determination, and includes the possession of property if the defendant was aware of the physical possession or control for a sufficient period to have been able to terminate it.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>