<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-47/chapter-30"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-47/chapter-30"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="47.30"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-47/chapter-30/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-47/chapter-30/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-47/chapter-30/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-47/chapter-30/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_47">
        <num>47</num>
        <heading>Welfare, Social Services, and Institutions</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_47__chp_30">
          <num>30</num>
          <heading>Mental Health</heading>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-350">
            <num>47.30.350</num>
            <heading>Department powers and duties; ratification of authority's actions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-350__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-350__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>develop and submit to the Surgeon General of the United States Public Health Service a comprehensive program for the constructing and equipping of hospitals and other facilities for the examination, observation, care, and treatment of the mentally ill;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-350__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>develop and submit to the Surgeon General plans and specifications for the constructing and equipping of the hospitals and other facilities;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-350__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>construct and equip the hospitals and other facilities in accordance with the program, plans, and specifications approved by the Surgeon General; construction and equipping under this paragraph is governed by
AS 36.30
(State Procurement Code);</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-350__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>cooperate, coordinate, and contract, wherever indicated and desirable, with other state boards, departments and agencies, and agencies of the United States in the construction program, and hire necessary personnel and enter into contracts with private individuals and companies, to the end that the hospitals and other facilities are constructed in the most economical and expeditious manner; contracting and construction under this section are governed by
AS 36.30
(State Procurement Code).</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-350__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An action, agreement, or transaction taken or entered before April 3, 1957, by the Mental Health Authority consistent with
AS 47.30.350
 47.30.400 is affirmed and ratified.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-360">
            <num>47.30.360</num>
            <heading>Acceptance and expenditure of funds.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.360.   Acceptance and expenditure of funds.
The department may accept on behalf of the state and deposit separate and apart from other public funds grants from the federal government or gifts or contributions from other sources to assist in carrying out the purposes of
AS 47.30.350
 47.30.400 and may expend the funds for those purposes.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-370">
            <num>47.30.370</num>
            <heading>Review by legislative budget and audit committee.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.370.   Review by legislative budget and audit committee.
Before implementation, the programs, plans, and actions of the department made under
AS 47.30.350
, except for the proposed geographic location of the mental health hospital, shall be reviewed by the legislative budget and audit committee.  The review and findings of the budget and audit committee shall be made public.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-380">
            <num>47.30.380</num>
            <heading>Appropriation authorized.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-380__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and submitted to the legislature under
AS 37.07.020
(a)(1).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-390">
            <num>47.30.390</num>
            <heading>Acquisition of existing mental health care facilities.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.390.   Acquisition of existing mental health care facilities.
The department may acquire existing facilities for mental health care.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-400">
            <num>47.30.400</num>
            <heading>Purpose ofAS 47.30.35047.30.400.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.400.   Purpose of
AS 47.30.350
47.30.400.
The purpose of
AS 47.30.350
 47.30.400 is to provide for the constructing and equipping of hospitals and other facilities in this state needed for carrying out a comprehensive mental health program, to accept the benefits of 42 U.S.C. 274, and to authorize the department to take action necessary to accomplish these purposes.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-410">
            <num>47.30.410</num>
            <heading>Persons subject to extradition.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.410.   Persons subject to extradition.
A person alleged to be of unsound mind found in this state, who has fled from another state, shall, on demand of the executive authority of the state from which the person fled, be delivered up to be removed to the state where, at the time of the flight the person
(1) was under detention by law in a hospital, asylum, or other institution for the insane as a person of unsound mind;
(2) had been determined by legal proceedings to be of unsound mind, the finding being unreversed and in full force and effect, and the control of the person having been acquired by a court of competent jurisdiction of the state from which the person fled; or
(3) was subject to detention in that state, which was then the person's legal domicile (personal service of process having been made) based on legal proceedings there pending to have the person declared of unsound mind.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-420">
            <num>47.30.420</num>
            <heading>Extradition proceedings.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.420.   Extradition proceedings.
If the executive authority of a state demands of the executive authority of this state a fugitive under
AS 47.30.410
and produces a copy of the commitment decree or other judicial process and proceedings, certified as authentic by the governor or chief magistrate of the state from which the person so charged has fled, with an affidavit made before a proper officer showing the person to be a fugitive, the executive authority of this state shall have the fugitive apprehended and secured, if found in this state, and have immediate notice of the apprehension given to the executive authority making the demand, or to the agent of that authority appointed to receive the fugitive, and have the fugitive delivered to the agent when the agent appears.  If no agent appears within 30 days from the time of the apprehension the fugitive may be discharged.  All costs and expenses incurred in the apprehending, securing, maintaining, and transmitting the fugitive to the state making the demand shall be paid by that state.  An agent so appointed who receives the fugitive into custody is empowered to transmit the fugitive to the state from which the fugitive fled.  The executive authority of this state may, on the application of a person interested, demand the return to this state of a fugitive under
AS 47.30.410
 47.30.460.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-430">
            <num>47.30.430</num>
            <heading>Time to commence proceedings.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.430.   Time to commence proceedings.
All proceedings under
AS 47.30.410
 47.30.460 shall be begun within one year after the flight referred to in
AS 47.30.410
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-440">
            <num>47.30.440</num>
            <heading>Interpretation and construction.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.440.   Interpretation and construction.
AS 47.30.410
 47.30.460 shall be so interpreted and construed as to effectuate its general purpose to make uniform the law of those states that enact it.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-450">
            <num>47.30.450</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.450.   Definitions.
In
AS 47.30.410
 47.30.460
(1) executive authority, governor, and chief magistrate, respectively, as applied to a request to return a person under
AS 47.30.410
 47.30.460 to or from the District of Columbia, include a justice of the supreme court of the District of Columbia and other authority;
(2) flight and fled mean a voluntary or involuntary departure from the jurisdiction of the court where the proceedings mentioned in
AS 47.30.410
 47.30.460 have been instituted and are still pending, with the effect of avoiding, impeding, or delaying the action of the court in which the proceedings have been instituted or are pending, or a voluntary or involuntary departure from the state where the person demanded then was, if the person then was under detention by law as a person of unsound mind and subject to detention;
(3) state includes states, territories, districts, and insular and other possessions of the United States.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-460">
            <num>47.30.460</num>
            <heading>Short title.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.460.   Short title.
AS 47.30.410
 47.30.460 may be cited as the Uniform Act for the Extradition of Persons of Unsound Mind.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-470">
            <num>47.30.470</num>
            <heading>Powers and duties of department.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.470.   Powers and duties of department.
The department shall
(1) ascertain and keep current a list of all institutions in the state that have available facilities for the care and treatment of alcoholics and drug abusers;
(2) encourage the development and advancement of standards of treatment of alcoholics and drug abusers in institutions;
(3) promote and encourage educational activities to make the public aware of the effects of intemperate use of alcoholic beverages and drugs, and promote and encourage the education of the general public about scientific facts regarding alcoholism and drug abuse;
(4) identify and utilize whatever facilities and services are available or can be made available through community organization for carrying out the purposes of this section, including identification and utilization for detoxification of under-utilized hospital beds;
(5) engage in research and educational activities that will aid in the understanding of alcoholism and drug abuse and in the treatment of alcoholics and drug abusers;
(6) administer a community grant-in-aid program for alcoholism and drug abuse;
(7) submit an annual report concerning alcoholism and drug abuse in the state and the grant-in-aid program within 10 days after the convening of the legislature in each regular session;
(8) prepare that part of the plan for the integrated comprehensive mental health program under
AS 44.25.290
that relates to the services and facilities that are necessary for the care and treatment of persons identified as chronic alcoholics suffering from psychoses, as defined in
AS 44.25.290
(b)(3) and (f); in preparing the plan of services for persons identified in this paragraph, the department shall coordinate with the Alaska Mental Health Trust Authority and the Advisory Board on Alcoholism and Drug Abuse;
(9) use money awarded to the department by grant or contract from the mental health trust settlement income account established under
AS 37.14.036
and appropriated from the general fund to provide the necessary services identified in (8) of this section and in accordance with
AS 44.25.290
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-475">
            <num>47.30.475</num>
            <heading>Grant-in-aid program.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-475__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A nonprofit corporation, a city or borough government, or other political subdivision of the state, or a combination of these, is eligible for grant-in-aid funds under this section. Applications shall be sent to the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-475__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Money available under this section shall be awarded by the department to applicants on the basis of community need, but only after consideration of comment and advice of the Advisory Board on Alcoholism and Drug Abuse. In awarding grants, the department shall further consider the amount of money that is available for all applications and whether an application would contribute to the wise development of a comprehensive program of alcoholic and drug abuse rehabilitation and prevention.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-475__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Grants shall be awarded in a ratio of 75 percent state money to 25 percent community money for the costs of providing staff and limited improvement, renovation, or new construction of facilities for alcohol or drug detoxification, rehabilitation, or half-way house care. The department may waive all or part of the requirement that state money be matched by community money if the department finds that community money is unavailable and waiver of the requirement is in the best interests of the state. A grant for improving, renovating, or constructing may not exceed $50,000 except when there is a lack of applicants for available money and then only with the approval of the Advisory Board on Alcoholism and Drug Abuse. The department is not required to award all money available under this program, or the full percentages specified in this subsection, when another source of money is available or could reasonably be made available to the applicant.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-475__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Money used by the applicant to qualify for state money may be from any source other than the state.  The cost of developing an application is not reimbursable from the grant. The value of real property to be used directly in conjunction with the grant may be used in calculating the required amount of community money, as allowed by regulations of the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-475__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A grant may not be awarded under this section unless the application includes a plan that provides for</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-475__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the expenditure of grant money for education and other preventative measures, or the treatment of alcoholics and drug abusers;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-475__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the reception of advice and comment from a local advisory board, or, if a local advisory board cannot be formed because the area is sparsely populated, from the governing bodies of private nonprofit health organizations, regarding the design, implementation, and evaluation of the plan and action to be taken;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-475__subsec_e__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>goals, expressed in quantifiable terms that express the intended effect of the assistance provided under the plan upon the number of individuals needing or utilizing that assistance.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-475__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall monitor the implementation of the plan required under (e) of this section, and shall terminate payment of grant money if the plan is not implemented or approval of the program as a public or private treatment program under
AS 47.37.140
is not granted within one year of the award of the grant, or is suspended, revoked, limited, or restricted. Modification of the plan required by (e) of this section shall be approved by the department before implementation of the modification.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-475__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall provide management training for persons administering a program receiving grant money under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-475__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the department determines, after the award of a grant under (c) of this section, that the community is capable of bearing a greater portion of the cost of a program than originally determined, the department may</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-475__subsec_h__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>reduce the award by that portion of the cost of a program that the department subsequently determined the community could bear; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-475__subsec_h__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>terminate payment of the grant entirely.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-477">
            <num>47.30.477</num>
            <heading>Grant-in-aid program regulations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.477.   Grant-in-aid program regulations.
The department shall adopt regulations implementing
AS 47.30.475
. The regulations must provide for the method of application, the time for consideration of applications, the processing of applications, the type of record keeping, the requirements for reporting the progress and statistics regarding the program, and the notification of the applicant as to the action taken on the application. The department shall also establish the necessary forms of application and may adopt other regulations considered necessary to meet the requirements of health and safety and the orderly administration of the grant-in-aid program.  The regulations must include reporting requirements that will permit an evaluation of the success of the program.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-480">
            <num>47.30.480</num>
            <heading>Judicial notice.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.480.   Judicial notice.
The superior courts of this state may take judicial notice of the fact that an alcoholic is suffering from an illness and is in need of proper medical, advisory, or rehabilitative treatment.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-490">
            <num>47.30.490</num>
            <heading>Acceptance of funds.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.490.   Acceptance of funds.
The department may accept on behalf of the state and deposit, apart from other public funds, grants from the federal government or gifts or contributions from other sources to assist in carrying out the purposes of
AS 47.30.470
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-500">
            <num>47.30.500</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.500.   Definitions.
In
AS 47.30.470
 47.30.490,
(1) alcoholism means a condition related to alcohol and concerns a physical compulsion which exists, coupled with a mental obsession;
(2) costs of improvement, renovation, or new construction of facilities includes, in addition to costs directly related to the project, the sum total of all costs of financing and carrying out the project; these include, but are not limited to, the costs of all necessary studies, surveys, plans and specifications, architectural, engineering, or other special services, acquisition of real property, site preparation and development, purchase, construction, reconstruction, and improvement of real property, and the acquisition of machinery and equipment as may be necessary in connection with the project; an allocable portion of the administrative and operating expenses of the grantee; the cost of financing the project, including interest on bonds issued to finance the project; and the cost of other items, including any indemnity and surety bonds and premiums on insurance, legal fees, fees and expenses of trustees, depositaries, financial advisors, and paying agents for the bonds issued as the issuer considers necessary;
(3) department means the Department of Health.
Article 4. Community Mental Health Services Act.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-520">
            <num>47.30.520</num>
            <heading>Legislative purpose.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.520.   Legislative purpose.
It is the purpose of the Community Mental Health Services Act to
(1) provide a range of community-based inpatient, outpatient, and support services for persons with mental disorders;
(2) assist communities in planning, organizing, and financing community mental health services through locally developed, administered, and controlled community mental health programs;
(3) better develop and use resources at both state and local levels;
(4) develop and implement plans for comprehensive mental health services based on demonstrated need on a regional basis;
(5) improve the effectiveness of existing mental health services;
(6) integrate state-operated and community mental health programs into a unified mental health system;
(7) ensure that consumers, families, and representatives of communities within mental health planning regions can participate in planning for, determining the need for, and allocating mental health resources;
(8) provide a means of allocating money available for state mental health services according to community needs;
(9) encourage the full use of all existing public or private agencies, facilities, personnel, and funds to accomplish these objectives; and
(10) prevent unnecessary duplication and fragmentation of services and expenditures.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-523">
            <num>47.30.523</num>
            <heading>Community mental health program policy and principles.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-523__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>It is the policy of the state that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-523__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the community mental health program provide a comprehensive and integrated system of community-based facilities, supports, and mental health services, including child and adolescent screening and diagnosis, inpatient, outpatient, prevention, consultation, and education services;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-523__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>persons most in need of community mental health services receive appropriate services as provided under
AS 44.25.290
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-523__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the community mental health program be coordinated, to the maximum extent possible, with the programs established under
AS 47.37
,
AS 47.65
,
AS 47.80
, and other programs affecting the well being of persons in need of mental health services.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-523__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Community mental health program service delivery principles include the principles that persons</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-523__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>have ready and prompt access to necessary screening, diagnosis, and treatment;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-523__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>receiving community mental health services be informed of their rights, including their rights to confidentiality and to treatment with dignity;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-523__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>be provided community mental health services by staff and programs that reflect the culture, linguistic, and other social characteristics of their community and that incorporate multidisciplinary professional staff to meet client functional levels and diagnostic and treatment needs;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-523__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in need of community mental health services, and their families, be encouraged to participate in formulating, delivering, and evaluating treatment and rehabilitation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-523__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in need of community mental health services be provided treatment and rehabilitation services designed to minimize institutionalization and maximize individual potential;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-523__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>be treated in the least restrictive alternative environment consistent with their treatment needs, enabling the person to live as normally as possible;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-523__subsec_b__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>be provided necessary treatment as close to the person's home as possible;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-523__subsec_b__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>be informed of and allowed to participate in planning their own treatment as much as possible.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-530">
            <num>47.30.530</num>
            <heading>Duties of department.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-530__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall administer the provisions of
AS 47.30.520
 47.30.620 and shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-530__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>define and develop standards for various levels and qualities of mental health care;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-530__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide fiscal and professional technical assistance in planning, organizing, developing, implementing, and administering local mental health services;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-530__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>develop budgets and receive and distribute state appropriations and funds in accordance with the provisions of
AS 47.30.520
 47.30.620;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-530__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establish standards of education and experience for professional, technical, and administrative personnel employed in community mental health services;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-530__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>assist the community in establishing the organization and operation of community mental health services;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-530__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>develop a standardized system for measuring and reporting to the department the types, quantities, and quality of services; and develop a cost accounting system that will demonstrate the cost of various levels and qualities of care;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-530__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide each local community planning and services delivery entity with statistics, reports, and other data relevant to development of indices indicating the need for mental health services, or relevant to evaluating the effectiveness of existing services;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-530__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>review each local community plan and require each plan to include
(A) an affirmative showing that the most effective and economic use will be made of all available public and private resources in the community including careful consideration of the most effective and economic alternative forms and patterns of services;
(B) a five-year projection of needs, services, and resources; and
(C) adequate provisions for review and evaluation of services provided in the local community;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-530__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>adopt regulations and establish priorities, after consultation with local communities affected and in conjunction with the Alaska Mental Health Board, that are necessary to carry out the purposes of
AS 47.30.520
 47.30.620.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-530__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In performing its duties under (a) of this section, the department shall coordinate with the Alaska Mental Health Trust Authority established in
AS 44.25.200
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-540">
            <num>47.30.540</num>
            <heading>Local community entities.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-540__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A city or borough government or other political subdivision of the state, a nonprofit corporation, or a combination of these, is eligible to receive funds and administer local programs under
AS 47.30.520
 47.30.620.  In order to ensure equitable access to funds and programs through the state, the department shall determine appropriate geographical areas to be served by local programs in consultation with representatives of the geographical areas in question.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-540__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An entity designated by the department to receive money under
AS 47.30.520
 47.30.620 shall ensure a broad base of community support as evidenced by a governing board reasonably representative of the professional, civic, and citizen groups in the community and including persons with mental disorders or family members of persons with mental disorders. No more than two members, or 40 percent of the membership, whichever is greater, may be providers of services under the program. In order to receive money under
AS 47.30.520
 47.30.620, a local community entity shall agree</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-540__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to give priority to mental health programs and services consistent with the priorities set out in
AS 44.25.290
and that provide the maximum services for the least expenditure of money from the mental health trust settlement income account;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-540__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to furnish services through a qualified staff meeting reasonable standards of experience and training;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-540__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to conform to a state cost accounting system showing the true cost of services rendered, collect fees for services according to a schedule based on an analysis of reasonable ability to pay, and provide that a person may not be refused services because of inability to pay for those services;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-540__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to maintain adequate clinical and administrative records and furnish periodic reports to the department;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-540__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to furnish the authority and the department an annual report of the preceding fiscal year, including an evaluation of the effectiveness of the previous year's programs and their costs;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-540__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to furnish the authority and the department satisfactory needs assessments for the population and area it serves and an annual update of a long-range planning and budget statement that describes program goals for the coming year, the steps and resources necessary to implement the goals, the projected means by which these resources will be secured, and the procedures necessary to evaluate the program;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-540__subsec_b__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to furnish the department with confidential and other information about recipients of services paid for, in whole or part, under
AS 47.30.520
 47.30.620 and comply with regulations of the department regarding the submission of this information; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-540__subsec_b__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to notify the department immediately of emergency situations involving recipients of services paid for, in whole or in part, under
AS 47.30.520
 47.30.620 and comply with regulations of the department regarding this notification; for purposes of this paragraph, emergency situations include the disappearance, injury, or death of a recipient.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-540__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Members of local governing boards may be reimbursed for necessary travel expenses incurred in the organization and operation of local programs as may be determined by the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-545">
            <num>47.30.545</num>
            <heading>Populations to be served.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-545__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>shall provide one or more of the services that are set out in
AS 44.25.290</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-545__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>to persons identified in
AS 44.25.290
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-547">
            <num>47.30.547</num>
            <heading>Standards for community mental health services.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.547.   Standards for community mental health services.
An entity that provides community mental health services shall
(1) make services available at times and locations that enable residents of the entity's service area to obtain services readily;
(2) ensure each client's right to confidentiality and treatment with dignity;
(3) establish staffing patterns of qualified and trained personnel that reflect the cultural, linguistic, and other social characteristics of the community and that incorporate multidisciplinary professional staff to meet client functional levels and diagnostic and treatment needs;
(4) promote client and family participation in formulating, delivering, and evaluating treatment and rehabilitation;
(5) design screening, diagnosis, treatment, and rehabilitation services to maximize individual potential and to minimize institutionalization; and
(6) provide services in the least restrictive setting, enabling the person receiving the services to live as normally as possible.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-550">
            <num>47.30.550</num>
            <heading>Cost sharing formulas; use of income.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-550__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In a district designated by the department as a poverty area, the department may fund not more than 90 percent of the eligible costs of the community mental health services to be furnished under an entity's approved plan.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-550__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In a district that has not been designated by the department as a poverty area, the department may fund not more than 75 percent of the eligible costs of the community mental health services to be furnished under an entity's approved plan.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-550__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (a) and (b) of this section, if the department determines that sufficient funds from other sources are unavailable, then the department shall fund the percent of the eligible costs that is necessary in order to ensure that services for chronically mentally ill adults and severely mentally ill children, and other community mental health services to be furnished under an entity's approved plan are made available by the entity. Funding under this subsection is subject to the availability of legislative appropriations for the purpose.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-550__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Income earned by an entity through a community mental health project funded under
AS 47.30.520
 47.30.620 shall be used to augment or enhance the entity's mental health services.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-550__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In (a) and (b) of this section, poverty area means a census district in which at least 15 percent of the population, based upon the most recent census data, falls under 125 percent of the United States Department of Health and Human Services' Poverty Income Guidelines for Alaska, as reported in the Federal Register.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-560">
            <num>47.30.560</num>
            <heading>Contracts and expenditures.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.560.   Contracts and expenditures.
The contracts for services provided for in
AS 47.30.520
 47.30.620 shall be reviewed, revised if necessary, and approved at the expiration of each contract year.  A contract shall be approved if the department finds that the community entity has complied with its plan,
AS 47.30.520
 47.30.620, and any applicable regulations adopted by the department. Expenditures for the purchase of services shall be made in accordance with the approved contract, budgets, and program projections.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-570">
            <num>47.30.570</num>
            <heading>Regulations; eligible services and costs.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.570.   Regulations; eligible services and costs.
The department shall adopt regulations specifying the types of services and program costs eligible for state participation. These regulations must include
(1) a provision excluding capital expenditures as eligible costs; and
(2) a requirement that the community entity contractor or applicant agrees as a condition of contract approval that it will not supplant existing local fund support of community mental health services with funds received under
AS 47.30.520
 47.30.620 and that it will continue local funding support of community mental health services, in any year in which it contracts with the department, at a level that is at least equal to the local funding support in the previous year.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-580">
            <num>47.30.580</num>
            <heading>Comprehensive services.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.580.   Comprehensive services.
Plans and regulations adopted under
AS 47.30.520
 47.30.620 must allow local programs sufficient administrative and program flexibility so that local community mental health programs may be joined with other programs such as intellectual and developmental disability programs, drug abuse programs, alcoholism programs, and comprehensive mental health services programs.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-585">
            <num>47.30.585</num>
            <heading>Telehealth.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-585__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An entity designated by the department under
AS 47.30.520
 47.30.620 may provide community mental health services authorized under
AS 47.30.520
 47.30.620 through telehealth to a patient in this state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-585__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If an individual employed by an entity designated by the department under
AS 47.30.520
 47.30.620, in the course of a telehealth encounter with a patient, determines that some or all of the encounter will extend beyond the community mental health services authorized under
AS 47.30.520
 47.30.620, the individual shall advise the patient that the entity is not authorized to provide some or all of the services to the patient, recommend that the patient contact an appropriate provider for the services the entity is not authorized to provide, and limit the encounter to only those services the entity is authorized to provide. The entity may not charge a patient for any portion of an encounter that extends beyond the community mental health services authorized under
AS 47.30.520
 47.30.620.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-585__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A fee for a service provided through telehealth under this section must be reasonable and consistent with the ordinary fee typically charged for that service and may not exceed the fee typically charged for that service.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-585__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An entity permitted to provide telehealth under this section may not be required to document a barrier to an in-person visit to provide health care services through telehealth. The department may not limit the physical setting from which an entity may provide health care services through telehealth.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-585__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing in this section requires the use of telehealth when an individual employed by an entity designated by the department under
AS 47.30.520
 47.30.620 determines that providing services through telehealth is not appropriate or when a patient chooses not to receive services through telehealth.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-585__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, telehealth has the meaning given in
AS 47.05.270
(e).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-590">
            <num>47.30.590</num>
            <heading>Patient rights and the confidential nature of records and information.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-590__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall adopt regulations to assure patient rights and to safeguard the confidential nature of records and information about the recipients of services provided under this chapter. The regulations must require that entities identified in
AS 47.30.540</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-590__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>develop and include in any plan submitted for approval adequate provisions for safeguarding confidential information. The regulations must provide for disclosure of confidential information to parents or guardians, to mental health professionals providing services to a recipient, and to other appropriate service agencies when it is in the defined best interests of the patient.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-590__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (a) of this section, the department is authorized to review, obtain, and copy confidential and other records and information about the clients of services requested or furnished under
AS 47.30.520
 47.30.620 to evaluate compliance with those statutes. The department may obtain the records and information regarding clients from the client or directly from an entity designated by the department under
AS 47.30.520
 47.30.620 that furnished those services. Records obtained by the department under this subsection are medical records, shall be handled confidentially, and are exempt from public inspection and copying under
AS 40.25.110
 40.25.120.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-610">
            <num>47.30.610</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.610.   Definitions.
In
AS 47.30.520
 47.30.610,
(1) authority means the Alaska Mental Health Trust Authority established in
AS 44.25.200
;
(2) department means the Department of Health;
(3) persons with mental disorders means persons with disorders currently included within nationally accepted diagnostic systems of the mental health professions;
(4) trust has the meaning given in
AS 44.25.295
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-620">
            <num>47.30.620</num>
            <heading>Short title.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.620.   Short title.
AS 47.30.520
 47.30.620 may be cited as the Community Mental Health Services Act.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-655">
            <num>47.30.655</num>
            <heading>Purpose and principles of major revision.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.655.   Purpose and principles of major revision.
The purpose of the 1981 major revision of Alaska civil commitment statutes (
AS 47.30.660
and 47.30.670  47.30.915) is to more adequately protect the legal rights of persons suffering from mental illness.  The legislature has attempted to balance the individual's constitutional right to physical liberty and the state's interest in protecting society from persons who are dangerous to others and protecting persons who are dangerous to themselves by providing due process safeguards at all stages of commitment proceedings.  In addition, the following principles of modern mental health care have guided this revision:
(1) that persons be given every reasonable opportunity to accept voluntary treatment before involvement with the judicial system;
(2) that persons be treated in the least restrictive alternative environment consistent with their treatment needs;
(3) that treatment occur as promptly as possible and as close to the individual's home as possible;
(4) that a system of mental health community facilities and supports be available;
(5) that patients be informed of their rights and be informed of and allowed to participate in their treatment program as much as possible;
(6) that persons who are mentally ill but not dangerous to others be committed only if there is a reasonable expectation of improving their mental condition.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-660">
            <num>47.30.660</num>
            <heading>Cooperative powers and duties of the Department of Family and Community Services and the Department of Health.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-660__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Family and Community Services and the Department of Health, in cooperation, shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-660__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>prepare, and periodically revise and amend, a plan for an integrated comprehensive mental health program, as that term is defined by
AS 44.25.290</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-660__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in planning expenditures from the mental health trust settlement income account, conform to the regulations adopted by the Alaska Mental Health Trust Authority under
AS 44.25.240</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-660__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>implement an integrated comprehensive system of care that, within the limits of money appropriated for that purpose and using grants and contracts that are to be paid for from the mental health trust settlement income account, meets the service needs of the beneficiaries of the trust established under the Alaska Mental Health Enabling Act of 1956, as determined by the plan.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-660__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Family and Community Services and the Department of Health, in fulfilling each department's duties under this section and through each department's divisions responsible for mental health, shall, as applicable,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-660__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>administer a comprehensive program of services for persons with mental disorders, for the prevention of mental illness, and for the care and treatment of persons with mental disorders, including inpatient and outpatient care and treatment and the procurement of services of specialists or other persons on a contractual or other basis;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-660__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>take the actions and undertake the obligations that are necessary to participate in federal grants-in-aid programs and accept federal or other financial aid from whatever sources for the study, prevention, examination, care, and treatment of persons with mental disorders;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-660__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>administer
AS 47.30.660
 47.30.915;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-660__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>designate, operate, and maintain treatment facilities equipped and qualified to provide inpatient and outpatient care and treatment for persons with mental disorders;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-660__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide for the placement of patients with mental disorders in designated treatment facilities;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-660__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>enter into arrangements with governmental agencies for the care or treatment of persons with mental disorders in facilities of the governmental agencies in the state or in another state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-660__subsec_b__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>enter into contracts with treatment facilities for the custody and care or treatment of persons with mental disorders; contracts under this paragraph are governed by
AS 36.30
(State Procurement Code);</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-660__subsec_b__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>enter into contracts, which incorporate safeguards consistent with
AS 47.30.660
 47.30.915 and the preservation of the civil rights of the patients with another state for the custody and care or treatment of patients previously committed from this state under 48 U.S.C. 46 et seq., and P.L. 84-830, 70 Stat. 709;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-660__subsec_b__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>prescribe the form of applications, records, reports, requests for release, and consents to medical or psychological treatment required by
AS 47.30.660
 47.30.915;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-660__subsec_b__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>require reports from the head of a treatment facility concerning the care of patients;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-660__subsec_b__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>visit each treatment facility at least annually to review methods of care or treatment for patients;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-660__subsec_b__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>investigate complaints made by a patient or an interested party on behalf of a patient;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-660__subsec_b__subsec_13">
                <num>(13)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>delegate upon mutual agreement to another officer or agency of it, or a political subdivision of the state, or a treatment facility designated, any of the duties and powers imposed upon it by
AS 47.30.660
 47.30.915;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-660__subsec_b__subsec_14">
                <num>(14)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>after consultation with the Alaska Mental Health Trust Authority, adopt regulations to implement the provisions of
AS 47.30.660
 47.30.915;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-660__subsec_b__subsec_15">
                <num>(15)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide technical assistance and training to providers of mental health services; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-660__subsec_b__subsec_16">
                <num>(16)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>set standards under which each designated treatment facility shall provide programs to meet patients' medical, psychological, social, vocational, educational, and recreational needs.
Article 6. Voluntary Admission for Treatment.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-670">
            <num>47.30.670</num>
            <heading>Criteria for voluntary admission.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.670.   Criteria for voluntary admission.
A person 18 years of age or older may be voluntarily admitted to a treatment facility if the person is suffering from mental illness and voluntarily signs the admission papers.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-675">
            <num>47.30.675</num>
            <heading>Required notices.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-675__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon the application of a person for voluntary admission, or at the time a person admitted under
AS 47.30.690
reaches the age of 18, the person shall be given a copy of the following documents which shall be explained as necessary:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-675__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>notice of rights as set out in
AS 47.30.825
 47.30.865 and an explanation of any document served upon the person; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-675__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>notice that should the person desire to leave at a time when the treatment facility determines that the person is mentally ill and as a result is likely to cause serious harm to self or others or is gravely disabled, the facility could initiate commitment proceedings against the person.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-675__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If an applicant for voluntary admission does not understand English, the explanation shall be given in a language the applicant understands.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-680">
            <num>47.30.680</num>
            <heading>Required discharge.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.680.   Required discharge.
A patient who no longer meets the standards established in
AS 47.30.670
shall be discharged from the treatment facility.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-685">
            <num>47.30.685</num>
            <heading>Request to leave; evaluation; 48-hour hold for commitment.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.685.   Request to leave; evaluation; 48-hour hold for commitment.
A voluntary patient who is 18 years of age or older and who desires to leave a treatment facility shall submit to the facility a request to leave on a form provided by the facility.  When the investigation is completed, the patient shall be evaluated immediately in writing and discharged immediately or given written notice that involuntary commitment proceedings will be initiated against the patient. The treatment facility may detain the patient for no more than 48 hours after receipt of the patient's request to leave in order to initiate involuntary commitment proceedings.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-690">
            <num>47.30.690</num>
            <heading>Admission of minors under 18 years of age.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-690__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A minor under the age of 18 may be admitted for 30 days of evaluation, diagnosis, and treatment at a designated treatment facility if the minor's parent or guardian signs the admission papers and if, in the opinion of the professional person in charge,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-690__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the minor is gravely disabled or is suffering from mental illness and as a result is likely to cause serious harm to the minor or others;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-690__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>there is no less restrictive alternative available for the minor's treatment; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-690__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>there is reason to believe that the minor's mental condition could be improved by the course of treatment or would deteriorate further if untreated.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-690__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A guardian ad litem for a minor admitted under this section shall be appointed under
AS 25.24.310
to monitor the best interests of the minor as soon as possible after the minor's admission.  If the guardian ad litem finds that placement is not appropriate, the guardian ad litem may request that an attorney be appointed under
AS 25.24.310
to represent the minor. The attorney may request a hearing on behalf of the minor during the 30-day admittance.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-690__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The minor may be released by the treatment facility at any time if the professional person in charge or the minor's designated mental health professional determines the minor would no longer benefit from continued treatment and the minor is not dangerous.  The minor's parents or guardian must be notified by the facility of the contemplated release.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-693">
            <num>47.30.693</num>
            <heading>Notice to parent or guardian.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.693.   Notice to parent or guardian.
When a minor under 18 years of age is detained at or admitted or committed to a treatment facility, the facility shall inform the parent or guardian of the location of the minor as soon as possible after the arrival of the minor at the facility. When an adult for whom a guardian has been appointed is detained at or admitted or committed to a treatment facility and the facility is aware of the appointment, the facility shall inform the guardian of the location of the adult as soon as possible after the arrival of the adult at the facility.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-695">
            <num>47.30.695</num>
            <heading>Request by parent or guardian for release of minors under 18 years of age from detention and commitment.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.695.   Request by parent or guardian for release of minors under 18 years of age from detention and commitment.
The parent or guardian of a minor who is less than 18 years of age may file a notice to withdraw the minor from the facility. On receipt of the notice,
(1) the facility may discharge the minor to the custody of the parent or guardian; or
(2) if, in the opinion of the treating physician, release of the minor would be seriously detrimental to the minor's health, the treating physician may
(A) discharge the minor to the custody of the parent or guardian after advising the parent or guardian that this action is against medical advice and after receiving a written acknowledgment of the advice; or
(B) refuse to discharge the minor, initiate involuntary commitment proceedings, and continue to hold the minor until a court order under
AS 47.30.700
has been issued; or
(3) if, in the opinion of the treating physician, the minor is likely to cause serious harm to self or others and there is reason to believe the release could place the minor in imminent danger, the treating physician shall refuse to discharge the minor, and shall initiate involuntary commitment proceedings and continue to hold the minor until a court order under
AS 47.30.700
has been issued.
Article 7. Involuntary Admission for Treatment.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-700">
            <num>47.30.700</num>
            <heading>Initial involuntary commitment procedures.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-700__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon petition of any adult, a judge shall immediately conduct a screening investigation or direct a local mental health professional employed by the department or by a local mental health program that receives money from the department under
AS 47.30.520
 47.30.620 or another mental health professional designated by the judge, to conduct a screening investigation of the person alleged to be mentally ill and, as a result of that condition, alleged to be gravely disabled or to present a likelihood of serious harm to self or others. Within 48 hours after the completion of the screening investigation, a judge may issue an ex parte order orally or in writing, stating that there is probable cause to believe the respondent is mentally ill and that condition causes the respondent to be gravely disabled or to present a likelihood of serious harm to self or others.  The court shall provide findings on which the conclusion is based, appoint an attorney to represent the respondent, and may direct that a peace officer take the respondent into custody and deliver the respondent to the nearest appropriate facility for emergency examination or treatment.  The ex parte order shall be provided to the respondent and made a part of the respondent's clinical record.  The court shall confirm an oral order in writing within 24 hours after it is issued.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-700__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The petition required in (a) of this section must allege that the respondent is reasonably believed to present a likelihood of serious harm to self or others or is gravely disabled as a result of mental illness and must specify the factual information on which that belief is based including the names and addresses of all persons known to the petitioner who have knowledge of those facts through personal observation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-700__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When a crisis stabilization center, crisis residential center, evaluation facility, or treatment facility admits a minor respondent under this section, the center or facility shall inform the parent or guardian of the location of the minor as soon as possible after the arrival of the minor at the center or facility. When a crisis stabilization center, crisis residential center, evaluation facility, or treatment facility admits an adult for whom a guardian has been appointed and the center or facility is aware of the appointment, the center or facility shall inform the guardian of the location of the adult as soon as possible after the arrival of the adult at the center or facility.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-700__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A peace officer may take a respondent into custody under (a) of this section only if the ex parte order authorizing the peace officer to take the respondent into custody is transmitted to the peace officer through a distribution method that permits the peace officer to verify that the order originated from a court. If the peace officer receives an order through a distribution method that does not permit the peace officer to verify that the order originated from a court, the peace officer shall contact the court and request that the court transmit the order to the peace officer through a suitable distribution method. The court shall immediately comply. A facsimile transmission from a telephone number, or electronic mail from an electronic mail address, known by the peace officer to belong to a court is sufficient to satisfy this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-705">
            <num>47.30.705</num>
            <heading>Emergency detention for evaluation.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-705__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A peace officer, health officer, mental health professional, or physician assistant licensed by the State Medical Board to practice in this state who has probable cause to believe that a person is gravely disabled or is suffering from mental illness and is likely to cause serious harm to self or others of such immediate nature that considerations of safety do not allow initiation of involuntary commitment procedures set out in
AS 47.30.700
, may cause the person to be taken into custody by a peace officer or health officer and delivered to the nearest crisis stabilization center, crisis residential center, evaluation facility, or treatment facility. A person taken into custody for emergency evaluation may not be placed in a jail or other correctional facility except for protective custody purposes and only while awaiting transportation to a crisis stabilization center, crisis residential center, evaluation facility, or treatment facility. However, protective custody under this section may not include placement of a minor in a jail or secure facility. The peace officer, health officer, mental health professional, or physician assistant shall complete an application for examination of the person in custody and be interviewed by a mental health professional at the crisis stabilization center, crisis residential center, evaluation facility, or treatment facility.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-705__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When delivering a person to a crisis stabilization center, crisis residential center, evaluation facility, or treatment facility under (a) of this section, a peace officer or health officer shall give priority to a crisis stabilization center or crisis residential center if one exists in the service area served by the peace officer or health officer.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-705__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When a crisis stabilization center, crisis residential center, evaluation facility, or treatment facility admits a minor under this section, the center or facility shall inform the parent or guardian that the minor has been admitted as soon as possible after the arrival of the minor at the facility. When a crisis stabilization center, crisis residential center, evaluation facility, or treatment facility admits an adult for whom a guardian has been appointed and the center or facility is aware of the appointment, the center or facility shall inform the guardian that the adult has been admitted as soon as possible.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-705__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, minor means an individual who is under 18 years of age.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-706">
            <num>47.30.706</num>
            <heading>Detention for evaluation after finding of incompetence.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-706__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a person who has been charged with a felony offense against a person under
AS 11.41
or felony arson has been found incompetent to proceed under
AS 12.47
, before the charges are dismissed, an attorney with the Department of Law shall petition a court to have the person delivered to the nearest evaluation facility for an evaluation under
AS 47.30.710
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-706__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon receiving a petition under (a) of this section, a court shall, unless the presumption in (d) of this section has been successfully rebutted, issue an ex parte order orally or in writing stating that there is probable cause to believe the respondent is mentally ill and that condition causes the respondent to present a likelihood of serious harm to self or others. The court shall appoint an attorney to represent the respondent and may direct that a peace officer take the respondent into custody and deliver the respondent to the nearest appropriate facility for evaluation. The ex parte order shall be provided to the respondent and made a part of the respondent's clinical record. The court shall set a date, time, and place for a 30-day commitment hearing, to be held within 72 hours after the respondent's arrival at the evaluation facility. The court shall confirm an oral order in writing within 24 hours after it is issued.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-706__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A respondent taken into custody for evaluation under this section may not be placed in a jail or other correctional facility except for protective custody purposes and only while awaiting transportation to an evaluation facility.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-706__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A defendant charged with a felony offense against a person under
AS 11.41
or felony arson and found to be incompetent to proceed under
AS 12.47.100
is rebuttably presumed to be mentally ill and to present a likelihood of serious harm to self or others. In evaluating whether a defendant is likely to cause serious harm under this section, the court may consider the conduct with which the defendant was originally charged as evidence of recent behavior, regardless of any time spent in custody.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-707">
            <num>47.30.707</num>
            <heading>Admission to and hold at a crisis stabilization center.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-707__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (b) of this section, when a crisis stabilization center admits a respondent under
AS 47.30.705
, the crisis stabilization center may hold the respondent at the center for a period not to exceed 23 hours and 59 minutes. A mental health professional shall examine the respondent within three hours after the respondent arrives at the center.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-707__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the professional person in charge at the crisis stabilization center determines that there is probable cause to believe that the respondent has a mental illness and is suffering an acute behavioral health crisis and, as a result, is likely to cause serious harm to self or others or is gravely disabled, the respondent's acute behavioral health crisis will be resolved during admission to a crisis residential center or evaluation facility, and the respondent is not willing to voluntarily go to the crisis residential center or evaluation facility, a mental health professional may submit an ex parte application to the court under this section for detention at the crisis residential center or evaluation facility. Based on the application, if the court finds that probable cause exists to believe that the respondent has a mental illness and is suffering an acute behavioral health crisis and, as a result, is likely to cause serious harm to self or others or is gravely disabled and the respondent's acute behavioral health crisis will be resolved during admission to a crisis residential center or evaluation facility, and the respondent is not willing to voluntarily go to a crisis residential center or evaluation facility, the court shall grant the application and appoint an attorney to represent the respondent, and the respondent may remain at the crisis stabilization center until admission to a crisis residential center or evaluation facility. If the court finds no probable cause, the court shall order the respondent released.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-708">
            <num>47.30.708</num>
            <heading>Admission to and detention at a crisis residential center.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-708__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A respondent who is delivered to a crisis residential center for emergency examination and treatment shall be examined and evaluated as to mental and physical condition by a mental health professional within three hours after arrival at the facility.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-708__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The mental health professional who performs the emergency examination under (a) of this section may admit the respondent to the crisis residential center if the mental health professional has probable cause to believe that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-708__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the respondent has a mental illness and is suffering an acute behavioral health crisis and, as a result, is likely to cause serious harm to self or others or is gravely disabled; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-708__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the respondent's acute behavioral health crisis will be resolved during admission to the crisis residential center.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-708__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a mental health professional admits a respondent to a crisis residential center and a judicial order has not been obtained under
AS 47.30.707
, the mental health professional may apply for an ex parte order under this section authorizing admission to the crisis residential center. Based on the application, if the court finds that probable cause exists to believe that the respondent has a mental illness and is suffering an acute behavioral health crisis and, as a result, is likely to cause serious harm to self or others or is gravely disabled and the respondent's acute behavioral health crisis will be resolved during admission to a crisis residential center, the court shall grant the application and appoint an attorney to represent the respondent. If the court finds no probable cause, the court shall order the respondent released.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-708__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When, under (c) of this section, the court grants an ex parte application to admit a respondent to a crisis residential center, the court shall set a time for a hearing, to be held if needed within 72 hours after the respondent's arrival at the crisis stabilization center or the crisis residential center, whichever is earlier, and the court shall notify the respondent, the respondent's attorney, the respondent's guardian, if any, the petitioner's attorney, if any, and the attorney general of the time and place of the hearing. Computation of the 72-hour period at a crisis residential center before a hearing does not include Saturdays, Sundays, and legal holidays, except that if the exclusion of Saturdays, Sundays, and legal holidays from the computation of the 72-hour period would result in the respondent being held for longer than 72 hours, the 72-hour period ends at 5:00 p.m. on the next day that is not a Saturday, Sunday, or legal holiday. The hearing shall be held at the crisis residential center in person, by contemporaneous two-way video conference, or by teleconference, absent extraordinary circumstances. If a hearing is held by contemporaneous two-way video conference, only the court may record the hearing. In this subsection, contemporaneous two-way video conference means a conference among people at different places by means of transmitted audio and visual signals, using any communication technology that allows people at two or more places to interact simultaneously by way of two-way video and audio transmission.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-708__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In the course of the 72-hour period, a petition for 30-day commitment or for seven-day detention at a crisis residential center may be filed in court. A petition for 30-day commitment must conform with
AS 47.30.730
. A petition for seven-day detention at a crisis residential center must be signed by two mental health professionals, one of whom must be a physician, who have examined the respondent. A copy of the petition shall be served on the respondent, the respondent's attorney, and the respondent's guardian, if any, before the hearing. The petition for detention must</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-708__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>allege that the respondent is suffering an acute behavioral health crisis and, as a result, is likely to cause serious harm to self or others or is gravely disabled;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-708__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>allege that resolution of the respondent's acute behavioral health crisis is likely during the admission to the crisis residential center;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-708__subsec_e__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>allege that the respondent has been advised of the need for, but has not accepted, voluntary treatment and request that the court order the respondent to be detained at the crisis residential center for up to seven days following the respondent's arrival at the crisis stabilization center or the crisis residential center, whichever is earlier;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-708__subsec_e__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>list prospective witnesses; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-708__subsec_e__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>list specific facts and describe behavior of the respondent supporting the allegations in (1)  (3) of this subsection.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-708__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If, at a hearing held under (d) of this section, the court reviews a petition for 30-day commitment, the court shall hold the next hearing in accordance with
AS 47.30.735
. If the court grants the petition for 30-day commitment, the respondent may remain at the crisis residential center until admission to a designated treatment facility.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-708__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If, at a hearing held under (d) of this section, the court reviews a petition for seven-day detention at a crisis residential center, the respondent has the rights listed in
AS 47.30.735
(b)(1)  (9). At the conclusion of a hearing on a petition for seven-day detention at a crisis residential center, the court</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-708__subsec_g__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>may order the respondent detained at the crisis residential center for up to seven days following the respondent's arrival at the crisis stabilization center or the crisis residential center, whichever is earlier, if the court finds there is probable cause to believe that
(A) the respondent is suffering an acute behavioral health crisis and, as a result, is likely to cause serious harm to self or others or is gravely disabled; and
(B) the respondent's acute behavioral health crisis will be resolved during admission to the crisis residential center; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-708__subsec_g__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall order the respondent released if the court finds no probable cause.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-709">
            <num>47.30.709</num>
            <heading>Rights of respondents at crisis stabilization centers and crisis residential centers; psychotropic medication; time.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-709__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If, at any time during a respondent's hold at a crisis stabilization center or detention at a crisis residential center, the professional person in charge determines that the respondent does not meet the standard for a hold or detention, the respondent may no longer be held or detained. The professional person in charge shall notify the petitioner and the court, if applicable.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-709__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When a respondent is held at a crisis stabilization center or detained at a crisis residential center, the respondent has the rights identified in
AS 47.30.725
and,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-709__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if an adult, the rights identified under
AS 47.30.817
 47.30.865; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-709__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if a minor, the rights identified in
AS 47.30.700
 47.30.865.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-709__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A respondent subject to an involuntary stabilization hold or detention at a crisis stabilization center or crisis residential center may, at any time, convert to voluntary status if the professional person in charge agrees that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-709__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the respondent is an appropriate patient for voluntary status; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-709__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the conversion is made in good faith.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-709__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A crisis stabilization center or crisis residential center may administer psychotropic medication to an involuntarily held or detained respondent only in a manner that is consistent with
AS 47.30.838
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-709__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Computation of a 23-hour and 59-minute holding time at a crisis stabilization center includes Saturdays, Sundays, and legal holidays, but does not include any period of time necessary to transport a respondent to a crisis stabilization center. Computation of a seven-day detention at a crisis residential center includes Saturdays, Sundays, and legal holidays, but does not include any period of time necessary to transport a respondent to a crisis residential center.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-710">
            <num>47.30.710</num>
            <heading>Examination; hospitalization.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-710__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A respondent who is delivered under
AS 47.30.700
 47.30.706 to an evaluation facility for examination and treatment shall be examined and evaluated as to mental and physical condition by a mental health professional and by a physician within 24 hours after arrival at the facility.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-710__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the mental health professional who performs the emergency examination under (a) of this section has reason to believe that the respondent is mentally ill and that condition causes the respondent to be gravely disabled or to present a likelihood of serious harm to self or others, and the respondent is in need of care or treatment, the mental health professional may</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-710__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>admit the respondent to a crisis residential center;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-710__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>hospitalize the respondent; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-710__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>arrange for hospitalization, on an emergency basis .</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-710__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a mental health professional hospitalizes a respondent or arranges for the hospitalization of a respondent under (b) of this section and a judicial order has not been obtained under
AS 47.30.700
, the mental health professional shall apply for an ex parte order authorizing the hospitalization for evaluation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-710__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a mental health professional readmits a respondent to an evaluation facility after a discharge from a subacute mental health facility, the respondent is not willing to remain at the evaluation facility on a voluntary basis, and a judicial order has not been obtained under
AS 47.30.700
, the mental health professional shall apply for an ex parte order authorizing hospitalization for evaluation. Unless otherwise ordered by the court upon receiving the application for an ex parte order, the respondent shall remain at the evaluation facility until the court issues a decision on the application for an ex parte order.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-715">
            <num>47.30.715</num>
            <heading>Procedure after order.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-715__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After the court grants an ex parte order authorizing hospitalization for evaluation, the department shall immediately transport a person who is detained at a medical or other facility, including a correctional facility, to a crisis residential center or evaluation facility for an evaluation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-715__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person being detained while awaiting transportation to a crisis residential center or evaluation facility may request a court hearing to review the detention at any time. The hearing shall be held not later than 72 hours after the request is filed. When the court rules on a request for review of the detention pending transportation, the court shall consider the factors listed in (d) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-715__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not be detained for more than seven days while awaiting transportation to a crisis residential center or evaluation facility; however, the department or a facility detaining a person under
AS 47.30.700
 47.30.815 may file a request to extend the detention based on the person continuing to meet the standards for commitment under
AS 47.30.700
and the need for a continued hold. The request must be supported by the verified or certified statement of a mental health professional and be served on the respondent, the respondent's attorney, and the division of the Department of Law that has responsibility for civil cases. When the court decides a request to extend the detention pending transportation, the court shall consider the factors identified in (d) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-715__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When ruling on a request to review or extend detention, the court shall consider the totality of the circumstances, including</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-715__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the length of time the person has been detained;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-715__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the reason the person has not yet been transported;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-715__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the person's current medical and psychiatric condition;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-715__subsec_d__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>whether the person is gravely disabled or is likely to cause serious harm to self or others; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-715__subsec_d__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>whether the person is receiving treatment at the person's current placement.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-715__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The court shall schedule a hearing to decide a request for review under (b) of this section or a request to extend detention under (c) of this section. The hearing shall be held not later than 72 hours after the request for review or the request to extend detention, as applicable. If a hearing is held after expiration of the seven-day detention period, the detention shall be extended until the hearing.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-715__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Regardless of whether a request to extend the respondent's detention has been filed, if, at any time in the course of the detention, a mental health professional at the detaining facility determines that the person does not meet the standards for commitment under
AS 47.30.700
, the respondent shall be released and the facility shall notify the petitioner, the respondent's attorney, the division of the Department of Law that has responsibility for civil cases, and the court.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-715__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When an evaluation facility receives a proper order for evaluation, it shall accept the order and the respondent for an evaluation period not to exceed 72 hours. The evaluation facility shall promptly notify the court of the date and time of the respondent's arrival. The court shall set a date, time, and place for a 30-day commitment hearing, to be held if needed within 72 hours after the respondent's arrival, and the court shall notify the evaluation facility, the respondent, the respondent's guardian, if any, the respondent's attorney, the petitioner's attorney, if any, and the attorney general of the time and place of the hearing. Evaluation personnel, when used, shall similarly notify the court of the date and time when they first met with the respondent.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-720">
            <num>47.30.720</num>
            <heading>Release before expiration of 72-hour period.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.720.   Release before expiration of 72-hour period.
If at any time in the course of the 72-hour period the mental health professionals conducting the evaluation determine that the respondent does not meet the standards for commitment specified in
AS 47.30.700
, the respondent shall be discharged from the facility or the place of evaluation by evaluation personnel and the petitioner and the court so notified.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-725">
            <num>47.30.725</num>
            <heading>Rights; notification.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-725__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When a respondent is detained for evaluation under
AS 47.30.660
 47.30.915, the respondent shall be immediately notified orally and in writing of the rights under this section. Notification must be in a language understood by the respondent. The respondent's guardian, if any, and if the respondent requests, an adult designated by the respondent, shall also be notified of the respondent's rights under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-725__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless a respondent is released or voluntarily admitted for treatment within 72 hours of arrival at the facility or, if the respondent is evaluated by evaluation personnel, within 72 hours from the beginning of the respondent's meeting with evaluation personnel, the respondent is entitled to a court hearing to be set for not later than the end of that 72-hour period to determine whether there is cause for detention after the 72 hours have expired for up to an additional 30 days on the grounds that the respondent is mentally ill, and as a result presents a likelihood of serious harm to the respondent or others, or is gravely disabled.  The facility or evaluation personnel shall give notice to the court of the releases and voluntary admissions under
AS 47.30.700
 47.30.815.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-725__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The respondent has a right to communicate immediately, at the department's expense, with the respondent's guardian, if any, or an adult designated by the respondent and the attorney designated in the ex parte order, or an attorney of the respondent's choice.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-725__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The respondent has the right to be represented by an attorney, to present evidence, and to cross-examine witnesses who testify against the respondent at the hearing.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-725__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The respondent has the right to be free of the effects of medication and other forms of treatment to the maximum extent possible before the 30-day commitment hearing; however, the facility or evaluation personnel may treat the respondent with medication under prescription by a licensed physician or by a less restrictive alternative of the respondent's preference if, in the opinion of a licensed physician in the case of medication, or of a mental health professional in the case of alternative treatment, the treatment is necessary to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-725__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>prevent bodily harm to the respondent or others;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-725__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>prevent such deterioration of the respondent's mental condition that subsequent treatment might not enable the respondent to recover; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-725__subsec_e__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>allow the respondent to prepare for and participate in the proceedings.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-725__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A respondent, if represented by counsel, may waive, orally or in writing, the 72-hour time limit on the 30-day commitment hearing and have the hearing set for a date no more than seven calendar days after arrival at the facility.  The respondent's counsel shall immediately notify the court of the waiver.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-725__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a criminal charge of a felony offense against a person under
AS 11.41
or felony arson against a respondent has been dismissed under
AS 12.47.110
and the respondent is detained for evaluation or committed under
AS 47.30.700
 47.30.915,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-725__subsec_g__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Department of Law shall notify a victim in the dismissed criminal case
(A) of the time and place of a hearing under
AS 47.30.700
 47.30.915;
(B) of the length of time for which the respondent is committed and findings of fact made by the court; and
(C) when the respondent is discharged from commitment; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-725__subsec_g__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a victim in the dismissed criminal case may attend a hearing under
AS 47.30.700
 47.30.915, but may not disclose confidential information from the hearing.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-725__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subsection (g) of this section may not be construed to give a victim in a dismissed criminal case the right to access a record that is confidential under
AS 47.30.845
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-727">
            <num>47.30.727</num>
            <heading>Provision of records and notice following a finding of incompetency in a criminal case.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-727__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Within 30 days after a respondent has been found incompetent to proceed under
AS 12.47.110
and committed under
AS 47.30.700
 47.30.915, and every 30 days thereafter until the civil commitment case has concluded, the division of the Department of Law that has responsibility for civil cases shall provide all information and records obtained during the civil commitment to the division of the Department of Law that has responsibility for criminal cases.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-727__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Records disclosed to the division of the Department of Law that has responsibility for criminal cases under (a) of this section are confidential and may not be disclosed to anyone unless disclosure is required by a court order or the respondent provides written consent to the disclosure. If the records are used in the criminal proceeding, the moving party shall file the records as confidential documents.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-727__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A facility housing a respondent found incompetent to proceed under
AS 12.47.110
and committed under
AS 47.30.700
 47.30.915 shall provide notice to the prosecutor in the criminal case of all hearings scheduled by the court in the civil commitment case. The prosecutor, or a staff member of the prosecutor's office, may attend a hearing in the civil commitment case but may not participate in the hearing as a party.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-730">
            <num>47.30.730</num>
            <heading>Petition for 30-day commitment.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-730__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In the course of the 72-hour evaluation period, a petition for commitment to a treatment facility may be filed in court.  The petition must be signed by two mental health professionals who have examined the respondent, one of whom is a physician. The petition must</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-730__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>allege that the respondent is mentally ill and as a result is likely to cause harm to self or others or is gravely disabled;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-730__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>allege that the evaluation staff has considered but has not found that there are any less restrictive alternatives available that would adequately protect the respondent or others; or, if a less restrictive involuntary form of treatment is sought, specify the treatment and the basis for supporting it;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-730__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>allege with respect to a gravely disabled respondent that there is reason to believe that the respondent's mental condition could be improved by the course of treatment sought;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-730__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>allege that a specified treatment facility or less restrictive alternative that is appropriate to the respondent's condition has agreed to accept the respondent;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-730__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>allege that the respondent has been advised of the need for, but has not accepted, voluntary treatment, and request that the court commit the respondent to the specified treatment facility or less restrictive alternative for a period not to exceed 30 days;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-730__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>list the prospective witnesses who will testify in support of commitment or involuntary treatment; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-730__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>list the facts and specific behavior of the respondent supporting the allegation in (1) of this subsection.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-730__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A copy of the petition shall be served on the respondent, the respondent's attorney, and the respondent's guardian, if any, before the 30-day commitment hearing.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-735">
            <num>47.30.735</num>
            <heading>30-day commitment; hearing.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-735__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon receipt of a proper petition for commitment, the court shall hold a hearing at the date and time previously specified according to procedures set out in
AS 47.30.715
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-735__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The hearing shall be conducted in a physical setting least likely to have a harmful effect on the mental or physical health of the respondent, within practical limits. At the hearing, in addition to other rights specified in
AS 47.30.660
 47.30.915, the respondent has the right</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-735__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to be present at the hearing; this right may be waived only with the respondent's informed consent; if the respondent is incapable of giving informed consent, the respondent may be excluded from the hearing only if the court, after hearing, finds that the incapacity exists and that there is a substantial likelihood that the respondent's presence at the hearing would be severely injurious to the respondent's mental or physical health;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-735__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to view and copy all petitions and reports in the court file of the respondent's case;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-735__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to have the hearing open or closed to the public as the respondent elects, except that, if the respondent was charged with a felony offense against a person under
AS 11.41
or felony arson and the criminal case was dismissed under
AS 12.47.110
, an alleged victim in the dismissed criminal case and the prosecutor, or a staff member of the prosecutor's office, may attend the hearing, but may not disclose confidential information from the hearing;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-735__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to have the rules of evidence and civil procedure applied so as to provide for the informal but efficient presentation of evidence;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-735__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to have an interpreter if the respondent does not understand English;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-735__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to present evidence on the respondent's behalf;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-735__subsec_b__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to cross-examine witnesses who testify against the respondent;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-735__subsec_b__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to remain silent;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-735__subsec_b__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to call experts and other witnesses to testify on the respondent's behalf.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-735__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>At the conclusion of the hearing the court may commit the respondent to a treatment facility for not more than 30 days if it finds, by clear and convincing evidence, that the respondent is mentally ill and as a result is likely to cause harm to the respondent or others or is gravely disabled.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-735__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the court finds that there is a viable less restrictive alternative available and that the respondent has been advised of and refused voluntary treatment through the alternative, the court may order the less restrictive alternative treatment for not more than 30 days if the program accepts the respondent.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-735__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The court shall specifically state to the respondent, and give the respondent written notice, that if commitment or other involuntary treatment beyond the 30 days is to be sought, the respondent has the right to a full hearing or jury trial.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-740">
            <num>47.30.740</num>
            <heading>Procedure for 90-day commitment following 30-day commitment.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-740__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>At any time during the respondent's 30-day commitment, the professional person in charge, or that person's professional designee, may file with the court a petition for a 90-day commitment of that respondent.  The petition must include all material required under
AS 47.30.730</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-740__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>except that references to 30 days shall be read as 90 days; and</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-740__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>allege that the respondent has attempted to inflict or has inflicted serious bodily harm upon the respondent or another since the respondent's acceptance for evaluation, or that the respondent was committed initially as a result of conduct in which the respondent attempted or inflicted serious bodily harm upon the respondent or another, or that the respondent continues to be gravely disabled, or that the respondent demonstrates a current intent to carry out plans of serious harm to the respondent or another;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-740__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>allege that the respondent has received appropriate and adequate care and treatment during the respondent's 30-day commitment;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-740__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>be verified by the professional person in charge, or that person's professional designee, during the 30-day commitment.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-740__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The court shall have copies of the petition for 90-day commitment served upon the respondent, the respondent's attorney, and the respondent's guardian, if any.  The petition for 90-day commitment and proofs of service shall be filed with the clerk of the court, and a date for hearing shall be set, by the end of the next judicial day, for not later than five judicial days from the date of filing of the petition. The clerk shall notify the respondent, the respondent's attorney, and the petitioner of the hearing date at least three judicial days in advance of the hearing.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-740__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Findings of fact relating to the respondent's behavior made at a 30-day commitment hearing under
AS 47.30.735
shall be admitted as evidence and may not be rebutted except that newly discovered evidence may be used for the purpose of rebutting the findings.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-745">
            <num>47.30.745</num>
            <heading>90-day commitment hearing rights; continued commitment.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-745__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A respondent subject to a petition for 90-day commitment has, in addition to the rights specified elsewhere in this chapter, or otherwise applicable, the rights enumerated in this section. Written notice of these rights shall be served on the respondent and the respondent's attorney and guardian, if any, and may be served on an adult designated by the respondent at the time the petition for 90-day commitment is served.  An attempt shall be made by oral explanation to ensure that the respondent understands the rights enumerated in the notice. If the respondent does not understand English, the explanation shall be given in a language the respondent understands.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-745__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless the respondent is released or is admitted voluntarily following the filing of a petition and before the hearing, the respondent is entitled to a judicial hearing within five judicial days of the filing of the petition as set out in
AS 47.30.740</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-745__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>to determine if the respondent is mentally ill and as a result is likely to cause harm to self or others, or if the respondent is gravely disabled.  If the respondent is admitted voluntarily following the filing of the petition, the voluntary admission constitutes a waiver of any hearing rights under
AS 47.30.740
or under
AS 47.30.685
.  If at any time during the respondent's voluntary admission under this subsection, the respondent submits to the facility a written request to leave, the professional person in charge may file with the court a petition for a 180-day commitment of the respondent under
AS 47.30.770
.  The 180-day commitment hearing shall be scheduled for a date not later than 90 days after the respondent's voluntary admission.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-745__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The respondent is entitled to a jury trial upon request filed with the court if the request is made at least two judicial days before the hearing.  If the respondent requests a jury trial, the hearing may be continued for no more than 10 calendar days.  The jury shall consist of six persons.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-745__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a jury trial is not requested, the court may still continue the hearing at the respondent's request for no more than 10 calendar days.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-745__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The respondent has a right to retain an independent licensed physician or other mental health professional to examine the respondent and to testify on the respondent's behalf.  Upon request by an indigent respondent, the court shall appoint an independent licensed physician or other mental health professional to examine the respondent and testify on the respondent's behalf.  The court shall consider an indigent respondent's request for a specific physician or mental health professional.  A motion for the appointment may be filed in court at any reasonable time before the hearing and shall be acted upon promptly.  Reasonable fees and expenses for expert examiners shall be determined by the rules of court.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-745__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The proceeding shall in all respects be in accord with constitutional guarantees of due process and, except as otherwise specifically provided in
AS 47.30.700
 47.30.915, the rules of evidence and procedure in civil proceedings.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-745__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Until the court issues a final decision, the respondent shall continue to be treated at the treatment facility unless the petition for 90-day commitment is withdrawn.  If a decision has not been made within 20 days of filing of the petition, not including extensions of time due to jury trial or other requests by the respondent, the respondent shall be released.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-750">
            <num>47.30.750</num>
            <heading>Conduct of hearing.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.750.   Conduct of hearing.
The hearing under
AS 47.30.745
shall be conducted in the same manner, and with the same rights for the respondent, as set out in
AS 47.30.735
(b).</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-755">
            <num>47.30.755</num>
            <heading>Court order.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-755__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After the hearing and within the time limit specified in
AS 47.30.745
, the court may commit the respondent to a treatment facility for no more than 90 days if the court or jury finds by clear and convincing evidence that the respondent is mentally ill and as a result is likely to cause harm to self or others, or is gravely disabled.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-755__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the court finds that there is a less restrictive alternative available and that the respondent has been advised of and refused voluntary treatment through the alternative, the court may order the less restrictive alternative treatment after acceptance by the program of the respondent for a period not to exceed 90 days.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-760">
            <num>47.30.760</num>
            <heading>Placement at closest facility.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.760.   Placement at closest facility.
Treatment shall always be available at a state-operated hospital; however, if space is available and upon acceptance by another treatment facility, a respondent who is committed by the court shall be placed by the department at the designated treatment facility closest to the respondent's home unless the court finds that
(1) another treatment facility in the state has a program more suited to the respondent's condition, and this interest outweighs the desirability of the respondent being closer to home;
(2) another treatment facility in the state is closer to the respondent's friends or relatives who could benefit the respondent through their visits and communications; or
(3) the respondent wants to be further removed from home, and the mental health professionals who sought the respondent's commitment concur in the desirability of removed placement.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-765">
            <num>47.30.765</num>
            <heading>Appeal.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.765.   Appeal.
The respondent has the right to an appeal from an order of involuntary commitment.  The court shall inform the respondent of this right.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-770">
            <num>47.30.770</num>
            <heading>Additional 180-day commitment.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-770__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The respondent shall be released from involuntary treatment at the expiration of 90 days unless the professional person in charge files a petition for a 180-day commitment conforming to the requirements of
AS 47.30.740</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-770__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>except that all references to 30-day commitment shall be read as the previous 90-day commitment and all references to 90-day commitment shall be read as 180-day commitment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-770__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The procedures for service of the petition, notification of rights, and judicial hearing shall be as set out in
AS 47.30.740
 47.30.750.  If the court or jury finds by clear and convincing evidence that the grounds for 90-day commitment as set out in
AS 47.30.755
are present, the court may order the respondent committed for an additional treatment period not to exceed 180 days from the date on which the first 90-day treatment period would have expired.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-770__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Successive 180-day commitments are permissible on the same ground and under the same procedures as the original 180-day commitment.  An order of commitment may not exceed 180 days.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-770__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Findings of fact relating to the respondent's behavior made at a 30-day commitment hearing under
AS 47.30.735
, a 90-day commitment hearing under
AS 47.30.750
, or a previous 180-day commitment hearing under this section shall be admitted as evidence and may not be rebutted except that newly discovered evidence may be used for the purpose of rebutting the findings.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-771">
            <num>47.30.771</num>
            <heading>Additional two-year commitment.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-771__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The respondent shall be released from involuntary treatment at the expiration of 180 days unless the professional person in charge or the attorney general's office files an additional 180-day petition or a petition for a commitment of up to two years conforming to the requirements of
AS 47.30.740</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-771__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>except that all references to 30-day commitment shall be read as the previous 180-day commitment and all references to 90-day commitment shall be read as two-year commitment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-771__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The procedures for service of the petition, notification of rights, and judicial hearing shall be as set out in
AS 47.30.740
 47.30.750. Following a 180-day commitment of a respondent, the court may order the respondent committed for an additional treatment period not to exceed two years from the date on which the 180-day treatment period would have expired if the court or jury finds by clear and convincing evidence that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-771__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the respondent is mentally ill and as a result is likely to cause serious harm to self or others;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-771__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the respondent has a criminal history that includes a felony offense against a person under
AS 11.41
or felony arson, including an offense for which the respondent was found incompetent to stand trial under
AS 12.47.100
and 12.47.110;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-771__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the respondent has been found incompetent to stand trial under
AS 12.47.100
and 12.47.110 for a felony offense against a person under
AS 11.41
or felony arson and that finding of incompetence led directly to the respondent's current period of commitment; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-771__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the period of commitment of the respondent, including a period of commitment for more than 180 days but not more than two years, is necessary to protect the public.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-771__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Findings of fact relating to the respondent's behavior made at a 30-day commitment hearing under
AS 47.30.735
, a 90-day commitment hearing under
AS 47.30.750
, a 180-day commitment hearing under
AS 47.30.770
, or a two-year commitment hearing under this section shall be admitted as evidence and may not be rebutted except that newly discovered evidence may be used for the purpose of rebutting the findings.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-771__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Successive commitments are permissible on the same ground and under the same procedures as the original commitment. An order of commitment may not exceed two years.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-771__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall, by January 30 of each year, submit to the attorney general, public defender, public advocate, Alaska Court System, and the attorney of record for the respondent, if any, a report that details how many respondents are committed under this section and how much time remains on each order of commitment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-772">
            <num>47.30.772</num>
            <heading>Medication and treatment.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.772.   Medication and treatment.
An evaluation facility or designated treatment facility may administer medication or other treatment to an involuntarily committed patient only in a manner that is consistent with the provisions of
AS 47.30.817
 47.30.865.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-775">
            <num>47.30.775</num>
            <heading>Commitment of minors.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.775.   Commitment of minors.
The provisions of
AS 47.30.700
 47.30.815 apply to minors. However, all notices required to be served on the respondent in
AS 47.30.700
 47.30.815 shall also be served on the parent or guardian of a respondent who is a minor, and parents or guardians of a minor respondent shall be notified that they may appear as parties in any commitment proceeding concerning the minor and that as parties they are entitled to retain their own attorney or have the office of public advocacy appointed for them by the court.  A minor respondent has the same rights to waiver and informed consent as an adult respondent under
AS 47.30.660
 47.30.915; however, the minor shall be represented by counsel in waiver and consent proceedings.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-780">
            <num>47.30.780</num>
            <heading>Early discharge.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-780__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (b) and (c) of this section, the professional person in charge shall at any time discharge a respondent on the ground that the respondent is no longer gravely disabled or likely to cause serious harm as a result of mental illness. A certificate to this effect shall be sent to the court, which shall enter an order officially terminating the involuntary commitment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-780__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The professional person in charge shall give the prosecuting authority 10 days' notice before discharging a respondent who was committed after having been found incompetent to proceed under
AS 12.47.110
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-780__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a respondent committed under
AS 47.30.770
or 47.30.771 has a criminal history that includes a felony offense against a person under
AS 11.41
or felony arson, including an offense for which the respondent was found incompetent to stand trial under
AS 12.47.100
and 12.47.110, the professional person in charge may not discharge the respondent under (a) of this section unless the court enters an order officially terminating the involuntary commitment. The court shall give the prosecuting authority 10 days' notice before the professional person in charge may discharge a respondent under this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-780__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (e) of this section, a respondent committed under
AS 47.30.771
may petition the court for early discharge at any time during the commitment if the respondent presents some evidence demonstrating that the respondent is no longer likely to cause serious harm to self or others. The court shall grant early discharge unless the state proves by clear and convincing evidence that the respondent remains likely to cause serious harm to self or others.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-780__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A respondent may not file a petition for early discharge within 180 days after the date the court enters an initial commitment order or a final order ruling on a previous petition for early discharge.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-785">
            <num>47.30.785</num>
            <heading>Authorized absences.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.785.   Authorized absences.
A respondent undergoing involuntary treatment on an inpatient basis under
AS 47.30.700
 47.30.815 may be authorized to be absent from the treatment facility during times specified by the professional person in charge, or that person's professional designee, when an authorization to be absent is in the best interests of the respondent and the respondent is not likely to cause harm to self or others.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-790">
            <num>47.30.790</num>
            <heading>Unauthorized absences: return to facility; required notice.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.790.   Unauthorized absences: return to facility; required notice.
When a respondent undergoing involuntary treatment on an inpatient basis is absent from the treatment facility without, or in excess of, authorization under
AS 47.30.785
, the professional person in charge, or that person's professional designee, may contact the appropriate peace officers who shall take the respondent into custody and return the respondent to the treatment facility.  If it is determined by the professional person in charge to be necessary, a member of the treatment facility staff shall accompany the peace officers when they take the respondent into custody.  In addition, the family or guardian of the patient and any person known to have been threatened by the patient shall be notified of the patient's unauthorized absence immediately upon its discovery.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-795">
            <num>47.30.795</num>
            <heading>Involuntary outpatient care for committed persons.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-795__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A respondent who was originally committed to involuntary inpatient care under
AS 47.30.700
 47.30.915 may be released before the expiration of the commitment period if a provider of outpatient care accepts the respondent for specified outpatient treatment for a period of time not to exceed the duration of the commitment, and if the professional person in charge, or that person's professional designee, finds that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-795__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>it is not necessary to treat the respondent as an inpatient to prevent the respondent from harming self or others; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-795__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>there is reason to believe that the respondent's mental condition would improve as a result of the outpatient treatment.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-795__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A copy of the conditions for early release shall be given to the respondent and the respondent's attorney and guardian, if any, the provider of outpatient care, and the court.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-795__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If during the commitment period the provider of outpatient care determines that the respondent can no longer be treated on an outpatient basis because the respondent is likely to cause harm to self or others or is gravely disabled, the provider shall give the respondent oral and written notice that the respondent must return to the treatment facility within 24 hours, with copies to the respondent's attorney and guardian, if any, the court, and the inpatient treatment facility.  If the respondent fails to arrive at the treatment facility within 24 hours after receiving the notice, the professional person in charge may contact the appropriate peace officers who shall take the respondent into custody and transport the respondent to the facility.  If it is determined by the professional person in charge to be necessary, a member of the treatment facility staff shall accompany the peace officers when they take the respondent into custody.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-795__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the provider of outpatient care determines that the respondent will require continued outpatient care after the expiration of the commitment period, the provider may initiate further commitment proceedings as if the provider were the professional person in charge, and the provisions of
AS 47.30.660
 47.30.915 apply, except that provisions relating to inpatient treatment shall be read as applicable to outpatient treatment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-800">
            <num>47.30.800</num>
            <heading>Conversion of involuntary outpatient treatment to inpatient commitment.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-800__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A respondent ordered by the court under the provisions of
AS 47.30.700
 47.30.915 to receive involuntary outpatient treatment may be required to undergo inpatient treatment when the provider of outpatient care finds that (1) the respondent is mentally ill and is likely to cause serious harm to self or others or is still gravely disabled; (2) the respondent's behavior since the hearing resulting in court-ordered treatment indicates that the respondent now needs inpatient treatment to protect self or others; (3) there is reason to believe that the respondent's mental condition will improve as a result of inpatient treatment; and (4) there is an inpatient facility appropriate to the respondent's need that will accept the respondent as a patient.  Treatment for these respondents shall be available at state-operated hospitals at all times.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-800__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon making the findings specified in (a) of this section, the provisions of
AS 47.30.795</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-800__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>relating to notice and
AS 47.30.745
relating to hearings apply.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-803">
            <num>47.30.803</num>
            <heading>Conversion from involuntary to voluntary status.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.803.   Conversion from involuntary to voluntary status.
A patient subject to involuntary hospitalization under
AS 47.30.705
, 47.30.735, or
AS 47.30.755
may at any time convert to voluntary status if the responsible physician agrees that
(1) the patient is an appropriate patient for voluntary hospitalization; and
(2) the conversion is made in good faith.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-805">
            <num>47.30.805</num>
            <heading>Computation, extension, and expiration of periods of time.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-805__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (b) of this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-805__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>computations of a 72-hour period under
AS 47.30.706
, 47.30.708, or 47.30.715 or a 48-hour period under
AS 47.30.685
do not include Saturdays, Sundays, legal holidays, or any period of time necessary to transport the respondent to the treatment facility, except that if the exclusion of Saturdays, Sundays, and legal holidays from the computation of a 72-hour evaluation period or 48-hour detention period would result in the respondent being held for longer than 72 hours or 48 hours, as applicable, the period ends at 5:00 p.m. on the next day that is not a Saturday, Sunday, or legal holiday;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-805__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a seven-day detention at a crisis residential center expires at the end of the seventh day following the respondent's arrival at the crisis stabilization center or the crisis residential center, whichever is earlier;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-805__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a 30-day commitment period expires at the end of the 30th day after the 72 hours following initial acceptance;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-805__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a 90-day commitment period expires at the end of the 90th day after the expiration of a 30-day period of treatment;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-805__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a 180-day commitment period expires at the end of the 180th day, after the expiration of a 90-day period of treatment or previous 180-day period, whichever is applicable;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-805__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a two-year commitment period expires not later than two years after the expiration of a 180-day period of treatment.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-805__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When a respondent has failed to appear or been absent through the respondent's own actions contrary to any order properly made or entered under
AS 47.30.660
 47.30.915, the relevant commitment period shall be extended for a period of time equal to the respondent's absence if written notice of absence is promptly provided to the respondent's attorney and guardian, if any, and if, within 24 hours after the respondent has returned to the evaluation or treatment facility, written notice of the corresponding extension and the reason for it is given to the respondent and the respondent's attorney and guardian, if any, and to the court.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-810">
            <num>47.30.810</num>
            <heading>Habeas corpus not limited.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.810.   Habeas corpus not limited.
Nothing in
AS 47.30.660
 47.30.915 may be construed as limiting a person's right to a writ of habeas corpus.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-815">
            <num>47.30.815</num>
            <heading>Limitation of liability; bad faith application a felony.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-815__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person acting in good faith upon either actual knowledge or reliable information who makes application for evaluation or treatment of another person under
AS 47.30.700
 47.30.915 is not subject to civil or criminal liability.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-815__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The following persons may not be held civilly or criminally liable for detaining a person under
AS 47.30.700
 47.30.915 or for releasing a person under
AS 47.30.700
 47.30.915 at or before the end of the period for which the person was admitted or committed for evaluation or treatment if the persons have performed their duties in good faith and without gross negligence:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-815__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an officer of a public or private agency;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-815__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the superintendent, the professional person in charge, the professional designee of the professional person in charge, and the attending staff of a public or private agency;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-815__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a public official performing functions necessary to the administration of
AS 47.30.700
 47.30.915;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-815__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a peace officer or mental health professional responsible for detaining or transporting a person under
AS 47.30.700
 47.30.915.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-815__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who wilfully initiates an involuntary commitment procedure under
AS 47.30.700
without having good cause to believe that the other person is suffering from a mental illness and as a result is gravely disabled or likely to cause serious harm to self or others, is guilty of a felony.
Article 8. Patient Rights.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-817">
            <num>47.30.817</num>
            <heading>Advance health care directives.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.817.   Advance health care directives.
A health care provider or a health care institution may not require or prohibit the execution or revocation of an advance health care directive as a condition for admission, discharge, or providing health care. In this section, advance health care directive, health care institution, and health care provider have the meanings given in
AS 13.52.390
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-825">
            <num>47.30.825</num>
            <heading>Patient medical rights.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-825__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A patient who is receiving services under
AS 47.30.660
 47.30.915 has the rights described in this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-825__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The patient and the following persons, at the request of the patient, are entitled to participate in formulating the patient's individualized treatment plan and to participate in the evaluation process as much as possible, at minimum to the extent of requesting specific forms of therapy, inquiring why specific therapies are or are not included in the treatment program, and being informed as to the patient's present medical and psychological condition and prognosis: (1) the patient's counsel, (2) the patient's guardian, (3) a mental health professional previously engaged in the patient's care outside of the evaluation facility or designated treatment facility, (4) a representative of the patient's choice, (5) a person designated as the patient's agent or surrogate with regard to mental health treatment decisions under
AS 13.52
, and (6) the adult designated under
AS 47.30.725
. The mental health care professionals may not withhold any of the information described in this subsection from the patient or from others if the patient has signed a waiver of confidentiality or has designated the person who would receive the information as an agent or surrogate under
AS 13.52
with regard to mental health treatment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-825__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A patient who is capable of giving informed consent has the right to give and withhold consent to medication and treatment in all situations that do not involve a crisis or impending crisis as described in
AS 47.30.838
(a)(1). A facility shall follow the procedures required under
AS 47.30.836
 47.30.839 before administering psychotropic medication.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-825__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A locked quiet room, or other form of physical restraint, may not be used, except as provided in this subsection, unless a patient is likely to physically harm self or others unless restrained. The form of restraint used shall be that which is in the patient's best interest and which constitutes the least restrictive alternative available. When practicable, the patient shall be consulted as to the patient's preference among forms of adequate, medically advisable restraints including medication, and that preference shall be honored. Nothing in this section is intended to limit the right of staff to use a quiet room at the patient's request or with the patient's knowing concurrence when considered in the best interests of the patient. Patients placed in a quiet room or other physical restraint shall be checked at least every 15 minutes or more often if good medical practice so indicates. Patients in a quiet room must be visited by a staff member at least once every hour and must be given adequate food and drink and access to bathroom facilities. At no time may a patient be kept in a quiet room or other form of physical restraint against the patient's will longer than necessary to accomplish the purposes set out in this subsection. All uses of a quiet room or other restraint shall be recorded in the patient's medical record, the information including but not limited to the reasons for its use, the duration of use, and the name of the authorizing staff member.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-825__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 12 ch 109 SLA 1992.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-825__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A patient capable of giving informed consent has the absolute right to accept or refuse electroconvulsive therapy or aversive conditioning. A patient who lacks substantial capacity to make this decision may not be given this therapy or conditioning without a court order unless the patient expressly authorized that particular form of treatment in an advance health care directive properly executed under
AS 13.52
or has authorized an agent or surrogate under
AS 13.52
to make this decision and the agent or surrogate consents to the treatment on behalf of the patient.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-825__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In no event may treatment include psychosurgery, lobotomy, or other comparable form of treatment without specific informed consent of the patient, including a minor unless the minor is clearly too young or disabled to give an informed consent in which case the consent of the minor's legal guardian is required.  In addition, this treatment may not be given without a court order after hearing compatible with full due process.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-825__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When, in the written opinion of a patient's attending physician, a true medical emergency exists and a surgical operation is necessary to save the life, physical health, eyesight, hearing, or member of the patient, the professional person in charge, or that person's professional designee, may give consent to the surgical operation if time will not permit obtaining the consent of the proper relatives or guardian or appropriate judicial authority.  However, an operation may not be authorized if the patient is not a minor and knowingly withholds consent on religious grounds.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-825__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A patient upon discharge shall be given a discharge plan specifying the kinds and amount of care and treatment the patient should have after discharge and such other steps as the patient might take to benefit the patient's mental health after leaving the facility.  The patient shall have the right to participate, as far as practicable, in formulating the patient's discharge plan.  A copy of the plan shall be given to the patient, the patient's guardian, an adult designated in accordance with
AS 47.30.725
, the court if appropriate, and any follow-up agencies.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-830">
            <num>47.30.830</num>
            <heading>Prohibition of experimental treatments.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-830__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Experimental treatments involving any significant risk of physical or psychological harm may not be administered to a patient.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-830__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the personnel of an evaluation or treatment facility are uncertain as to whether a proposed treatment is experimental or is experimental as applied to a particular patient or would involve a significant risk of mental or physical harm to the patient, the matter may be referred to the commissioner for a determination.  The patient, the patient's attorney and guardian, if any, and an adult designated by the patient, shall, simultaneously with the referral to the commissioner, be provided with copies of all the documents by which the referral is made and shall have the opportunity to provide evidence to the commissioner on the question.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-830__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A determination by the commissioner that a treatment is experimental and entails significant risks of mental or physical harm is binding upon all persons involved in the administration of treatment to a patient.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-833">
            <num>47.30.833</num>
            <heading>Nutritional evaluation; right to proper diet.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-833__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A treatment facility shall conduct a nutritional evaluation of a person admitted or committed to a treatment facility for evaluation or treatment, whether the person is a voluntary or involuntary patient.  The evaluation shall be conducted within the first week after the patient is admitted or committed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-833__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (a) of this section, a treatment facility is not required to conduct a nutritional evaluation of a patient who is released within 72 hours of arrival.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-833__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A patient has the right to a nutritionally sound and medically appropriate diet.  After conducting the nutritional evaluation required under (a) of this section, the treatment facility shall take appropriate steps to correct the patient's nutritional deficiencies.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-835">
            <num>47.30.835</num>
            <heading>Civil rights not impaired.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-835__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not deny to a person who is undergoing evaluation or treatment under
AS 47.30.660
 47.30.915 a civil right, including but not limited to, the right to free exercise of religion and the right to dispose of property, sue and be sued, enter into contractual relationships, and vote.  A person who violates this subsection commits the crime of interference with constitutional rights under
AS 11.76.110
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-835__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Court-ordered evaluation or treatment under
AS 47.30.660
 47.30.915 is not a determination of legal incapacity under
AS 13.26.005
 13.26.580.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-836">
            <num>47.30.836</num>
            <heading>Psychotropic medication in non-crisis situation.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-836__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An evaluation facility or designated treatment facility may not administer psychotropic medication to a patient in a situation that does not involve a crisis under
AS 47.30.838
(a)(1) unless the patient</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-836__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has the capacity to give informed consent to the medication, as described in
AS 47.30.837
, and gives that consent; the facility shall document the consent in the patient's medical chart;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-836__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>authorized the use of psychotropic medication in an advance health care directive properly executed under
AS 13.52
or authorized an agent or surrogate under
AS 13.52
to consent to the use of psychotropic medication for the patient and the agent or surrogate does consent; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-836__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is determined by a court to lack the capacity to give informed consent to the medication and the court approves use of the medication under
AS 47.30.839
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-836__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before administering psychotropic medication to a minor patient under this section, a mental health professional shall consult with a parent or guardian of the minor, evaluate the minor for drug withdrawal and medical psychosis caused by currently prescribed drugs or self-medication, and review all available information regarding the minor's family history, diet, medications, and other contributing factors.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-837">
            <num>47.30.837</num>
            <heading>Informed consent.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-837__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A patient has the capacity to give informed consent for purposes of
AS 47.30.836
if the patient is competent to make mental health or medical treatment decisions and the consent is voluntary and informed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-837__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When seeking a patient's informed consent under this section, the evaluation facility or designated treatment facility shall give the patient information that is necessary for informed consent in a manner that ensures maximum possible comprehension by the patient.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-837__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If an evaluation facility or designated treatment facility has provided to the patient the information necessary for the patient's consent to be informed and the patient voluntarily consents, the facility may administer psychotropic medication to the patient unless the facility has reason to believe that the patient is not competent to make medical or mental health treatment decisions. If the facility has reason to believe that the patient is not competent to make medical or mental health treatment decisions and the facility wishes to administer psychotropic medication to the patient, the facility shall follow the procedures of
AS 47.30.839
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-837__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-837__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>competent means that the patient
(A) has the capacity to assimilate relevant facts and to appreciate and understand the patient's situation with regard to those facts, including the information described in (2) of this subsection;
(B) appreciates that the patient has a mental disorder or impairment, if the evidence so indicates; denial of a significantly disabling disorder or impairment, when faced with substantial evidence of its existence, constitutes evidence that the patient lacks the capability to make mental health treatment decisions;
(C) has the capacity to participate in treatment decisions by means of a rational thought process; and
(D) is able to articulate reasonable objections to using the offered medication;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-837__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>informed means that the evaluation facility or designated treatment facility has given the patient all information that is material to the patient's decision to give or withhold consent, including
(A) an explanation of the patient's diagnosis and prognosis, or their predominant symptoms, with and without the medication;
(B) information about the proposed medication, its purpose, the method of its administration, the recommended ranges of dosages, possible side effects and benefits, ways to treat side effects, and risks of other conditions, such as tardive dyskinesia;
(C) a review of the patient's history, including medication history and previous side effects from medication;
(D) an explanation of interactions with other drugs, including over-the-counter drugs, street drugs, and alcohol;
(E) information about alternative treatments and their risks, side effects, and benefits, including the risks of nontreatment; and
(F) a statement describing the patient's right to give or withhold consent to the administration of psychotropic medications in nonemergency situations, the procedure for withdrawing consent, and notification that a court may override the patient's refusal;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-837__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>voluntary means having genuine freedom of choice; a choice may be encouraged and remain voluntary, but consent obtained by using force, threats, or direct or indirect coercion is not voluntary.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-838">
            <num>47.30.838</num>
            <heading>Psychotropic medication in crisis situations.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-838__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (c) and (d) of this section, an evaluation facility or designated treatment facility may administer psychotropic medication to a patient without the patient's informed consent, regardless of whether the patient is capable of giving informed consent, only if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-838__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>there is a crisis situation, or an impending crisis situation, that requires immediate use of the medication to preserve the life of, or prevent significant physical harm to, the patient or another person, as determined by a physician, physician assistant, or advanced practice registered nurse; the behavior or condition of the patient giving rise to a crisis under this paragraph and the staff's response to the behavior or condition must be documented in the patient's medical record; the documentation must include an explanation of alternative responses to the crisis that were considered or attempted by the staff and why those responses were not sufficient; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-838__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the medication is ordered by a physician, physician assistant, or advanced practice registered nurse; the order
(A) may be written or oral and may be received by telephone, facsimile machine, or in person;
(B) may include an initial dosage and may authorize additional, as needed, doses; if additional, as needed, doses are authorized, the order must specify the medication, the quantity of each authorized dose, the method of administering the medication, the maximum frequency of administration, the specific conditions under which the medication may be given, and the maximum amount of medication that may be administered to the patient in a 24-hour period;
(C) is valid for only 24 hours and may be renewed by a physician, physician assistant, or advanced practice registered nurse for a total of 72 hours, including the initial 24 hours, only after a personal assessment of the patient's status and a determination that there is still a crisis situation as described in (1) of this subsection; upon renewal of an order under this subparagraph, the facts supporting the renewal shall be written into the patient's medical record.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-838__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When a patient is no longer in the crisis situation that led to the use of psychotropic medication without consent under (a) of this section, an appropriate health care professional shall discuss the crisis with the patient, including precursors to the crisis, in order to increase the patient's and the professional's understanding of the episode and to discuss prevention of future crises. The professional shall seek and consider the patient's recommendations for managing potential future crises.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-838__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If crisis situations as described in (a)(1) of this section occur repeatedly, or if it appears that they may occur repeatedly, the evaluation facility, crisis stabilization center, crisis residential center, or designated treatment facility may administer psychotropic medication during not more than three crisis periods without the patient's informed consent only with court approval under
AS 47.30.839
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-838__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An evaluation facility or designated treatment facility may administer psychotropic medication to a patient without the patient's informed consent if the patient is unable to give informed consent but has authorized the use of psychotropic medication in an advance health care directive properly executed under
AS 13.52
or has authorized an agent or surrogate under
AS 13.52
to consent to this form of treatment for the patient and the agent or surrogate does consent.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-838__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before determining whether a minor patient should be given psychotropic medication under this section, a mental health professional shall, to the extent time and the nature of the crisis permit, consult with a parent or guardian of the minor, evaluate the minor for drug withdrawal and medical psychosis caused by currently prescribed drugs or self-medication, and review all available information regarding the minor's family history, diet, medications, and other possibly relevant factors.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-839">
            <num>47.30.839</num>
            <heading>Court-ordered administration of medication.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-839__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An evaluation facility or designated treatment facility may use the procedures described in this section to obtain court approval of administration of psychotropic medication if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-839__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>there have been, or it appears that there will be, repeated crisis situations as described in
AS 47.30.838</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-839__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the facility wishes to use psychotropic medication in a noncrisis situation and has reason to believe the patient is incapable of giving informed consent.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-839__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An evaluation facility or designated treatment facility may seek court approval for administration of psychotropic medication to a patient by filing a petition with the court, requesting a hearing on the capacity of the person to give informed consent and on the proposed use of psychotropic medication. The petition shall provide specific information regarding the factors listed in
AS 47.30.837
(d)(2)(A) - (E)..</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-839__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A patient who is the subject of a petition under (b) of this section is entitled to an attorney to represent the patient at the hearing. If the patient cannot afford an attorney, the court shall direct the Public Defender Agency to provide an attorney. The court may, upon request of the patient's attorney, direct the office of public advocacy to provide a guardian ad litem for the patient.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-839__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon the filing of a petition under (b) of this section, the court shall appoint a visitor to assist the court in investigating the issue of whether the patient has the capacity to give or withhold informed consent to the administration of psychotropic medication. The visitor shall gather pertinent information and present it to the court in written or oral form at the hearing. The information must include documentation of the following:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-839__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the patient's responses to a capacity assessment instrument administered at the request of the visitor;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-839__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>any expressed wishes of the patient regarding medication, including wishes that may have been expressed in a power of attorney, a living will, an advance health care directive under
AS 13.52
, or oral statements of the patient, including conversations with relatives and friends that are significant persons in the patient's life as those conversations are remembered by the relatives and friends; oral statements of the patient should be accompanied by a description of the circumstances under which the patient made the statements, when possible.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-839__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Within 72 hours after the filing of a petition under (b) of this section, the court shall hold a hearing to determine the patient's capacity to give or withhold informed consent as described in
AS 47.30.837
and the patient's capacity to give or withhold informed consent at the time of previously expressed wishes regarding medication if previously expressed wishes are documented under (d)(2) of this section. The court shall consider all evidence presented at the hearing, including evidence presented by the guardian ad litem, the petitioner, the visitor, and the patient. The patient's attorney may cross-examine any witness, including the guardian ad litem and the visitor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-839__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the court determines that the patient is competent to provide informed consent, the court shall order the facility to honor the patient's decision about the use of psychotropic medication.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-839__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the court determines by clear and convincing evidence that the patient is not competent to provide informed consent and was not competent to provide informed consent at the time of previously expressed wishes documented under (d)(2) of this section, that the proposed use of medication is in the best interests of the patient considering at a minimum the factors listed in
AS 47.30.837
(d)(2)(A)  (E), and that there is no feasible less intrusive alternative, the court shall approve the facility's proposed use of psychotropic medication. The court's approval under this subsection applies to the patient's initial period of commitment if the decision is made during that time period. If the decision is made during a period for which the initial commitment has been extended, the court's approval under this subsection applies to the period for which commitment is extended.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-839__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If an evaluation facility or designated treatment facility wishes to continue the use of psychotropic medication without the patient's consent during a period of commitment that occurs after the period in which the court's approval was obtained, the facility shall file a request to continue the medication when it files the petition to continue the patient's commitment. The court that determines whether commitment shall continue shall also determine whether the patient continues to lack the capacity to give or withhold informed consent by following the procedures described in (b)  (e) of this section. The reports prepared for a previous hearing under (e) of this section are admissible in the hearing held for purposes of this subsection, except that they must be updated by the visitor and the guardian ad litem.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-839__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a patient for whom a court has approved medication under this section regains competency at any time during the period of the patient's commitment and gives informed consent to the continuation of medication, the evaluation facility or designated treatment facility shall document the patient's consent in the patient's file in writing.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-839__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Alaska Court System shall provide visitors in proceedings under this section. The Alaska Court System may contract for services of court-appointed visitors.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-840">
            <num>47.30.840</num>
            <heading>Right to privacy and personal possessions; other rights.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-840__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person undergoing evaluation or treatment under
AS 47.30.660
 47.30.915</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-840__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>may not be photographed without the person's consent and that of the person's guardian if a minor, except that the person may be photographed upon admission to a facility for identification and for administrative purposes of the facility; all photographs shall be confidential and may only be released by the facility to the patient or the patient's designee unless a court orders otherwise;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-840__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>at the time of admission to an evaluation or treatment facility, shall have reasonable precautions taken by the staff to inventory and safeguard the patient's personal property; a copy of the inventory signed by the staff member making it shall be given to the patient and made available to the patient's attorney and any other person authorized by the patient to inspect the document;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-840__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall have access to an individual storage space for the patient's private use while undergoing evaluation or treatment;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-840__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall be permitted to wear personal clothing, to keep and use personal possessions including toilet articles if they are not considered unsafe for the patient or other patients who might have access to them, and to keep and be allowed to spend a reasonable sum of the patient's own money for the patient's needs and comfort;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-840__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall be allowed to have visitors at reasonable times;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-840__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall have ready access to letter writing materials, including stamps, and have the right to send and receive unopened mail;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-840__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall have reasonable access to a telephone, both to make and receive confidential calls;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-840__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has the right to be free of corporal punishment;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-840__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has the right to reasonable opportunity for indoor and outdoor exercise and recreation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-840__subsec_a__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has the right, at any time, to have a telephone conversation with or be visited by an attorney;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-840__subsec_a__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>may not be retaliated against or subjected to any adverse change of conditions or treatment solely because of assertion of rights under this section;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-840__subsec_a__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>who is a minor or an adult for whom a guardian has been appointed may not be transferred from a crisis stabilization center, evaluation facility, or treatment facility to a different crisis stabilization center, evaluation facility, or treatment facility before the center or facility makes a good faith attempt to notify the parent or guardian of the person, as applicable, of the proposed transfer.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-840__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The patient's rights under (a)(4), (5), (7) and (9) of this section may be suspended temporarily, following the initial evaluation period, if the professional person in charge of the patient determines that granting the patient those rights will pose a threat to the safety or well-being of the patient or others.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-845">
            <num>47.30.845</num>
            <heading>Confidential records.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.845.   Confidential records.
Information and records obtained in the course of a screening investigation, evaluation, examination, or treatment are confidential and are not public records, except as the requirements of a hearing under
AS 47.30.660
 47.30.915 may necessitate a different procedure. Information and records may be copied and disclosed under regulations established by the department only to
(1) a physician or a provider of health, mental health, or social and welfare services involved in caring for, treating, or rehabilitating the patient;
(2) the patient or an individual to whom the patient has given written consent to have information disclosed;
(3) a person authorized by a court order;
(4) a person doing research or maintaining health statistics if the anonymity of the patient is assured and the facility recognizes the project as a bona fide research or statistical undertaking;
(5) the Department of Corrections in a case in which a prisoner confined to the state prison is a patient in the state hospital on authorized transfer either by voluntary admission or by court order;
(6) a governmental or law enforcement agency when necessary to secure the return of a patient who is on unauthorized absence from a facility where the patient was undergoing evaluation or treatment;
(7) a law enforcement agency when there is substantiated concern over imminent danger to the community by a presumed mentally ill person;
(8) the department in a case in which services provided under
AS 47.30.660
 47.30.915 are paid for, in whole or in part, by the department or in which a person has applied for or has received assistance from the department for those services;
(9) the Department of Public Safety as provided in
AS 47.30.907
;
information provided under this paragraph may not include diagnostic or clinical information regarding a patient;
(10)  the Department of Law as provided in
AS 47.30.727
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-847">
            <num>47.30.847</num>
            <heading>Patients' grievance procedures.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-847__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A patient has the right to bring grievances about the patient's treatment, care, or rights to an impartial body within an evaluation facility or designated treatment facility.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-847__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An evaluation facility and a designated treatment facility shall have a formal grievance procedure for patient grievances brought under (a) of this section. The facility shall inform each patient of the existence and contents of the grievance procedure.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-847__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An evaluation facility and a designated treatment facility shall have a designated staff member who is trained in mental health consumer advocacy who will serve as an advocate, upon a patient's request, to assist the patient in bringing grievances or pursuing other redress for complaints concerning care, treatment, and rights.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-850">
            <num>47.30.850</num>
            <heading>Sealing records.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.850.   Sealing records.
Following the discharge of a person from a treatment facility or the issuance of a court order denying a petition for commitment, the person may at any time move to have all court records pertaining to the proceedings sealed on condition that the person file a full release of all claims of whatever nature arising out of the proceedings and the statements and actions of persons and facilities in connection with the proceedings. Upon the filing of the motion and full release, the court shall order the court records sealed.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-851">
            <num>47.30.851</num>
            <heading>Relief from legal disability.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-851__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who is prohibited from possessing a firearm or ammunition under 18 U.S.C. 922(g)(4) as a result of an involuntary commitment or an adjudication of mental illness or mental incompetence that occurred in this state may, at any time, move to be relieved from the disability resulting from an involuntary commitment or an adjudication of mental illness or mental incompetence.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-851__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In ruling on a motion under (a) of this section, the court</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-851__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall consider
(A) the circumstances of the involuntary commitment or adjudication of mental illness or mental incompetence;
(B) the time that has elapsed since the involuntary commitment or adjudication of mental illness or mental incompetence;
(C) the person's reputation and mental health and criminal history records;
(D) any conduct by the person that would constitute a crime against a person under
AS 11.41
or a violation of
AS 11.61.190
 11.61.250; and
(E) any changes in the person's condition or circumstances relevant to the relief sought; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-851__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall grant relief from the disability resulting from an involuntary commitment or adjudication of mental illness or mental incompetence if the court finds, by a preponderance of the evidence, that
(A) the person is unlikely to act in a manner dangerous to self or to public safety; and
(B) granting the relief is not contrary to the public interest.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-851__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The court shall order a hearing conducted under (b) of this section to be held open or closed to the public at the option of the person.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-851__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A decision to grant or deny relief under this section may be appealed as provided in
AS 22.05.010
. In reviewing the decision of the superior court, the standard of review may be de novo.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-855">
            <num>47.30.855</num>
            <heading>Posting of rights.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.855.   Posting of rights.
The rights set out in
AS 47.30.817
 47.30.855 shall be prominently posted in all treatment facilities in places accessible to all patients. A patient who does not understand English shall have the patient rights explained in a language the patient understands.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-860">
            <num>47.30.860</num>
            <heading>Documents and notices in other languages.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.860.   Documents and notices in other languages.
When practicable, all documents and notices required by
AS 47.30.660
 47.30.915 to be served on a respondent, or on the respondent's parents, guardian or adult designee, shall be explained in a language the person understands if the respondent is not competent in English.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-865">
            <num>47.30.865</num>
            <heading>Discrimination prohibited.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-865__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The fact that a person is or has been evaluated or treated for mental illness may not be a basis for discrimination in</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-865__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>seeking employment;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-865__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>resuming or continuing professional practice or previous occupation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-865__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>obtaining or retaining housing;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-865__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>obtaining or retaining licenses or permits, including but not limited to a motor vehicle license, motor vehicle operator's and chauffeur's license, and a professional or occupational license.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-865__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Applications for positions, licenses, and housing may not contain requests for information concerning evaluation or treatment experiences.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-865__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not aid, abet, incite, compel, or coerce the doing of an act forbidden under this section or attempt to do so.
Article 9. Miscellaneous Provisions.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-870">
            <num>47.30.870</num>
            <heading>Transportation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.870.   Transportation.
When a person is to be involuntarily committed to a facility, the department shall arrange, and is authorized to pay for, the person's necessary transportation to the designated facility accompanied by appropriate persons and, if necessary, by a peace officer.  The department shall pay return transportation of a person, the person's escorts, and, if necessary, a peace officer, after a determination that the person is not committable, at the end of a commitment period, or at the end of a voluntary stay at a treatment facility following an evaluation conducted in accordance with
AS 47.30.715
.  When advisable, one or more relatives or friends shall be permitted to accompany the person. The department may pay necessary travel, housing, and meal expenses incurred by one relative or friend in accompanying the person if the department determines that the person's best interests require that the person be accompanied by the relative or friend and the relative or friend is indigent.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-875">
            <num>47.30.875</num>
            <heading>Residence; nonresident patients; interstate agreements.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-875__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The admission papers of a person who is admitted to a treatment facility under
AS 47.30.660
 47.30.915 must include a statement as to the person's residence.  The department may return a patient who is not a resident of the state to the state of the person's residence with court approval if the person has been committed. If the state in which the person has residence does not accept the person as a patient, the person shall be treated as a resident of this state under the provisions of
AS 47.30.660
 47.30.915.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-875__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To facilitate the return of nonresident patients the department may enter into a reciprocal agreement or compact with another state providing for the prompt return under appropriate supervision of residents of that state who are mentally ill.  A mentally ill resident of this state who has been placed in a facility outside this state may be admitted with the approval of the department to a treatment facility in the state designated by the department.  The department may enter into reciprocal agreements or contracts with another state providing for custody, care or treatment, or return of mentally ill residents of this state by the other state and for the custody and care or treatment of mentally ill residents of that state by this state on a reimbursable basis.  A resident of this state who has been committed in another state and is returned in accordance with this section shall, within 72 hours of admission to the designated facility, be examined. After examination the mental health professional in charge shall release the person or shall petition for involuntary commitment as prescribed in
AS 47.30.740
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-875__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In taking action under (a) and (b) of this section, consideration shall be given to the best interests of the patient, particularly to the relationship of the patient to the patient's family, legal guardian, or friends to maintain relationships and encourage visits beneficial to the patient.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-880">
            <num>47.30.880</num>
            <heading>Interstate Compact on Mental Health ratified.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.880.   Interstate Compact on Mental Health ratified.
This state ratifies and adopts by reference The Interstate Compact on Mental Health consisting of 14 articles approved on September 30, 1955, by the Northeast State Governments Conference on Mental Health. The department is designated as compact administrator with full power to carry out the purpose of the compact and to adopt all necessary regulations to implement the compact.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-885">
            <num>47.30.885</num>
            <heading>Rights outside state.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.885.   Rights outside state.
Nothing in
AS 47.30.660
 47.30.915 alters or impairs the application or availability to a patient, while hospitalized in another state under contractual arrangements entered in accordance with
AS 47.30.660
 47.30.915, of the rights, remedies, or safeguards provided by the laws of this state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-890">
            <num>47.30.890</num>
            <heading>Provision for personal needs upon discharge.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.890.   Provision for personal needs upon discharge.
The department shall ensure that
(1) a patient is not discharged from a treatment facility without suitable clothing; and
(2) a discharged indigent patient is furnished
(A) suitable transportation to the patient's permanent residence in this state or to another suitable place at the discretion of the department; and
(B) a reasonable amount of money to meet the patient's immediate needs.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-895">
            <num>47.30.895</num>
            <heading>Disposition of unclaimed property; recovery of personal property.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-895__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Those unclaimed articles of personal property that are covered by
AS 34.45.110
 34.45.260 and the unclaimed money in the custody of a treatment facility that belong to a patient who dies before discharge, or to a patient who leaves the hospital without authority, if unclaimed by the patient or the legal heirs or representatives of the patient within one year after the patient's death or departure, shall be disposed of in accordance with
AS 34.45.110
 34.45.780, and the other articles of the patient's personal property shall be disposed of in the manner prescribed by the department and the proceeds deposited in the general fund.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-895__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a mentally ill individual has died in a foreign facility and the department desires to recover the patient's personal property under this section, the commissioner or the commissioner's designated representative may secure the property and for that purpose only is designated the decedent's administrator.  Property so recovered shall be disposed of as provided by law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-900">
            <num>47.30.900</num>
            <heading>Diligent inquiry; personal property delivery and claims.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.900.   Diligent inquiry; personal property delivery and claims.
The department shall make diligent inquiry in every instance after departure without authority or death of a patient, to ascertain the whereabouts of the patient or that of the patient's legal heirs or representatives, and shall turn over to the proper person the money or articles of personal property in the custody of the facility to the credit of the patient. Claims to the money or articles of personal property, including claims by the state, may be presented to the department at any time.  If a claim other than by the state is established by clear and convincing evidence more than one year after the death or departure without authority of a patient, it shall be certified to the legislature for consideration and the legislature may pay the claim.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-905">
            <num>47.30.905</num>
            <heading>Fees and expenses for judicial proceedings.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-905__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The witnesses, expert witnesses, and the jury in commitment proceedings under
AS 47.30.660
 47.30.915 are entitled to the fees, compensation, and mileage established by the administrative rules of court for other jurors and witnesses. Compensation, mileage, fees, transportation expenses for a respondent, and other expenses arising from evaluation and commitment proceedings shall be audited and allowed by the superior court of the judicial district in which the proceedings are held.  To the extent that services of a peace officer are used to carry out the provisions of
AS 47.30.660
 47.30.915, the officer is entitled to fees and actual expenses from the same source and in the same manner as for the officer's other official duties.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-905__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An attorney appointed for a person under
AS 47.30.660
 47.30.915 shall be compensated for services as follows:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-905__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the person for whom an attorney is appointed shall, if the person is financially able under standards as to financial capability and indigency set by the court, pay the costs of the legal services;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-905__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if the person is indigent under those standards, the costs of the services shall be paid by the state.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-907">
            <num>47.30.907</num>
            <heading>Report to Department of Public Safety.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-907__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding
AS 47.30.845
, when a superior court orders the involuntary commitment of a person under
AS 47.30.735
 47.30.755 or when relief from a disability resulting from an involuntary commitment or an adjudication of mental illness or mental incompetence is granted under
AS 47.30.851
(b), the court shall immediately transmit the following information, if known, to the Department of Public Safety:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-907__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the person's
(A) name, date of birth, and address;
(B) aliases;
(C) social security number;
(D) driver's license or state identification card number;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-907__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the date of the order and whether the order is
(A) an involuntary commitment; or
(B) relief from the disability resulting from an involuntary commitment or an adjudication of mental illness or mental incompetence;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-907__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the statutory authority for the involuntary commitment or the disability resulting from an involuntary commitment or an adjudication of mental illness or mental incompetence;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-907__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>whether the person was offered an opportunity to be heard and represented by counsel in the involuntary commitment proceeding or adjudication of mental illness or mental incompetence; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-30-907__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>any other information required by the Department of Public Safety or by the United States Department of Justice for inclusion in the National Instant Criminal Background Check System established under P.L. 103-159, 107 Stat. 1536 (Brady Handgun Violence Prevention Act).</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-907__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This section does not apply to initial involuntary commitment procedures, emergency detention for evaluation, or hospitalization for examination under
AS 47.30.700
 47.30.715 if the person is released under
AS 47.30.720
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-910">
            <num>47.30.910</num>
            <heading>Payment of patient expenses.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-30-910__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A patient, the patient's spouse, or the patient's parent if the patient is under 18 years of age shall pay the charges for the care, transportation, and treatment of the patient when the patient is hospitalized under
AS 47.30.670
 47.30.915 at a state-operated facility, an evaluation facility, or a designated treatment facility providing services under
AS 47.30.670
 47.30.915. The patient, the patient's spouse, or the patient's parent if the patient is under 18 years of age shall make arrangements with a state-operated facility, an evaluation facility, or a designated treatment facility for payment of charges, including providing income information necessary to determine eligibility for benefits under
AS 47.31
. Charges assessed for services provided under
AS 47.30.670
 47.30.915 when a patient is hospitalized at a state-operated facility may not exceed the actual cost of care and treatment. The department may, when assessing charges for services provided at a state-operated facility, consider the ability to pay of a patient, a patient's spouse, or a patient's parent if the patient is under 18 years of age. In order to impose liability for a patient's cost of care at a state-operated facility, the department shall issue an order for payment within six months after the date on which the charge was incurred. The order remains in effect unless modified by subsequent court order or department order. The department may not impose liability for a patient's cost of care at a state-operated facility if the patient would otherwise meet the eligibility criteria, other than location of service, in
AS 47.31.010
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-910__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department, the evaluation facility, or a designated treatment facility shall make reasonable efforts to determine whether the patient, the patient's spouse, or the patient's parent if the patient is under 18 years of age has a third-party payor or has the available means to substantially contribute to the payment of charges, or whether the patient is eligible for assistance under
AS 47.31
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-910__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a patient is hospitalized at a state-operated facility and the patient, the patient's spouse, or the patient's parent if the patient is under 18 years of age fails to provide to the department information necessary to determine whether there is a third-party payor or available means to substantially contribute to the payment of charges, or whether the patient would, if not hospitalized at a state-operated facility, be eligible for assistance under
AS 47.31
, the department may issue an administrative order imposing full liability for the patient's actual cost of care on the patient, the patient's spouse, or the patient's parent if the patient is under 18 years of age. The order remains in effect unless modified by subsequent court order or department order.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-910__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a person who is hospitalized under
AS 47.30.670
 47.30.915 at an evaluation facility or a designated treatment facility cannot pay or substantially contribute to the payment of charges described under this section, the patient may apply for assistance under
AS 47.31
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-910__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may charge or accept money or property from a person for the care or treatment of a patient at a state-operated facility.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-30-910__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Money paid by the patient or on the patient's behalf to the department under this section shall be deposited in the general fund.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-912">
            <num>47.30.912</num>
            <heading>Regulations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.912.   Regulations.
The department shall adopt regulations to implement
AS 47.30.700
 47.30.915.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-30-915">
            <num>47.30.915</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.30.915.   Definitions.
In
AS 47.30.660
 47.30.915,
(1) adjudication of mental illness or mental incompetence means a court order finding that a person is
(A) not guilty by reason of insanity or guilty but mentally ill under
AS 12.47.040
;
(B) incompetent to stand trial for a criminal offense under
AS 12.47.100
 12.47.120; or
(C) a danger to self or others, or is gravely disabled because of incapacity, incompetence, mental illness, dementia, or some other cause;
(2) commissioner means the commissioner of family and community services;
(3) court means a superior court of the state;
(4) crisis residential center has the meaning given in
AS 47.32.900
;
(5) crisis stabilization center has the meaning given in
AS 47.32.900
;
(6) department means the Department of Family and Community Services;
(7) designated treatment facility or treatment facility means a hospital, clinic, institution, center, or other health care facility that has been designated by the department for the treatment or rehabilitation of mentally ill persons under
AS 47.30.670
 47.30.915 but does not include correctional institutions;
(8) disability resulting from an involuntary commitment or an adjudication of mental illness or mental incompetence means the prohibition against the possession of a firearm or ammunition under 18 U.S.C. 922(g)(4) that results from an involuntary commitment or adjudication of mental illness or mental incompetence;
(9) evaluation facility means a hospital or crisis residential center that has been designated or is operated by the department to perform the evaluations described in
AS 47.30.660
 47.30.915, or a medical facility operated under 25 U.S.C. 5301  5423 (Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act), as amended, that performs evaluations;
(10) evaluation personnel means mental health professionals designated by the department to conduct evaluations as prescribed in
AS 47.30.660
 47.30.915 who conduct evaluations in places in which no staffed evaluation facility exists;
(11) gravely disabled means a condition in which a person as a result of mental illness
(A) is in danger of physical harm arising from such complete neglect of basic needs for food, clothing, shelter, or personal safety as to render serious accident, illness, or death highly probable if care by another is not taken; or
(B) is so incapacitated that the person is incapable of surviving safely in freedom;
(12) health officer means a federally certified health care provider, public health nurse, emergency medical technician, paramedic, firefighter, or a person authorized by the court to carry out
AS 47.30.660
 47.30.915;
(13) inpatient treatment means care and treatment rendered inside or on the premises of a treatment facility, or a part or unit of a treatment facility, for a continual period of 24 hours or longer;
(14) least restrictive alternative means mental health treatment facilities and conditions of treatment that
(A) are no more harsh, hazardous, or intrusive than necessary to achieve the treatment objectives of the patient; and
(B) involve no restrictions on physical movement nor supervised residence or inpatient care except as reasonably necessary for the administration of treatment or the protection of the patient or others from physical injury;
(15) likely to cause serious harm means a person who
(A) poses a substantial risk of bodily harm to that person's self, as manifested by recent behavior causing, attempting, or threatening that harm;
(B) poses a substantial risk of harm to others as manifested by recent behavior causing, attempting, or threatening harm, and is likely in the near future to cause physical injury, physical abuse, or substantial property damage to another person; or
(C) manifests a current intent to carry out plans of serious harm to that person's self or another;
(16) [See delayed amendment note.]  mental health professional means a psychiatrist or physician who is licensed by the State Medical Board to practice in this state or is employed by the federal government; a clinical psychologist licensed by the state Board of Psychologist and Psychological Associate Examiners; a psychological associate trained in clinical psychology and licensed by the Board of Psychologist and Psychological Associate Examiners; an advanced practice registered nurse or a registered nurse with a master's degree in psychiatric nursing, licensed by the State Board of Nursing; a marital and family therapist licensed by the Board of Marital and Family Therapy; a professional counselor licensed by the Board of Professional Counselors; a clinical social worker licensed by the Board of Social Work Examiners; and a person who
(A) has a master's degree in the field of mental health;
(B) has at least 12 months of post-masters working experience in the field of mental illness; and
(C) is working under the supervision of a type of licensee listed in this paragraph;
(17) mental illness means an organic, mental, or emotional impairment that has substantial adverse effects on an individual's ability to exercise conscious control of the individual's actions or ability to perceive reality or to reason or understand; intellectual disability, developmental disability, or both, epilepsy, drug addiction, and alcoholism do not per se constitute mental illness, although persons suffering from these conditions may also be suffering from mental illness;
(18) peace officer has the meaning given in
AS 01.10.060
(a);
(19) persons with mental disorders has the meaning given in
AS 47.30.610
;
(20) professional person in charge means the senior mental health professional at a facility or that person's designee; in the absence of a mental health professional it means the chief of staff or a physician designated by the chief of staff;
(21) provider of outpatient care means a mental health professional or hospital, clinic, institution, center, or other health care facility designated by the department to accept for treatment patients who are ordered to undergo involuntary outpatient treatment by the court or who are released early from inpatient commitments on condition that they undergo outpatient treatment;
(22) screening investigation means the investigation and review of facts that have been alleged to warrant emergency examination or treatment, including interviews with the persons making the allegations, any other significant witnesses who can readily be contacted for interviews, and, if possible, the respondent, and an investigation and evaluation of the reliability and credibility of persons providing information or making allegations;
(23) state means a state of the United States, the District of Columbia, the territories and possessions of the United States, and the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, and, with the approval of the United States Congress, Canada;
(24) subacute mental health facility has the meaning given in
AS 47.32.900
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>