<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-33/chapter-36"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-33/chapter-36"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="33.36"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-33/chapter-36/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-33/chapter-36/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-33/chapter-36/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-33/chapter-36/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_33">
        <num>33</num>
        <heading>Probation, Prisons, Pardons, and Prisoners</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_33__chp_36">
          <num>36</num>
          <heading>Interstate Corrections Compacts</heading>
          <section eId="sec_33-36-010">
            <num>33.36.010</num>
            <heading>Compact enacted.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 33.36.010.   Compact enacted.
The Interstate Corrections Compact as contained in this section is enacted into law and entered into on behalf of the State of Alaska with any other states legally joining in it in a form substantially as follows. It is the policy of the State of Alaska not to transfer a resident inmate outside of the state under this compact if that inmate's continued confinement in Alaska will better facilitate rehabilitation or treatment:</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-36-020">
            <num>33.36.020</num>
            <heading>Commitment or transfer of inmates under compact.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 33.36.020.   Commitment or transfer of inmates under compact.
An agency or officer of the State of Alaska having power to commit or transfer an inmate to an institution for confinement may commit or transfer the inmate to an institution inside or outside the State of Alaska, if the State of Alaska has entered into a contract for the confinement of inmates in the institution under Article III of the Interstate Corrections Compact.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-36-030">
            <num>33.36.030</num>
            <heading>Enforcement of compact.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 33.36.030.   Enforcement of compact.
The courts, departments, agencies, and officers of the State of Alaska and its subdivisions shall enforce the Interstate Corrections Compact and shall do all things appropriate to carry out its purposes and intent which may be within their respective jurisdictions but not limited to making and submitting required reports.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-36-040">
            <num>33.36.040</num>
            <heading>Implementation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 33.36.040.   Implementation.
The commissioner of corrections or the commissioner's designee shall do all things necessary or incidental to the carrying out of the Interstate Corrections Compact. However, no contract is of any force or effect until approved by the commissioner of administration.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-36-060">
            <num>33.36.060</num>
            <heading>Compact enacted.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 33.36.060.   Compact enacted.
The Western Interstate Corrections Compact as contained in this section is enacted into law and entered into on behalf of the State of Alaska with any and all other states legally joining in it in a form substantially as follows:</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-36-070">
            <num>33.36.070</num>
            <heading>Commitment or transfer of inmates under compact.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 33.36.070.   Commitment or transfer of inmates under compact.
An agency or officer of the State of Alaska having power to commit or transfer an inmate, as defined in art. II(d) of the Western Interstate Corrections Compact, to any institution for confinement may commit or transfer the inmate to an institution within or without the State of Alaska if the State of Alaska has entered into a contract or contracts for the confinement of inmates in the institution under art. III of the Western Interstate Corrections Compact.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-36-080">
            <num>33.36.080</num>
            <heading>Enforcement of compact.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 33.36.080.   Enforcement of compact.
The courts, departments, agencies and officers of the State of Alaska and its subdivisions shall enforce this compact and shall do all things appropriate to carry out its purposes and intent which may be within their respective jurisdictions including but not limited to the making and submission of reports required by the compact.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-36-090">
            <num>33.36.090</num>
            <heading>Board of parole to hold hearings under compact.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 33.36.090.   Board of parole to hold hearings under compact.
The Alaska board of parole shall hold such hearings as may be requested by another party state under art. IV(f) of the Western Interstate Corrections Compact.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-36-100">
            <num>33.36.100</num>
            <heading>Implementation of compact.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 33.36.100.   Implementation of compact.
The commissioner of corrections may enter into such contracts on behalf of the State of Alaska as may be appropriate to implement the participation of this state in the Western Interstate Corrections Compact under art. III of the compact. No contract is of any force or effect until approved by the commissioner of administration.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-36-110">
            <num>33.36.110</num>
            <heading>Authorizing governor to execute interstate compact.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 33.36.110.   Authorizing governor to execute interstate compact.
The governor of this state is authorized and directed to execute a compact on behalf of this state with any of the United States legally joining in the compact in the form substantially as follows:</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-36-130">
            <num>33.36.130</num>
            <heading>Compact administrator.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-36-130__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The governor shall appoint the administrator for the compact set out in
AS 33.36.110
in consultation with the legislature and judiciary. The compact administrator must have a background in criminal justice.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-36-130__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The compact administrator is responsible for the administration and management of the state's supervision and transfer of offenders under
AS 33.36.110
, and shall report to the state council under
AS 33.36.140
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-36-130__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The compact administrator shall work within the Department of Corrections under the direction of the commissioner of corrections. The compact administrator serves at the pleasure of the governor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-36-135">
            <num>33.36.135</num>
            <heading>Review of rules.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 33.36.135.   Review of rules.
The compact administrator shall annually, not later than January 31, provide a report on any rules that have been adopted by the Interstate Commission during the previous calendar year to the legislature. The legislature shall review the rules to determine if the compact should be repealed, amended, or permitted to continue. In this section, compact, compact administrator, and Interstate Commission, have the meanings given in
AS 33.36.110
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-36-140">
            <num>33.36.140</num>
            <heading>State council.</heading>
            <subsection eId="33-36-140__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>There is created the State Council for Interstate Adult and Juvenile Offender Supervision to implement the provisions of the compact set out in
AS 33.36.110
as the State Council for Interstate Adult Offender Supervision and the compact set out in
AS 47.15.010
as the State Council for Interstate Juvenile Supervision. The state council shall meet as frequently as necessary to carry out its responsibilities.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-36-140__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The state council consists of nine members as follows:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-36-140__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the commissioner of corrections; the commissioner of corrections may name a designee to serve in this capacity;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-36-140__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the compact administrator appointed under
AS 33.36.130
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-36-140__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an attorney employed in the Department of Law, appointed by the governor;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-36-140__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>two members appointed by the governor from among the citizens of the state, at least one of whom must be a representative from victims' groups;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-36-140__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>one ex officio nonvoting member from the legislative branch selected by the legislature and one ex officio nonvoting member from the judicial branch selected by the judiciary;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-36-140__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the commissioner of family and community services; the commissioner of family and community services may name a designee to serve in this capacity;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-36-140__subsec_b__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the compact administrator appointed under
AS 47.15.020
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-36-140__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner of corrections or the commissioner's designee shall serve as chair of the state council.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-36-140__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The term of office of a member of the state council appointed under (b)(4) of this section is three years. The members of the state council appointed under (b)(3) and (4) of this section serve at the pleasure of the governor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-36-140__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Voting members of the state council who are not state employees receive no salary for their work on the council, but are entitled to per diem and travel expenses authorized for other boards and commissions.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="33-36-140__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The state council shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="33-36-140__subsec_f__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>designate the compact administrator, appointed under
AS 33.36.130
, as its commissioner to the Interstate Commission for Adult Offender Supervision under the Interstate Compact for Adult Offender Supervision set out in
AS 33.36.110
; if the compact administrator is unavailable to serve as commissioner at a meeting of the Interstate Commission for Adult Offender Supervision, the council shall designate another person to serve in place of the compact administrator;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-36-140__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>exercise oversight and advocacy concerning the state's participation in the Interstate Commission for Adult Offender Supervision;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-36-140__subsec_f__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>subject to available appropriations and other legal obligations, recommend policy development concerning the operations and procedures of the compact within the state; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="33-36-140__subsec_f__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>make recommendations to the legislature to facilitate the implementation of the compact and the rules and bylaws adopted by the Interstate Commission for Adult Offender Supervision.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_33-36-145">
            <num>33.36.145</num>
            <heading>Application fee</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 33.36.145.   Application fee
A person under probation or parole supervision by the Department of Corrections who applies for a transfer of supervision to another state under the Interstate Compact for Adult Offender Supervision shall pay to the Department of Corrections a nonrefundable application fee of $100.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>