<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-15/chapter-13"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-15/chapter-13"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="15.13"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-15/chapter-13/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-15/chapter-13/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-15/chapter-13/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-15/chapter-13/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_15">
        <num>15</num>
        <heading>Elections</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_15__chp_13">
          <num>13</num>
          <heading>State Election Campaigns</heading>
          <section eId="sec_15-13-010">
            <num>15.13.010</num>
            <heading>Applicability.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-13-010__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This chapter applies</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-010__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in every election for governor, lieutenant governor, a member of the state legislature, a delegate to a constitutional convention, or judge seeking judicial retention;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-010__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to every candidate for election to a municipal office in a municipality with a population of more than 1,000 inhabitants according to the latest United States census figures or estimates of population certified as correct for administrative purposes by the Department of Commerce, Community, and Economic Development unless the municipality has exempted itself from the provisions of this chapter; a municipality may exempt its elected municipal officers from the requirements of this chapter if a majority of the voters voting on the question at a regular election, as defined by
AS 29.71.800
(21), or a special municipality-wide election called for that purpose, votes to exempt its elected municipal officers from the requirements of this chapter; the question of exemption from the requirements of this chapter may be submitted by the governing body by ordinance or by initiative election.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-010__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as otherwise provided, this chapter applies to contributions, expenditures, and communications made for the purpose of influencing the outcome of a ballot proposition or question as well as those made to influence the nomination or election of a candidate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-010__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This chapter does not prohibit a municipality from regulating by ordinance election campaign contributions and expenditures in municipal elections, or from regulating those campaign contributions and expenditures more strictly than provided in this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-010__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This chapter does not limit the authority of a person to make contributions to influence the outcome of a voter proposition submitted to the public for a vote at a municipal election. In this subsection, in addition to its meaning under
AS 15.13.065
(c), proposition means a municipal reclassification, proposal to adopt or amend a home rule charter, a unification proposal, a boundary change proposal, or the approval of an ordinance when approval by public vote is a requirement for the ordinance.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-13-020">
            <num>15.13.020</num>
            <heading>Alaska Public Offices Commission.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-13-020__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>There is created in the Department of Administration the Alaska Public Offices Commission consisting of five members. The governor shall appoint all members of the commission in the manner prescribed in (b) and (c) of this section, subject to confirmation by a majority of the legislature meeting in joint session.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-020__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The governor shall appoint two members of each of the two political parties or political groups with the largest number of registered voters at the time of the most recent preceding general election at which a governor was elected. The two appointees from each of these two parties or groups shall be chosen from a list of four names to be submitted by the central committee of each party or group.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-020__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The four members selected under (b) of this section shall, by a majority vote, nominate to the governor an individual to serve as the fifth member of the commission. The governor shall either appoint the nominee to the commission, or shall reject the nominee and request those four members to nominate another individual to serve as the fifth member of the commission.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-020__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Members of the commission serve staggered terms of five years, or until a successor is appointed and qualifies. The terms of no two members who are members of the same political party or political group may expire in consecutive years. A member may not serve more than one term. However, a person appointed to fill the unexpired term of a predecessor may be appointed to a successive full five-year term.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-020__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A member of the commission, during tenure, may not</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-020__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>hold or campaign for elective office;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-020__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>be an officer of a political party, political committee, or group;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-020__subsec_e__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>permit the member's name to be used, or make any contributions whatsoever, in support of or in opposition to a candidate or proposition or question that appears on any ballot in the state, including that of a municipality; however, contributions may be made to a candidate for the office of President of the United States;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-020__subsec_e__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>participate in any way in an election campaign or participate in or contribute to any political party; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-020__subsec_e__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>lobby, employ, or assist a lobbyist.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-020__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Members of the commission shall receive compensation of $50 a day while attending commission meetings and shall be entitled to travel expenses and per diem authorized by law for members of other boards and commissions.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-020__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The members shall elect a chairperson. Three members of the commission constitute a quorum. A vacancy does not impair the powers of the remaining members to exercise all of the powers of the commission.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-020__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A vacancy on the commission shall be filled through the appropriate appointing method for the position within 30 days after the occurrence of the vacancy. Except as provided in
AS 39.05.080</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-020__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission may employ an executive director and other employees it considers necessary. Neither the executive director nor an employee may have a vote.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-020__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall establish an office, which may be called a regional office, in each senate district in the state to keep on file for public inspection copies of all reports filed with the commission by candidates for statewide office and by candidates for legislative office in that district; however, where one municipality contains more than one house district, only one commission office shall be established in that municipality. The regional office shall make all forms and pertinent material available to candidates. All reports shall be filed by candidates, groups, and individuals directly with the commission's central district office. The commission shall ensure that copies of all reports by statewide and legislative candidates in each senate district are forwarded promptly to that district or regional office.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-020__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall ensure that copies of reports filed by candidates for municipal office are made available for public inspection in the appropriate municipality.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-13-030">
            <num>15.13.030</num>
            <heading>Duties of the commission.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.13.030.   Duties of the commission.
The commission shall
(1) develop and provide all forms for the reports and statements required to be made under this chapter,
AS 24.45
, and
AS 39.50
;
(2) prepare and publish a manual setting out uniform methods of bookkeeping and reporting for use by persons required to make reports and statements under this chapter and otherwise assist all persons in complying with the requirements of this chapter;
(3) receive and hold open for public inspection reports and statements required to be made under this chapter and, upon request, furnish copies at cost to interested persons;
(4) compile and maintain a current list of all filed reports and statements;
(5) prepare a summary of each report filed under
AS 15.13.110
and make copies of this summary available to interested persons at their actual cost;
(6) notify, by registered or certified mail, all persons who are delinquent in filing reports and statements required to be made under this chapter;
(7) examine, investigate, and compare all reports, statements, and actions required by this chapter,
AS 24.45
, and
AS 39.50
;
(8) prepare and publish a biennial report concerning the activities of the commission, the effectiveness of this chapter, its enforcement by the attorney general's office, and recommendations and proposals for change; the commission shall notify the legislature that the report is available;
(9) adopt regulations necessary to implement and clarify the provisions of
AS 24.45
,
AS 39.50
, and this chapter, subject to the provisions of
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act); and
(10) consider a written request for an advisory opinion concerning the application of this chapter,
AS 24.45
,
AS 24.60.200
 24.60.260, or
AS 39.50
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-13-040">
            <num>15.13.040</num>
            <heading>Contributions, expenditures, and supplying of services to be reported.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-13-040__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (g) and (l) of this section, each candidate shall make a full report, upon a form prescribed by the commission,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-040__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>listing
(A) the date and amount of all expenditures made by the candidate;
(B) the total amount of all contributions, including all funds contributed by the candidate;
(C) the name, address, date, and amount contributed by each contributor; and
(D) for contributions in excess of $50 in the aggregate during a calendar year, the principal occupation and employer of the contributor; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-040__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>filed in accordance with
AS 15.13.110
and certified correct by the candidate or campaign treasurer.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-040__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each group shall make a full report upon a form prescribed by the commission, listing</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-040__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name and address of each officer and director;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-040__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the aggregate amount of all contributions made to it; and, for all contributions in excess of $100 in the aggregate a year, the name, address, principal occupation, and employer of the contributor, and the date and amount contributed by each contributor; for purposes of this paragraph, contributor means the true source of the funds, property, or services being contributed; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-040__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the date and amount of all contributions made by it and all expenditures made, incurred, or authorized by it.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-040__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The report required under (b) of this section shall be filed in accordance with
AS 15.13.110
and shall be certified as correct by the group's treasurer.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-040__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Every person making an independent expenditure shall make a full report of expenditures made and contributions received, upon a form prescribed by the commission, unless exempt from reporting.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-040__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each person required to report under (d) of this section shall file a full report in accordance with
AS 15.13.110</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-040__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>on a form prescribed by the commission. The report must contain</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-040__subsec_h__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name, address, principal occupation, and employer of the individual filing the report;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-040__subsec_h__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an itemized list of all expenditures made, incurred, or authorized by the person;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-040__subsec_h__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name of the candidate or the title of the ballot proposition or question supported or opposed by each expenditure and whether the expenditure is made to support or oppose the candidate or ballot proposition or question;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-040__subsec_h__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name and address of each officer and director, when applicable;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-040__subsec_h__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the aggregate amount of all contributions made to the person, if any, for the purpose of influencing the outcome of an election; for all contributions, the date of the contribution and amount contributed by each contributor; and, for a contributor
(A) who is an individual, the name and address of the contributor and, for contributions in excess of $50 in the aggregate during a calendar year, the name, address, principal occupation, and employer of the contributor; or
(B) that is not an individual, the name and address of the contributor and the name and address of each officer and director of the contributor.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-040__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>During each year in which an election occurs, all businesses, persons, or groups that furnish any of the following services, facilities, or supplies to a candidate or group shall maintain a record of each transaction: newspapers, radio, television, advertising, advertising agency services, accounting, billboards, printing, secretarial, public opinion polls, or research and professional campaign consultation or management, media production or preparation, or computer services. Records of provision of services, facilities, or supplies shall be available for inspection by the commission.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-040__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The provisions of (a) and (l) of this section do not apply to a delegate to a constitutional convention, a judge seeking judicial retention, or a candidate for election to a municipal office under
AS 15.13.010
, if that delegate, judge, or candidate</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-040__subsec_g__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>indicates, on a form prescribed by the commission, an intent not to raise and not to expend more than $5,000 in seeking election to office, including both the primary and general elections;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-040__subsec_g__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>accepts contributions totaling not more than $5,000 in seeking election to office, including both the primary and general elections; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-040__subsec_g__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>makes expenditures totaling not more than $5,000 in seeking election to office, including both the primary and general elections.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-040__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The provisions of (d) of this section do not apply to one or more expenditures made by an individual acting independently of any other person if the expenditures</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-040__subsec_h__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>cumulatively do not exceed $500 during a calendar year; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-040__subsec_h__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>are made only for billboards, signs, or printed material concerning a ballot proposition as that term is defined by
AS 15.13.065</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-040__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The permission of the owner of real or personal property to post political signs, including bumper stickers, or to use space for an event or to store campaign-related materials is not considered to be a contribution to a candidate under this chapter unless the owner customarily charges a fee or receives payment for that activity. The fact that the owner customarily charges a fee or receives payment for posting signs that are not political signs is not determinative of whether the owner customarily does so for political signs.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-040__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (l) of this section, each nongroup entity shall make a full report in accordance with
AS 15.13.110
upon a form prescribed by the commission and certified by the nongroup entity's treasurer, listing</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-040__subsec_j__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name and address of each officer and director of the nongroup entity;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-040__subsec_j__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the aggregate amount of all contributions made to the nongroup entity for the purpose of influencing the outcome of an election;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-040__subsec_j__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for all contributions described in (2) of this subsection, the name, address, date, and amount contributed by each contributor, for all contributions described in (2) of this subsection in excess of $250 in the aggregate during a calendar year, the principal occupation and employer of the contributor, and for all contributions described in (2) of this subsection in excess of $2,000 in the aggregate during a calendar year, the true source of such contributions and all intermediaries, if any, who transferred such funds, and a certification from the treasurer that the report discloses all of the information required by this paragraph; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-040__subsec_j__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the date and amount of all contributions made by the nongroup entity, and, except as provided for certain independent expenditures in
AS 15.13.135</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-040__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Every individual, person, nongroup entity, or group contributing a total of $500 or more to a group organized for the principal purpose of influencing the outcome of a proposition, and every individual, person, nongroup entity, or group contributing a total of $500 or more to a group organized for the principal purpose of filing an initiative proposal application under
AS 15.45.020
or that has filed an initiative proposal application under
AS 15.45.020
, shall report the contribution or contributions on a form prescribed by the commission not later than 30 days after the contribution that requires the contributor to report under this subsection is made. The report must include the name, address, principal occupation, and employer of the individual filing the report and the amount of the contribution, as well as the total amount of contributions made to that group by that individual, person, nongroup entity, or group during the calendar year.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-040__subsec_l">
              <num>(l)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (a), (b), and (j) of this section, for any fund-raising activity in which contributions are in amounts or values that do not exceed $50 a person, the candidate, group, or nongroup entity shall report contributions and expenditures and supplying of services under this subsection as follows:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-040__subsec_l__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a report under this subsection must
(A) describe the fund-raising activity;
(B) include the number of persons making contributions and the total proceeds from the activity;
(C) report all contributions made for the fund-raising activity that do not exceed $50 a person in amount or value; if a contribution for the fund-raising activity exceeds $50, the contribution shall be reported under (a), (b), and (j) of this section;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-040__subsec_l__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for purposes of this subsection,
(A) contribution means a cash donation, a purchase such as the purchase of a ticket, the purchase of goods or services offered for sale at a fund-raising activity, or a donation of goods or services for the fund-raising activity;
(B) fund-raising activity means an activity, event, or sale of goods undertaken by a candidate, group, or nongroup entity in which contributions are $50 a person or less in amount or value.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-040__subsec_m">
              <num>(m)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Information required under this chapter shall be submitted to the commission electronically, except that the following information may be submitted in clear and legible black typeface or hand-printed in dark ink on paper in a format approved by the commission or on forms provided by the commission:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-040__subsec_m__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>information submitted by
(A) a candidate for election to a borough or city office of mayor, membership on a borough assembly, city council, or school board, or any state office, who</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-040__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>meets the requirements of (g)(1)  (3) of this section; or
(ii) does not have reasonable access to the technology necessary to file electronically; in this sub-subparagraph, a candidate is considered not to have reasonable access to the technology necessary to file electronically if the candidate does not own a personal computer or does not have broadband Internet access at the candidate's residence; in this sub-subparagraph, broadband Internet access means high-speed Internet access that is always on and that is faster than traditional dial-up access; or
(B) a candidate for municipal office for a municipality with a population of less than 15,000; in this subparagraph, municipal office means the office of an elected borough or city</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-040__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>mayor; or
(ii) assembly, council, or school board member;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-040__subsec_i__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>any information if the commission determines that circumstances warrant an exception to the electronic submission requirement.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-040__subsec_n">
              <num>(n)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall print the forms to be provided under this chapter so that the front and back of each page have the same orientation when the page is rotated on the vertical axis of the page.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-040__subsec_o">
              <num>(o)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Information required by this chapter that is submitted to the commission on paper and not electronically shall be electronically scanned and published on the Internet by the commission, in a format accessible to the general public, within two working days after the commission receives the information.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-040__subsec_p">
              <num>(p)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding the requirement in (a) of this section that a candidate shall make a full report upon a form prescribed by the commission, the commission shall accept information submitted electronically by a candidate if the information is</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-040__subsec_p__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>entered onto a version of a form accessed on the Internet website of the commission; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-040__subsec_p__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in the form of an electronic spreadsheet or data file that contains field names and data types that conform to a standard defined by the commission.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-040__subsec_q">
              <num>(q)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of (b), (e), and (j) of this section, contributor means the true source of the funds, property, or services being contributed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-040__subsec_r">
              <num>(r)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Every individual, person, nongroup entity, or group that contributes more than $2,000 in the aggregate in a calendar year to an entity that made one or more independent expenditures in one or more candidate elections in the previous election cycle, that is making one or more independent expenditures in one or more candidate elections in the current election cycle, or that the contributor knows or has reason to know is likely to make independent expenditures in one or more candidate elections in the current election cycle shall report making the contribution or contributions on a form prescribed by the commission not later than 24 hours after the contribution that requires the contributor to report under this subsection is made. The report must include the name, address, principal occupation, and employer of the individual filing the report and the amount of the contribution, as well as the total amount of contributions made to that entity by that individual, person, nongroup entity, or group during the calendar year. For purposes of this subsection, the reporting contributor is required to report and certify the true sources of the contribution, and intermediaries, if any, as defined by
AS 15.13.400</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-040__subsec_s">
              <num>(s)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of (e) of this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-040__subsec_s__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>director means a member of the board of directors of a corporation or any person performing a similar function with respect to any organization;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-040__subsec_s__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>officer means a president, vice-president, secretary, treasurer, principal financial officer, or comptroller of a corporation, or any person routinely performing functions similar to those of a president, vice-president, secretary, treasurer, principal financial officer, or comptroller with respect to any organization.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-13-045">
            <num>15.13.045</num>
            <heading>Investigations, hearings.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-13-045__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission may issue subpoenas, administer oaths, hold hearings, and conduct investigations.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-045__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In conjunction with (a) of this section, the commission may compel the attendance of witnesses and production of papers, books, records, accounts, documents, and testimony, and may have the deposition of witnesses taken in a manner prescribed by court rule or law for the taking of depositions in civil actions when consistent with the powers and duties assigned to the commission by this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-045__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission may examine the papers, books, records, accounts, and documents of any person subject to this chapter to ascertain the correctness of a report filed with the commission, or in conjunction with an investigation or inspection conducted under (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-045__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subpoenas may be issued and shall be served in the manner prescribed by
AS 44.62.430
and court rule. The failure, refusal, or neglect to obey a subpoena is punishable as contempt in the manner prescribed by law or court rule.  The superior court may compel obedience to the commission's subpoena in the same manner as prescribed for obedience to a subpoena issued by the court.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-13-050">
            <num>15.13.050</num>
            <heading>Registration before expenditure.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-13-050__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before making an expenditure in support of or in opposition to a candidate or before making an expenditure in support of or in opposition to a ballot proposition or question or to an initiative proposal application filed with the lieutenant governor under
AS 15.45.020
, each person other than an individual shall register, on forms provided by the commission, with the commission.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-050__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a group intends to support only one candidate or to contribute to or expend on behalf of one candidate 33 1/3 percent or more of its funds, the name of the candidate shall be a part of the name of the group. If the group intends to oppose only one candidate or to contribute its funds in opposition to or make expenditures in opposition to a candidate, the group's name must clearly state that it opposes that candidate by using a word such as opposes, opposing, in opposition to, or against in the group's name. Promptly upon receiving the registration, the commission shall notify the candidate of the group's organization and intent. A candidate may register more than one group to support the candidate; however, multiple groups controlled by a single candidate shall be treated as a single group for purposes of the contribution limit in
AS 15.13.070
(b)(1).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-050__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a group intends to make more than 50 percent of its contributions or expenditures in support of or in opposition to a single initiative on the ballot, the title or common name of the initiative must be a part of the name of the group. If the group intends to make more than 50 percent of its contributions or expenditures in opposition to a single initiative on the ballot, the group's name must clearly state that the group opposes that initiative by using a word such as opposes, opposing, in opposition to, or against in the group's name.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-13-052">
            <num>15.13.052</num>
            <heading>Independent expenditures; political activities accounts.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-13-052__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before making an independent expenditure in support of or in opposition to a candidate or before making an independent expenditure in support of or in opposition to a ballot proposition or question, each person other than an individual, candidate, or nongroup entity with an annual operating budget of $250 or less shall establish a political activities account. The political activities account may be a separate account in the person's general treasury. The political activities account must be administered using generally accepted accounting principles. All funds used by the person to make independent expenditures must be drawn from the person's political activities account.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-052__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Records necessary to substantiate that the requirements of (a) of this section have been met must be made available for inspection by the commission.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-052__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each person who has established a political activities account under this section shall preserve all records necessary to substantiate the person's compliance with the requirements of this section for each of the six preceding years.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-13-060">
            <num>15.13.060</num>
            <heading>Campaign treasurers.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-13-060__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each candidate and group shall appoint a campaign treasurer who is responsible for receiving, holding, and disbursing all contributions and expenditures, and for filing all reports and statements required by law.  A candidate may be a campaign treasurer.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-060__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each group shall file the name and address of its campaign treasurer with the commission at the time it registers with the commission under
AS 15.13.050
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-060__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each candidate for state office shall file the name and address of the campaign treasurer with the commission, or submit, in writing, the name and address of the campaign treasurer to the director for filing with the commission, no later than 15 days after the date of filing the declaration of candidacy or the nominating petition.  Each candidate for municipal office shall file the name and address of the campaign treasurer with the commission no later than seven days after the date of filing the declaration of candidacy or the nominating petition. If the candidate does not designate a campaign treasurer, the candidate is the campaign treasurer.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-060__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In the case of the death, resignation, or removal of a campaign treasurer, the candidate shall appoint a successor as soon as practicable and file the successor's name and address with the commission within 48 hours of the appointment.  The candidate is disqualified if found to have been in wilful violation of this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-060__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A campaign treasurer may appoint as many deputy campaign treasurers as necessary. The candidate shall file the names and addresses of the deputy campaign treasurers with the commission.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-060__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The candidate is responsible for the performance of the campaign treasurer, and any default or violation by the treasurer also shall be considered a default or violation by the candidate if the candidate knew or had reason to know of the default or violation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-13-065">
            <num>15.13.065</num>
            <heading>Contributions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-13-065__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Individuals, groups, nongroup entities, and political parties may make contributions to a candidate. An individual, group, or nongroup entity may make a contribution to a group, to a nongroup entity, or to a political party.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-065__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A political party may contribute to a subordinate unit of the political party, and a subordinate unit of a political party may contribute to the political party of which it is a subordinate unit.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-065__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except for reports required by
AS 15.13.040
and 15.13.110 and except for the requirements of
AS 15.13.050
, 15.13.060, and 15.13.112  15.13.114, the provisions of
AS 15.13.010
 15.13.116 do not apply to limit the authority of a person to make contributions to influence the outcome of a ballot proposition. In this subsection, in addition to its meaning in
AS 15.80.010
, proposition includes</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-065__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an issue placed on a ballot to determine whether
(A) a constitutional convention shall be called;
(B) a debt shall be contracted;
(C) an advisory question shall be approved or rejected; or
(D) a municipality shall be incorporated;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-065__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an initiative proposal application filed with the lieutenant governor under
AS 15.45.020
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-13-067">
            <num>15.13.067</num>
            <heading>Who may make expenditures.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.13.067.   Who may make expenditures.
Only the following may make an expenditure that is not an independent expenditure in an election for candidates for elective office:
(1) the candidate;
(2) an individual;
(3) a group that has registered under
AS 15.13.050
; and
(4) a nongroup entity that has registered under
AS 15.13.050
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-13-068">
            <num>15.13.068</num>
            <heading>Expenditures and contributions by foreign-influenced corporations and foreign nationals.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-13-068__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A foreign-influenced corporation or foreign national may not, directly or indirectly, in connection with an election under this chapter, make a contribution or expenditure or make an express or implied promise to make a contribution or expenditure.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-068__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The provisions of this section prohibit a foreign-influenced corporation or foreign national from making a contribution or expenditure in connection with a state election only to the extent</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-068__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>federal law prohibits the foreign-influenced corporation or foreign national from making a contribution or expenditure in connection with a state election; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-068__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>permitted by federal law.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-068__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (a) of this section, a foreign-influenced corporation may make a contribution to a person who makes covered expenditures or contributions if that person segregates contributions from foreign nationals and foreign-influenced corporations into a separate bank account that may not be used, directly or indirectly, to finance covered expenditures or contributions.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-068__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, when determining the percentage of a corporation's shares outstanding or equity owned by two or more foreign nationals,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-068__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>ownership in a mutual or pension fund that holds securities is not a form of ownership or control in such securities unless the foreign national or foreign owner can exercise control or participate in the management of the fund;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-068__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for privately held corporations, a corporation shall determine its percentage of foreign ownership at the time it obligates funds to make covered expenditures or contributions;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-068__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a publicly held corporation shall determine whether it is a foreign-influenced corporation based on its aggregate foreign ownership percentage at the close of trading on the last business day of the calendar quarter preceding the date the corporation makes or obligates funds to make a covered expenditure or contribution, unless the corporation has actual knowledge of its foreign ownership percentage at the time it makes or becomes obligated to make the covered expenditure or contribution; for the purposes of this paragraph, the corporation shall rely on facts, including information
(A) in the corporation's shareholder register;
(B) in possession of the United States Securities and Exchange Commission or another governmental agency that is available to the general public;
(C) known to the corporation as a result of litigation, financing transactions, or proxies voted at annual or other meetings; and
(D) known to the corporation from another source.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-068__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-068__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>corporation means any corporation, company, limited liability company, limited partnership, business trust, business association, or other similar entity;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-068__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>covered expenditure means an independent expenditure, electioneering expenditure, or express communication, but does not include a media communication, membership communication, shareholder communication, or expenditure as defined in
AS 15.13.400
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-068__subsec_e__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>election means any state or local election, including a special or runoff election;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-068__subsec_e__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>electioneering expenditure means a purchase or transfer of, or a promise or agreement to purchase or transfer, money or a thing of value to enable or facilitate the broadcast or other distribution of a communication that
(A)  clearly refers to a candidate for an election under (B) of this paragraph;
(B)  occurs in a 60-day period immediately preceding a general, special, or runoff election or within the 30 days preceding a primary or preference election, or a convention or caucus of a political party legally permitted to nominate a candidate for an election under this chapter; and
(C)  may be received by 500 or more persons in the jurisdiction the candidate seeks to represent;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-068__subsec_e__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>foreign-influenced corporation means a corporation for which
(A)  a foreign national or foreign owner holds, owns, controls, or has direct or indirect beneficial ownership of equity or voting shares in an amount equal to or greater than five percent of all corporate voting shares outstanding or all corporate equity;
(B)  two or more foreign nationals or foreign owners combined hold, own, control, or have direct or indirect beneficial ownership of equity or voting shares in an amount equal to or greater than 20 percent of all corporate voting shares outstanding or all corporate equity; or
(C)  a foreign national or foreign owner participates directly or indirectly in decisions relating to covered expenditures or contributions;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-068__subsec_e__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>foreign national means
(A) an individual who is not a United States citizen or lawfully admitted for permanent residence under 8 U.S.C. 1101(a)(20);
(B) a foreign government, every political subdivision of a foreign government, every official, agent, or representative of a foreign government, and every agency, corporation, or instrumentality of the foreign government or of a political subdivision of a foreign government;
(C) a person outside of the United States, unless it is established that the person is an individual and a citizen of and domiciled in the United States, or that the person is not an individual and is organized under or created by the laws of the United States or of any state or other place subject to the jurisdiction of the United States and has its principal place of business in the United States; or
(D) a partnership, association, corporation, organization, or other combination of persons organized under the laws of or having its principal place of business in a foreign country;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-068__subsec_e__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>foreign owner means a person for whom a foreign national holds, owns, controls, or otherwise has directly or indirectly acquired beneficial ownership of equity or voting shares in a corporation in an amount equal to or greater than 50 percent of all corporate voting shares outstanding or all corporate equity;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-068__subsec_e__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>media communication means a communication
(A)  in a news story, commentary, or editorial distributed through the facilities of a radio station, television station, cable television system, or satellite system, newspaper, magazine, or other periodical publication, unless the facilities are owned or controlled by a political party, political committee, or candidate; or
(B)  that constitutes a public debate or forum that includes at least two opposing candidates for an office or one advocate and one opponent of an issue, or that solely promotes such a debate or forum and is made by or on behalf of the person sponsoring the debate or forum, provided that the staging organization</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-068__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>is a charitable organization that does not make other covered expenditures and does not otherwise support or oppose any political candidate, political party, ballot propositions or questions, or initiative proposals or is a newspaper, radio station, television station, cable television system, or satellite system, newspaper, magazine, or other periodical publication, or other recognized news medium; and
(ii)  does not structure the debate to promote or advance one candidate or issue position over another;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-068__subsec_i__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>membership communication means a direct and private communication between a membership organization or union and one or more members of the organization or union, if the membership organization or union
(A)  has members with authority to administer the membership organization or union;
(B)  expressly states the qualifications and requirements for membership in articles, bylaws, or other formal organizational documents; and
(C)  is not organized primarily for the purpose of making covered expenditures or influencing elections, ballot propositions, ballot questions, or ballot initiative proposals;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-068__subsec_i__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shareholder communication means a direct and private communication between a corporation and shareholders, executives, or administrative personnel of the corporation.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-13-069">
            <num>15.13.069</num>
            <heading>Certain expenditures that comply with charitable gaming provisions permitted.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.13.069.   Certain expenditures that comply with charitable gaming provisions permitted.
Notwithstanding another provision of this title, a charitable gaming permittee that is a qualified organization under
AS 05.15.690
may use the net proceeds of a raffle or lottery to make expenditures for the purposes permitted under
AS 05.15.150
(a)(3).</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-13-070">
            <num>15.13.070</num>
            <heading>Limitations on amount of political contributions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-13-070__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An individual or group may make contributions, subject only to the limitations of this chapter and
AS 24.45
, including the limitations on the maximum amounts set out in this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-070__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An individual may contribute not more than</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-070__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>$500 per year to a nongroup entity for the purpose of influencing the nomination or election of a candidate, to a candidate, to an individual who conducts a write-in campaign as a candidate, or to a group that is not a political party;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-070__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>$5,000 per year to a political party.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-070__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A group that is not a political party may contribute not more than $1,000 per year</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-070__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to a candidate, or to an individual who conducts a write-in campaign as a candidate;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-070__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to another group, to a nongroup entity, or to a political party.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-070__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A political party may contribute to a candidate, or to an individual who conducts a write-in campaign, for the following offices an amount not to exceed</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-070__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>$100,000 per year, if the election is for governor or lieutenant governor;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-070__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>$15,000 per year, if the election is for the state senate;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-070__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>$10,000 per year, if the election is for the state house of representatives; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-070__subsec_d__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>$5,000 per year, if the election is for
(A) delegate to a constitutional convention;
(B) judge seeking retention; or
(C) municipal office.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-070__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This section does not prohibit a candidate from using up to a total of $1,000 from campaign contributions in a year to pay the cost of</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-070__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>attendance by a candidate or guests of the candidate at an event or other function sponsored by a political party or by a subordinate unit of a political party;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-070__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>membership in a political party, subordinate unit of a political party, or other entity within a political party, or subscription to a publication from a political party; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-070__subsec_e__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>co-sponsorship of an event or other function sponsored by a political party or by a subordinate unit of a political party.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-070__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A nongroup entity may contribute not more than $1,000 a year to another nongroup entity for the purpose of influencing the nomination or election of a candidate, to a candidate, to an individual who conducts a write-in campaign as a candidate, to a group, or to a political party.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-070__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Where contributions are made to a joint campaign for governor and lieutenant governor,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-070__subsec_g__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an individual may contribute not more than $1,000 per year; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-070__subsec_g__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a group may contribute not more than $2,000 per year.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-13-072">
            <num>15.13.072</num>
            <heading>Restrictions on solicitation and acceptance of contributions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-13-072__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A candidate or an individual who has filed with the commission the document necessary to permit that individual to incur election-related expenses under
AS 15.13.100
may not solicit or accept a contribution from</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-072__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a person not authorized by law to make a contribution;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-072__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an individual who is not a resident of the state at the time the contribution is made, except as provided in (e) of this section;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-072__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a group organized under the laws of another state, resident in another state, or whose participants are not residents of this state at the time the contribution is made; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-072__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a person registered as a lobbyist if the contribution violates
AS 15.13.074</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-072__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or
AS 24.45.121
(a)(8).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-072__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A candidate or an individual who has filed with the commission the document necessary to permit the individual to incur election-related expenses under
AS 15.13.100
, or a group, may not solicit or accept a cash contribution that exceeds $100.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-072__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An individual, or one acting directly or indirectly on behalf of that individual, may not solicit or accept a contribution</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-072__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>before the date for which contributions may be made as determined under
AS 15.13.074</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-072__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>later than the day after which contributions may not be made as determined under
AS 15.13.074</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-072__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>While the legislature is convened in a regular or special legislative session, a legislator or legislative employee may not solicit or accept a contribution to be used for the purpose of influencing the outcome of an election under this chapter unless</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-072__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>it is an election in which the legislator or legislative employee is a candidate and the contribution is for that legislator's or legislative employee's campaign;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-072__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the solicitation or acceptance occurs during the 90 days immediately preceding that election; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-072__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the solicitation or acceptance occurs in a place other than the capital city or a municipality in which the legislature is convened in special session if the legislature is convened in a municipality other than the capital city.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-072__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A candidate or an individual who has filed with the commission the document necessary to permit that individual to incur election-related expenses under
AS 15.13.100
may solicit or accept contributions from an individual who is not a resident of the state at the time the contribution is made if the amounts contributed by individuals who are not residents do not exceed</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-072__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>$20,000 a calendar year, if the candidate or individual is seeking the office of governor or lieutenant governor;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-072__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>$5,000 a calendar year, if the candidate or individual is seeking the office of state senator;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-072__subsec_e__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>$3,000 a calendar year, if the candidate or individual is seeking the office of state representative or municipal or other office.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-072__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A group or political party may solicit or accept contributions from an individual who is not a resident of the state at the time the contribution is made, but the amounts accepted from individuals who are not residents may not exceed 10 percent of total contributions made to the group or political party during the calendar or group year in which the contributions are received.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-072__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A candidate or an individual who has filed with the commission the document necessary to permit that individual to incur election-related expenses under
AS 15.13.100
for election or reelection to the office of governor or lieutenant governor may not solicit or accept a contribution in the capital city while the legislature is convened in a regular or special legislative session.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-072__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A nongroup entity may solicit or accept contributions for the purpose of influencing the nomination or election of a candidate from an individual who is not a resident of the state at the time the contribution is made or from an entity organized under the laws of another state, resident in another state, or whose participants are not residents of this state at the time the contribution is made. The amounts accepted by the nongroup entity from these individuals and entities for the purpose of influencing the nomination or election of a candidate may not exceed 10 percent of total contributions made to the nongroup entity for the purpose of influencing the nomination or election of a candidate during the calendar year in which the contributions are received.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-13-074">
            <num>15.13.074</num>
            <heading>Prohibited contributions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-13-074__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person, group, or nongroup entity may not make a contribution if the making of the contribution would violate this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-074__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person or group may not make a contribution anonymously, using a fictitious name, or using the name of another. Individuals, persons, nongroup entities, or groups subject to
AS 15.13.040</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-074__subsec_r">
              <num>(r)</num>
              <content>
                <p>may not contribute or accept $2,000 or more of dark money as that term is defined in
AS 15.13.400</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-074__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person or group may not make a contribution</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-074__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to a candidate or an individual who files with the commission the document necessary to permit that individual to incur certain election-related expenses as authorized by
AS 15.13.100
when the office is to be filled at a general election before the date that is 18 months before the general election;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-074__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to a candidate or an individual who files with the commission the document necessary to permit that individual to incur certain election-related expenses as authorized by
AS 15.13.100
for an office that is to be filled at a special election or municipal election before the date that is 18 months before the date of the regular municipal election or that is before the date of the proclamation of the special election at which the candidate or individual seeks election to public office; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-074__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to any candidate later than the 45th day
(A) after the date of the primary or special primary election if the candidate was not chosen to appear on the general or special election ballot at the primary or special primary election; or
(B) after the date of the general or special election, or after the date of a municipal or municipal runoff election.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-074__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person or group may not make a contribution to a candidate or a person or group who is prohibited by
AS 15.13.072</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-074__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>from accepting it.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-074__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person or group may not make a cash contribution that exceeds $100.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-074__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A corporation, company, partnership, firm, association, entity recognized as tax-exempt under 26 U.S.C. 501(c)(3) (Internal Revenue Code), organization, business trust or surety, labor union, or publicly funded entity that does not satisfy the definition of group or nongroup entity in
AS 15.13.400
may not make a contribution to a candidate, group, or nongroup entity.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-074__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An individual required to register as a lobbyist under
AS 24.45
may not make a contribution to a candidate for the legislature at any time the individual is subject to the registration requirement under
AS 24.45
and for one year after the date of the individual's initial registration or its renewal. However, the individual may make a contribution under this section to a candidate for the legislature in a district in which the individual is eligible to vote or will be eligible to vote on the date of the election. An individual who is subject to the restrictions of this subsection shall report to the commission, on a form provided by the commission, each contribution made while required to register as a lobbyist under
AS 24.45
. Upon request of the commission, the information required under this subsection shall be submitted electronically. This subsection does not apply to a representational lobbyist as defined in regulations of the commission.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-074__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding
AS 15.13.070
, a candidate for governor or lieutenant governor and a group that is not a political party and that, under the definition of the term group, is presumed to be controlled by a candidate for governor or lieutenant governor, may not make a contribution to a candidate for another office, to a person who conducts a write-in campaign as a candidate for other office, or to another group of amounts received by that candidate or controlled group as contributions between January 1 and the date of the general election of the year of a general election for an election for governor and lieutenant governor. This subsection does not prohibit</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-074__subsec_h__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the group described in this subsection from making contributions to the candidates for governor and lieutenant governor whom the group supports; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-074__subsec_h__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the governor or lieutenant governor, or the group described in this subsection, from making contributions under
AS 15.13.116</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-074__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A nongroup entity may not solicit or accept a contribution to be used for the purpose of influencing the outcome of an election unless the potential contributor is notified that the contribution may be used for that purpose.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-13-076">
            <num>15.13.076</num>
            <heading>Authorized recipients of contributions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.13.076.   Authorized recipients of contributions.
A contribution to a
(1) candidate may be received only by
(A) the candidate; or
(B) the candidate's campaign treasurer or a deputy campaign treasurer;
(2) group may be received only by the group's campaign treasurer or a deputy treasurer.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-13-078">
            <num>15.13.078</num>
            <heading>Contributions and loans from the candidate.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-13-078__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The provisions of this chapter do not prohibit the individual who is a candidate from giving any amount of the candidate's own money or other thing of value to the campaign of the candidate. Donations made by the candidate to the candidate's own campaign shall be reported as contributions in accordance with
AS 15.13.040
and 15.13.110.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-078__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The provisions of this chapter do not prohibit the individual who is a candidate from lending any amount to the campaign of the candidate. Loans made by the candidate shall be reported as contributions in accordance with
AS 15.13.040
and 15.13.110. However, the candidate may not</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-078__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>recover, under this section and
AS 15.13.116</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-078__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>the legislature; or
(ii) delegate to a constitutional convention;
(C) $10,000, if the candidate was a judge seeking retention;
(D) $5,000, if the candidate ran in a municipal election; or</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-078__subsec_i__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>repay a loan that the candidate has made to the candidate's own campaign unless, within five days of making the loan, the candidate notifies the commission, on a form provided by the commission, of the candidate's intention to repay the loan under
AS 15.13.116</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-078__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>On and after the date determined under
AS 15.13.110
as the last day of the period ending three days before the due date of the report required to be filed under
AS 15.13.110
(a)(1) and until the date of the election for which the report is filed, a candidate may not give or loan to the candidate's campaign the candidate's money or other thing of value of the candidate in an amount that exceeds $5,000.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-078__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The provisions of this section apply only to the individual who is a candidate, as that term is defined by
AS 15.13.400</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-13-082">
            <num>15.13.082</num>
            <heading>Limitations on expenditures.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-13-082__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A candidate or group may not make an expenditure in cash that exceeds $100 unless the candidate, or the campaign treasurer or deputy campaign treasurer, obtains a written receipt from the person to whom the expenditure is made.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-082__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person, other than an individual exempt from reporting under
AS 15.13.040
(h), may not make an expenditure unless the source of the expenditure has been disclosed as required by this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-082__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a candidate receives a contribution in the form of cash, check, money order, or other negotiable instrument and is subject to being reported to the commission under this chapter, the candidate may neither expend the contribution nor, in the case of a negotiable instrument, convert it to cash unless the candidate, campaign treasurer, or deputy campaign treasurer first records the following information for disclosure to the commission:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-082__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name, address, principal occupation, and employer of the contributor; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-082__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the date and amount of the contribution.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-13-084">
            <num>15.13.084</num>
            <heading>Prohibited expenditures.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-13-084__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>a billboard or sign; or
(ii) printed material, other than an advertisement made in a newspaper or other periodical;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-084__subsec_i__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>using a fictitious name or using the name of another.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-13-086">
            <num>15.13.086</num>
            <heading>Authorized makers of expenditures.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.13.086.   Authorized makers of expenditures.
An expenditure
(1) authorized by or in behalf of a candidate may be made only by
(A) the candidate; or
(B) the candidate's campaign treasurer or a deputy campaign treasurer;
(2) authorized by
AS 15.13.067
(3) by or in behalf of a group may be made only by the group's campaign treasurer.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-13-090">
            <num>15.13.090</num>
            <heading>Identification of communication.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-13-090__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>All communications shall be clearly identified by the words paid for by followed by the name and address of the person paying for the communication. In addition, except as provided by (d) of this section, a person shall clearly</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-090__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide the person's address or the person's principal place of business;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-090__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for a person other than an individual or candidate, include
(A) the name and title of the person's principal officer;
(B) a statement from the principal officer approving the communication; and
(C) unless the person is a political party, identification of the name and city and state of residence or principal place of business, as applicable, of each of the person's three largest contributors under
AS 15.13.040</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-090__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The provisions of (a) of this section do not apply when the communication</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-090__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is paid for by an individual acting independently of any other person;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-090__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is made to influence the outcome of a ballot proposition as that term is defined by
AS 15.13.065</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-090__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is made for
(A) a billboard or sign; or
(B) printed material other than an advertisement made in a newspaper or other periodical.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-090__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To satisfy the requirements of (a)(1) of this section and, if applicable, (a)(2)(C) of this section, a communication that includes a print or video component must have the following statement or statements placed in the communication so as to be easily discernible, and, in a broadcast, cable, satellite, Internet or other digital communication, the statement must remain onscreen throughout the entirety of the communication; the second statement is not required if the person paying for the communication has no contributors or is a political party:
This communication was paid for by (person's name and city and state of principal place of business). The top contributors of (person's name) are (the name and city and state of residence or principal place of business, as applicable, of the largest contributors to the person under
AS 15.13.090
(a)(2)(C)).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-090__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding the requirements of (a) of this section, in a communication transmitted through radio or other audio media and in a communication that includes an audio component, the following statements must be read in a manner that is easily heard; the second statement is not required if the person paying for the communication has no contributors or is a political party:
This communication was paid for by (person's name). The top contributors of (person's name) are (the name of the largest contributors to the person under
AS 15.13.090
(a)(2)(C)).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-090__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Contributors required to be identified under (a)(2)(C) of this section must be listed in order of the amount of their contributions. If more than three of the largest contributors to a person paying for a communication contribute equal amounts, the person may select which of the contributors of equal amounts to identify under (a)(2)(C) of this section. In no case shall a person be required to identify more than three contributors under (a)(2)(C) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-090__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The provisions of this subsection apply to a person who makes an independent expenditure for a communication described in (a) of this section. If the person paying for the communication is not a natural person, the provisions also apply to the responsible officer or officers of the corporation, company, partnership, firm, association, organization, labor organization, business trust, or society who approve the independent expenditure for the communication. A person who makes a communication under this subsection may not, with actual malice, include within or as a part of the communication a false statement of material fact about a candidate for election to public office that constitutes defamation of the candidate. For purposes of this subsection, a statement constitutes defamation of the candidate if the statement</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-090__subsec_f__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>exposes the candidate to strong disapproval, contempt, ridicule, or reproach; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-090__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>tends to deprive the candidate of the benefit of public confidence.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-090__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To satisfy the requirements of (a)(1) of this section and, if applicable, (a)(2)(C) of this section, a communication paid for by an outside-funded entity as that term is defined in
AS 15.13.400</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-090__subsec_g__subsec_15">
                <num>(15)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>that includes a print or video component must have the following statement placed in the communication so as to be easily discernible, and, in a broadcast, cable, satellite, Internet or other digital communication, the statement must remain onscreen throughout the entirety of the communication; the statement is not required if the outside entity paying for the communication has no contributors or is a political party: A MAJORITY OF CONTRIBUTIONS TO (OUTSIDE-FUNDED ENTITY'S NAME) CAME FROM OUTSIDE THE STATE OF ALASKA.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-13-095">
            <num>15.13.095</num>
            <heading>False statements in telephone polling and calls to convince.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-13-095__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A candidate who is damaged as the result of a false statement about the candidate made with knowledge that it was false, or with reckless disregard for whether it was false or not, made as part of a telephone poll or an organized series of calls, and made with the intent to convince potential voters concerning the outcome of an election in which the candidate is running may recover damages in an action in superior court under this section against the individual who made the telephone call, the individual's employer, and the person who contracted for or authorized the poll or calls to convince. However, the employer of the individual or the person who contracted for or authorized the poll or calls to convince is liable to the defamed candidate only if the employer or person authorized the statement to be made, knowing that it was false or with reckless disregard for whether it was false or not, as part of the poll or calls to convince.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-095__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The court may award damages, including punitive damages. If the court finds that the result of the statement places the integrity of the election process in substantial doubt, the eligibility of the successful candidate to hold the office to which elected shall be determined as provided in
AS 15.56.110</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-095__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or, in the case of a candidate for governor or lieutenant governor, by impeachment under art. II, sec. 20, Constitution of the State of Alaska.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-13-100">
            <num>15.13.100</num>
            <heading>Expenditures before filing.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.13.100.   Expenditures before filing.
A political campaign expenditure may not be made or incurred by a person in an election or by a person or group with the person's knowledge and on the person's behalf before the date upon which the person files for nomination for the office which the person seeks, except for personal travel expenses or for opinion surveys or polls.  These expenditures must be included in the first report required under this chapter after filing for office.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-13-110">
            <num>15.13.110</num>
            <heading>Filing of reports.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-13-110__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each candidate, group, and nongroup entity shall make a full report in accordance with
AS 15.13.040
for the period ending three days before the due date of the report and beginning on the last day covered by the most recent previous report. If the report is a first report, it must cover the period from the beginning of the campaign to the date three days before the due date of the report. If the report is a report due February 15, it must cover the period beginning on the last day covered by the most recent previous report or on the day that the campaign started, whichever is later, and ending on February 1 of that year. The report shall be filed</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-110__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>30 days before the election; however, this report is not required if the deadline for filing a nominating petition or declaration of candidacy is within 30 days of the election;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-110__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>one week before the election;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-110__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>105 days after a special election; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-110__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>February 15 for expenditures made and contributions received that were not reported previously, including, if applicable, all amounts expended from a public office expense term account established under
AS 15.13.116</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-110__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each contribution that exceeds $250 and that is made within nine days of the election shall be reported to the commission by date, amount, and contributor within 24 hours of receipt by the candidate, group, campaign treasurer, or deputy campaign treasurer. Each contribution to a nongroup entity for the purpose of influencing the outcome of an election that exceeds $250 and that is made within nine days of the election shall be reported to the commission by date, amount, and contributor within 24 hours of receipt by the nongroup entity.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-110__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>All reports required by this chapter shall be filed with the commission's central office and shall be kept open to public inspection. The commission shall keep a report filed on paper under
AS 15.13.040</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-110__subsec_m">
              <num>(m)</num>
              <content>
                <p>open to public inspection by scanning the report and posting a copy of the scanned image on the commission's Internet website within two working days after the report is filed. The commission shall prepare a summary of each report, which shall be made available to the public at cost upon request. Each summary must use uniform categories of reporting. Summaries for reports filed</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-110__subsec_m__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>electronically shall be made available within 30 days after the report is filed; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-110__subsec_m__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>on paper shall be made available within 30 days after each election.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-110__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 35 ch 126 SLA 1994.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-110__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A group formed to sponsor a referendum or a recall shall report 30 days after its first filing with the lieutenant governor. Thereafter, each group shall report within 10 days after the end of each calendar quarter on the contributions received and expenditures made during the preceding calendar quarter until reports are due under (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-110__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>During the year in which the election is scheduled, each of the following shall file the campaign disclosure reports in the manner and at the times required by this section:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-110__subsec_f__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a person who, under the regulations adopted by the commission to implement
AS 15.13.100
, indicates an intention to become a candidate for elective state executive or legislative office;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-110__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a person who campaigns as a write-in candidate for elective state executive or legislative office at the general election; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-110__subsec_f__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a group or nongroup entity that receives contributions or makes expenditures on behalf of or in opposition to a person described in (1) or (2) of this subsection, except as provided for certain independent expenditures by nongroup entities in
AS 15.13.135</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-110__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An initiative committee, person, group, or nongroup entity receiving contributions exceeding $500 or making expenditures exceeding $500 in a calendar year in support of or in opposition to an initiative on the ballot in a statewide election or an initiative proposal application filed with the lieutenant governor under
AS 15.45.020
shall file a report within 10 days after the end of each calendar quarter on the contributions received and expenditures made during the preceding calendar quarter until reports are due under (a) and (b) of this section. If the report is a first report, it must cover the period beginning on the day an initiative proposal application is filed under
AS 15.45.020
and ending three days before the due date of the report.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-110__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An independent expenditure report required under
AS 15.13.040</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-110__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>shall be filed with the commission not later than 10 days after an independent expenditure has been made. However, an independent expenditure that exceeds $250 and that is made within nine days of an election shall be reported to the commission not later than 24 hours after the expenditure is made.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-110__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>During a campaign period, the commission may not change the manner or format in which reports required of a candidate under this chapter must be filed. In this subsection, campaign period means the period beginning on the date that a candidate becomes eligible to receive campaign contributions under this chapter and ending on the date that a final report for that same campaign must be filed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-110__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before the primary election, a candidate seeking nomination by petition under
AS 15.25.140
 15.25.200 for the office of governor, lieutenant governor, state senator, or state representative shall file the reports under (a)(1) and (2) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-110__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Once contributions from an individual, person, nongroup entity, or group to an entity that made one or more independent expenditures in one or more candidate elections in the previous election cycle, that is making one or more independent expenditures in one or more candidate elections in the current election cycle, or that the contributor knows or has reason to know is likely to make independent expenditures in one or more candidate elections in the current election cycle exceed $2,000 in a single year, that entity shall report that contribution, and all subsequent contributions, not later than 24 hours after receipt. For purposes of this subsection, the entity is required to certify and report the true source, and all intermediaries, if any, of the contribution as defined by
AS 15.13.400</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-13-111">
            <num>15.13.111</num>
            <heading>Preservation of records.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-13-111__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each person required to report under this chapter shall preserve all records necessary to substantiate information required to be reported under this chapter for a period of six years from the date of the election for which the information was required to be reported, unless the records have been submitted to the commission under (c) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-111__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Information preserved under (a) of this section must be made available for inspection by the commission.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-111__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A candidate for state elected office who was not elected or a person who has left state elected office may submit the records required to be preserved under (a) of this section to the commission electronically. Records submitted under this subsection shall be preserved by the commission for a period of six years from the date of the election for which the information was required to be reported.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-13-112">
            <num>15.13.112</num>
            <heading>Uses of campaign contributions held by candidate or group.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-13-112__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as otherwise provided, campaign contributions held by a candidate or group may be used only to pay the expenses of the candidate or group, and the campaign expenses incurred by the candidate or group, that reasonably relate to election campaign activities, and in those cases only as authorized by this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-112__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Campaign contributions held by a candidate or group may not be</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-112__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>used to give a personal benefit to the candidate or to another person;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-112__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>converted to personal income of the candidate;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-112__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>loaned to a person;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-112__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>knowingly used to pay more than the fair market value for goods or services purchased for the campaign;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-112__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>used to pay a criminal fine;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-112__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>used to pay civil penalties; however, campaign contributions held by a candidate or group may be used to pay a civil penalty assessed under this chapter if authorized by the commission or a court after it first determines that
(A) the candidate, campaign treasurer, and deputy campaign treasurer did not cause or participate in the violation for which the civil penalty is imposed and exercised a reasonable level of oversight over the campaign; and
(B) the candidate, campaign treasurer, and deputy campaign treasurer cooperated in the revelation of the violation and in its immediate correction; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-112__subsec_b__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>used to make contributions to another candidate or to a group; however, it is not a violation of this paragraph if, in circumstances in which a candidate or group participates in a shared campaign activity, the candidate or group participating in the activity
(A) uses campaign contributions of the candidate or group for payment of</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-112__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>all of the shared campaign activity expense; or
(ii) more than the candidate's or group's pro rata share of the activity expense; and
(B) receives, within seven days after payment of the expense, complete reimbursement of the amount of campaign contributions used for payments made on behalf of another candidate or group participating in the activity.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-112__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A candidate may use up to a total of $1,000 in campaign contributions in a year to pay the cost of</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-112__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>attending, or paying the cost for guests of the candidate to attend, an event or other function sponsored by a political party or subordinate unit of a political party;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-112__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>membership in a political party, subordinate unit of a political party, or other entity within a political party, or subscription to a publication from a political party; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-112__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>co-sponsorship of an event or other function sponsored by a political party or by a subordinate unit of a political party.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-13-114">
            <num>15.13.114</num>
            <heading>Disposition of prohibited contributions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-13-114__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A candidate, group, or nongroup entity that receives and accepts a contribution given in violation of
AS 15.13.072
or 15.13.074 shall immediately, upon discovery that the contribution is prohibited, return it to the contributor. A candidate, group, or nongroup entity that receives and accepts a contribution in excess of the limitation on contributions set out in
AS 15.13.070
shall immediately, upon discovery of the prohibited excess contribution, return the excess to the contributor. If the contribution or excess amount cannot be returned in the same form, the equivalent value of the contribution or excess amount shall be returned.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-114__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An anonymous contribution is forfeited to the state unless the contributor is identified within five days of its receipt. Money that forfeits to the state under this subsection shall be delivered immediately to the Department of Revenue for deposit in the general fund.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-13-116">
            <num>15.13.116</num>
            <heading>Disbursement of campaign assets after election.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-13-116__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A candidate who, after the date of the general, special, municipal, or municipal runoff election or after the date the candidate withdraws as a candidate, whichever comes first, holds unused campaign contributions shall distribute the amount held on February 1 for a general election or within 90 days after a special election. The distribution may only be made to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-116__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>pay bills incurred for expenditures reasonably related to the campaign and the winding up of the affairs of the campaign, including a victory or thank you party, thank you advertisements, and thank you gifts to campaign employees and volunteers, and to pay expenditures associated with post-election fund raising that may be needed to raise funds to pay off campaign debts;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-116__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>make donations, without condition, to
(A) a political party;
(B) the state's general fund;
(C) a municipality of the state; or
(D) the federal government;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-116__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>make donations, without condition, to organizations qualified as charitable organizations under 26 U.S.C. 501(c)(3) if the organization is not controlled by the candidate or a member of the candidate's immediate family;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-116__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>repay loans from the candidate to the candidate's own campaign under
AS 15.13.078</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-116__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>repay contributions to contributors, but only if repayment of the contribution is made pro rata in approximate proportion to the contributions made using one of the following, as the candidate determines:
(A) to all contributors;
(B) to contributors who have contributed most recently; or
(C) to contributors who have made larger contributions;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-116__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establish a fund for, and from that fund to pay, attorney fees or costs incurred in the prosecution or defense of an administrative or civil judicial action that directly concerns a challenge to the victory or defeat of the candidate in the election;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-116__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>transfer all or a portion of the unused campaign contributions to an account for a future election campaign; a transfer under this paragraph is limited to
(A) $50,000, if the transfer is made by a candidate for governor or lieutenant governor;
(B) $10,000, if the transfer is made by a candidate for the state senate;
(C) $5,000, if the transfer is made by a candidate for the state house of representatives; and
(D) $5,000, if the transfer is made by a candidate for an office not described in (A)  (C) of this paragraph;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-116__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>transfer all or a portion of the unused campaign contributions to a public office expense term account; a transfer under this paragraph is subject to the following:
(A) the authority to transfer is limited to candidates who are elected to the state legislature;
(B) the public office expense term account established under this paragraph may be used only for expenses associated with the candidate's serving as a member of the legislature;
(C) all amounts expended from the public office expense term account shall be annually accounted for under
AS 15.13.110</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-116__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>transfer all or a portion of the unused campaign contributions to a municipal office account; a transfer under this paragraph is subject to the following:
(A) the authority to transfer is limited to candidates who are elected to municipal office, including a municipal school board;
(B) the municipal office account established under this paragraph may be used only for expenses associated with the candidate's serving as mayor or as a member of the assembly, city council, or school board;
(C) all amounts expended from the municipal office account shall be annually accounted for under
AS 15.13.110</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-116__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After a general, special, municipal, or municipal runoff election, a candidate may retain the ownership of one computer and one printer and of personal property, except money, that was acquired by and for use in the campaign. The current fair market value of the property retained, exclusive of the computer and printer, may not exceed $5,000. All other property shall be disposed of, or sold and the sale proceeds disposed of, in accordance with (a) or (c) of this section. Notwithstanding any other provision of this chapter,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-116__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a candidate may (A) retain a bulk mailing permit that was paid for with campaign funds, and (B) use personal funds, campaign funds, or unused campaign contributions transferred to a public office expense term account under (a)(8) of this section to pay the continuing charges for the permit after the election; money used to continue the life of the permit is not considered to be a contribution under this chapter; in addition to any other use permitted under this chapter, during the candidate's term of office, the candidate may use the bulk mailing permit for mailings associated with service in the office to which the candidate was elected; during the candidate's term of office, if the candidate files a declaration of candidacy or the document necessary to permit the candidate to incur election-related expenses under
AS 15.13.100
for the same or a different elective office, the candidate may also use the bulk mailing permit in that election campaign;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-116__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a candidate may retain campaign photographs and use the photographs for any purpose associated with service in the office to which the candidate was elected;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-116__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a candidate may retain seasonal greeting cards purchased with campaign funds; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-116__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>campaign signs prepared for an election that has already taken place have no monetary value and may be retained or disposed of at the candidate's discretion.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-116__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Property remaining after disbursements are made under (a)  (b) of this section is forfeited to the state. Within 30 days, the candidate shall deliver the property to the Department of Revenue. The Department of Revenue shall deposit any money received into the general fund and dispose of any other property in accordance with law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-116__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 4 ch 44 SLA 2012.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-13-135">
            <num>15.13.135</num>
            <heading>Independent expenditures for or against candidates.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-13-135__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An independent expenditure supporting or opposing a candidate for election to public office, except an independent expenditure made by a nongroup entity with an annual operating budget of $250 or less, shall be reported in accordance with
AS 15.13.040
and 15.13.100  15.13.110 and other requirements of this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-135__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who makes independent expenditures for a mass mailing, for distribution of campaign literature of any sort, for a television, radio, newspaper, or magazine advertisement, or any other communication that supports or opposes a candidate for election to public office</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-135__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall comply with
AS 15.13.090
; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-135__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall place the following statement in the mailing, literature, advertisement, or other communication so that it is readily and easily discernible:
This NOTICE TO VOTERS is required by Alaska law. (I/we) certify that this (mailing/literature/advertisement) is not authorized, paid for, or approved by the candidate.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-13-140">
            <num>15.13.140</num>
            <heading>Independent expenditures for or against ballot proposition or question.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-13-140__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 19 ch 36 SLA 2010.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-140__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An independent expenditure for or against a ballot proposition or question</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-140__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall be reported in accordance with
AS 15.13.040
and 15.13.100  15.13.110 and other requirements of this chapter; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-140__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>may not be made if the expenditure is prohibited by
AS 15.13.145
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-13-145">
            <num>15.13.145</num>
            <heading>Money of the state and its political subdivisions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-13-145__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (b) and (c) of this section, each of the following may not use money held by the entity to influence the outcome of the election of a candidate to a state or municipal office:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-145__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the state, its agencies, and its corporations;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-145__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the University of Alaska and its Board of Regents;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-145__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>municipalities, school districts, and regional educational attendance areas, or another political subdivision of the state; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-145__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an officer or employee of an entity identified in (1)  (3) of this subsection.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-145__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Money held by an entity identified in (a)(1)  (3) of this section may be used to influence the outcome of an election concerning a ballot proposition or question, but only if the funds have been specifically appropriated for that purpose by a state law or a municipal ordinance.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-145__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Money held by an entity identified in (a)(1)  (3) of this section may be used</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-145__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to disseminate information about the time and place of an election and to hold an election;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-145__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to provide the public with nonpartisan information about a ballot proposition or question or about all the candidates seeking election to a particular public office.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-145__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When expenditure of money is authorized by (b) or (c) of this section and is used to influence the outcome of an election, the expenditures shall be reported to the commission in the same manner as an individual is required to report under
AS 15.13.040
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-13-150">
            <num>15.13.150</num>
            <heading>Election educational activities not prohibited.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.13.150.   Election educational activities not prohibited.
This chapter does not prohibit a person from engaging in educational election-related communications and activities, including
(1) the publication of the date and location of an election;
(2) the education of students about voting and elections;
(3) the sponsorship of candidate debate forums open to the public;
(4) participation in get-out-the-vote or voter registration drives that do not favor a particular candidate, political party, or political position;
(5) the dissemination of the views of all candidates running for a particular office.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-13-155">
            <num>15.13.155</num>
            <heading>Restrictions on earned income and honoraria.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-13-155__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A candidate for the state legislature, for governor, or for lieutenant governor, including an individual campaigning as a write-in candidate for the office, may not</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-155__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>seek or accept compensation for personal services that involves payments that are not commensurate with the services rendered taking into account the higher rates generally charged by specialists in a profession; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-155__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>accept a payment of anything of value, except for actual and necessarily incurred travel expenses, for an appearance or speech; this paragraph does not apply to the salary paid to the candidate for making an appearance or speech as part of the candidate's normal course of employment.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-155__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (a) of this section, a candidate for the state legislature, for governor, or for lieutenant governor, including an individual campaigning as a write-in candidate for the office, may accept a payment for an appearance or speech if the appearance or speech is not connected with the individual's status as a state official or as a candidate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-13-374">
            <num>15.13.374</num>
            <heading>Advisory opinion.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-13-374__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Any person may request an advisory opinion from the commission concerning this chapter,
AS 24.45
,
AS 24.60.200
 24.60.260, or
AS 39.50
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-374__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A request for an advisory opinion</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-374__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>must be in writing or contained in a message submitted by electronic mail;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-374__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>must describe a specific transaction or activity that the requesting person is presently engaged in or intends to undertake in the future;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-374__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>must include a description of all relevant facts, including the identity of the person requesting the advisory opinion; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-374__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>may not concern a hypothetical situation or the activity of a third party.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-374__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Within seven days after receiving a request satisfying the requirements of (b) of this section, the executive director of the commission shall recommend a draft advisory opinion for the commission to consider at its next meeting.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-374__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The approval of a draft advisory opinion requires the affirmative vote of four members of the commission. A draft advisory opinion failing to receive four affirmative votes of the members of the commission is disapproved.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-374__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A complaint under
AS 15.13.380
may not be considered about a person involved in a transaction or activity that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-374__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>was described in an advisory opinion approved under (d) of this section;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-374__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is indistinguishable from the description of an activity that was approved in an advisory opinion approved under (d) of this section; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-374__subsec_e__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>was undertaken after the executive director of the commission recommended a draft advisory opinion under (c) of this section and before the commission acted on the draft advisory opinion under (d) of this section, if
(A) the draft advisory opinion would have approved the transaction or activity described; and
(B) the commission disapproved the draft advisory opinion.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-374__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Advisory opinion requests and advisory opinions are public records subject to inspection and copying under
AS 40.25.100
 40.25.295, except that, if a person requesting an advisory opinion requests that the person's name be kept confidential, the person's name shall be kept confidential and the commission shall redact the name of the requester from the request and from the advisory opinion before making the request and opinion public.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-13-380">
            <num>15.13.380</num>
            <heading>Violations; limitations on actions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-13-380__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Promptly after the final date for filing statements and reports under this chapter, the commission shall notify all persons who have become delinquent in filing them, including contributors who failed to file a statement in accordance with
AS 15.13.040
, and shall make available a list of those delinquent filers for public inspection. The commission shall also report to the attorney general the names of all candidates in an election whose campaign treasurers have failed to file the reports required by this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-380__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who believes a violation of this chapter or a regulation adopted under this chapter has occurred or is occurring may file an administrative complaint with the commission within five years after the date of the alleged violation. If a member of the commission has filed the complaint, that member may not participate as a commissioner in any proceeding of the commission with respect to the complaint. The commission may consider a complaint on an expedited basis or a regular basis.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-380__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The complainant or the respondent to the complaint may request in writing that the commission expedite consideration of the complaint. A request for expedited consideration must be accompanied by evidence to support expedited consideration and be served on the opposing party. The commission shall grant or deny the request within two days after receiving it. In deciding whether to expedite consideration, the commission shall consider such factors as whether the alleged violation, if not immediately restrained, could materially affect the outcome of an election or other impending event; whether the alleged violation could cause irreparable harm that penalties could not adequately remedy; and whether there is reasonable cause to believe that a violation has occurred or will occur. Notwithstanding the absence of a request to expedite consideration, the commission may independently expedite consideration of the complaint if the commission finds that the standards for expedited consideration set out in this subsection have been met.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-380__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the commission expedites consideration, the commission shall hold a hearing on the complaint within two days after granting expedited consideration. Not later than one day after affording the respondent notice and an opportunity to be heard, the commission shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-380__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>enter an emergency order requiring the violation to be ceased or to be remedied and assess civil penalties under
AS 15.13.390
if the commission finds that the respondent has engaged in or is about to engage in an act or practice that constitutes or will constitute a violation of this chapter or a regulation adopted under this chapter;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-380__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>enter an emergency order dismissing the complaint if the commission finds that the respondent has not or is not about to engage in an act or practice that constitutes or will constitute a violation of this chapter or a regulation adopted under this chapter; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-380__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>remand the complaint to the executive director of the commission for consideration by the commission on a regular rather than an expedited basis.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-380__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the commission accepts the complaint for consideration on a regular rather than an expedited basis, the commission shall notify the respondent within seven days after receiving the complaint and shall investigate the complaint. The respondent may answer the complaint by filing a written response with the commission within 15 days after the commission notifies the respondent of the complaint. The commission may grant the respondent additional time to respond to the complaint only for good cause. The commission shall hold a hearing on the complaint not later than 45 days after the respondent's written response is due. Not later than 10 days after the hearing, the commission shall issue its order. If the commission finds that the respondent has engaged in or is about to engage in an act or practice that constitutes or will constitute a violation of this chapter or a regulation adopted under this chapter, the commission shall enter an order requiring the violation to be ceased or to be remedied and shall assess civil penalties under
AS 15.13.390
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-380__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the complaint involves a challenge to the constitutionality of a statute or regulation, necessary witnesses that are not subject to the commission's subpoena authority, or other issues outside the commission's authority, the commission may request the attorney general to file a complaint in superior court alleging a violation of this chapter. The commission may request the attorney general to file a complaint in superior court to remedy the violation of a commission order.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-380__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A commission order under (d) or (e) of this section may be appealed to the superior court by either the complainant or respondent within 30 days in accordance with the Alaska Rules of Appellate Procedure.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-380__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the commission does not complete action on an administrative complaint within 90 days after the complaint was filed, the complainant may file a complaint in superior court alleging a violation of this chapter by a respondent as described in the administrative complaint filed with the commission. The complainant shall provide copies of the complaint filed in the superior court to the commission and the attorney general. This subsection does not create a private cause of action against the commission; against the commission's members, officers, or employees; or against the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-380__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a person who was a successful candidate or the campaign treasurer or deputy campaign treasurer of a person who was a successful candidate is convicted of a violation of this chapter, after the candidate is sworn into office, proceedings shall be held and appropriate action taken in accordance with</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-380__subsec_i__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>art. II, sec. 12, Constitution of the State of Alaska, if the successful candidate is a member of the state legislature;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-380__subsec_i__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>art. II, sec. 20, Constitution of the State of Alaska, if the successful candidate is governor or lieutenant governor;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-380__subsec_i__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the provisions of the call for the constitutional convention, if the successful candidate is a constitutional convention delegate;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-380__subsec_i__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>art. IV, sec. 10, Constitution of the State of Alaska, if the successful candidate is a judge.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-380__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Information developed by the commission under (b)  (e) of this section shall be considered during a proceeding under (i) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-380__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If, after a successful candidate is sworn into office, the successful candidate or the campaign treasurer or deputy campaign treasurer of the person who was a successful candidate is charged with a violation of this chapter, the case shall be promptly tried and accorded a preferred position for purposes of argument and decision so as to ensure a speedy disposition of the matter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-13-385">
            <num>15.13.385</num>
            <heading>Legal counsel.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-13-385__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The attorney general is legal counsel for the commission.  The attorney general shall advise the commission in legal matters arising in the discharge of its duties and represent the commission in actions to which it is a party.  If, in the opinion of the commission, the public interest warrants, the commission may request the chief justice of the supreme court to appoint a special prosecutor to represent the commission in a proceeding involving an alleged violation of this chapter and to prosecute that violation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-385__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the public interest warrants, the commission may employ temporary legal counsel from time to time in matters in which the commission is involved.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-13-390">
            <num>15.13.390</num>
            <heading>Civil penalty; late filing of required reports.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-13-390__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-390__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>fails to register when required by
AS 15.13.050</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-390__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or who fails to file a properly completed and certified report within the time required by
AS 15.13.040
, 15.13.060(b)  (d), 15.13.110(a)(1), (3), or (4), (e), or (f) is subject to a civil penalty of not more than $50 a day for each day the delinquency continues as determined by the commission subject to right of appeal to the superior court. A person who fails to file a properly completed and certified report within the time required by
AS 15.13.110
(a)(2) or 15.13.110(b) is subject to a civil penalty of not more than $500 a day for each day the delinquency continues as determined by the commission subject to right of appeal to the superior court;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-390__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>whether as a contributor or intermediary, delays in reporting a contribution as required by
AS 15.13.040</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-390__subsec_r">
              <num>(r)</num>
              <content>
                <p>is subject to a civil penalty of not more than $1,000 a day for each day the delinquency continues as determined by the commission subject to right of appeal to the superior court;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-390__subsec_r__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>whether as a contributor or intermediary, misreports or fails to disclose the true source of a contribution in violation of
AS 15.13.040</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-390__subsec_r">
              <num>(r)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or 15.13.074(b) is subject to a civil penalty of not more than the amount of the contribution that is the subject of the misreporting or failure to disclose; upon a showing that the violation was intentional, a civil penalty of not more than three times the amount of the contribution in violation may be imposed; these penalties as determined by the commission are subject to right of appeal to the superior court;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-390__subsec_r__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>violates a provision of this chapter, except as otherwise specified in this section, is subject to a civil penalty of not more than $50 a day for each day the violation continues as determined by the commission, subject to right of appeal to the superior court; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-390__subsec_r__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is assessed a civil penalty may submit to the commission an affidavit stating facts in mitigation; however, the imposition of the penalties prescribed in this section or in
AS 15.13.380
does not excuse that person from registering or filing reports required by this chapter.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-390__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When an administrative complaint has been filed under
AS 15.13.380
, the commission shall give the respondent due notice and an opportunity to be heard. If, at the conclusion of the hearing, the commission determines that the respondent engaged in the alleged violation, the commission shall assess</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-390__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>civil penalties under (a) of this section;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-390__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the commission's costs of investigation and adjudication; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-390__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>reasonable attorney fees.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-390__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission's determination under (b) of this section may be appealed to the superior court under
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-390__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When an action has been filed in the superior court under
AS 15.13.380
, upon proof of the violation, the court shall enter a judgment in the amount of the civil penalty authorized to be collected by (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-390__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the commission or superior court finds that the violation was not a repeat violation or was not part of a series or pattern of violations, was inadvertent, was quickly corrected, and had no adverse effect on the campaign of another, the commission or the court may</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-390__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>suspend imposition of the penalties; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-390__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>order the penalties set aside if the person does not engage in a similar violation for a period of one year.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-390__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A party who has filed a civil action under
AS 15.13.380</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-390__subsec_f__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is not entitled to trial by jury on the civil action;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-390__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is not entitled to be represented by legal counsel at public expense.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-13-400">
            <num>15.13.400</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-13-400__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>a candidate's campaign treasurer and a deputy campaign treasurer;
(ii) a member of the candidate's immediate family;
(iii) a person acting as agent for the candidate;
(iv) the candidate's campaign committee; and</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-400__subsec_v">
              <num>(v)</num>
              <content>
                <p>a group that makes expenditures or receives contributions with the authorization or consent, express or implied, or under the control, direct or indirect, of the candidate;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-400__subsec_v__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>commission means the Alaska Public Offices Commission;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-400__subsec_v__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>communication means an announcement or advertisement disseminated through print or broadcast media, including radio, television, cable, and satellite, the Internet, or through a mass mailing, excluding those placed by an individual or nongroup entity and costing $500 or less and those that do not directly or indirectly identify a candidate or proposition, as that term is defined in
AS 15.13.065</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-400__subsec_v__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>contribution
(A) means a purchase, payment, promise or obligation to pay, loan or loan guarantee, deposit or gift of money, goods, or services for which charge is ordinarily made, and includes the payment by a person other than a candidate or political party, or compensation for the personal services of another person, that is rendered to the candidate or political party, and that is made for the purpose of</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-400__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>influencing the nomination or election of a candidate;
(ii) influencing a ballot proposition or question; or
(iii) supporting or opposing an initiative proposal application filed with the lieutenant governor under
AS 15.45.020
;
(B) does not include</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-400__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>services provided without compensation by individuals volunteering a portion or all of their time on behalf of a political party, candidate, or ballot proposition or question;
(ii) ordinary hospitality in a home;
(iii) two or fewer mass mailings before each election by each political party describing members of the party running as candidates for public office in that election, which may include photographs, biographies, and information about the candidates;
(iv) the results of a poll limited to issues and not mentioning any candidate, unless the poll was requested by or designed primarily to benefit the candidate;</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-400__subsec_v">
              <num>(v)</num>
              <content>
                <p>any communication in the form of a newsletter from a legislator to the legislator's constituents, except a communication expressly advocating the election or defeat of a candidate or a newsletter or material in a newsletter that is clearly only for the private benefit of a legislator or a legislative employee;
(vi) a fundraising list provided without compensation by one candidate or political party to a candidate or political party; or
(vii) an opportunity to participate in a candidate forum provided to a candidate without compensation to the candidate by another person and for which a candidate is not ordinarily charged;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-400__subsec_v__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>dark money means a contribution whose source or sources, whether from wages, investment income, inheritance, or revenue generated from selling goods or services, is not disclosed to the public; notwithstanding the foregoing, to the extent a membership organization receives dues or contributions of less than $2,000 per person per year, the organization itself shall be considered the true source;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-400__subsec_v__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>electioneering communication means a communication that
(A) directly or indirectly identifies a candidate;
(B) addresses an issue of national, state, or local political importance and attributes a position on that issue to the candidate identified; and
(C) occurs within the 30 days preceding a general or municipal election;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-400__subsec_v__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>expenditure
(A) means a purchase or a transfer of money or anything of value, or promise or agreement to purchase or transfer money or anything of value, incurred or made for the purpose of</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-400__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>influencing the nomination or election of a candidate or of any individual who files for nomination at a later date and becomes a candidate;
(ii) use by a political party;
(iii) the payment by a person other than a candidate or political party of compensation for the personal services of another person that are rendered to a candidate or political party;
(iv) influencing the outcome of a ballot proposition or question; or</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-13-400__subsec_v">
              <num>(v)</num>
              <content>
                <p>supporting or opposing an initiative proposal application filed with the lieutenant governor under
AS 15.45.020
;
(B) does not include a candidate's filing fee or the cost of preparing reports and statements required by this chapter;
(C) includes an express communication and an electioneering communication, but does not include an issues communication;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-400__subsec_v__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>express communication means a communication that, when read as a whole and with limited reference to outside events, is susceptible of no other reasonable interpretation but as an exhortation to vote for or against a specific candidate;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-400__subsec_v__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>group means
(A) every state and regional executive committee of a political party;
(B) any combination of two or more individuals acting jointly who organize for the principal purpose of influencing the outcome of one or more elections and who take action the major purpose of which is to influence the outcome of an election; a group that makes expenditures or receives contributions with the authorization or consent, express or implied, or under the control, direct or indirect, of a candidate shall be considered to be controlled by that candidate; a group whose major purpose is to further the nomination, election, or candidacy of only one individual, or intends to expend more than 50 percent of its money on a single candidate, shall be considered to be controlled by that candidate and its actions done with the candidate's knowledge and consent unless, within 10 days from the date the candidate learns of the existence of the group the candidate files with the commission, on a form provided by the commission, an affidavit that the group is operating without the candidate's control; a group organized for more than one year preceding an election and endorsing candidates for more than one office or more than one political party is presumed not to be controlled by a candidate; however, a group that contributes more than 50 percent of its money to or on behalf of one candidate shall be considered to support only one candidate for purposes of
AS 15.13.070
, whether or not control of the group has been disclaimed by the candidate; and
(C) any combination of two or more individuals acting jointly who organize for the principal purpose of filing an initiative proposal application under
AS 15.45.020
or who file an initiative proposal application under
AS 15.45.020
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-400__subsec_v__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>immediate family means the spouse, parent, child, including a stepchild and an adopted child, and sibling of an individual;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-400__subsec_v__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>independent expenditure means an expenditure that is made without the direct or indirect consultation or cooperation with, or at the suggestion or the request of, or with the prior consent of, a candidate, a candidate's campaign treasurer or deputy campaign treasurer, or another person acting as a principal or agent of the candidate;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-400__subsec_v__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>individual means a natural person;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-400__subsec_v__subsec_13">
                <num>(13)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>issues communication means a communication that
(A) directly or indirectly identifies a candidate; and
(B) addresses an issue of national, state, or local political importance and does not support or oppose a candidate for election to public office;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-400__subsec_v__subsec_14">
                <num>(14)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>nongroup entity means a person, other than an individual, that takes action the major purpose of which is to influence the outcome of an election, and that
(A) cannot participate in business activities;
(B) does not have shareholders who have a claim on corporate earnings; and
(C) is independent from the influence of business corporations.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-400__subsec_v__subsec_15">
                <num>(15)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>outside-funded entity means an entity that makes one or more independent expenditures in one or more candidate elections and that, during the previous 12-month period, received more than 50 percent of its aggregate contributions from true sources, or their equivalents, who, at the time of the contribution, resided or had their principal place of business outside Alaska;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-400__subsec_v__subsec_16">
                <num>(16)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>person has the meaning given in
AS 01.10.060
, and includes a labor union, nongroup entity, and a group;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-400__subsec_v__subsec_17">
                <num>(17)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>political party means any group that is a political party under
AS 15.80.010
and any subordinate unit of that group if, consistent with the rules or bylaws of the political party, the unit conducts or supports campaign operations in a municipality, neighborhood, house district, or precinct;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-400__subsec_v__subsec_18">
                <num>(18)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>publicly funded entity means a person, other than an individual, that receives half or more of the money on which it operates during a calendar year from government, including a public corporation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-13-400__subsec_v__subsec_19">
                <num>(19)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>true source means the person or legal entity whose contribution is funded from wages, investment income, inheritance, or revenue generated from selling goods or services; a person or legal entity who derived funds via contributions, donations, dues, or gifts is not the true source, but rather an intermediary for the true source; notwithstanding the foregoing, to the extent a membership organization receives dues or contributions of less than $2,000 per person per year, the organization itself shall be considered the true source.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>