<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-47/chapter-21"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-47/chapter-21"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="47.21"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-47/chapter-21/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-47/chapter-21/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-47/chapter-21/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-47/chapter-21/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_47">
        <num>47</num>
        <heading>Welfare, Social Services, and Institutions</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_47__chp_21">
          <num>21</num>
          <heading>Adventure-Based Education</heading>
          <section eId="sec_47-21-010">
            <num>47.21.010</num>
            <heading>Establishment.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-21-010__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Family and Community Services shall establish an adventure-based education program designed to bring adventure-based education to appropriate juvenile offenders and others selected by referral agencies.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-21-010__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Adventure-based education is a short-term, intensive training program designed to remedy failure patterns and encourage development of self-esteem, self-confidence, and social awareness in</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-21-010__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>certain delinquent juveniles in the custody of the Department of Family and Community Services;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-21-010__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>certain juveniles identified by the schools, division of social services, the courts, youth workers, or other community referral systems, as being able to benefit from adventure-based education.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-21-020">
            <num>47.21.020</num>
            <heading>Program.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-21-020__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An adventure-based education program must include provisions for the following phases:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-21-020__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Phase I: Basic Skills Learning
(A) physical conditioning: running, hiking, swimming, and other related activities;
(B) technical training: the use of specialized tools and equipment, camping, cooking, map reading, navigation, life saving, drown proofing, and solo survival;
(C) safety training: first aid skills, emergency care, preventative medicine, nutrition, health, and personal hygiene care;
(D) team training: rescue techniques, evacuation exercises, and fire fighting;
(E) solo: solitary living for a short period with minimal equipment;
(F) interpersonal skills training: coping skills, individual and group problem solving, and societal communication skills;
(G) culturally relevant activities: traditional modes of subsistence living, traveling and surviving in wilderness areas and communities in the state, and cross-cultural experiences;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-21-020__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Phase II: Skills Generalization
(A) vocational counseling and placement;
(B) family and interpersonal counseling;
(C) community systems utilization: transportation, community services systems, and community problem solving.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-21-020__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Criteria for adventure-based education programs shall be established by the Department of Family and Community Services and must include provisions for</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-21-020__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>staff members with background experience in Outward Bound, NOLS, Alaska Wilderness Experience, Inc., or other similar wilderness skills programs or Indigenous cultural experience;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-21-020__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>minimum program standards.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>