<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-56"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-56"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="14.56"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-56/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-56/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-56/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-56/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_14">
        <num>14</num>
        <heading>Education, Libraries, and Museums</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_14__chp_56">
          <num>56</num>
          <heading>State and Community Libraries</heading>
          <section eId="sec_14-56-010">
            <num>14.56.010</num>
            <heading>Department of Education and Early Development to govern library.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.56.010.   Department of Education and Early Development to govern library.
The Department of Education and Early Development shall manage and have complete charge of all of the property contained in the institutions known as the state library and state historical library.  The state library and state historical library shall be maintained in the state capital.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-56-020">
            <num>14.56.020</num>
            <heading>Powers of the Department of Education and Early Development.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.56.020.   Powers of the Department of Education and Early Development.
The department shall
(1) stimulate and encourage citizens' participation in the development and improvement of library facilities; and
(2) establish policies, plans, and procedures of the department, and adopt reasonable regulations and orders, with penalties, as may be required.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-56-030">
            <num>14.56.030</num>
            <heading>State library duties.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.56.030.   State library duties.
The department shall undertake state library functions that will benefit the state and its citizens, including
(1) coordinating library services of the state with other educational services and agencies to increase effectiveness and eliminate duplication;
(2) providing reference library service to state and other public officials;
(3) providing library services and administering state and other grants-in-aid to public libraries to supplement and improve their services, the grants to be paid from funds appropriated for that purpose, or from other funds available for that purpose;
(4) providing library service directly to areas in which there is not sufficient population or local revenue to support independent library units;
(5) distributing financial aid to public libraries for extension of library service to surrounding areas and to improve inadequate local library service under regulations adopted by the department;
(6) offering consultant service on library matters to state and municipal libraries, community libraries, school libraries, and libraries in unincorporated communities;
(7) serving as a depository for state and federal publications concerning Alaska;
(8) applying for, receiving, and spending, in accordance with
AS 37.07
(the Executive Budget Act), federal, state, or private funds available for library purposes;
(9) recording and distributing the election pamphlet provided for by
AS 15.58
to libraries throughout the state for use by blind voters;
(10) establishing and charging fees for reproduction, printing, and handling costs, for mailing and distributing state publications and research data, and for other services authorized by this chapter;
(11) operating and maintaining the Alaska State Archives under
AS 40.21
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-56-080">
            <num>14.56.080</num>
            <heading>Historical library duties.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.56.080.   Historical library duties.
The department shall
(1) collect, catalog, and preserve an Alaska collection consisting of books, laws, pamphlets, periodicals, manuscripts, microreproductions, audiovisual materials, etc.;
(2) serve as a depository for state and federal historical publications concerning Alaska;
(3) acquire, catalog, and maintain private papers and manuscripts relative to Alaska which are adjudged worthy of preservation for reference and research purposes;
(4) perform other functions necessary to the operation of a historical library.
Article 2. State Library Distribution and Data Access Center.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-56-090">
            <num>14.56.090</num>
            <heading>State library distribution and data access center established.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.56.090.   State library distribution and data access center established.
There is established in the state library the state library distribution and data access center.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-56-100">
            <num>14.56.100</num>
            <heading>Duties of center.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.56.100.   Duties of center.
The center shall, in cooperation with federal, municipal, and private data collection and research efforts, promote the establishment of an orderly depository library and data index distribution and access system.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-56-110">
            <num>14.56.110</num>
            <heading>Regulations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.56.110.   Regulations.
The Department of Education and Early Development shall adopt regulations necessary to carry out the provisions of
AS 14.56.090
 14.56.180.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-56-120">
            <num>14.56.120</num>
            <heading>Deposit of publications and research data.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-56-120__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each state agency shall deposit, upon release, at least four copies of each of its state publications in the center. Additional copies of each publication may be requested by the center for deposit in quantities necessary to meet the needs of the depository library system and to provide inter-library service to those libraries not having depository status.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-56-120__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each state agency shall notify the center of the creation of all data published or compiled by or for it at public expense, including automated data bases, and provide for its accessibility through the center unless the data is protected by the constitutional right to privacy or is of a type stated by law to be confidential or the agency is otherwise prohibited by law from doing so.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-56-120__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The center is also a depository for publications of municipalities and regional educational attendance areas, including surveys and studies produced by a municipality or regional educational attendance area or produced for it on contract.  Four copies of each publication produced for a municipality or regional educational attendance area may be deposited with the center for record and distribution purposes.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-56-120__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each municipality or regional educational attendance area may notify the center of the creation of all data published or compiled by or for it at public expense and provide for its accessibility through the center, unless the data is protected by the constitutional right to privacy or is of a type stated by law to be confidential or the municipality or regional educational attendance area is otherwise prohibited by law from doing so.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-56-120__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When a research project or study is conducted for a person by a state agency, a municipality, or a regional educational attendance area, even though no state funding is involved, the state agency, municipality, or regional educational attendance area shall request that person for permission to make copies of its final report available to the center under
AS 14.56.090
 14.56.180.  If permission is granted, the report shall be deposited with the center.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-56-123">
            <num>14.56.123</num>
            <heading>Liaison with center.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.56.123.   Liaison with center.
Each state agency shall and each municipality and regional educational attendance area may designate one of its employees to be responsible for depositing the materials and information specified in
AS 14.56.120
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-56-125">
            <num>14.56.125</num>
            <heading>Summaries and indices.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-56-125__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon notification of the creation of data under
AS 14.56.120
, a state agency shall and a municipality or regional educational attendance area may prepare an abstract or summary of it.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-56-125__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The center shall prepare and keep current an index of all publications and data abstracts or summaries on file and shall publish and distribute that index regularly to contracting depository libraries and to other Alaska libraries upon request.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-56-130">
            <num>14.56.130</num>
            <heading>Other documents required of state agencies.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.56.130.   Other documents required of state agencies.
Upon the request of the center, a state agency shall furnish the center with a complete list of its current state publications, data published or compiled by or for it at public expense, and a copy of its mailing or exchange lists. However, data that is protected by the constitutional right to privacy or is of a type stated by law to be confidential or that the agency is otherwise prohibited by law from distributing may not be furnished to the center.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-56-135">
            <num>14.56.135</num>
            <heading>Efficiency and computerization.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.56.135.   Efficiency and computerization.
The center shall, to the extent practicable, avoid duplication, coordinate its activities with other state agencies charged with record-keeping functions, and employ computerization to compile or organize research data and other materials.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-56-150">
            <num>14.56.150</num>
            <heading>Depository library contracts.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.56.150.   Depository library contracts.
The center may enter into depository contracts with municipal, regional educational attendance area, university or community college libraries, public library associations, state library agencies, the Library of Congress, and other state and federal library systems.  The requirements for eligibility to contract as a depository library shall be established by the Department of Education and Early Development upon the recommendation of the state librarian and shall include and take into consideration the type of library, its ability to preserve publications or data and to make them available for public use, and the geographical location of the library for ease of access to residents in all areas of the state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-56-160">
            <num>14.56.160</num>
            <heading>Depository library designations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.56.160.   Depository library designations.
Libraries may be designated as either complete depository or selective depository.  A complete depository library shall be sent one copy of every state publication.  A selective depository library shall be sent one copy of every publication from the specific state agencies it designates.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-56-170">
            <num>14.56.170</num>
            <heading>Distribution of state publications and research data.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.56.170.   Distribution of state publications and research data.
The center may not engage in general public distribution of either (1) state publications or lists of publications or (2) the index of publications and research data. However, unless expressly prohibited by law, the center shall make available to any person, upon request and under procedures established by it, publications, summaries, research data, indices, and other materials in its possession.  Reasonable fees for reproduction or printing costs and for mailing and distribution of materials may be charged by the center.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-56-180">
            <num>14.56.180</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.56.180.   Definitions.
In
AS 14.56.090
  14.56.180, unless the context otherwise requires,
(1) center means the state library distribution and data access center;
(2) research data or data means a representation of facts, concepts or instructions in a formalized manner suitable for communication, interpretation, or processing by humans or by automatic means that was prepared to serve as a basis for reasoning, calculation, discussion, or decision and that is determined appropriate for indexing by the state librarian;
(3) state agency includes state departments, divisions, agencies, boards, associations, commissions, corporations, and offices, and the University of Alaska and its affiliated research institutes;
(4) state publication includes any official document, compilation, journal, bill, law, resolution, bluebook, statute, code, register, pamphlet, list, book, report, study, hearing transcript, leaflet, order, regulation, directory, periodical, or magazine issued or contracted for by a state agency determined by the state librarian to be appropriate for retention in the center.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-56-300">
            <num>14.56.300</num>
            <heading>Library assistance grant program.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.56.300.   Library assistance grant program.
There is established in the department a library assistance grant program. From legislative appropriations, the department shall make grants to eligible libraries for public library operations, for interlibrary cooperation, or for regional library services.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-56-310">
            <num>14.56.310</num>
            <heading>Eligibility.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-56-310__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Libraries eligible for grants under
AS 14.56.300
are</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-56-310__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>public libraries established under
AS 14.56.400
or, in a municipality that does not have a public library established under
AS 14.56.400
, another library that
(A) is a nonprofit corporation and holds meetings of its board of directors in public;
(B) provides services listed in
AS 14.56.400</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-56-310__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>libraries sharing resources free of charge with other libraries in the state; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-56-310__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>libraries providing regional library services.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-56-310__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A library described in (a)(1) of this section is eligible for a public library assistance grant. A library described in (a)(2) of this section is eligible for an interlibrary cooperation assistance grant. A library described in (a)(3) of this section is eligible for a regional library services assistance grant.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-56-320">
            <num>14.56.320</num>
            <heading>Applications.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.56.320.   Applications.
An eligible library may apply to the department for a grant under
AS 14.56.300
 14.56.340 in accordance with regulations adopted by the board.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-56-330">
            <num>14.56.330</num>
            <heading>Limitations.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-56-330__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A public library assistance grant under
AS 14.56.310
(a)(1) may be a basic grant or a per capita grant. A basic grant may not be more than $7,000 for each service outlet of the public library in any one fiscal year. The amount of a basic grant must be equally matched by local money, the fair value of volunteer labor, or a combination of local money and volunteer labor. If the amount available for public library assistance grants during a fiscal year is not sufficient to fully fund basic grants for all eligible libraries, the amount available shall be prorated so that the amount of basic grants for all eligible libraries is reduced by the same percentage. After payment of basic grants to all eligible libraries during a fiscal year, any amount remaining for public library assistance grants shall be distributed as per capita grants to each library that received a basic grant. The amount of the per capita grants shall be based on the population of the municipality or unincorporated community served by each of the libraries.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-56-330__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>State money granted to a library under
AS 14.56.300
 14.56.340 may not be used to supplant local money equal to local expenditures for that library in fiscal year 1980, as adjusted annually by the commissioner to conform approximately to changes in the United States Department of Labor Bureau of Labor Statistics consumer price index for Anchorage, Alaska. A library that uses state money to supplant local money forfeits eligibility for grants under
AS 14.56.300
 14.56.340 for two years.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-56-340">
            <num>14.56.340</num>
            <heading>Regulations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.56.340.   Regulations.
The board shall adopt regulations necessary to carry out the purposes of
AS 14.56.300
 14.56.330. The regulations must include qualifications for grant eligibility and provisions regarding the use of grant funds.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-56-355">
            <num>14.56.355</num>
            <heading>Library construction and major expansion matching grant program.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-56-355__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>There is established in the Department of Commerce, Community, and Economic Development a matching grant program for library construction and major expansion.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-56-355__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person in charge of construction or major expansion of an eligible library may apply to the department for a matching grant under regulations adopted by the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-56-355__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subject to appropriation, the department shall award not more than 50 percent of the total proposed grant project costs to an eligible applicant.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-56-355__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall establish regulations to implement this section and the eligibility standards under
AS 14.56.356
. The regulations must include consideration for and establishment of an eligibility priority for an application that is submitted by a community that does not have a public library described in
AS 14.56.356
(a)(2).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-56-355__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-56-355__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>department means the Department of Commerce, Community, and Economic Development;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-56-355__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>major expansion means an expansion of an existing library to increase the square footage of the structure by not less than 30 percent.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-56-356">
            <num>14.56.356</num>
            <heading>Eligibility.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-56-356__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To be a library eligible for a grant under
AS 14.56.355
, a library must be</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-56-356__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>publicly owned and operated by a community; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-56-356__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a public library as described in
AS 14.56.400
that is not a public school library.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-56-356__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An applicant for a grant under
AS 14.56.355
must provide matching funds from</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-56-356__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the local government entity in an amount not less than 20 percent of the total proposed grant project costs; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-56-356__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>private donors in an amount not less than the amount remaining of the total proposed grant project costs after the state and local contributions are made toward the project.
Article 5. Public School Library Collection Development Grants.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-56-360">
            <num>14.56.360</num>
            <heading>Public school library collection development grants.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-56-360__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>There is established in the department a public school library collection development grant program.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-56-360__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The person or division in charge of the state library shall award and administer grants of not more than $3,000 for a fiscal year for use by a public school library eligible under
AS 14.56.365
to expand and improve the library collection to include relevant and current reading materials.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-56-360__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If money appropriated for the program is insufficient to fund all eligible grant requests submitted under
AS 14.56.365
, the available funding shall be awarded to the highest ranked applicants, according to criteria established by the department in regulation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-56-365">
            <num>14.56.365</num>
            <heading>Eligibility.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-56-365__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A library eligible for a grant under
AS 14.56.360
must be a public school library established and supported by a school district that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-56-365__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provides physical space or, if a correspondence school operated by a school district, resources for use as a library;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-56-365__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provides regularly scheduled library hours for all students enrolled in the school;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-56-365__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provides designated library personnel to staff the library;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-56-365__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provides acceptable evidence of the promotion of library and information literacy standards;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-56-365__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>maintains an annual library budget that includes library staffing and materials; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-56-365__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>contributes, from the school district's budget, an amount that is not less than the grant award that is paid for library collection materials or contributes in-kind value of services.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-56-365__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall establish by regulation an application and review procedure, including requirements for submission of adequate documentation to prove eligibility under this section. Documentation must include submission of library class schedules, job descriptions for library staff, and a copy of an annual budget for the library.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-56-370">
            <num>14.56.370</num>
            <heading>Eligible expenditures.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-56-370__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A library collection development grant may be used only to purchase library collection materials by a public school or by a school district if the district operates a correspondence program with an eligible school library. In this subsection, library collection materials means books, magazines, reference and audio-visual materials, and electronic subscriptions that support school curriculum and student reading activities.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-56-370__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A library collection development grant may not be used to supplant school district expenditures for the library or to purchase classroom materials, textbooks, testing software, library automation software, computer hardware, operating software, or technology support.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-56-375">
            <num>14.56.375</num>
            <heading>Report.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.56.375.   Report.
A recipient of a grant awarded under
AS 14.56.360
shall prepare a brief annual report to the department describing the effects of the grant and whether all conditions of the grant were met or exceeded.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-56-400">
            <num>14.56.400</num>
            <heading>Public libraries.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-56-400__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A public library established under this section shall provide at least the following services free of charge to the residents of the municipality or community:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-56-400__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establish and maintain a collection of books and other materials for loaning;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-56-400__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide access to interlibrary loan services;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-56-400__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide reading or other educational programs for children; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-56-400__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide reference information.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-56-400__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A public library established under this section shall submit an annual report of its operations and the services it provides to the director of the division that has responsibility for state libraries.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>