<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-76"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-76"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="8.76"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-76/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-76/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-76/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-76/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_8">
        <num>8</num>
        <heading>Business and Professions</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_8__chp_76">
          <num>76</num>
          <heading>Pawnbrokers and Secondhand Dealers</heading>
          <section eId="sec_08-76-010">
            <num>08.76.010</num>
            <heading>Transactions to be entered in book kept at place of business; electronic records.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-76-010__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person engaged in the business of buying and selling secondhand articles, except a bank or a person regulated by
AS 08.76.100
 08.76.590, shall maintain a book, in permanent form, in which the person shall enter in legible English at the time of each purchase or sale</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-010__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the date of the transaction;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-010__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name of the person conducting the transaction;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-010__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name, age, and address of the customer;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-010__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a description of the property bought, which includes, for any firearm, watch, camera, or optical equipment bought, the name of the maker, the serial, model, or other number, and all letters and marks inscribed;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-010__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the price paid;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-010__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the signature of the customer.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-76-010__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 7 ch 49 SLA 2010.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-76-020">
            <num>08.76.020</num>
            <heading>Manner of recording entry.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.76.020.   Manner of recording entry.
The entries in the book required by
AS 08.76.010
shall appear in chronological order in ink or indelible pencil. Blank lines may not be left between entries. Obliterations, alterations, or erasures may not be made. Corrections shall be made by drawing a line through the entry without destroying its legibility, and the line shall be drawn in ink. The book shall be open to the inspection of a peace officer at reasonable times.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-76-030">
            <num>08.76.030</num>
            <heading>Criminal liability.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.76.030.   Criminal liability.
A person who violates
AS 08.76.010
or 08.76.020 is guilty of a misdemeanor and upon conviction is punishable by a fine of not more than $500, or by imprisonment for not more than six months, or by both.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-76-100">
            <num>08.76.100</num>
            <heading>Licensing required.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-76-100__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not engage in business as a pawnbroker without holding a license issued by the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-76-100__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A license is not transferable or assignable.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-76-110">
            <num>08.76.110</num>
            <heading>Requirements for license.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.76.110.   Requirements for license.
The department may issue a license to a person if the person
(1) has good character;
(2) has the experience to engage in business as a pawnbroker;
(3) is fit to engage in business as a pawnbroker;
(4) submits an application as required by the department under
AS 08.01.060
; and
(5) pays a fee established by the department under
AS 08.01.065
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-76-130">
            <num>08.76.130</num>
            <heading>Withdrawal of application.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.76.130.   Withdrawal of application.
The department may consider that a person has withdrawn the person's application for a license if
(1) the application does not contain all of the required information; or
(2) the information required for the application is not submitted to the department within 90 days after the department requests in writing that the person provide the department with the information.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-76-140">
            <num>08.76.140</num>
            <heading>Duration and renewal of license.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-76-140__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A license is valid for two years.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-76-140__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may renew a license under
AS 08.01.100
. The renewal fee must be equal to the fee established under
AS 08.76.110</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-76-140__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding
AS 08.01.100
(b), if a person fails to renew a license before the expiration date of the license, the person shall pay the department a delayed renewal penalty of $100 in addition to the regular renewal fee.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-76-140__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a person fails to renew the person's license, the person may not engage in business as a pawnbroker until the person's license is renewed or a new license is issued.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-76-140__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may refuse to renew a license under this section for reasons that would have prevented the issuance of the license to the person under
AS 08.76.110
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-76-160">
            <num>08.76.160</num>
            <heading>Limit on pawn transaction amount.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.76.160.   Limit on pawn transaction amount.
A licensee may not enter into a pawn transaction that exceeds $750, excluding the finance fee and any fees charged under
AS 08.76.220
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-76-170">
            <num>08.76.170</num>
            <heading>Customer and transaction limitations.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-76-170__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A pawnbroker may not knowingly enter into a pawnbroker transaction with a person who is</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-170__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>under 18 years of age;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-170__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>under the influence of alcohol or a controlled substance when the influence is apparent; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-170__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>using the name of another person.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-76-170__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A pawnbroker may not knowingly accept or receive misappropriated property from a person in a pawnbroker transaction.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-76-180">
            <num>08.76.180</num>
            <heading>Register of pawnbroker transactions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-76-180__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A pawnbroker shall maintain a register in which the pawnbroker shall enter in legible English at the time of each pawnbroker transaction</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-180__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the date of the pawnbroker transaction;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-180__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name of the person conducting the pawnbroker transaction;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-180__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name, age, and address of the pledgor or purchaser;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-180__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a description of the pledged property or purchased property, including the serial number, model number, or other number on the item of property;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-180__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the price paid or amount loaned;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-180__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the signature of the pledgor or seller; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-180__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the type of identification used by the pledgor or seller, the name of the government agency that issued the identification, and the number written on the identification.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-76-180__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A register may be contained in a book or in an electronic format, except that, subject to (c) of this section, the register for pawn transactions must be in an electronic format.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-76-180__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If, on July 1, 2011, a pawnbroker is located in a municipality that has a population of 6,000 or fewer individuals, the pawnbroker's register for pawn transactions may be contained in a book.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-76-180__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A pawnbroker may not falsify or intentionally fail to make an entry of a material matter in a register.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-76-180__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A pawnbroker shall maintain in good condition the record in the register of a completed pawnbroker transaction for one year after the completion of the pawnbroker transaction.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-76-190">
            <num>08.76.190</num>
            <heading>Recording requirements.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.76.190.   Recording requirements.
The records required to be maintained in a register by
AS 08.76.180
must appear in chronological order and, if made in a book, in ink or indelible pencil. Blank lines may not be left between entries. A pawnbroker may not change a record in a register by obliteration, alteration, or erasure. A pawnbroker may correct a record in a register by drawing a line through the entry without destroying its legibility.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-76-200">
            <num>08.76.200</num>
            <heading>Transaction agreement.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.76.200.   Transaction agreement.
A pawnbroker shall provide to a pledgor or seller a copy of the transaction agreement between the pawnbroker and the pledgor or seller. The agreement must clearly and conspicuously disclose
(1) the name and address of the pawnbroker and the name and mailing address of the pledgor or seller;
(2) the date of the transaction;
(3) a description of the item sold or pledged;
(4) the amount of each fee charged under
AS 08.76.210
and 08.76.220;
(5) if the transaction is a pawn transaction, the amount financed and the maturity date; and
(6) if the transaction is a purchase by the pawnbroker, the amount of the purchase price.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-76-210">
            <num>08.76.210</num>
            <heading>Finance fee.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-76-210__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in
AS 08.76.280
, for each 30-day period of a pawn transaction, including a grace period, a pawnbroker may charge a pledgor a finance fee of $5 or an amount that equals interest at a rate that does not exceed 20 percent of the amount financed, whichever amount is greater.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-76-210__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A finance fee is considered to be earned on the day that the pawn transaction is entered into and on the first day of each subsequent 30-day period of the pawn transaction.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-76-220">
            <num>08.76.220</num>
            <heading>Other charges allowed.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-76-220__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in
AS 08.76.280
, a pawnbroker may charge a processing fee of not more than $5 for each pawn transaction for preparing and processing the pawn transaction documentation, for providing law enforcement reports, for paying expenses, for providing other services, and for losses.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-76-220__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A pawnbroker may charge a pledgor who places a firearm with the pawnbroker as pledged property</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-220__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a firearm processing fee of not more than $5; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-220__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a governmental fee.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-76-230">
            <num>08.76.230</num>
            <heading>Insurance.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.76.230.   Insurance.
A pawnbroker may not sell to a pledgor or otherwise charge a pledgor for insurance in connection with a pawn transaction, except to cover the shipment of pledged property that is redeemed by mail.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-76-240">
            <num>08.76.240</num>
            <heading>Return of pledged property.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.76.240.   Return of pledged property.
A pawnbroker shall return pledged property to a pledgor when the pledgor redeems the pledged property. The pawnbroker shall provide the pledgor with a receipt showing the redemption. The receipt must be on a form approved by the department.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-76-250">
            <num>08.76.250</num>
            <heading>Extension of grace period.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.76.250.   Extension of grace period.
A pawnbroker and a pledgor may agree to extend the 30-day grace period allowed under
AS 08.76.270
(b), but each extension may not exceed 30 days. An extension must be in writing, and the pawnbroker shall give the pledgor a copy of the extension agreement. The agreement must clearly state the last day of the extension and the finance fee charged for the extension.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-76-260">
            <num>08.76.260</num>
            <heading>Retention, storage, and lease.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.76.260.   Retention, storage, and lease.
A pawnbroker shall store pledged property in a secure area and maintain the pledged property in an unaltered condition. A pawnbroker may not lease pledged property.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-76-270">
            <num>08.76.270</num>
            <heading>Redemption.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-76-270__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless there is a hold order on the pledged property, the pledged property is subject to a claim under
AS 08.76.370
or 08.76.380, or the property is returned to a lessor under
AS 08.76.400
, a pledgor may redeem pledged property by paying the amount financed and the finance fee in full before the pawnbroker's scheduled closing time on the maturity date.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-76-270__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a pledgor does not pay the amount financed and the finance fee in full before the pawnbroker's scheduled closing time on the maturity date, the pawnbroker shall hold the pledged property on the pawnbroker's business premises for a grace period of 30 days plus any extension allowed under
AS 08.76.250
. A pledgor may redeem the pledged property during the actual grace period by paying the amount financed and the finance fee, but a pledgor may not redeem pledged property after the pawnbroker's scheduled closing time on the last day of the actual grace period. In this subsection, actual grace period means the grace period plus any extension allowed under
AS 08.76.250
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-76-270__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If there is a hold order on pledged property, the pledgor may redeem the pledged property only when the hold order is released.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-76-270__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If pledged property is subject to a claim under
AS 08.76.370
or 08.76.380, the pledgor may redeem the pledged property only when the pledged property becomes available under
AS 08.76.370
or 08.76.380 for redemption.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-76-270__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a pledgor does not redeem pledged property under (a)  (d) of this section, the title and all interest in the pledged property transfer to the pawnbroker.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-76-270__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The holder of a transaction agreement is presumed to be the person who is entitled to redeem the pledged property that is the subject of the transaction agreement, and a pawnbroker shall deliver the pledged property to the person who presents the transaction agreement and pays the amount financed and the finance fee for the pawn transaction.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-76-280">
            <num>08.76.280</num>
            <heading>Military personnel.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.76.280.   Military personnel.
A pawnbroker shall waive the unpaid amount financed and the finance fee due on a pawn transaction and hold, except as provided in
AS 08.76.320
 08.76.380, the pledged property that is the subject of the pawn transaction on the pawnbroker's business premises until 60 days after the pledgor, the pledgor's spouse, or the pledgor's dependent returns to the United States, if the pawnbroker receives a copy of military orders indicating that
(1) the pledgor, or the pledgor's spouse or dependent, is enlisted in the military service of a state or the federal government; and
(2) after the pawn transaction was entered into, the person was or is to be deployed abroad for service relating to a military conflict.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-76-290">
            <num>08.76.290</num>
            <heading>Business operation method and hours.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.76.290.   Business operation method and hours.
A pawnbroker may not engage in the business of being a pawnbroker
(1) by using a method, including a drive-through window, in which a person remains in a motor vehicle while conducting the pawnbroker transaction; or
(2) between the hours of 12 midnight and 6:00 a.m.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-76-300">
            <num>08.76.300</num>
            <heading>Waiver prohibited.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.76.300.   Waiver prohibited.
A pawnbroker may not require or allow a person to waive a provision of
AS 08.76.100
 08.76.590.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-76-310">
            <num>08.76.310</num>
            <heading>Employees.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.76.310.   Employees.
A pawnbroker may not knowingly employ a person to work in a pawnshop if, within five years before the employment begins, the person was convicted of, entered a plea of guilty to, entered a plea of no contest to, or had adjudication withheld for a felony or for a misdemeanor involving dishonesty.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-76-320">
            <num>08.76.320</num>
            <heading>Issuance of police hold order.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-76-320__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When a law enforcement officer has probable cause to believe that property in the possession of a pawnbroker at a pawnshop in the law enforcement officer's jurisdiction has been misappropriated, the law enforcement officer may issue a police hold order that directs the pawnbroker not to release or dispose of the property until the police hold order terminates or a court orders the release or disposal.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-76-320__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless a pawnbroker or the pawnbroker's designee refuses to sign the police hold order, a police hold order begins when the pawnbroker or the pawnbroker's designee receives the police hold order. If the pawnbroker or the pawnbroker's designee refuses to sign the police hold order, the police hold order begins when the refusal occurs.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-76-330">
            <num>08.76.330</num>
            <heading>Evidentiary hold order.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-76-330__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When property in the possession of the pawnbroker may be needed as evidence in a filed court action involving a criminal charge, a law enforcement agency may issue an evidentiary hold order to a pawnbroker that directs the pawnbroker not to release or dispose of the property until the evidentiary hold order terminates or a court orders the release or disposal.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-76-330__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A pawnbroker who receives an evidentiary hold order under (a) of this section shall hold the property until the attorney general notifies the pawnbroker in writing of the disposition of the filed court action. The attorney general shall notify the pawnbroker within 15 days after the disposition of the filed court action for which the property may be needed as evidence.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-76-340">
            <num>08.76.340</num>
            <heading>Contents and form of hold order.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.76.340.   Contents and form of hold order.
A hold order must be in writing and contain
(1) the name of the pawnbroker;
(2) if a police hold order, the name, title, and identification number of the law enforcement officer issuing the police hold order, and the name and address of the law enforcement agency for which the law enforcement officer is acting;
(3) if an evidentiary hold order, the name and address of the law enforcement agency issuing the evidentiary hold order;
(4) the number, if any, assigned by the law enforcement agency to the case, and, for an evidentiary hold order, the number and caption of the filed court action;
(5) a complete description of the property being held, including the model number and serial number, if any;
(6) if a police hold order, the name of the person, if any, who reported the property as misappropriated;
(7) the mailing address of the pawnshop where the property is being held; and
(8) the expiration date of the hold order.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-76-350">
            <num>08.76.350</num>
            <heading>Duration of police hold order.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-76-350__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A police hold order may not exceed 30 days. However, a law enforcement officer may extend the police hold order for two additional successive 30-day periods by giving written notification to the pawnbroker before the expiration of each 30-day period.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-76-350__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A law enforcement agency may not issue a new police hold order for the same property after the second additional 30-day period allowed under this section. However, the termination of the police hold order does not affect an existing evidentiary hold order on the same property or prevent the issuance of an evidentiary hold order for the same property.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-76-350__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A law enforcement agency may release a police hold order before the end of a 30-day period by issuing a written release to the pawnbroker.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-76-360">
            <num>08.76.360</num>
            <heading>Noncompliance with hold order.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.76.360.   Noncompliance with hold order.
The department may suspend or revoke a pawnbroker's license if the pawnbroker knowingly fails to comply with a hold order.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-76-370">
            <num>08.76.370</num>
            <heading>Claim notification.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-76-370__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a person believes that property in the possession of a pawnbroker was misappropriated from the person, and if the person wants to obtain possession of the property from the pawnbroker, the person shall first notify the pawnbroker by certified mail, return receipt requested, of the person's claim.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-76-370__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A notice under (a) of this section must contain a complete and accurate description of the property and must be accompanied by proof that the claimant owns the property and, if the claimant alleges that the property was stolen, a legible copy of a law enforcement agency's report indicating that the property was stolen.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-76-370__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in
AS 08.76.380
, a pawnbroker may not, for 30 days after the pawnbroker receives notice of the claim under this section, dispose of property that is the subject of a claim.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-76-380">
            <num>08.76.380</num>
            <heading>Court action on claim.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.76.380.   Court action on claim.
If a claimant and a pawnbroker do not resolve a claim within 10 days after the pawnbroker's receipt of a notice of the claim under
AS 08.76.370
, the claimant may bring an action in superior court to require the pawnbroker to return the property to the claimant. After a pawnbroker is notified that a court action has been filed, the pawnbroker may not dispose of the property until the court disposes of the court action, disposes of the property, or allows the pawnbroker to dispose of the property.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-76-390">
            <num>08.76.390</num>
            <heading>Liability of pledgor.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.76.390.   Liability of pledgor.
A pledgor or seller of property to a pawnbroker is liable to the pawnbroker for the full amount that the pledgor or seller received from the pawnbroker, all charges owed by the pledgor for the pawnbroker transaction, and attorney fees and other costs as allowed by the rules of court if, in an action under
AS 08.76.380
,
(1) the superior court determines that the pledgor or seller misappropriated the property from the claimant; and
(2) the superior court orders the pawnbroker to return the property to the claimant.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-76-400">
            <num>08.76.400</num>
            <heading>Recovery of leased property.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-76-400__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If property in the possession of a pawnbroker was leased to a pledgor or seller when the pledgor or seller pledged or sold the property to the pawnbroker, but the property did not have a permanent label or other conspicuous mark identifying it as the lessor's property, the pawnbroker shall return the property to the lessor if the lessor</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-400__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provides the pawnbroker with evidence that the property was the lessor's property and was leased to the pledgor or seller at the time the property was pledged or sold to the pawnbroker; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-400__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>pays the pawnbroker
(A) the amount financed and the finance fee for the pawn transaction, if the property was pledged to the pawnbroker; or
(B) the amount that the pawnbroker paid the seller if the property was sold to the pawnbroker.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-76-400__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A pawnbroker is not liable to the pledgor or seller of property that is recovered by a lessor under (a) of this section for returning the property to a lessor under (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-76-410">
            <num>08.76.410</num>
            <heading>Law enforcement reports.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-76-410__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A pawnbroker shall provide a law enforcement officer with a law enforcement report in paper or in an electronic format on a weekly basis.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-76-410__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A law enforcement report is confidential under
AS 40.25.100
 40.25.220, and a law enforcement officer and a law enforcement agency may only use a law enforcement report to investigate a crime involving the property that is the subject of the pawnbroker transactions of the pawnbroker.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-76-420">
            <num>08.76.420</num>
            <heading>Contents of law enforcement reports.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-76-420__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A law enforcement report must contain</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-420__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a complete and accurate description of all property pledged to or purchased by the pawnbroker, including, as applicable, the property's
(A) brand name, model number, and manufacturer's serial number; and
(B) type of action and caliber or gauge, if the property is a firearm; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-420__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the number of the pawnbroker transaction document that the pawnbroker used to document the pawnbroker transaction.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-76-420__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (a) of this section, the description of the items under (a)(1) of this section is adequate if the description gives the quantity of the items and describes the type of the items if the pawnbroker transaction consists solely of multiple items that are of a similar type, do not have serial or model numbers, and do not contain precious metals or gemstones.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-76-430">
            <num>08.76.430</num>
            <heading>Inspection by law enforcement entities.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.76.430.   Inspection by law enforcement entities.
If a law enforcement agency provides the case number assigned to the investigation for which the inspection is being made, a pawnbroker may not refuse to allow the law enforcement agency to inspect during normal business hours the pawnbroker's register and the purchased property involved in the investigation or the unredeemed pledged property involved in the investigation.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-76-440">
            <num>08.76.440</num>
            <heading>Discipline.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-76-440__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may, after notice to the licensee and reasonable opportunity to be heard, take the following disciplinary action against a licensee if the licensee or an officer, agent, or employee of the licensee violates
AS 08.76.100
 08.76.590:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-440__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>permanently revoke a license;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-440__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>suspend a license for a specified period;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-440__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>censure or reprimand a licensee;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-440__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>impose limitations or conditions on the licensee;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-440__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>impose probation requiring a licensee to report regularly to the department on matters related to the grounds for probation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-440__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>order the licensee to make restitution.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-76-440__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the department takes disciplinary action under (a) of this section, the department may not, for one year after the date of the disciplinary action, issue another license to the licensee or a license to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-440__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the spouse of the licensee;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-440__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a partnership if the licensee is a partner of the partnership;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-440__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a corporation if the licensee is an officer of the corporation, including a member of the board of directors of the corporation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-440__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a limited liability company if the licensee is a member or manager of the limited liability company; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-440__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an employee of the licensee.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-76-440__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before taking disciplinary action under (a) of this section, the department shall allow a licensee 30 days to correct the violation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-76-450">
            <num>08.76.450</num>
            <heading>Civil penalty.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.76.450.   Civil penalty.
If a licensee, or an officer, agent, or employee of a licensee violates
AS 08.76.100
 08.76.590, the licensee is liable to the state for a civil penalty. Notwithstanding
AS 08.01.075
(a)(8), the penalty may not be less than $200 or more than $2,000. The amount of the civil penalty must be adjusted to the seriousness of the violation.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-76-460">
            <num>08.76.460</num>
            <heading>Municipal regulation.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-76-460__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subject to (b) of this section, a municipality with the authority under
AS 29
to enact ordinances regulating pawnbrokers and pawnbroker transactions may adopt an ordinance regulating pawnbrokers and pawnbroker transactions if, at a minimum, the ordinance complies with
AS 08.76.100
 08.76.590.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-76-460__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may not enact an ordinance that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-460__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>requires the payment of a fee or tax related to a pawnbroker transaction; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-460__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>restricts the hours of operation of a pawnbroker, except that an ordinance may prohibit pawnbrokers from operating as provided under
AS 08.76.290
(2).</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-76-460__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An ordinance that violates this section is void.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-76-470">
            <num>08.76.470</num>
            <heading>Regulations.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-76-470__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may adopt regulations to implement
AS 08.76.100
 08.76.590.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-76-470__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before the department adopts a regulation to implement
AS 08.76.100
 08.76.590, the department shall, in addition to any other requirements under
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act), notify licensees of the proposed regulation. After the regulation is adopted, the department shall send each licensee a copy of the regulation adopted.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-76-500">
            <num>08.76.500</num>
            <heading>Exemptions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.76.500.   Exemptions.
This chapter does not apply to
(1) a financial institution that is subject to the regulation of the department under
AS 06
, including a commercial bank, savings bank, credit union, premium finance company, small loan company, bank holding company, financial holding company, trust company, savings and loan association, and deferred deposit advance licensee under
AS 06.50
; or
(2) a financial institution organized under federal law.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-76-590">
            <num>08.76.590</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-76-590__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>to retain possession of pledged property;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-590__subsec_b__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>hold order means a police hold order or an evidentiary hold order;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-590__subsec_b__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>identification means
(A) a government-issued identification document that contains a photograph; or
(B) an electronic image of a document identified under (A) of this paragraph;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-590__subsec_b__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>knowingly has the meaning given in
AS 11.81.900
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-590__subsec_b__subsec_13">
                <num>(13)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>law enforcement agency means
(A) the police department of a municipality where a pawnshop is located;
(B) the Department of Law;
(C) the Department of Public Safety;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-590__subsec_b__subsec_14">
                <num>(14)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>law enforcement officer means
(A) a police officer of the municipality where a pawnshop is located; or
(B) a state trooper if a pawnshop is located in the unorganized borough or if a pawnshop is located in a municipality that does not provide police protection services;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-590__subsec_b__subsec_15">
                <num>(15)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>law enforcement report means a report required by
AS 08.76.410
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-590__subsec_b__subsec_16">
                <num>(16)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>lease means any form of rental;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-590__subsec_b__subsec_17">
                <num>(17)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>license means a license to engage in business as a pawnbroker issued under
AS 08.76.110
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-590__subsec_b__subsec_18">
                <num>(18)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>licensee means a person who holds a license;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-590__subsec_b__subsec_19">
                <num>(19)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>maturity date means the date by which a pledgor is required to pay a pawnbroker the amount financed and the finance fee for a pawn transaction, but does not include a grace period;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-590__subsec_b__subsec_20">
                <num>(20)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>misappropriated means pledged or sold to a pawnbroker
(A) after being stolen; or
(B) while being leased to the pledgor or seller by another person if the property has a permanent label or other conspicuous mark identifying it as another person's property;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-590__subsec_b__subsec_21">
                <num>(21)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>pawnbroker means a person who lends money in exchange for a pledge of property;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-590__subsec_b__subsec_22">
                <num>(22)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>pawnbroker transaction means a pawn transaction or purchase;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-590__subsec_b__subsec_23">
                <num>(23)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>pawn transaction means a pledge given in exchange for a loan by a pawnbroker;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-590__subsec_b__subsec_24">
                <num>(24)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>personal property means tangible personal property, but does not include a security, a title to property, a deed, a bill of sale, or printed evidence of indebtedness;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-590__subsec_b__subsec_25">
                <num>(25)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>pledge means a deposit of property as security for payment of financial obligations to a pawnbroker in a pawn transaction;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-590__subsec_b__subsec_26">
                <num>(26)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>pledged property means the property that is pledged in a pawn transaction;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-590__subsec_b__subsec_27">
                <num>(27)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>pledgor means
(A) a person who delivers property to a pawnbroker for a pawn transaction; or
(B) the principal, if the person who delivers property to a pawnbroker for a pawn transaction discloses that the delivery person is acting for a principal;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-590__subsec_b__subsec_28">
                <num>(28)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>police hold order means a hold order authorized under
AS 08.76.320
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-590__subsec_b__subsec_29">
                <num>(29)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>property means personal property;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-590__subsec_b__subsec_30">
                <num>(30)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>purchase means a purchase of property by a pawnbroker that is not a pawn transaction;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-590__subsec_b__subsec_31">
                <num>(31)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>redeem means to obtain the return of pledged property under
AS 08.76.270
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-590__subsec_b__subsec_32">
                <num>(32)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>register means the register required to be maintained by
AS 08.76.180
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-590__subsec_b__subsec_33">
                <num>(33)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>registration fee means a fee for registering a firearm;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-590__subsec_b__subsec_34">
                <num>(34)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>seller means a person who sells property to a pawnbroker, but does not include a pledgor;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-76-590__subsec_b__subsec_35">
                <num>(35)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>transaction agreement means the transaction agreement required by
AS 08.76.200
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>