<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-44"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-44"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="14.44"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-44/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-44/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-44/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-44/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_14">
        <num>14</num>
        <heading>Education, Libraries, and Museums</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_14__chp_44">
          <num>44</num>
          <heading>Interstate Education Compacts</heading>
          <section eId="sec_14-44-010">
            <num>14.44.010</num>
            <heading>Ratification, approval, and adherence.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.44.010.   Ratification, approval, and adherence.
The Western Regional Higher Education Compact, recommended by the Western Governors' Conference on November 10, 1950, for adoption by the states or territories of Alaska, Arizona, California, Colorado, Idaho, Hawaii, Montana, Nevada, New Mexico, Oregon, Utah, Washington, and Wyoming, is ratified and approved and the adherence of this state to this Compact, upon its ratification and approval by four or more of these states or territories in addition to this state, is declared.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-44-015">
            <num>14.44.015</num>
            <heading>Terms and provisions of Compact.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.44.015.   Terms and provisions of Compact.
The terms and provisions of the Compact referred to in
AS 14.44.010
are as follows:</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-44-020">
            <num>14.44.020</num>
            <heading>Execution of Compact by governor.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.44.020.   Execution of Compact by governor.
Upon ratification and approval of the Western Regional Higher Education Compact by four or more of the specified states or territories in addition to this state, the governor shall execute the Compact on behalf of the state and perform other acts requisite to its formal ratification and promulgation.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-44-025">
            <num>14.44.025</num>
            <heading>Provisions of services.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-44-025__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>State participation under Articles VIII and XIII of the Western Regional Higher Education Compact shall be limited to the provision of adequate services and facilities in the professional fields of study available through the Professional Student Exchange Program administered by the Western Interstate Commission on Higher Education. The Alaska Commission on Postsecondary Education shall establish funding priorities under
AS 14.44.035
for the available fields of study by analyzing student access and state labor needs.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-44-025__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding the funding priorities established under (a) of this section, the Alaska Commission on Postsecondary Education shall provide adequate funding for not fewer than five students each year to attend four-year programs in each of the following fields:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-44-025__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>dentistry;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-44-025__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>optometry; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-44-025__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>pharmacy.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-44-030">
            <num>14.44.030</num>
            <heading>Members of the commission.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-44-030__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The governor, with the advice and consent of the legislature, shall appoint the members for this state of the Western Interstate Commission for Higher Education, created under the provisions of Article III of the Western Regional Higher Education Compact.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-44-030__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The qualifications and terms of office of the members of the commission of this state shall conform with the provisions of Article IV of the Compact.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-44-030__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioners shall serve without compensation and shall be reimbursed for actual and necessary expenses by the Western Interstate Commission for Higher Education.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-44-035">
            <num>14.44.035</num>
            <heading>Administration.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.44.035.   Administration.
The Alaska Commission on Postsecondary Education shall administer the state's participation in the Western Regional Higher Education Compact. The Alaska Commission on Postsecondary Education may adopt regulations to implement
AS 14.44.010
 14.44.040.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-44-040">
            <num>14.44.040</num>
            <heading>Repayment condition for program participants.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-44-040__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>As a condition of eligibility for receiving financial support from the state under the Professional Student Exchange Program of the Western Interstate Commission on Higher Education, a program participant shall agree to repay to the state the support provided by the state on behalf of that person, plus interest.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-44-040__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A repayment under this section shall be paid into the education loan fund created under
AS 14.42.210
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-44-040__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a program participant defaults on the repayment obligation, the provisions of
AS 14.43.145
 14.43.155 apply to collect on the obligation as if it were a defaulted loan under
AS 14.43
.
Article 2. Compact for Education.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-44-050">
            <num>14.44.050</num>
            <heading>Entry into compact.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.44.050.   Entry into compact.
The Compact for Education is enacted into law and entered into in behalf of the State of Alaska with all other states and jurisdictions legally joining in it in a form substantially as contained in
AS 14.44.055
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-44-055">
            <num>14.44.055</num>
            <heading>Terms and provisions of compact.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.44.055.   Terms and provisions of compact.
The terms and provisions of the compact referred to in
AS 14.44.050
are as follows:</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-44-060">
            <num>14.44.060</num>
            <heading>Members of the commission.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-44-060__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>One of the commission members shall be the governor; one shall be the state commissioner of education and early development; two shall be members of the state legislature selected by its respective houses and serving in the manner the legislature may determine; one shall be the president of the state Board of Education and Early Development; and two shall be appointed at large by and serve at the pleasure of the governor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-44-060__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The terms of office of the at-large members shall be four years; however, the first members shall be appointed as follows: one for two years, and one for four years.  Each member shall hold office until a successor is appointed and qualified.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-44-060__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The legislative and at-large members of the commission serve without compensation but are entitled to per diem and travel expenses provided by law for other state boards and commissions.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>