<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-47/chapter-25"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-47/chapter-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="47.25"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-47/chapter-25/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-47/chapter-25/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-47/chapter-25/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-47/chapter-25/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_47">
        <num>47</num>
        <heading>Welfare, Social Services, and Institutions</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_47__chp_25">
          <num>25</num>
          <heading>Public Assistance</heading>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-001">
            <num>47.25.001</num>
            <heading>Powers and duties.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.25.001.   Powers and duties.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-011">
            <num>47.25.011</num>
            <heading>Administrative costs of program contractors.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-25-011__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>may only retain $1,000 or 12 percent, whichever is greater, of the child care assistance program funds it receives from the department under the contract.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-021">
            <num>47.25.021</num>
            <heading>Conditions of receipt of benefits.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.25.021.   Conditions of receipt of benefits.
Benefits may be paid for the care of children of a low or moderate income family only if a parent or guardian, because of the child care, is freed to work or to seek work or to attend school. Benefits may not be paid for the care of children of a family where one parent or guardian is not working, actively seeking work, or attending school and is physically and mentally capable of caring for the children.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-031">
            <num>47.25.031</num>
            <heading>Eligibility of families for benefits.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.25.031.   Eligibility of families for benefits.
The department shall determine the eligibility of families for child care benefits on the basis of the following factors:
(1) income of the family including salary, alimony, child support, retirement benefits, social security, and any other source of income;
(2) number of children in the family;
(3) whether there is one parent or guardian solely responsible for the care of the family.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-041">
            <num>47.25.041</num>
            <heading>Contributions by parent or guardian.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.25.041.   Contributions by parent or guardian.
The department shall develop a sliding fee scale based on the factors listed in
AS 47.25.031
for purposes of determining the amount to be contributed by the parent or guardian for child care; the amount may not exceed seven percent of the family monthly income. The contribution of the parent or guardian shall be paid to the child care facility.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-051">
            <num>47.25.051</num>
            <heading>Placement; payment by state.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-25-051__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Parents or guardians shall select the child care facility for the care of their children.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-051__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Benefits shall be paid by the department directly to the municipality or organization contracting with the child care facility.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-051__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall use a market rate study or a cost of care study to establish a subsidy rate for each region served by the program established under
AS 47.25.001
. The department shall use the subsidy rate to determine the amount of benefits payable by the department under (b) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-071">
            <num>47.25.071</num>
            <heading>Child care grant program.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-25-071__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A child care grant program is established in the department to provide state assistance in the operation of child care facilities. The department shall provide grants for the operation of child care facilities, including private nonprofit child care facilities. Participation in the program is optional.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-071__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To qualify for a grant under (a) or (d) of this section, the child care facility must</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-25-071__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>be currently licensed under
AS 47.32
and applicable municipal licensing requirements;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-25-071__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>participate in the child care assistance program under
AS 47.25.001
 47.25.095;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-25-071__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide care under a payment system as provided in (g) of this section; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-25-071__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>be designated as a quality child care facility by the department.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-071__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 28 ch 4 SLA 2024; § 44 ch 15 SLA 2024.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-071__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to the grants provided in (a) of this section, the department may, subject to appropriations for that purpose, provide by grant or contract for the education and training of child care employees or administrators. To receive a grant or contract under this subsection or to participate in a training program under this subsection, the child care facility must meet all the requirements of (b) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-071__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An application for a grant under this section shall be made in a format established by the department. The department shall establish an electronic application for a grant and allow an applicant to submit an application in electronic format or in other formats required by state and federal law. The electronic application must inform an applicant that a false statement made on the application will be investigated and is punishable under
AS 11.56.210
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-071__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A grant under (a) of this section shall be made monthly or quarterly and shall be based on the monthly average daily full-time equivalent enrollment in the child care facility. If the method of payment for the grant is other than monthly, it shall be at the request of the child care facility with the approval of the department. Based on criteria established by the department, the department may make quarterly advance payments.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-071__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A child care facility receiving a grant under (a) or (d) of this section shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-25-071__subsec_g__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>assure that at least 15 percent or one of its child care spaces receiving subsidy under this section, whichever is greater, will be made available, if requested, to children eligible for child care assistance under
AS 47.25.001
 47.25.095, whose parents or guardians wish to pay for care based on attendance only;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-25-071__subsec_g__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>give priority to children from low-income families when filling available child care spaces in the facility.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-071__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall, in consultation with a child care resource and referral agency in the state and parents, adopt regulations to carry out the purposes of this section, including criteria used to designate a child care facility as a quality child care facility under (b)(4) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-071__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to the grants provided in (a) and (d) of this section, the department may, subject to appropriations for that purpose, provide grants to the highest performing and highest quality child care facilities in the state. The department may use quality recognition and improvement system metrics to determine the highest performing and highest quality child care facilities in the state. To receive a grant under this subsection, the child care facility must be currently licensed under
AS 47.32
and applicable municipal licensing requirements.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-071__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A child care facility receiving a grant under (a) or (d) of this section may not deny a child acceptance to the facility based on disability or socioeconomic status.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-095">
            <num>47.25.095</num>
            <heading>Definitions for child care assistance and child care grant programs.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.25.095.   Definitions for child care assistance and child care grant programs.
In
AS 47.25.001
 47.25.095,
(1) child means a person below 13 years of age, or a minor who has a developmental disability;
(2) child care means the care, supervision, and guidance of a child or children unaccompanied by a parent or legal guardian on a regular basis for periods of less than 24 hours a day;
(3) child care facility means an establishment licensed as a child care facility under
AS 47.32
that provides care for children not related by blood, marriage, or legal adoption to the owner, operator, or manager of the facility or an establishment recognized by the federal government for the care of children;
(4) department means the Department of Health;
(5) developmental disability means a disability under which a person is incapable of self-care, as verified by a physician or licensed or certified psychologist who has examined the person;
(6) electronic application means an application for benefits or renewal of benefits electronically completed and submitted through the department's Internet website.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-120">
            <num>47.25.120</num>
            <heading>Eligibility for assistance.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.25.120.   Eligibility for assistance.
Financial assistance may be given under
AS 47.25.120
 47.25.300, so far as practicable under the conditions in this state, to a needy person who is eligible under the regulations of the department.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-130">
            <num>47.25.130</num>
            <heading>Amount and type of assistance.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-25-130__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The amount of assistance for a needy person shall be determined by the department with regard to the resources and needs of the person and the conditions existing in each case. Where possible, assistance shall be sufficient to provide the applicant with reasonable subsistence according to standards of assistance established by the department. However, the amount of assistance for subsistence needs may not exceed $120 a person a calendar month.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-130__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may enter into competitively awarded group service agreements with providers, and may require needy persons under
AS 47.25.120
 47.25.300 to obtain services from these designated providers.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-140">
            <num>47.25.140</num>
            <heading>Residents of public institutions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-25-140__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Payment under
AS 47.25.120
 47.25.300 may not be made to or on behalf of an individual who is a resident of a public institution, except as a patient in a public medical institution, or an individual who is a patient in a public or private institution for tuberculosis or mental disease. A resident of a public institution who is otherwise eligible to receive an allowance under
AS 47.25.120
 47.25.300 may apply for the allowance instead of the support and maintenance provided in the public institution.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-140__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, public institution does not include the Alaska Pioneers' Home or the Alaska Veterans' Home.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-150">
            <num>47.25.150</num>
            <heading>Application for assistance.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.25.150.   Application for assistance.
A person requesting assistance shall apply for it, either personally or through another person, in a format and manner prescribed in regulations adopted by the department. Regulations adopted under this section must establish an electronic application for assistance and allow an applicant to submit an application in electronic format or in other formats required by state and federal law. The electronic application must inform an applicant that a false statement made on the application will be investigated and is punishable under
AS 11.56.210
. In this section, electronic application means an application for benefits or renewal of benefits, whether the department exclusively administers the benefits or administers the benefits in coordination with another state agency or federal agency, electronically completed and submitted through the department's Internet website.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-160">
            <num>47.25.160</num>
            <heading>Investigation of applicant.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.25.160.   Investigation of applicant.
The department shall promptly investigate each applicant to determine the applicant's eligibility.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-170">
            <num>47.25.170</num>
            <heading>Granting of assistance.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.25.170.   Granting of assistance.
Upon the completion of its investigation, the department shall decide whether the applicant is eligible for and should receive assistance promptly under
AS 47.25.120
 47.25.300, the amount of assistance, the manner of paying or providing it, and the date on which the assistance shall begin.  The department shall notify the applicant of its decision.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-180">
            <num>47.25.180</num>
            <heading>Appeal.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.25.180.   Appeal.
An applicant whose application is not acted upon or is denied, discontinued, or modified by the department shall be granted an opportunity for fair hearing before the office of the administrative hearings (
AS 44.64.010
). The hearing shall be held within a reasonable time after demand for it. The conduct of the hearing shall be governed by the regulations adopted for that purpose by the department.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-190">
            <num>47.25.190</num>
            <heading>Payment to guardians.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.25.190.   Payment to guardians.
When a guardian is appointed by the court for a person receiving assistance, the department may pay the assistance to the guardian.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-195">
            <num>47.25.195</num>
            <heading>Payment to facilities for treatment of needy persons.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-25-195__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may make payments to a health facility for the treatment of a needy person.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-195__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (e) of this section, a health facility receiving a payment under this chapter is subject to the requirements of
AS 47.07.070
 47.07.075.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-195__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (e) of this section, if insufficient money is appropriated to fund medical assistance under
AS 47.25.120
 47.25.300 when taking into consideration projected use and the health facility payment rates established in accordance with (b) of this section, the department may, by regulation, establish at any time in the fiscal year a prospective pro rata reduction of the facilities' established payment rates that will be paid by the department for services provided by facilities under
AS 47.25.120
 47.25.300.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-195__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (a)  (c) of this section, the department may enter into agreements with a facility to provide services at a payment rate lower than the rate established in accordance with (b) of this section, except that the department may not enter into an agreement with an assisted living home to provide services at a daily reimbursement rate lower than $70.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-195__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding other provisions of this section and the provisions of
AS 47.07
, if the assistance provided to a needy person under
AS 47.25.120
 47.25.300 includes the initiation or continuation of placement of the person in an assisted living home at the state's expense, the department's minimum daily reimbursement rate to the assisted living home for the person is $70. This minimum rate is not subject to reduction under (c) of this section. The department may, under its regulations and under the procedures of
AS 47.07.070
 47.07.075, provide for a daily rate higher than $70 if the care provided to the needy person in the assisted living home justifies the higher reimbursement. A daily rate higher than $70 for assisted living homes may be reduced under (c) of this section, but not below $70.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-195__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-25-195__subsec_f__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>assisted living home means an assisted living home licensed under
AS 47.32
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-25-195__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>health facility includes a hospital, skilled nursing facility, intermediate care facility, intermediate care facility for persons with intellectual and developmental disabilities, rehabilitation facility, inpatient psychiatric facility, home health agency, rural health clinic, and outpatient surgical clinic.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-200">
            <num>47.25.200</num>
            <heading>Review of eligibility.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.25.200.   Review of eligibility.
Assistance grants under
AS 47.25.120
 47.25.300 shall be reviewed by the department as frequently as it considers necessary, and the amount of assistance may be changed or entirely withdrawn if the review of the circumstances warrants this action.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-205">
            <num>47.25.205</num>
            <heading>Priority of general relief medical assistance.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.25.205.   Priority of general relief medical assistance.
If the department finds that the cost of medical assistance for all persons eligible under
AS 47.25.120
 47.25.300 will exceed the amount allocated in the state budget for that assistance for the fiscal year, the department shall eliminate coverage for medical services in the following order:
(1) treatment of speech, hearing, and language disorders;
(2) optometrists' services and eyeglasses;
(3) occupational therapy;
(4) emergency dental services for adults;
(5) prosthetic devices not including dentures;
(6) medical supplies and equipment;
(7) physical therapy;
(8) outpatient laboratory and outpatient x-ray services;
(9) ambulatory surgical center services;
(10) nonemergency medical transportation;
(11) outpatient physician services;
(12) outpatient hospital services;
(13) intermediate care facility services;
(14) skilled nursing facility services;
(15) emergency medical transportation;
(16) pharmaceuticals;
(17) inpatient physician services;
(18) inpatient hospital services.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-210">
            <num>47.25.210</num>
            <heading>Alienation and attachment.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.25.210.   Alienation and attachment.
Assistance granted under
AS 47.25.120
 47.25.300 is inalienable by assignment or transfer and is exempt from garnishment, levy, or execution as provided in
AS 09.38
(exemptions).</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-220">
            <num>47.25.220</num>
            <heading>State's claim for assistance.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.25.220.   State's claim for assistance.
The total amount paid in assistance to a recipient constitutes a claim against the recipient and the recipient's estate.  On the death of a person receiving assistance, the total amount paid as assistance shall be allowed by the court having jurisdiction over the estate.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-230">
            <num>47.25.230</num>
            <heading>Persons liable for support and burial.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.25.230.   Persons liable for support and burial.
Every needy person shall be supported while living and upon dying, shall be given a decent burial by the spouse, children, parents, grandparents, grandchildren, or siblings of the needy person, if they, or any of them, have the ability to do so, in the order named.  Every designated person who fails to support the needy person when directed by the department to do so, or fails to give the needy person a decent burial shall reimburse the state or a municipality for the funds expended by either the state or a municipality for the relief or burial of the needy person, and these sums with interest and costs may be recovered by the state or a municipality of the state in a civil action.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-240">
            <num>47.25.240</num>
            <heading>Action against person liable for care of recipient.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.25.240.   Action against person liable for care of recipient.
If, during the continuance of an allowance, the department ascertains that a person liable for the support of the recipient of assistance is able to provide the necessary care and support of the recipient, and the person liable for the care and support of the recipient fails or refuses to support and care for the recipient, the state has a claim for the assistance against the person liable for it.  This claim may be enforced by civil action brought in the name of the state by the attorney general against the person liable for the recovery of the amount of money, with interest, paid to the recipient, together with the costs and disbursements of the action.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-250">
            <num>47.25.250</num>
            <heading>Temporary relief.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.25.250.   Temporary relief.
When a needy person is not entitled to assistance under
AS 47.25.120
  47.25.300 and has no relatives in the state liable for support under
AS 47.25.230
and 47.25.240, the needy person may receive temporary assistance in the form and amount which the department considers necessary. Temporary assistance for needs other than transportation and medical care may not exceed $120 per person per month.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-252">
            <num>47.25.252</num>
            <heading>Discretionary assistance.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.25.252.   Discretionary assistance.
When a needy person is not entitled to assistance under
AS 47.25.120
 47.25.300, the needy person may receive assistance in the form and amount that the department considers necessary.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-260">
            <num>47.25.260</num>
            <heading>Recovery and disposition of allowances improperly granted.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.25.260.   Recovery and disposition of allowances improperly granted.
If the department finds that a general relief allowance has been improperly granted, it shall investigate, and if it appears from the investigation that the assistance was improperly granted, the department may cancel the allowance and notify the recipient of the cancellation.  The state then has a claim against the person who received the improper allowance.  The claim may be enforced by civil action in the name of the state by the attorney general to recover the amount paid to the person, with interest, together with the necessary costs of the action.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-265">
            <num>47.25.265</num>
            <heading>Cancellation of disbursements.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-25-265__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Disbursements issued to a general relief assistance recipient after the date of death of the recipient shall be canceled.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-265__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>General relief assistance disbursements made before the death of the recipient but not collected by the recipient before death shall be canceled, unless claimed by the authorized representative of the estate of the recipient within 90 days after the date of death.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-265__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The state is not liable to the estate, heirs, or creditors of the deceased general relief assistance recipient for payment on disbursements canceled under (a) and (b) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-270">
            <num>47.25.270</num>
            <heading>Agreements with federal government.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.25.270.   Agreements with federal government.
The department may enter into agreements, arrangements, or contracts with any federal agency, department, or official under which funds made available to the federal agency, department, or official may be transferred to the department and spent in accordance with
AS 47.25.120
 47.25.300 for assistance to needy persons.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-290">
            <num>47.25.290</num>
            <heading>Penalty for violation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.25.290.   Penalty for violation.
A person who violates a provision of
AS 47.25.120
 47.25.300 is guilty of a misdemeanor and upon conviction is punishable by a fine of not more than $1,000 or by imprisonment for not more than one year, or by both.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-300">
            <num>47.25.300</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.25.300.   Definitions.
In
AS 47.25.120
 47.25.300,
(1) assistance means financial assistance to or on behalf of a needy person, including subsistence (food, shelter, fuel, clothing, and utilities) and transportation, medical needs (including, but not limited to, hospitalization, nursing, and convalescent care), burial, and other determined needs;
(2) department means the Department of Health;
(3) needy person means a needy resident of the state who is not eligible for aid from another public agency or department providing similar services in the state;
(4) public medical institution means a public hospital or medical institution, except an institution for the treatment of tuberculosis or mental disease.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-430">
            <num>47.25.430</num>
            <heading>Adult public assistance.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-25-430__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Financial assistance shall be given under
AS 47.25.430
 47.25.615, so far as practicable under appropriations made by law, to every aged, blind, or disabled needy resident who has not made a voluntary assignment or transfer of property to qualify for assistance.  In this subsection, resident means a person who is living in the state voluntarily with the intention of making the state the person's home and who is not living in the state for a temporary purpose.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-430__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall determine the amount of assistance with regard to the resources and needs of the person and the conditions existing in each case. Assistance shall be in an amount that will provide the applicant with reasonable subsistence compatible with decency and health in accordance with standards established by the department and with the standards established under 42 U.S.C. 1381  1383 (Title XVI, Social Security Act Supplemental Security Income Program). Direct payments for medical services and remedial care may not be considered in determining the maximum amount payable. When benefit amounts under 42 U.S.C. 1381  1383 are increased as a result of an increase in the cost of living, the state shall pass along the increase to recipients and shall increase the amount of the state contribution to recipients, other than those receiving a personal needs allowance, by a percentage of the state contribution equal to the percentage increase in the benefit amounts under 42 U.S.C. 1381  1383 if the legislature has appropriated money specifically for the purpose of increasing the state contribution because of an increase in federal benefit amounts under 42 U.S.C. 1381  1383; this increase in the state contribution takes effect on the same day that the corresponding federal increase in benefits under 42 U.S.C. 1381  1383 takes effect.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-430__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Payment under
AS 47.25.430
 47.25.615 may not be made to a person who is a resident of a public institution, except as a patient in a public medical institution, or a person who is a patient in a public or private institution for treatment of a mental disease. For purposes of this subsection, resident and patient do not include a person who is institutionalized for medical services for a period of less than three months if the person needs to continue to maintain and provide for the expenses of a home or living arrangement to which that person may return upon discharge from the institution.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-430__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A resident of an institution may, upon or in anticipation of leaving the institution, apply for assistance under
AS 47.25.430
 47.25.615 instead of the support and maintenance provided in the institution.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-430__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (a) and (b) of this section, the department shall, in a manner that complies with federal requirements, reduce the maximum state contribution to recipients otherwise payable on August 24, 1993 to the maximum state contribution to recipients that was in effect on January 1, 1992. On and after August 24, 1993, the department shall, in a manner that complies with federal requirements, calculate the amount of monthly assistance for a recipient based on the maximum state contribution to recipients in effect on January 1, 1992, as modified by any increase under (b) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-430__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless the person is not eligible under the limited eligibility provision of 8 U.S.C. 1613, a state payment under
AS 47.25.430
 47.25.615 shall be made to a person who</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-25-430__subsec_f__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>meets the requirements of state law;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-25-430__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is a qualified alien as defined in 8 U.S.C. 1641; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-25-430__subsec_f__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>otherwise meets the eligibility requirements of 42 U.S.C. 1381  1383.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-435">
            <num>47.25.435</num>
            <heading>Exclusion of income.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.25.435.   Exclusion of income.
Notwithstanding the provisions of
AS 47.25.430
 47.25.615, if the applicable provisions of 42 U.S.C. 301  1397f (Social Security Act), as amended, permit, in determining the need of an applicant for, or a recipient of, an assistance grant under
AS 47.25.430
 47.25.615, the department shall exclude from the computation of the applicant's or recipient's income the amounts specified in 42 U.S.C. 1382a(b), as amended, amounts specified in regulations adopted to implement the supplemental security income provisions of federal law, and any amounts specified by the department by regulation so long as exclusion of those amounts is not in conflict with federal law.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-440">
            <num>47.25.440</num>
            <heading>Application for assistance.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.25.440.   Application for assistance.
A person requesting assistance shall apply for it, either personally or through another, in a format and manner prescribed in regulations adopted by the department. Regulations adopted under this section must establish an electronic application for assistance and allow an applicant to submit an application in electronic format or in other formats required by state and federal law. The electronic application must inform an applicant that a false statement made on the application will be investigated and is punishable under
AS 11.56.210
. In this section, electronic application means an application for benefits or renewal of benefits, whether the department exclusively administers the benefits or administers the benefits in coordination with another state agency or federal agency, electronically completed and submitted through the department's Internet website.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-450">
            <num>47.25.450</num>
            <heading>Investigation of applicant.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.25.450.   Investigation of applicant.
Upon application, the department shall investigate promptly and record the circumstances of each applicant to determine the facts supporting the application and other information required by the department.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-455">
            <num>47.25.455</num>
            <heading>Interim assistance.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-25-455__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall pay at least $280 a month to a person eligible for assistance under this chapter while the eligibility of the person for benefits under 42 U.S.C. 1381  1385 (Title XVI, Social Security Act, Supplemental Security Income Program) is being determined.  Payments in excess of $280 a month may be made under this section if the department determines that money is available for excess payments.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-455__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (a) of this section, the department may not make monthly payments in excess of the total amount of state and federal monthly payments to which the person would be entitled if the person is determined to be eligible for benefits under 42 U.S.C. 1381  1385.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-455__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person applying for assistance under this section shall, as a condition of eligibility for assistance, agree to repay the state for assistance granted upon the person's receipt of a benefit under 42 U.S.C. 1381  1383 for a month in which the person received interim assistance under this section. The monthly repayment required by this subsection may not exceed the amount of assistance that the person received under 42 U.S.C. 1381  1383 for that month.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-455__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Beginning the first full month after a person is determined to be eligible for assistance under 42 U.S.C. 1381  1383, the department shall terminate interim assistance to that person under this section and begin payments to the person under
AS 47.25.430
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-460">
            <num>47.25.460</num>
            <heading>Award, reduction, termination, and appeal.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-25-460__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon completion of the investigation, the department shall promptly decide whether the applicant is eligible for and should receive adult public assistance, the amount of it, the manner of paying it, and the date on which it starts.  The department may make additional investigation that it considers necessary and shall make its decision as to the granting of assistance and the amount and nature of assistance as is justified and in conformity with
AS 47.25.430
 47.25.615. The department shall notify the applicant of its decision in writing.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-460__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Assistance under
AS 47.25.430
 47.25.615 is subject to review.  If a recipient of adult public assistance or the spouse of a recipient with whom the recipient is living acquires nonexempt property exceeding resource limitations, or income sufficient to maintain the recipient properly, then the assistance granted to the recipient shall either be terminated or reduced to an amount reflecting the reduced need as determined by the department in accordance with applicable regulations.  Upon review, the department may, after having provided opportunity for a hearing under (c) of this section, change the assistance granted or terminate it entirely if it finds that the circumstances are changed sufficiently to warrant this action.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-460__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A recipient whose award is proposed to be modified or terminated, or an applicant whose application is denied by the department, shall be granted an opportunity for a hearing before the office of administrative hearings (
AS 44.64.010
). The hearing shall be held promptly after a request for hearing is made. The hearing shall be conducted in accordance with regulations adopted by the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-460__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each award shall be paid on a monthly basis. In case it is impracticable by reason of slow or interrupted means of communication for a disbursement covering a month's assistance to reach the recipient in due course, the department may transmit disbursements covering assistance for future months and may deliver all of them to the recipient at one time.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-470">
            <num>47.25.470</num>
            <heading>Payment when recipient incapacitated.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.25.470.   Payment when recipient incapacitated.
If a person receiving assistance is incapable of self-care or care of the funds granted under
AS 47.25.430
 47.25.615, the department may direct the payment of the funds to the recipient's legally appointed guardian or to another person as designated by the department for the recipient's benefit.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-490">
            <num>47.25.490</num>
            <heading>Imprisoned recipients.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.25.490.   Imprisoned recipients.
If a recipient is convicted of a crime or offense, and punished by imprisonment, payment may not be made during the period of imprisonment, and the department may, in its discretion, declare the assistance forfeited.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-500">
            <num>47.25.500</num>
            <heading>Recovery of assistance improperly granted.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-25-500__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the department has reasonable grounds for believing that assistance was improperly granted, it shall investigate and document the grounds in the case file, and, if it appears as a result of the investigation that assistance was improperly granted, it may, after providing an opportunity for a hearing, terminate or reduce assistance and notify the recipient to that effect.  The department shall continue the payment of benefits pending the hearing. The state has a claim against a person who received an improper amount of assistance.  The claim may be enforced by an action instituted in the name of the state by the attorney general to recover the amount paid to the person, with interest, together with the necessary costs of the action.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-500__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the department finds that recovery would work a financial hardship on the recipient to the extent that the health and well-being of the recipient would be threatened or that the costs of recovery would exceed the amount of assistance improperly granted, it shall waive recovery or reduce the amount to be recovered.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-515">
            <num>47.25.515</num>
            <heading>Cancellation of disbursements.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-25-515__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Disbursements issued to a recipient of assistance under
AS 47.25.430
 47.25.615 after the date of death of the recipient shall be canceled.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-515__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Assistance disbursements issued before the death of the recipient but not collected before death shall be canceled, unless claimed by the authorized representative of the estate of the recipient within 90 days after the date of death.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-515__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The state is not liable to the estate, heirs, or creditors of the deceased assistance recipient for payment on disbursements canceled under (a) or (b) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-520">
            <num>47.25.520</num>
            <heading>Leaving the state.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-25-520__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person receiving assistance who leaves the state may not receive assistance during the absence.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-520__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This section does not apply to a recipient who temporarily leaves the state for</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-25-520__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>medical treatment;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-25-520__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a vacation, business trip, or other absence of less than 30 days unless the time is extended in specific cases by the department;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-25-520__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>vocational, professional, or other special education of more than 90 days if a comparable program is not reasonably available in the state; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-25-520__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>postsecondary education.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-530">
            <num>47.25.530</num>
            <heading>Reports by department.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.25.530.   Reports by department.
The department shall make reports in detail that are required of it by the governor or by the federal government or a federal agency.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-550">
            <num>47.25.550</num>
            <heading>Alienation and attachment.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.25.550.   Alienation and attachment.
Assistance granted under
AS 47.25.430
 47.25.615 is inalienable by an assignment or transfer and is exempt from garnishment, levy, or execution as provided in
AS 09.38
(exemptions).</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-575">
            <num>47.25.575</num>
            <heading>Property taken under eminent domain powers.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.25.575.   Property taken under eminent domain powers.
If a recipient's property is taken for urban renewal or other public purposes and the recipient expresses an intent to purchase a personal dwelling, the proceeds that are paid the recipient as a result of the taking shall be paid by the taking authority into an escrow account under escrow instructions approved by the department.  If the proceeds are paid into such an account and are applied by the recipient within one year to the purchase of a personal dwelling, the proceeds may not cause a reduction of the amount of assistance to which the recipient would otherwise be entitled.  The department shall inform the recipient of the provisions of this section at the time of the taking.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-580">
            <num>47.25.580</num>
            <heading>Action against person liable for care of recipient.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.25.580.   Action against person liable for care of recipient.
If during the continuance of assistance the department finds that a person liable for the support of the recipient of assistance is able to provide the necessary care and support of the recipient and the person liable for the care and support of the recipient fails or refuses to support and care for the recipient, then the state has a cause of action for the assistance against the person liable for it.  The action may be brought in the name of the state by the attorney general against the person liable for the recovery of the amount of money, with interest, paid to the recipient, together with the costs and disbursements of the action.  The amount collected shall be paid to the Department of Revenue.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-590">
            <num>47.25.590</num>
            <heading>Policy and purpose ofAS 47.25.430 47.25.615.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-25-590__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>It is the policy of the state and the purpose of
AS 47.25.430
 47.25.615 to cooperate and coordinate with the United States government and its agencies in providing for and administering the laws of the federal and state governments having for their purpose adult public assistance for residents of this state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-590__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The purpose of
AS 47.25.430
 47.25.615 is to furnish financial assistance as far as practicable to needy aged, blind, and disabled persons, and to help them attain self-support or self-care.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-595">
            <num>47.25.595</num>
            <heading>Transfer of funds.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.25.595.   Transfer of funds.
The department may enter into contracts or arrangements with any federal agency, department, or official under which funds made available to the federal agency, department, or official may be transferred to the department and spent in accordance with
AS 47.25.430
 47.25.615.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-610">
            <num>47.25.610</num>
            <heading>Penalty for violations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.25.610.   Penalty for violations.
A person who violates a provision of
AS 47.25.430
 47.25.615 is guilty of a class B misdemeanor.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-615">
            <num>47.25.615</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.25.615.   Definitions.
In
AS 47.25.430
 47.25.615,
(1) aged means 65 or more years of age;
(2) assistance means money payments to or medical care on behalf of, or any type of remedial care recognized by the department on behalf of, needy aged, blind, or disabled persons who are 18 or more years of age and residents of the state;
(3) blind means having no vision or having vision that is so defective as to prevent the performance of ordinary activities for which eyesight is essential;
(4) department means the Department of Health;
(5) disabled means being unable to engage in substantial gainful activity by reason of a medically determinable physical or mental impairment that can be expected to result in death or that has lasted or can be expected to last for a continuous period of not less than 12 months;
(6) public institution means a governmentally owned establishment that furnishes food, shelter, and some additional treatment or services to 16 or more persons;
(7) public medical institution means a public hospital or a public institution providing medical care, except an institution for the treatment of mental disease.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-621">
            <num>47.25.621</num>
            <heading>Alaska affordable heating program.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-25-621__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Alaska affordable heating program is established in the Department of Health to provide expanded eligibility for Alaska residents for home heating assistance, to the extent funds are available in the Alaska affordable heating fund.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-621__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Alaska affordable heating program established under this section is in addition to the federal low-income heating and energy assistance provided under 42 U.S.C. 8621  8629 (Low-Income Home Energy Assistance Act of 1981), as amended, and implementing regulations.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-621__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Alaska affordable heating fund is established as a separate fund to be managed by the Department of Revenue. The fund consists of appropriations made to it. Interest earned by the fund may be appropriated to it. The Department of Health shall use money in the fund for Alaska affordable heating payments.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-622">
            <num>47.25.622</num>
            <heading>Duties.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.25.622.   Duties.
The Department of Health shall
(1) administer the Alaska affordable heating program provided under
AS 47.25.621
;
(2) adopt regulations under
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act) to carry out the purpose of the program;
(3) coordinate payments among other heating assistance programs to avoid duplication of payments;
(4) establish an electronic application for the Alaska affordable heating program and allow an applicant to submit an application in electronic format or in other formats required by state and federal law; the electronic application must inform an applicant that a false statement made on the application will be investigated and is punishable under
AS 11.56.210
; in this paragraph, electronic application means an application for benefits or renewal of benefits, whether the department exclusively administers the benefits or administers the benefits in coordination with another state agency or federal agency, electronically completed and submitted through the department's Internet website.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-623">
            <num>47.25.623</num>
            <heading>Eligibility; payment amount.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-25-623__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An individual is eligible for home heating assistance payments under the Alaska affordable heating program if the individual</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-25-623__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is a resident of the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-25-623__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is physically present and resides in a home in the state when the home heating costs are incurred;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-25-623__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for assistance calculated under (b) and (c) of this section, has gross household income not to exceed, as a percentage of the federal poverty guideline for Alaska set by the United States Department of Health and Human Services and revised under 42 U.S.C. 9902(2),
(A) 225 percent for a determination to be made under (c)(1)  (3) of this section; and
(B) 250 percent for a determination to be made under (c)(4) of this section; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-25-623__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>meets other eligibility requirements specified in regulations adopted under
AS 47.25.622
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-623__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Health shall determine the number of points for each eligible individual based on the point formula used under 42 U.S.C. 8621  8629 (Low-Income Home Energy Assistance Act of 1981), as amended, and implementing regulations. Except as provided in (d) of this section, the amount of the Alaska affordable heating payment for an individual equals the base amount calculated under (c) of this section minus the amount the individual is eligible to receive under the federal low-income home energy assistance program under 42 U.S.C. 8621  8629, as amended, and implementing regulations.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-623__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Health shall calculate the base amount of the Alaska affordable heating payment for the individual based on points determined under (b) of this section and on the average price a barrel of Alaska North Slope crude oil for sale on the United States West Coast during September through February of the preceding fiscal year as follows:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-25-623__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>$130 a point when the average price is not more than $75 a barrel;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-25-623__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>$140 a point when the average price is more than $75 and not more than $100 a barrel;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-25-623__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>$150 a point when the average price is more than $100 and not more than $150 a barrel;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-25-623__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>$165 a point when the average price is more than $150 a barrel.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-623__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Under the program authorized by
AS 47.25.621
 47.25.626, taking into consideration the gross household income rates established in (a) of this section and the base amounts to be calculated under (b) and (c) of this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-25-623__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if insufficient money is appropriated to fully fund the Alaska affordable heating payments during the fiscal year, the department
(A) shall, for the duration of that fiscal year, suspend calculation and payment under (a)(3)(B) of this section and calculate and pay all eligible individuals under (a)(3)(A) of this section; and
(B) may, to the extent there is or may be an appropriation balance surplus to the amount required to make all payments under (A) of this paragraph, by regulation, establish at any time during the fiscal year a prospective pro rata reduction of the payment rates that the department will pay to eligible individuals under the program during that fiscal year qualifying under (a)(3)(B) of this section and, thereafter, may provide for prorated payments; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-25-623__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if the commissioner reasonably determines that the total of appropriations from all sources during the fiscal year may exceed the amount required to fully fund all applications for assistance for Alaska affordable heating payments, the commissioner may expend the amount of excess money, not to exceed the total amount of the appropriations, to carry out the purpose of
AS 47.25.621
 47.25.626; under the authority of this paragraph, the commissioner shall distribute the estimated excess money pro rata among individuals receiving assistance under this section without regard to the limitations set out in the dollar value of the point formula expressed in (c)(1)  (4) of this section.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-624">
            <num>47.25.624</num>
            <heading>Appeal rights.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.25.624.   Appeal rights.
Except as provided in
AS 47.25.626
(e), an individual who receives a determination from the department that denies, limits, or modifies home heating payments under
AS 47.25.621
 47.25.626, other than a determination based on insufficient funding of the program, may request a hearing before the office of administrative hearings (
AS 44.64.010
) under regulations adopted by the department.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-625">
            <num>47.25.625</num>
            <heading>Ability to recover or recoup improper home heating assistance payments.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.25.625.   Ability to recover or recoup improper home heating assistance payments.
An individual is liable to the department for the value of assistance improperly paid under
AS 47.25.623
if the improper payment was based on inaccurate or incomplete information provided by the individual. In a civil action brought by the state to recover from the individual the value of the assistance improperly paid, the state may recover from the individual the costs of investigation and prosecution of the civil action, including attorney fees as determined under court rules.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-626">
            <num>47.25.626</num>
            <heading>Regional heating assistance program.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-25-626__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Health may develop a regional Alaska heating program for the administration of
AS 47.25.621
 47.25.626 to provide home heating assistance in a uniform and cost-effective manner in a region of this state if an Alaska Native organization is authorized to implement a federally approved tribal family assistance plan that includes that region and has been awarded a tribal energy assistance grant for a program that includes that region under 42 U.S.C. 8623(d).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-626__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may award contracts to implement a program developed under (a) of this section. A contract authorized for delivery of home heating assistance under a regional Alaska heating program under this section is exempt from the competitive bid requirements of
AS 36.30
(State Procurement Code). Subject to appropriation, a contract under this section must be in an amount that represents a fair and equitable share of the money appropriated for the Alaska affordable heating program under
AS 47.25.621
 47.25.626 to serve the state residents specified in (a) of this section. The authority provided under this section to contract is in addition to the authority to contract in
AS 47.05.015
or other law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-626__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may award a contract under this section only to an organization that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-25-626__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has been awarded a tribal energy assistance grant under 42 U.S.C. 8623(d) for a program that includes that region;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-25-626__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>agrees to administer home heating assistance under
AS 47.25.621
 47.25.626 to state residents in the region; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-25-626__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>agrees to implement an appeals process as described in (e) of this section.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-626__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Records pertaining to recipients of home heating assistance under a contract awarded under this section are confidential and not subject to disclosure under
AS 40.25.100
 40.25.220.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-626__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An organization that receives a contract under this section shall provide an appeals process to applicants for or recipients of home heating assistance covered by the contract awarded under this section. The appeals process must be the same as the method available under
AS 47.25.624
, except that the decision reached shall be considered a recommended decision to the department. Within 30 days after receiving a recommended decision, the department shall review the recommended decision and issue a decision accepting or rejecting the recommended decision. If the department rejects the recommended decision, the department shall independently review the record and issue its final decision. The final decision of the department on the matter is appealable to the courts of this state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-626__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the department establishes a regional Alaska heating program and awards a contract to provide home heating assistance under this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-25-626__subsec_f__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a person applying for home heating assistance under
AS 47.25.621
 47.25.626 in the region of the state covered by the regional Alaska heating program may obtain home heating assistance from the department only through the organization designated by the department to serve the region;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-25-626__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the department may require the contractor
(A) to operate and administer the contract in a manner consistent with the organization's federally approved energy assistance grant and plan; or
(B) to apply the provisions of
AS 47.25.623
to determine eligibility for home heating assistance to a person for whom assistance may be paid under the contract or may allow the contractor to use other criteria to determine that eligibility.
Article 5. Food Stamp Program.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-975">
            <num>47.25.975</num>
            <heading>Food stamp program.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-25-975__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department is authorized to implement the food stamp program.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-975__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Householders determined by the department to be eligible for assistance under the food stamp program may obtain food stamp allotments; however, under regulations adopted by the department, a householder may receive all or part of the value of the food stamp allotment in the form of a wage subsidy under
AS 47.27.025</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-975__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-25-975__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the householder is a member of a family eligible for the Alaska temporary assistance program under
AS 47.27
; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-25-975__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the department determines that the wage subsidy authorized under this subsection would aid the householder in the successful completion of the family self-sufficiency plan under
AS 47.27.030
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-975__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Food stamp allotments, other than a wage subsidy authorized under (b) of this section, shall be used to purchase food from retail food stores that have been approved for participation in the food stamp program. Eligible households living in certain remote areas shall be permitted to purchase certain items of hunting and fishing equipment for the purpose of procuring food for the household, except firearms, ammunition, and other explosives, in accordance with regulations that the Secretary of Agriculture adopts.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-980">
            <num>47.25.980</num>
            <heading>Duties of department.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-25-980__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[See delayed amendment note.]  The department shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-25-980__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>adopt regulations necessary to carry out the food stamp program;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-25-980__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>cooperate with the federal government and do all things necessary to continue state eligibility under the food stamp program;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-25-980__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>comply with the requirements of 7 U.S.C. 2011  2036 (Food Stamp Program);</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-25-980__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establish an electronic application for the food stamp program and allow an applicant to submit an application in electronic format or in other formats required by state and federal law; the electronic application must inform an applicant that a false statement made on the application will be investigated and is punishable under
AS 11.56.210
; in this paragraph, electronic application means an application for benefits or renewal of benefits, whether the department exclusively administers the benefits or administers the benefits in coordination with another state agency or federal agency, electronically completed and submitted through the department's Internet website.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-980__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may designate and change areas in the state in which the food stamp program shall be carried out.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-985">
            <num>47.25.985</num>
            <heading>Violations; penalty.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-25-985__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person is guilty of a misdemeanor if the person</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-25-985__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>knowingly acquires, possesses, uses, alters, or transfers food stamp allotments in violation of
AS 47.25.975
 47.25.980 or the regulations adopted under
AS 47.25.980
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-25-985__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>presents food stamp allotments or causes them to be presented for payment or redemption knowing them to have been transferred, received, altered, or used in a manner violating
AS 47.25.975
 47.25.980 or the regulations adopted under
AS 47.25.980
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-25-985__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>knowingly acquires, uses, alters, or transfers a wage subsidy authorized under
AS 47.25.975</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-985__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>in violation of
AS 47.25.975
 47.25.980,
AS 47.27.025
(e), or the regulations adopted under
AS 47.25.980
or
AS 47.27.025
(e).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-25-985__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon conviction a person shall be fined not more than $1,000 or imprisoned for not more than one year, or both.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-25-990">
            <num>47.25.990</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.25.990.   Definitions.
In
AS 47.25.975
 47.25.985,
(1) department means Department of Health;
(2) food means any food or food product for human consumption except alcoholic beverages and tobacco and includes seeds and plants for use in gardens to produce food for the personal consumption of the eligible household;
(3) food stamp allotments means any coupon, stamp, electronic benefit, or type of allotment issued under 7 U.S.C. 2011  2036 (Food Stamp Program);
(4) food stamp program means the federal food stamp program authorized by 7 U.S.C. 2011  2036.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>