<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-47/chapter-18"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-47/chapter-18"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="47.18"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-47/chapter-18/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-47/chapter-18/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-47/chapter-18/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-47/chapter-18/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_47">
        <num>47</num>
        <heading>Welfare, Social Services, and Institutions</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_47__chp_18">
          <num>18</num>
          <heading>Programs and Services Related to Adolescents</heading>
          <section eId="sec_47-18-010">
            <num>47.18.010</num>
            <heading>Development of statewide plan.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-18-010__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>With the advice of the Alaska Human Relations Commission, the department shall develop a comprehensive statewide plan to ensure the effectiveness and efficiency of state programs that relate to the prevention of adolescent pregnancy and the provision of services to adolescent parents and their children under
AS 47.18.100
 47.18.140, and to peer counseling under
AS 47.18.200
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-18-010__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The plan developed under (a) of this section must</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-010__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>review and include existing programs and services of state government;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-010__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>examine and consider the achievements and experiences of projects that are similar to those authorized under
AS 47.18.100
 47.18.140 and 47.18.200;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-010__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>give priority to the consolidation and improvement of existing programs;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-010__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>make recommendations with regard to the need for new or expanded programs and services within the existing level of funding;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-010__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>consider the findings and recommendations of the Alaska's Adolescent Pregnancy and Parenthood Task Force; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-010__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>make recommendations concerning the incremental implementation of the plan.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-18-010__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Education and Early Development, the Department of Commerce, Community, and Economic Development, and the Department of Labor and Workforce Development shall assist the department in developing the plan required under (a) of this section. In addition, through appropriate means, the department shall solicit advice from teens, parents, educators, school administrators, taxpayers, civic groups, community organizations, Native organizations, officials of local governments, religious institutions, and other concerned persons about how state programs can be coordinated and operated in a manner that will enhance their effectiveness and efficiency in addressing the many needs associated with adolescent parenting, the prevention of adolescent pregnancies, and the provision of adolescent peer counseling.
Article 2. Public Information About Programs.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-18-050">
            <num>47.18.050</num>
            <heading>Public awareness campaign.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-18-050__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall develop and implement statewide a continuing public awareness campaign, including appropriate public forums and workshops, radio and television public service announcements, and press releases designed to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-050__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>communicate to the public the scope and magnitude of the adolescent pregnancy and parenthood problem in the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-050__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>encourage community activities that will educate adults and adolescents about the importance of reducing adolescent pregnancy;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-050__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>enlist the active support and involvement of members of the public and community organizations in the development and implementation of community-based programs and activities to reduce adolescent pregnancy and assist adolescent parents in obtaining needed educational, vocational, and parenting skills.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-18-050__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A primary policy and objective of the public awareness campaign required under (a) of this section shall be to encourage adolescents to abstain from premarital sexual intimacy.
Article 3. Adolescent Pregnancy Projects.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-18-100">
            <num>47.18.100</num>
            <heading>State funding authorized.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.18.100.   State funding authorized.
In order to encourage and support community-based initiatives to combat the many problems associated with adolescent pregnancy and parenthood, the department shall, from appropriations for that purpose, give grants or award contracts to fund a percentage of the cost of local projects designed to prevent adolescent pregnancy and assist adolescent parents in obtaining needed educational, vocational, and parenting skills.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-18-110">
            <num>47.18.110</num>
            <heading>Eligible projects.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-18-110__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Projects funded under
AS 47.18.100
shall be designed with a holistic approach that recognizes the interconnectedness of adolescent parenthood and a broad array of related circumstances, such as low self-esteem, domestic violence, substance abuse, economic security, financial responsibilities of having a child, cultural integrity, sources of adolescent stress, parenting skills, educational and vocational opportunities, and access to reproductive health services.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-18-110__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Projects funded under
AS 47.18.100
may include one or more of the following types of activities:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-110__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>family life education;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-110__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>counseling services for adolescents who are, or who may think they are, pregnant or who want to avoid pregnancy;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-110__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>prenatal care for pregnant adolescents;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-110__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>job training and placement for adolescent parents;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-110__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>educational and support services for adolescent parents;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-110__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>other activities that, in the judgment of the department, are likely to have a tangible effect on combating a problem associated with adolescent pregnancy or parenthood.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-18-120">
            <num>47.18.120</num>
            <heading>Applications for project funding.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-18-120__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person or group seeking funding under
AS 47.18.100
shall apply to the department on a form provided by the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-18-120__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When applying under (a) of this section, the applicant must demonstrate to the satisfaction of the department that the proposed project</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-120__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has been designed with extensive assistance from local community members who represent a variety of interests, cultures, and perspectives on adolescent pregnancy and parenthood;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-120__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is based on sound research, to the maximum extent possible;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-120__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>will maximize collaboration among all relevant agencies involved in the needs being addressed by the project;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-120__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>includes an evaluation component to measure project effectiveness;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-120__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>includes a public awareness campaign component.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-18-140">
            <num>47.18.140</num>
            <heading>Promotion of program and projects.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-18-140__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall take appropriate actions to publicize the availability of funds under
AS 47.18.100
 47.18.140.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-18-140__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall annually conduct regional conferences or workshops across the state to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-140__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>showcase the activities and achievements of projects funded under
AS 47.18.100
 47.18.140 for which the evaluation components have shown a high level of success;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-140__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>encourage and support the replication of these successful projects; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-140__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>increase public awareness of the availability of state administered services and programs to address the many problems associated with adolescent pregnancy and parenthood.
Article 4. Adolescent Peer Counseling.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-18-200">
            <num>47.18.200</num>
            <heading>Peer counselor program.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-18-200__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall develop and implement a continuing statewide program of technical support and assistance to encourage school districts, municipalities, and nonprofit corporations incorporated under
AS 10.20
that initiate implementation, or that are considering implementation, of adolescent peer counseling groups under adult supervision for</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-200__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>prevention of adolescent behavioral patterns that jeopardize physical and mental health and that hamper social, educational, and personal development; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-200__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>spreading information about services that are available to adolescents to help them with their health needs.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-18-200__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The program of technical support required under (a) of this section must include</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-200__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>suggested methods for maintaining a high level of adolescent, parental, and community support for peer counseling groups;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-200__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>workshops, seminars, or other training opportunities for adolescent peer counselors and their adult leaders; this training must include sessions to
(A) develop interpersonal communications skills;
(B) teach accurate health information, emphasizing sexual development;
(C) provide information about services that are available in the peer counselors' areas and how those services can be obtained for pregnancy prevention, and prenatal care; and
(D) encourage adolescents to avoid major risk-taking behavior and to reinforce responsible behavior and self control;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-200__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>assistance in selecting appropriate resource materials for the groups;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-200__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>recommended mechanisms for effectively monitoring and evaluating the activities and accomplishments of the groups; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-200__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>other similar services to assist and encourage school districts and municipalities in establishing and administering adolescent peer counseling groups.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-18-200__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In developing the program of technical support and assistance required under (a) of this section, the department shall review and consider the activities and accomplishments in other states that have developed peer counseling networks. The department shall solicit contributions of money and expertise from the private sector that may be available for this type of program.
Article 5. Foster Care Transition Program.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-18-300">
            <num>47.18.300</num>
            <heading>Program authorized.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-18-300__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department, in coordination with local public and private agencies, shall design, develop, and implement a foster care transition program to provide support and services to individuals who</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-300__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>reach or have reached the age of 16 or older while in state foster care and have not yet reached 23 years of age; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-300__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>meet other eligibility criteria established by the department under (b) of this section.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-18-300__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may adopt regulations to carry out the purposes of
AS 47.18.300
 47.18.390, including regulations establishing eligibility thresholds, standards, and limits for the program. The department shall develop the regulations in consultation with those public and private organizations considered necessary by the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-18-310">
            <num>47.18.310</num>
            <heading>Program design.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.18.310.   Program design.
The department, in coordination with local public and private agencies, shall design the program as a continuation of the training efforts related to independent living skills that were initiated when the state foster care recipients were identified as being likely to remain in state foster care until reaching the age of 18. The program design must require that program participants are directly involved in identifying the program activities that will prepare them for independent living.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-18-320">
            <num>47.18.320</num>
            <heading>Program development.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-18-320__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subject to the availability of an appropriation made for the purposes of
AS 47.18.300
 47.18.390, the program may provide</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-320__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>education and vocational training;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-320__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>assistance in obtaining educational and vocational training;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-320__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>career and employment services;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-320__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>training in basic life skills;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-320__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>housing and utility assistance;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-320__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>mentoring and counseling; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-320__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>other appropriate services to complement the efforts of former state foster care recipients to achieve self-sufficiency.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-18-320__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In developing the program, the department shall cooperate with and coordinate the use of the resources available from other state and federal agencies designed to provide support and services consistent with the purposes of the program.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-18-320__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If appropriations to meet the purposes of this section are insufficient, the department shall submit a written report to the legislature advising the legislature of</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-320__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the department's efforts to use existing funds efficiently; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-320__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the opportunities and services the department cannot provide under the existing appropriation level.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-18-320__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When an individual 16 years of age or older who has been in state custody under
AS 47.10
for at least six months is released from state custody, the department shall, in addition to any training, services, and assistance provided under (a)  (c) of this section, provide the individual with or assist the individual with obtaining the individual's</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-320__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>birth certificate; the birth certificate may be an official or certified copy;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-320__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>social security card;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-320__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>health insurance information;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-320__subsec_d__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>medical records;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-320__subsec_d__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>driver's license or identification card; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-18-320__subsec_d__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>certificate of degree of Indian or Alaska Native blood, if applicable.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-18-330">
            <num>47.18.330</num>
            <heading>Program implementation.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-18-330__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may implement the program through the award of contracts or grants to qualified entities to provide services under the program. The department may award contracts and grants if the contracts and grants further the purposes of and meet the requirements of
AS 47.18.300
 47.18.390 and applicable regulations adopted under those sections.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-18-330__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Contracts awarded under this section shall be administered in accordance with
AS 47.05.015
and regulations adopted under that section. Grants awarded under this section shall be awarded using requirements established in regulations adopted under
AS 47.18.300
 47.18.390 that are substantially similar to those set out in
AS 47.05.015
for contracts.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-18-390">
            <num>47.18.390</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.18.390.   Definitions.
In
AS 47.18.300
 47.18.390,
(1) program means the foster care transition program authorized under
AS 47.18.300
 47.18.390;
(2) qualified entities means municipalities, other political subdivisions of the state, nonprofit corporations formed under
AS 10.20
, churches and religious organizations, and incorporated and unincorporated entities operating within the state that meet the requirements established by the department in regulation;
(3) state foster care means foster care, as defined in
AS 47.10.990
, that is provided to a person who is in the custody of the department under
AS 47.10
and
AS 47.12
.
Article 6. General Provisions.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-18-900">
            <num>47.18.900</num>
            <heading>Definition.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.18.900.   Definition.
In this chapter, department means the Department of Family and Community Services.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>