<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-34/chapter-45"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-34/chapter-45"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="34.45"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-34/chapter-45/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-34/chapter-45/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-34/chapter-45/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-34/chapter-45/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_34">
        <num>34</num>
        <heading>Property</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_34__chp_45">
          <num>45</num>
          <heading>Unclaimed Property</heading>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-010">
            <num>34.45.010</num>
            <heading>Record of consignee or bailee.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.45.010.   Record of consignee or bailee.
When personal property is consigned to or deposited with a forwarding merchant, wharf, warehouse, or tavern keeper, or the keeper of a depot for the reception and storage of trunks, baggage, merchandise, or other personal property, the consignee or bailee shall immediately record a description of the property, and the date of receipt, in a book kept by the consignee or bailee.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-020">
            <num>34.45.020</num>
            <heading>Consignee's or bailee's notice to owner.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.45.020.   Consignee's or bailee's notice to owner.
If the property is not left with the consignee or bailee for the purpose of being forwarded, disposed of, or kept according to directions received by the consignee or bailee, at or before the time of the reception of the property, and if the name and residence of the owner of the property is known to the person having possession of the property, the consignee or bailee shall immediately notify the owner, by letter directed to the owner and deposited in the post office, of the reception of the property.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-030">
            <num>34.45.030</num>
            <heading>Sale.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.45.030.   Sale.
If property held by a person described in
AS 34.45.010
is not claimed and taken away within one year after the time it is received, the person having possession of the property may sell the property in the manner provided in
AS 34.45.010
 34.45.080, except that property described in
AS 34.45.110
 34.45.260 shall be reported to the Department of Revenue under
AS 34.45.280
and is subject to
AS 34.45.290
 34.45.780.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-040">
            <num>34.45.040</num>
            <heading>Presale inventory and notice.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-45-040__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before the property is sold, the person in possession of it shall request the district judge or magistrate in the judicial district where the property is located to inventory the property.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-040__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon the request the district judge or magistrate or a person, other than the holder of the property or the holder's agent, appointed by the district judge or magistrate, shall attend and, in the presence of the holder, or the holder's agent, shall open, examine, and inventory the property.  The inventory must be in duplicate, one copy of which shall be filed with the district judge or magistrate and one copy retained by the holder of the property.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-040__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After the property is inventoried, the holder, or the holder's agent, may give notice of an intention to sell it in the following manner:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-040__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if the name and residence of the owner of the property is known, by serving the notice upon the owner either personally, or at the owner's place of residence or business, or by registered mail;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-040__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if the name and residence of the owner of the property is unknown to the holder, then the holder may serve the notice by publication once a week for two successive weeks in a newspaper of general circulation published in the area nearest to where the property is held.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-040__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The notice must contain (1) a reasonably correct description of the property; (2) the name and residence of the owner, if known; (3) the name and residence of the holder; (4) the amount of the charges accrued and costs incurred; and (5) a statement that the holder on a certain date, that shall be specified and may not be less than three weeks after the day on which the notice is served or, if published, on which the notice is first published, will apply to the district judge or magistrate for an order to sell the property to satisfy all charges and costs that have accrued or been incurred to that date.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-050">
            <num>34.45.050</num>
            <heading>Order of sale.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-45-050__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the owner or person entitled to the possession of the property, before the date specified in the notice, fails to redeem it as provided in
AS 34.45.060
, the district judge or magistrate, upon verified proof that the service or publication is filed with the court, shall enter an order directing the sale of the property at public auction on a date not less than 10 days after the order to satisfy all charges and costs.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-050__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The holder or the holder's agent shall give public notice of sale by posting, within five miles of the place of sale, in three public places, a notice that the property will be sold at public auction. The notice must also contain a reasonably correct description of the property, the name and residence of the owner if known, the name and residence of the holder, and the time and place of sale.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-060">
            <num>34.45.060</num>
            <heading>Sale at public auction.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-45-060__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The peace officer shall sell the property at public auction to the highest bidder in the manner provided for the sale of personal property on execution.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-060__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The sale of the property conveys good title superior to all liens, encumbrances, and mortgages, and without right of redemption; but the owner or mortgagee, at any time before the sale, may redeem the property by claiming it and paying all charges of the holder against it and all costs incurred or accrued under
AS 34.45.010
 34.45.080 up to and including the date on which the owner or mortgagee redeems it.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-060__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The proceeds from the sale shall be applied in payment, first, of all reasonable costs of sale, inventory and publishing, posting, serving and preparing notices, including the district judge's or magistrate's fees and the fees of the peace officer, and second, of the holder's charges, with interest at the legal rate, against the property.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-070">
            <num>34.45.070</num>
            <heading>Proceeds of sale.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-45-070__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The peace officer, upon completion of the sale of the property, shall make and file with the district judge or magistrate a verified, written return of the conduct of the sale and of the application of the proceeds derived from it, and shall pay all money in excess of costs and charges to the district judge or magistrate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-070__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The district judge or magistrate shall hold the money in trust for the owner of the property and shall pay it to the owner upon the latter's making a written, verified claim to it, with proof of ownership, within one year after the date of the sale.  If no claim is made within one year after the date of the sale, the district judge or magistrate shall immediately pay the excess proceeds to the Department of Revenue.  Excess proceeds that are required to be paid over to the Department of Revenue under this section are subject to
AS 34.45.280
and 34.45.330  34.45.780.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-080">
            <num>34.45.080</num>
            <heading>Sale of perishable property.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-45-080__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Property of a perishable nature and subject to decay by keeping, if not taken away within 30 days after it has been left, may be sold by giving 10 days' notice of sale.  In that case the notice provided in
AS 34.45.040
need not be given.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-080__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The sale shall be conducted and the proceeds of the sale shall be applied in the manner provided in
AS 34.45.010
 34.45.080, except that property in a state of decay, or that is plainly subject to immediate decay, may be summarily sold by order of a district judge or magistrate, after inspection of it, as provided in
AS 34.45.010
 34.45.080.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-080__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The return of the sale shall be made and the proceeds derived from it shall be applied in the manner provided in
AS 34.45.060
and 34.45.070.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-085">
            <num>34.45.085</num>
            <heading>Definition.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.45.085.   Definition.
In
AS 34.45.010
and 34.45.020, property does not include property covered by
AS 14.57.200
 14.57.290.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-110">
            <num>34.45.110</num>
            <heading>General rule for property presumed abandoned.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-45-110__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as otherwise provided in
AS 34.45.120
 34.45.780, all intangible property, including income or increment derived from the property, less lawful charges, that is held, issued, or owing in the ordinary course of a holder's business and has remained unclaimed by the owner for more than three years after becoming payable or distributable is presumed abandoned.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-110__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Property is payable or distributable for the purposes of
AS 34.45.120
 34.45.780 even if the owner failed to demand the property or to present an instrument or document required to receive payment of the property.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-120">
            <num>34.45.120</num>
            <heading>General rules for taking custody of unclaimed intangible property.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.45.120.   General rules for taking custody of unclaimed intangible property.
Unless otherwise provided in this chapter or by another statute of the state, intangible property is subject to the custody of the state as unclaimed property if the conditions raising a presumption of abandonment under
AS 34.45.110
or 34.45.140  34.45.260 are satisfied and
(1) the last known address of the apparent owner, as shown on the records of the holder, is in the state;
(2) the records of the holder do not reflect the identity of the person entitled to the property and it is established that the last known address of the person entitled to the property is in the state;
(3) the records of the holder do not reflect the last known address of the apparent owner, and it is established that
(A) the last known address of the person entitled to the property is in the state, or
(B) the holder is a domiciliary or a government or governmental subdivision or agency, including a municipality, of the state and has not previously paid or delivered the property to the state of the last known address of the apparent owner or other person entitled to the property;
(4) the last known address of the apparent owner, as shown on the records of the holder, is in a state that either does not provide by law for the escheat or custodial taking of the property, or its escheat or unclaimed property law is not applicable to the property, and the holder is a domiciliary, government, or governmental subdivision or agency, including a municipality, of the state;
(5) the last known address of the apparent owner, as shown on the records of the holder, is in a foreign nation and the holder is a domiciliary, government, or governmental subdivision, including a municipality, or agency of the state; or
(6) the transaction out of which the property arose occurred in the state and
(A) the last known address of the apparent owner or other person entitled to the property is unknown, or the last known address of the apparent owner or other person entitled to the property is in a state that either does not provide by law for the escheat or custodial taking of the property or its escheat or unclaimed property law does not apply to the property, and
(B) the holder is a domiciliary of a state that either does not provide by law for the escheat or custodial taking of the property or its escheat or unclaimed property law does not apply to the property.
Article 3. Conditions Leading to Presumption of Abandonment of Particular Types of Personal Property.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-140">
            <num>34.45.140</num>
            <heading>Traveler's checks and money orders.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-45-140__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subject to (d) of this section, money payable on a traveler's check that has been outstanding for more than 15 years after its issuance is presumed abandoned unless the owner, within the preceding 15 years, has communicated in writing with the issuer concerning it or otherwise indicated an interest as evidenced by a memorandum or other record, on file, prepared by an employee of the issuer.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-140__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subject to (d) of this section, money payable on a money order or similar written instrument, other than a third-party bank check, that has been outstanding for more than seven years after its issuance is presumed abandoned unless the owner, within the preceding seven years, has communicated in writing with the issuer concerning it or otherwise indicated an interest as evidenced by a memorandum or other record, on file, prepared by an employee of the issuer.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-140__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A holder may not deduct from the amount of a traveler's check or money order a charge imposed for failure to present the instrument for payment unless there is a valid and enforceable written contract between the issuer and the owner of the instrument under which the issuer may impose a charge, and the issuer regularly imposes charges and does not regularly reverse or otherwise cancel them.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-140__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Money payable on a traveler's check, money order, or similar written instrument, other than a third-party check, described in (a) and (b) of this section, is not subject to the custody of the state as unclaimed property unless</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-140__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the records of the issuer show that the traveler's check, money order, or similar written instrument was purchased in the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-140__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the issuer has its principal place of business in the state and the records of the issuer do not show the state in which the traveler's check, money order, or similar written instrument was purchased; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-140__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the issuer has its principal place of business in the state, the records of the issuer show the state in which the traveler's check, money order, or similar written instrument was purchased and the state of purchase either does not provide by law for the escheat or custodial taking of the property or its escheat or unclaimed property law is not applicable to the property.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-140__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding any other provision of
AS 34.45.110
 34.45.780, (d) of this section applies to money payable on traveler's checks, money orders, and similar written instruments, other than a third-party bank check, presumed abandoned after January 31, 1965, except to the extent that those sums have been paid over to a state before January 1, 1974.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-150">
            <num>34.45.150</num>
            <heading>Checks, drafts, and similar instruments issued or certified by banking and financial organizations.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-45-150__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Other than money payable on an instrument that is subject to
AS 34.45.140
, money payable on a check, draft, or similar instrument on which a banking or financial organization is directly liable, including a cashier's check and a certified check, that has been outstanding for more than five years after it was payable or after its issuance if payable on demand, is presumed abandoned. This presumption does not apply if the owner, within the preceding five years, has communicated in writing with the banking or financial organization concerning the instrument or has otherwise indicated an interest as evidenced by a memorandum or other record, on file, prepared by an employee of the organization.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-150__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A holder may not deduct from the amount of an instrument subject to this section a charge imposed for failure to present the instrument for payment unless there is a valid and enforceable written contract between the holder and the owner of the instrument under which the holder may impose a charge, and the holder regularly imposes the charges and does not regularly reverse or otherwise cancel them.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-160">
            <num>34.45.160</num>
            <heading>Bank deposits and money in financial organizations.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-45-160__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A demand, savings, or matured time deposit with a banking or financial organization, including a deposit that is automatically renewable, and money paid toward the purchase of a share, a mutual investment certificate, or other intangible property interest in a banking or financial organization is presumed abandoned unless the owner, within the preceding five years, has</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-160__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in the case of a deposit, increased or decreased its amount or presented the passbook or other similar evidence of the deposit for the crediting of interest;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-160__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>communicated in writing with the banking or financial organization concerning the property; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-160__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>otherwise indicated an interest in the property as evidenced by a memorandum or other record, on file, prepared by an employee of the banking or financial organization.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-160__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A holder may not impose, with respect to property described in (a) of this section, a charge due to dormancy or inactivity, or cease payment of interest.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-160__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Property described in (a) of this section that is automatically renewable is matured for purposes of (a) of this section upon the expiration of its initial time period. However, in the case of a renewal to which the owner consents at or about the time of renewal by communicating in writing with the banking or financial organization or by otherwise indicating consent as evidenced by a memorandum or other record on file, prepared by an employee of the organization, the property is matured upon the expiration of the last time period for which consent was given.  If, at the time provided for delivery in
AS 34.45.320
, a penalty or forfeiture in the payment of interest would result from the delivery of the property, the time for delivery is extended until the time when no penalty or forfeiture would result.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-160__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of this section, property includes interest and dividends.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-170">
            <num>34.45.170</num>
            <heading>Money owing under life insurance policies.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-45-170__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Money held or owing under a life or endowment insurance policy or annuity contract that has matured or terminated is presumed abandoned if unclaimed for more than three years after the money became due and payable as established from the records of the insurance company holding or owing the money.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-170__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a person other than the insured or annuitant is entitled to the money and the address of that person is not known to the company, or it is not definite and certain from the records of the company who is entitled to the money, it is presumed that the last known address of the person entitled to the money is the same as the last known address of the insured or annuitant according to the records of the company.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-170__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of this section, a life endowment insurance policy or annuity contract not matured by actual proof of the death of the insured or annuitant according to the records of the company is matured and the proceeds are due and payable if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-170__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the company has received due proof that the insured or annuitant has died; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-170__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the insured has attained, or would have attained if still living, the limiting age under the mortality table on which the reserve is based and
(A) the policy was in force at the time the insured attained, or would have attained, the limiting age; and
(B) neither the insured nor another person appearing to have an interest in the policy has, within the preceding two years, according to the records of the company, assigned, readjusted, or paid premiums on the policy, subjected the policy to a loan, corresponded in writing with the company concerning the policy, or otherwise indicated an interest as evidence by a memorandum or other record, on file, prepared by an employee of the company.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-170__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of this section, the application of an automatic premium loan provision or other nonforfeiture provision contained in an insurance policy does not prevent a policy from being matured or terminated under (a) of this section if the insured has died or the insured or the beneficiary of the policy otherwise has become entitled to the proceeds of the policy before the depletion of the cash surrender value of a policy by the application of those nonforfeiture provisions.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-170__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the laws of the state or the terms of the life insurance policy require the company to give notice to the insured or the owner that an automatic premium loan provision or other nonforfeiture provision has been exercised and the notice is to be given to an insured or owner whose last known address, according to the records of the company, is in the state but is undeliverable, the company shall make a reasonable search to ascertain the policyholder's correct address to which the notice must be mailed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-170__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, if the company learns of the death of the insured or annuitant and the beneficiary has not communicated with the insurer within four months after the death, the company shall take reasonable steps to pay the proceeds to the beneficiary.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-170__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Commencing September 8, 1988, every change-of-beneficiary form issued by an insurance company under a life or endowment insurance policy or annuity contract to an insured or owner who is a resident of the state must request the following information:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-170__subsec_g__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name of each beneficiary, or if a class of beneficiaries is named, the name of each current beneficiary in the class;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-170__subsec_g__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the address of each beneficiary; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-170__subsec_g__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the relationship of each beneficiary to the insured.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-175">
            <num>34.45.175</num>
            <heading>Certain property distributed in insurance company reorganizations.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-45-175__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The following property distributable in the course of a demutualization or related reorganization of an insurance company is considered abandoned two years after the date of demutualization or reorganization as follows:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-175__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>money that remains unclaimed and the owner has not otherwise communicated with the holder or its agent regarding the property as evidenced by a memorandum or other record on file with the holder or its agent;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-175__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>stock or other equity interest if
(A) the instruments or statements reflecting the distribution are either mailed to the owner and returned by the post office as undeliverable, or not mailed to the owner because of an address on the books and records of the holder that is known to be incorrect; and
(B) the owner has not otherwise communicated with the holder or its agent regarding the property as evidenced by a memorandum or other record on file with the holder or agent.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-175__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Property that is not subject to (a) of this section is reportable as otherwise provided in
AS 34.45.110
 34.45.780.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-180">
            <num>34.45.180</num>
            <heading>Deposits held by utilities.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.45.180.   Deposits held by utilities.
A deposit, including interest on the deposit, made by a subscriber with a utility to secure payment, or money paid in advance for utility services to be furnished, less lawful deductions, that remains unclaimed by the owner for more than one year after the termination of the services for which the deposit or advance payment was made is presumed abandoned.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-190">
            <num>34.45.190</num>
            <heading>Refunds held by business associations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.45.190.   Refunds held by business associations.
Except to the extent otherwise ordered by a court or administrative agency, money that a business association has been ordered by the court or administrative agency to refund is presumed abandoned if it remains unclaimed by the owner for more than one year after it became payable in accordance with the final determination or order providing for the refund, regardless of whether the final determination or order requires the owner to make a claim for it.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-200">
            <num>34.45.200</num>
            <heading>Stock and other intangible interests in business associations.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-45-200__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Stock or other equity interest in a business association is presumed abandoned five years after the earliest of the date</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-200__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>of the most recent dividend, stock split, or other distribution unclaimed by the owner;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-200__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>that a statement of account or other notification or communication concerning the stock or other equity interest was returned as undeliverable; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-200__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>that the holder of the stock or other equity interest discontinued mailings, notifications, or communications to the owner.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-200__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unmatured or unredeemed debt of a business association, other than a bearer bond or an original issue discount bond, is presumed abandoned five years after the date of the most recent interest payment unclaimed by the owner.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-200__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Matured or redeemed debt, including bearer bonds and original issue discount bonds, is presumed abandoned five years after the date of maturity or redemption.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-200__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>At the time property is presumed abandoned under this section, any other property right accrued or accruing to the owner as a result of the property interest and not previously presumed abandoned is also presumed abandoned.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-200__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A distribution of net margins by a cooperative incorporated under
AS 10.25
is presumed abandoned if the distribution remains unclaimed by the owner for more than one year after the date authorized for the distribution. The distribution presumed abandoned under this subsection reverts to the cooperative if the cooperative has, at least six months before the proposed date that the distribution reverts to the cooperative, mailed a notice of the proposed reversion to the last known address of the owner as shown on the cooperative records and</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-200__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if the cooperative does not have an Internet website, published notice of the proposed reversion in the manner provided by law or court rule for service of a summons by publication; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-200__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if the cooperative has an Internet website,
(A) posted for at least 180 days on the cooperative's Internet website</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-200__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>a list of the persons for whom the cooperative has unclaimed distributions; and
(ii) a notice of the proposed reversion that prominently displays a notice line and that provides a link to the list identified in (i) of this subparagraph; the notice must appear on the home page of the cooperative's Internet website; and
(B) published once a week for four consecutive weeks in a newspaper of general circulation in the judicial district where the cooperative is located a notice of the proposed reversion that provides the address of the cooperative's Internet website and indicates that the list identified in (A)(i) of this paragraph can be found at that address; the notice shall be published simultaneously</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-200__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>in the print version of the newspaper in a display advertisement; the display advertisement must be at least 18 square inches in area and must prominently display the notice line at the top; and
(ii) on the Internet version of the newspaper, if an Internet version of the newspaper exists.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-200__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In (e) of this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-200__subsec_f__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>newspaper of general circulation has the meaning given in
AS 09.35.140
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-200__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>notice line means the words do we owe you money? unclaimed (name of cooperative) capital credits in capital letters.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-210">
            <num>34.45.210</num>
            <heading>Property of business associations held in course of dissolution.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.45.210.   Property of business associations held in course of dissolution.
Intangible property distributable in the course of a dissolution of a business association that remains unclaimed by the owner for more than one year after the date specified for final distribution is presumed abandoned.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-220">
            <num>34.45.220</num>
            <heading>Property held by agents and fiduciaries.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-45-220__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Intangible property and income or increment derived from the intangible property held in a fiduciary capacity for the benefit of another person is presumed abandoned unless the owner, within three years after it has become payable or distributable, has increased or decreased the principal, accepted payment of principal or income, communicated concerning the property, or otherwise indicated an interest as evidenced by a memorandum or other record, on file, prepared by the fiduciary.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-220__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Money in an individual retirement account or a retirement plan for self-employed individuals or similar account or plan established under the internal revenue laws of the United States is not payable or distributable within the meaning of (a) of this section unless, under the terms of the account or plan, distribution of all or part of the funds would then be mandatory.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-220__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For the purpose of this section, a person who holds property as an agent for a business association is considered as holding the property in a fiduciary capacity for that business association alone, unless the agreement between that person and the business association provides otherwise.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-220__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For the purposes of this chapter, a person who is considered as holding property in a fiduciary capacity for a business association alone is the holder of the property only so far as the interest of the business association in the property is concerned, and the business association is the holder of the property so far as the interest of another person in the property is concerned.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-230">
            <num>34.45.230</num>
            <heading>Property held by courts and public agencies.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.45.230.   Property held by courts and public agencies.
Except as provided by
AS 34.45.720
(d), intangible property held for the owner by a court, state, municipality, or other government, governmental subdivision, or agency, public corporation, or public authority, that remains unclaimed by the owner for more than one year after becoming payable or distributable, is presumed abandoned.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-240">
            <num>34.45.240</num>
            <heading>Gift certificates and credit memos.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-45-240__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A gift certificate or a credit memo, issued in the ordinary course of an issuer's business, that remains unclaimed by the owner for more than three years after becoming payable or distributable is presumed abandoned.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-240__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In the case of a gift certificate, the amount presumed abandoned is the price paid by the purchaser for the gift certificate.  In the case of a credit memo, the amount presumed abandoned is the amount credited to the recipient of the memo.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-250">
            <num>34.45.250</num>
            <heading>Wages.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.45.250.   Wages.
Unpaid wages, including wages represented by unpresented payroll checks, owing in the ordinary course of the holder's business and that remain unclaimed by the owner for more than one year after becoming payable are presumed abandoned.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-260">
            <num>34.45.260</num>
            <heading>Contents of safe deposit box or other safekeeping repository.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.45.260.   Contents of safe deposit box or other safekeeping repository.
All tangible and intangible personal property held in a safe deposit box or other safekeeping repository in a financial organization in the state in the ordinary course of the holder's business, and proceeds resulting from the sale of the property permitted by other law, that remain unclaimed by the owner for more than one year after the lease or rental period on the box or other repository has expired, are presumed abandoned.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-270">
            <num>34.45.270</num>
            <heading>Burden of proof as to property evidenced by record of check, draft, or similar instrument.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.45.270.   Burden of proof as to property evidenced by record of check, draft, or similar instrument.
A record of the issuance of a check, draft, or similar instrument is prima facie evidence of an obligation.  In claiming property from a holder who is also the issuer, the department's burden of proof as to the existence and amount of the property and its abandonment is satisfied by showing issuance of the instrument and passage of the requisite period of abandonment.  Defenses of payment, satisfaction, discharge, and want of consideration are affirmative defenses that must be established by the holder.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-280">
            <num>34.45.280</num>
            <heading>Report of abandoned personal property.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-45-280__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person holding personal property, tangible or intangible, presumed abandoned and subject to custody as unclaimed property under
AS 34.45.110
 34.45.430, shall report to the department concerning the property as provided in this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-280__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The report must be made on a form bearing a notice that statements are made under penalty of unsworn falsification and must include</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-280__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>except with respect to traveler's checks and money orders, the name, if known, and last known address, if any, of each person appearing from the records of the holder to be the owner of property, the value of which is $100 or more, presumed abandoned under
AS 34.45.110
 34.45.430 and other statutes specifically made subject to this reporting requirement;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-280__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in the case of unclaimed money amounting to $100 or more, held or owing under a life or endowment insurance policy or annuity contract, the full name and last known address of the insured or annuitant and of the beneficiary or other person who is entitled to the proceeds according to the records of the insurance company holding or owing the funds;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-280__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in the case of the contents of a safe deposit box or other safekeeping repository or of other tangible personal property, a description of the property and the place where it is held and may be inspected by the department and any amounts owing to the holder;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-280__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the nature and identifying number, if any, or description of the property and the amount appearing from the records to be due; items of value under $100 each may be reported in the aggregate;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-280__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the date the property became payable, demandable, or returnable, and the date of the last transaction with the apparent owner with respect to the property; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-280__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>other information that the department prescribes by regulation as necessary for the administration of this chapter.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-280__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the holder of property presumed abandoned and subject to custody as unclaimed property is a successor to other persons who previously held the property for the apparent owner, or the holder has changed the holder's name while holding the property, the holder shall file with the holder's report all known names and addresses of each previous holder of the property.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-280__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The report required under (a) of this section shall be filed before November 1 of each year for unclaimed property held as of June 30 of that year. On written request by a person required to file a report, the commissioner may postpone the reporting date.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-280__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Not more than 120 days before filing the report required by this section, the holder in possession of property presumed abandoned and subject to custody as unclaimed property under
AS 34.45.110
 34.45.430 shall send written notice to the apparent owner at the owner's last known address informing the owner that the holder is in possession of property subject to this chapter if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-280__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the holder has in its records an address for the apparent owner that the holder believes to be accurate;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-280__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the claim of the apparent owner is not barred by the statute of limitations; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-280__subsec_e__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the property has a value of $100 or more.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-280__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The requirements of this section apply to the holder of intangible property with a total aggregate value greater than $750 that is presumed abandoned under
AS 34.45.110
 34.45.780 during the year preceding June 30 of each year. For purposes of determining total aggregate value under this subsection, the holder shall include all intangible property from prior years that was not reported under
AS 34.45.110
 34.45.780.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-290">
            <num>34.45.290</num>
            <heading>Requests for reports and examination of records.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-45-290__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may require a person who has not filed a report under
AS 34.45.280
or a person who the department believes has filed an inaccurate, incomplete, or false report to file a verified report in a form specified by the department. The report must state whether the person is holding property reportable under
AS 34.45.110
 34.45.780, describe property not previously reported or as to which the department has made inquiry, and specifically identify and state the amounts of the property that may be in issue.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-290__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department, at reasonable times and upon reasonable notice, may examine the records of any person to determine whether the person has complied with
AS 34.45.110
 34.45.780. The department may conduct the examination even if the person believes it is not in possession of any property that must be reported, paid, or delivered under
AS 34.45.110
 34.45.780. The department may contract with any other person to conduct the examination on behalf of the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-290__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department at reasonable times may examine the records of an agent, including a dividend disbursing agent or transfer agent, of a business association that is the holder of property presumed abandoned if the department has given the notice required by (b) of this section to both the association and the agent at least 90 days before the examination.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-290__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Documents and working papers obtained or compiled by the department or the department's agents, employees, contractors, or designated representatives in the course of conducting an examination under
AS 34.45.110
 34.45.780 are confidential and are not public records, but the documents and papers may be</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-290__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>used by the department in the course of an action to collect unclaimed property or otherwise enforce
AS 34.45.110
 34.45.780;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-290__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>used in joint examinations conducted with or under an agreement with another state, the federal government, or any other governmental subdivision, agency, or instrumentality;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-290__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>produced under subpoena or court order; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-290__subsec_d__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>disclosed to the unclaimed property office of another state for that state's use in circumstances equivalent to those described in this subsection, if the other state is bound to keep the documents and papers confidential.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-290__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If an examination of the records of a person results in the disclosure of property reportable under
AS 34.45.110
 34.45.780, the department may assess the cost of the examination against the holder at the rate of $200 a day for each examiner, or a greater amount that is reasonable and was incurred, but the assessment may not exceed the value of the property found to be reportable under
AS 34.45.110
 34.45.780. The cost of an examination made under (c) of this section may be assessed only against the business association.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-290__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a holder does not maintain the records required by
AS 34.45.300
and the records of the holder available for the periods subject to
AS 34.45.110
 34.45.780 are insufficient to permit the preparation of a report, the department may require the holder to report and pay to the department the amount the department reasonably estimates, on the basis of any available records of the holder or by any other reasonable method of estimation, should have been but was not reported.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-300">
            <num>34.45.300</num>
            <heading>Retention of records.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-45-300__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as otherwise provided in (b) of this section, a holder required to file a report under
AS 34.45.280
shall maintain the records containing the information required to be included in the report for 10 years after the holder files the report, unless a shorter period is provided by regulations adopted by the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-300__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A business association that sells, or provides such instruments to others for sale, in the state its traveler's checks, money orders, or other similar written instruments, other than third-party bank checks on which the business association is directly liable, shall maintain a record of the instruments while they remain outstanding, indicating the state and date of issue, for three years after the date the property is reportable.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-310">
            <num>34.45.310</num>
            <heading>Notice and publication of lists of unclaimed property.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-45-310__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall notify apparent owners of unclaimed property under
AS 34.45.110
 34.45.780 in the manner and method set out in (b) of this section. In deciding whether to use an additional method specified in (b)(2) of this section, and which of those methods to use, the department shall employ the most cost-effective method available within its appropriations.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-310__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-310__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall notify all apparent owners of the unclaimed property in accordance with this section by means of posting on the department's website on the Internet;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-310__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>may use any of the following to provide additional notice to the apparent owners:
(A) publication in a newspaper of general circulation in the area of the state in which the last known address of a person to be named in the notice is located or, if the address is unknown, in the area in which the holder has its principal place of business in the state;
(B) individual contact by regular or electronic mail, or by telephone, if the department has current contact information on file under
AS 34.45.110
 34.45.780;
(C) any other manner and method that the department considers effective for providing notice and publication under
AS 34.45.110
 34.45.780.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-310__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In its notice and publication under (b) of this section, the department shall provide the names of the apparent owners of the property and information regarding recovery of the unclaimed property.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-310__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department is not required to publish in the notice an item of less than $100 in value.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-310__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This section does not apply to money payable on traveler's checks, money orders, and other written instruments presumed abandoned under
AS 34.45.140
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-320">
            <num>34.45.320</num>
            <heading>Payment or delivery of abandoned property.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-45-320__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as otherwise provided in (b) of this section, a person who is required to file a report under
AS 34.45.280
, shall, at the time of filing the report under that section, pay or deliver to the administrator all of the property shown on the report and remaining unclaimed by the apparent owner. Upon written request showing good cause, the administrator may postpone the payment or delivery upon the terms or conditions the administrator considers necessary and appropriate. The property paid or delivered to the administrator must include all interest, dividends, increments, and accretions due, payable, or distributable on the property at the time of filing the report. If payment or delivery is postponed, the property paid or delivered to the administrator must include all interest, dividends, increments, and accretions due, payable, or distributable on the day that the property is paid or delivered to the administrator.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-320__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the owner establishes the right to receive the abandoned property to the satisfaction of the holder before the property has been delivered or if it appears that the presumption of abandonment is erroneous, the holder need not pay or deliver the property to the department, and the property is no longer presumed abandoned. The holder shall file with the department a written explanation, made under penalty of unsworn falsification in the second degree, of the proof of claim or of the error in the presumption of abandonment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-320__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 12 ch 145 SLA 1996.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-320__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The holder of an equity interest under
AS 34.45.200
shall deliver a duplicate certificate, or other evidence of ownership if the holder does not issue certificates of ownership, to the department. Upon delivery of a duplicate certificate to the department, the holder and a transfer agent, registrar, or other person acting for or on behalf of a holder in executing or delivering the duplicate certificate is relieved of all liability, in accordance with the provisions of
AS 34.45.330
to every person, including a person acquiring the original certificate or the duplicate of the certificate issued to the department, for loss or damage resulting to a person by the issuance and delivery to the department of the duplicate certificate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-330">
            <num>34.45.330</num>
            <heading>Custody by state.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-45-330__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon the payment or delivery of property to the department, the state assumes custody and responsibility for the safekeeping of the property.  A person who pays or delivers property to the department in good faith is relieved of all liability to the extent of the value of the property paid or delivered for a claim existing at the time of the payment or delivery or that may arise or be made with respect to the property after the payment or delivery.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-330__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A holder who has paid money to the department under
AS 34.45.110
 34.45.430 may make payment to a person appearing to the holder to be entitled to payment.  Upon receiving proof of payment from the holder and proof that the payee was entitled to the payment, the department shall promptly reimburse the holder for the payment without imposing a fee or other charge.  If reimbursement is sought for a payment made on a negotiable instrument, including a traveler's check or money order, the department shall reimburse the holder under this subsection when the holder files proof that the instrument was presented and that payment was made to a person who appeared to the holder to be entitled to payment.  The department shall reimburse the holder for payment made under this subsection even if the holder paid a person whose claim was barred under
AS 34.45.430
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-330__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A holder who has delivered property other than money to the department under
AS 34.45.110
 34.45.430 may reclaim the property if it is still in the possession of the department, without payment of a fee or other charge, upon filing proof that the owner has claimed the property from the holder.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-330__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may accept the holder's affidavit as sufficient proof of the facts that entitle the holder to recover money and property under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-330__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a holder pays or delivers property to the department in good faith and another person subsequently claims the property from the holder or another state claims the property under the laws of the other state relating to escheat or unclaimed property, the department, upon receiving written notice of the claim, shall defend the holder against the claim and indemnify the holder against liability on the claim.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-330__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Property removed from a safe deposit box or other safekeeping repository is received by the department subject to the holder's right under this subsection to be reimbursed for the actual cost of the opening and to a valid lien or contract providing for the holder to be reimbursed for unpaid rent or storage charges.  For charges other than the actual cost of the opening, the department shall reimburse or pay the holder an amount no greater than the value of the property recovered less the department's selling cost.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-330__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For the purposes of this section, good faith means that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-330__subsec_g__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>payment or delivery was made in a reasonable attempt to comply with this chapter;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-330__subsec_g__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the person delivering the property was not a fiduciary then in breach of trust in respect to the property, and had a reasonable basis for believing, based on the facts then known to the person, that the property was abandoned for the purposes of this chapter; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-330__subsec_g__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>there is no showing that the records under which the delivery was made did not meet reasonable commercial standards of practice in the industry.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-340">
            <num>34.45.340</num>
            <heading>Crediting of dividends, interest, or increments to owner's account.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-45-340__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>for appreciation of securities, if property other than money is paid or delivered to the department under
AS 34.45.110
 34.45.430, the owner is entitled to receive from the department dividends, interest, or other increments realized or accruing on the property at or before the department's liquidation or conversion of the property into money.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-360">
            <num>34.45.360</num>
            <heading>Public sale of abandoned property.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-45-360__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (c) and (d) of this section, the department, within three years after receiving abandoned property, shall sell it to the highest bidder at public sale in the area of the state that the department determines to be the most favorable market for the property involved.  The department may decline the highest bid and reoffer the property for sale if in the judgment of the department the bid is insufficient.  If in the judgment of the department the probable cost of sale exceeds the value of the property, the department need not offer the property for sale.  A sale held under this section must be preceded by a single publication of notice, at least three weeks in advance of sale, in a newspaper of general circulation in the general area in which the property is to be sold.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-360__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Securities listed on an established stock exchange must be sold at prices prevailing at the time of sale on the exchange.  Other securities may be sold over the counter at prices prevailing at the time of sale or by another method the department considers advisable.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-360__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless the department considers it to be in the best interest of the state to do otherwise, the department shall hold all securities that have been delivered to the department, other than those presumed abandoned under
AS 34.45.200
, for at least one year before the department may sell the securities.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-360__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless the department considers it to be in the best interest of the state to do otherwise, the department shall hold all securities presumed abandoned under
AS 34.45.200
and delivered to the department for at least three years before selling the securities.  A person making a claim under
AS 34.45.380
is entitled to receive either the securities delivered to the department by the holder, if they still remain in the hands of the department, or the proceeds received from sale, less amounts deducted under
AS 34.45.380
(c).  A person does not have a claim under this section or
AS 34.45.380
against the state, the holder, a transfer agent, a registrar, or other person acting for or on behalf of a holder for appreciation in the value of the property occurring after delivery by the holder to the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-360__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The purchaser of property at a sale conducted by the department under this section takes the property free of all claims of the owner or previous holder of the property and of all persons claiming through or under them.  The department shall execute all documents necessary to complete the transfer of ownership.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-370">
            <num>34.45.370</num>
            <heading>Deposit of money and accounting.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-45-370__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as otherwise provided by this section, the department shall promptly deposit in the general fund of the state all money received under
AS 34.45.110
 34.45.780, including the proceeds from the sale of abandoned property under
AS 34.45.360
.  The department shall retain in a separate trust fund an amount not less than $100,000 from which the department shall make prompt payment of allowed claims. Before making the deposit, the department shall record the name and last known address of each person appearing from the holders' reports to be entitled to the property and the name and last known address of each insured person or annuitant and beneficiary and, with respect to each policy or contract listed in the report of an insurance company, its number, the name of the company, and the amount due.  The department shall make the record available for public inspection at all reasonable business hours.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-370__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 28 ch 90 SLA 1991.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-380">
            <num>34.45.380</num>
            <heading>Filing of claim with department.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-45-380__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person, excluding another state, claiming an interest in property paid or delivered to the department may file a claim on a form prescribed by the department and bearing a notice that statements are made under penalty of unsworn falsification in the second degree.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-380__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall consider each claim after it is filed and shall give written notice to the claimant if the claim is denied in whole or in part.  The notice may be given by mailing it to the address, if any, stated in the claim as the address to which notices are to be sent.  If an address for notices is not stated in the claim, the notice may be mailed to the address, if any, of the claimant as stated in the claim.  A notice of denial need not be given if the claim states neither the address to which notices are to be sent nor the address of the claimant.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-380__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a claim is allowed, the department shall pay or deliver to the claimant the property or the amount the department actually received, or the net proceeds if it has been sold by the department, together with an additional amount required by
AS 34.45.340
.  For the purposes of determining net proceeds after sale of the property, the department may deduct</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-380__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>costs incurred in connection with the sale of the property;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-380__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>costs of mailing and publication in connection with the property;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-380__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>reasonable service charges; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-380__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>costs incurred in examining records of the holder of the property and in collecting the property from the holder.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-380__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a claim is allowed and the property claimed was interest-bearing to the owner on the date of surrender by the holder, the department also shall pay interest at the rate prescribed in
AS 45.45.010
or a lesser rate the property earned while in the possession of the holder.  Interest begins to accrue when the property is delivered to the department and ceases on the expiration of 10 years after delivery or the date on which payment is made to the owner, whichever is earlier.  The department may not pay interest on interest-bearing property for a period occurring before September 7, 1986.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-380__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A holder who pays the owner for property that has been delivered to the state and that, if claimed from the department, would be subject to (d) of this section shall add interest as provided in (d) of this section.  The added interest shall be repaid to the holder by the commissioner in the same manner as the principal.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-380__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless another state files a claim to recover the property, if the identity of the owner of the property is known, the department shall apply the fair market value of the property to satisfaction of the following, in the order listed:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-380__subsec_f__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the child support obligations of the owner;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-380__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>upon application of the Department of Law or submission of documentation satisfactory to the Department of Revenue, court-ordered restitution owed by the owner under
AS 12
or
AS 47
, including any interest, collection costs, and attorney fees awarded by the court.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-390">
            <num>34.45.390</num>
            <heading>Claim of another state to recover property.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-45-390__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After personal property has been paid or delivered to the department under this chapter another state may recover the property if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-390__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>this state took custody of the property because the records of the holder did not reflect the last known address of the apparent owner when the property was presumed abandoned under this chapter, the person entitled to the property was in the other state, and under the laws of the other state the property escheated to or was subject to a claim of abandonment by that state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-390__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the last known address of the apparent owner or other person entitled to the property, as reflected by the records of the holder, is in the other state and under the laws of the other state the property has escheated to or become subject to a claim of abandonment by that state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-390__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the records of the holder were erroneous in that they did not accurately reflect the actual owner of the property and the last known address of the actual owner is in the other state and under the laws of the other state the property escheated to or was subject to a claim of abandonment by the other state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-390__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>this state took custody of the property under
AS 34.45.120
(6), and, under the laws of the state of domicile of the holder, the property has escheated to or become subject to a claim of abandonment by the state of domicile; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-390__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the property is the sum payable on a traveler's check, money order, or other similar instrument of which this state took custody under
AS 34.45.140
, and the instrument was purchased in the other state, and, under the laws of the other state, the property escheated to or became subject to a claim of abandonment by the other state.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-390__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The claim of another state to recover escheated or abandoned property must be presented in a form prescribed by the department.  The department shall allow the claim if it determines that the other state is entitled to the abandoned property under (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-390__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall require a state, before recovering property under this section, to agree to indemnify this state and its officers and employees against liability on a claim for the property.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-400">
            <num>34.45.400</num>
            <heading>Action to establish claim.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-45-400__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person aggrieved by a decision or action of the department under this chapter may apply to the department within 60 days after the mailing date of the department's notice to the person, giving notice of the grievance and requesting an informal conference.  At the conference the person aggrieved may present arguments and evidence relevant to the decision or action of the department.  If the department determines that a correction is warranted, the department shall make the correction.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-400__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person aggrieved by a decision or action of the department may apply to the department and request a formal hearing</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-400__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in place of the informal conference provided for in (a) of this section, within 60 days after the mailing date of the department's notice to the person; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-400__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>within 30 days after the decision resulting from an informal conference.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-400__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>At the formal hearing, the administrative law judge from the office of administrative hearings (
AS 44.64.010
) may subpoena witnesses and may administer oaths and make inquiries necessary to determine the validity of the claim. The person aggrieved may present arguments and evidence relevant to the decision or action of the department. If, after the hearing, the department determines that a correction is warranted, the department shall make the correction.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-400__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person aggrieved by the decision of the department may, within 30 days after the formal hearing and decision by the department, appeal to the superior court in the judicial district in which the person resides.  The department shall give appellant access to the department's file in the matter for preparation of the appeal.  If, after the appeal is heard, it appears that the decision of the department was correct, the court shall confirm that decision.  If incorrect the court shall determine the amount that the person aggrieved is entitled to recover and shall order the repayment.  The department shall immediately pay the amount due and attach a certified copy of the judgment to the payment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-410">
            <num>34.45.410</num>
            <heading>Election to take delivery.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-45-410__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may decline to receive property reported under this chapter.  If the department elects not to receive custody of the property, the department shall notify the holder within 120 days after the holder files the report required under
AS 34.45.280
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-410__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A holder, with the written consent of the department and upon terms prescribed by the department, may report and deliver property before the property is presumed abandoned.  Property delivered under this subsection shall be held by the department and is not presumed abandoned until the property would otherwise be presumed abandoned under this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-420">
            <num>34.45.420</num>
            <heading>Destruction or disposition of property having insubstantial commercial value.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.45.420.   Destruction or disposition of property having insubstantial commercial value.
If the department determines after investigation that property delivered under this chapter has insubstantial commercial value, the department may destroy or otherwise dispose of the property at any time.  An action or proceeding may not be maintained against the state or an officer of the state or against the holder because of an action taken by the department under this section.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-430">
            <num>34.45.430</num>
            <heading>Periods of limitation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.45.430.   Periods of limitation.
The expiration of a period of time specified by contract, statute, or court order, during which a claim for money or property may be made or during which an action or proceeding may be commenced or enforced to obtain payment of a claim for money or to recover property, does not prevent the money or property from being presumed abandoned and does not affect a duty to file a report or to pay or deliver abandoned property to the department as required by
AS 34.45.110
 34.45.430.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-450">
            <num>34.45.450</num>
            <heading>Enforcement.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.45.450.   Enforcement.
The department may bring an action in a court of competent jurisdiction to enforce
AS 34.45.110
 34.45.780.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-460">
            <num>34.45.460</num>
            <heading>Interstate agreements and cooperation.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-45-460__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may enter into agreements with other states to exchange information needed to enable this or another state to audit or otherwise determine unclaimed personal property that this state or another state may be entitled to subject to a claim of custody.  The department may, by regulation, require the reporting of information needed to enable compliance with agreements made under this section, and prescribe the form for the report.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-460__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To avoid conflicts between the department's procedures and the procedures in other jurisdictions that enact the Uniform Unclaimed Property Act, the department, so far as is consistent with the purposes, policies, and provisions of this chapter, shall, before adopting, amending, or repealing regulations, advise and consult with administrators in other jurisdictions that enact, substantially, the Uniform Unclaimed Property Act, and shall take into consideration the rules of administrators in other jurisdictions that enact the Uniform Unclaimed Property Act.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-460__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may join with other states to seek enforcement of
AS 34.45.110
 34.45.780 against a person who is or may be holding property reportable under
AS 34.45.110
 34.45.430.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-460__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>At the request of another state, the attorney general of this state may bring an action in the name of the other state in a court of competent jurisdiction to enforce the unclaimed property laws of the other state against a holder in this state or property laws of the other state against a holder in this state of property subject to escheat or a claim of abandonment by the other state.  An action may be brought under this subsection only if the other state has agreed to pay expenses incurred by the attorney general of this state in bringing the action.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-460__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may request that the attorney general of another state, or another person, bring an action to enforce this chapter in the other state in the name of the department.  This state shall pay all expenses including attorney fees in an action under this subsection.  The department may agree to pay the person bringing the action attorney fees based in whole or in part on a percentage of the value of property recovered in the action.  Expenses paid under this subsection may not be deducted from the amount that is subject to a claim by the owner under
AS 34.45.110
 34.45.430.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-470">
            <num>34.45.470</num>
            <heading>Interest and penalties.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-45-470__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who fails to pay or deliver property within the time prescribed by this chapter may be required to pay to the department interest at the annual rate calculated under
AS 43.05.225
on the property or the value of it from the date the property should have been paid or delivered.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-470__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who fails to pay or deliver property or fails to perform other duties required under this chapter may be required to pay the civil penalties calculated under
AS 43.05.220
, on the property, or the value of the property, that the person had a duty to pay, deliver, or report to the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-470__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who intentionally refuses after written demand by the department to pay or deliver property to the department as required under this chapter is guilty of a class A misdemeanor.
Article 7. General Provisions.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-700">
            <num>34.45.700</num>
            <heading>Agreement to locate reported property.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-45-700__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An agreement to pay compensation to locate, deliver, recover, or assist in the recovery of property reported under
AS 34.45.280
while in the possession of a holder is unenforceable if made</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-700__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>before the date payment or delivery is made under
AS 34.45.320
; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-700__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>within 24 months after the date payment or delivery is made under
AS 34.45.320
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-700__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An agreement executed after the 24-month period is enforceable only if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-700__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the fee or compensation is not more than
(A) 20 percent of the value of the property if the value of the property is less than $500; and
(B) 10 percent of the value of the property if the value of the property is $500 or more;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-700__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the agreement is in writing, signed by the apparent owner, does not exceed six months, and specifies the fees to be charged, nature and value of the property, and the value of the apparent owner's share after the fee or compensation is deducted.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-700__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This section does not preclude an owner from asserting that an agreement to locate property is otherwise invalid.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-710">
            <num>34.45.710</num>
            <heading>Foreign transactions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.45.710.   Foreign transactions.
AS 34.45.110
 34.45.780 do not apply to property held, due, and owing in a foreign country and arising out of a foreign transaction.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-720">
            <num>34.45.720</num>
            <heading>Application; exceptions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-45-720__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>AS 34.45.110
 34.45.780 do not relieve a holder of a duty that arose before September 7, 1986 to report, pay, or deliver property.  A holder who did not comply with the law in effect before September 7, 1986 is subject to the applicable enforcement and penalty provisions that existed before September 7, 1986, and the applicable enforcement and penalty provisions are continued in effect for the purpose of this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-720__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The initial report filed under
AS 34.45.280
for property that was not required to be reported before September 7, 1986 but that is subject to
AS 34.45.110
 34.45.780 must include all items of property that would have been presumed abandoned during the six-year period preceding September 7, 1986, as if
AS 34.45.110
 34.45.780 had been in effect during that period.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-720__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>AS 34.45.110
 34.45.780 do not apply to a disbursement for the payment of a permanent fund dividend.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-720__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Checks, drafts, currency, and tangible property that are found and turned over to, or found and recovered by, a law enforcement agency of a municipality are not subject to
AS 34.45.110
 34.45.780 if the municipality has adopted an ordinance providing for the custody and disposition of the property.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-730">
            <num>34.45.730</num>
            <heading>Regulations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.45.730.   Regulations.
The department shall adopt regulations necessary to carry out the provisions of
AS 34.45.110
 34.45.780.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-740">
            <num>34.45.740</num>
            <heading>Uniformity of application and construction.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.45.740.   Uniformity of application and construction.
AS 34.45.110
 34.45.780 shall be applied and construed so as to effectuate their general purpose to make uniform the law with respect to unclaimed property among states enacting the Uniform Unclaimed Property Act.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-750">
            <num>34.45.750</num>
            <heading>Report by department upon failure to make report or making false report.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.45.750.   Report by department upon failure to make report or making false report.
If a person fails to submit a report as required under
AS 34.45.110
 34.45.780, or makes, wilfully or otherwise, a false report, the department shall make the report from the information it obtains under
AS 43.05.050
.  A report made by the department is prima facie valid for all legal purposes.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-760">
            <num>34.45.760</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-45-760__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>money, checks, drafts, warrants, deposits, interest, dividends, and income;
(ii) credit balances, customer overpayments, gift certificates, security deposits, refunds, credit memos, unpaid wages, and unidentified remittances;
(iii) stocks and other intangible equity interests in business associations;
(iv) money deposited to redeem stocks, bonds, coupons, and other securities, or to make distributions;</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-760__subsec_v">
              <num>(v)</num>
              <content>
                <p>amounts due and payable under the terms of insurance policies;
(vi) amounts distributable from a trust or custodial fund established under a plan to provide health, welfare, pension, vacation, severance, retirement, death, stock purchase, profit-sharing, employee savings, supplemental unemployment insurance, or similar benefits; and
(vii) amounts due and payable as mineral proceeds;
(B) does not include</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-45-760__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>unused airline tickets;
(ii) shares of stock issued by a corporation organized under 43 U.S.C. 1601 et seq. (Alaska Native Claims Settlement Act) or unclaimed dividends payable on the shares of stock; or
(iii) overpaid contributions by employers to the unemployment compensation fund under
AS 23.20.130
;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-760__subsec_i__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>mineral means gas; oil; other gaseous, liquid, and solid hydrocarbons; oil shale; cement material; sand and gravel; road material; building stone; chemical raw material; gemstone; fissionable and nonfissionable ores; colloidal and other clay; steam and other geothermal resources; or any other substance defined as mineral by other state law;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-760__subsec_i__subsec_13">
                <num>(13)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>mineral proceeds means amounts payable for the extraction, production, or sale of minerals, or, upon the abandonment of those payments, all payments that become payable after the abandonment; mineral proceeds includes amounts payable
(A) for the acquisition and retention of a mineral lease, including bonuses, royalties, compensatory royalties, shut-in royalties, minimum royalties, and delay rentals;
(B) for the extraction, production, or sale of minerals, including net revenue interests, royalties, overriding royalties, extraction payments, and production payments;
(C) under an agreement or option, including a joint operating agreement, unit agreement, pooling agreement, and farm-out agreement;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-760__subsec_i__subsec_14">
                <num>(14)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>owner means a depositor in the case of a deposit, a beneficiary in the case of a trust other than a deposit in trust, a creditor, claimant, or payee in the case of other intangible property, or a person having a legal or equitable interest in property subject to
AS 34.45.110
 34.45.780; the term includes a person's legal representative;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-760__subsec_i__subsec_15">
                <num>(15)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>person means an individual, business association, state, municipality or other government, including the United States government, subdivision or agency, public corporation, public authority, estate, trust, two or more persons having a joint or common interest, or other legal or commercial entity;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-760__subsec_i__subsec_16">
                <num>(16)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>property means personal property, but does not include property covered by
(A)
AS 14.57.200
 14.57.290;
(B)
AS 23.20
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-760__subsec_i__subsec_17">
                <num>(17)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>state means a state, district, commonwealth, territory, insular possession, or other area subject to the legislative authority of the United States;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-760__subsec_i__subsec_18">
                <num>(18)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>unsworn falsification means the offense described in
AS 11.56.210
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-45-760__subsec_i__subsec_19">
                <num>(19)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>utility means a person who owns or operates for public use a plant, equipment, property, franchise, or license for the transmission of communications or the production, storage, transmission, sale, delivery, or furnishing of electricity, water, steam, or gas.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-45-780">
            <num>34.45.780</num>
            <heading>Short title.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.45.780.   Short title.
AS 34.45.110
 34.45.780 may be cited as the Uniform Unclaimed Property Act.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>