<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-28/chapter-10"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-28/chapter-10"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="28.10"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-28/chapter-10/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-28/chapter-10/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-28/chapter-10/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-28/chapter-10/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_28">
        <num>28</num>
        <heading>Motor Vehicles</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_28__chp_10">
          <num>10</num>
          <heading>Vehicle Registration, Liens, and Title</heading>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-011">
            <num>28.10.011</num>
            <heading>Vehicles subject to registration.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.10.011.   Vehicles subject to registration.
Every vehicle driven, moved, or parked upon a highway or other public parking place in the state shall be registered under this chapter except when the vehicle is
(1) driven or moved on a highway only for the purpose of crossing the highway from one private property to another, including an implement of husbandry as defined by regulation;
(2) driven or moved on a highway under a dealer's plate or temporary permit as provided for in
AS 28.10.031
and 28.10.181(j);
(3) special mobile equipment as defined by regulation;
(4) owned by the United States;
(5) moved by human or animal power;
(6) exempt under 50 U.S.C. App. 501-591 (Soldiers' and Sailors' Civil Relief Act);
(7) driven or parked only on private property;
(8) the vehicle of a nonresident as provided under
AS 28.10.121
;
(9) transported under a special permit under
AS 28.10.151
;
(10) being driven or moved on a highway, vehicular way, or a public parking place in the state that is not connected by a land highway or vehicular way to
(A) the land-connected state highway system; or
(B) a highway or vehicular way with an average daily traffic volume greater than 499;
(11) an implement of husbandry operated in accordance with the provisions of
AS 19.10.065
;
(12) an electric personal motor vehicle.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-021">
            <num>28.10.021</num>
            <heading>Application for registration.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-021__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The owner of a vehicle subject to registration shall apply for registration under this chapter by properly completing the form prescribed by the commissioner under
AS 28.05.041
. Before the issuance of a certificate of registration by the department, the owner shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-021__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>pay all registration fees and taxes required under this chapter and federal heavy vehicle use taxes required under 26 U.S.C. 4481 (Internal Revenue Code of 1954);</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-021__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>unless the owner qualifies as a self-insurer under
AS 28.20.400
or is exempted from obtaining liability insurance under
AS 28.22.011
, certify to the department the existence of a motor vehicle liability policy that complies with
AS 28.22.011
for the vehicle being registered; in this paragraph, certify means to indicate by check-off on the vehicle registration form prescribed by the department the existence of a policy of insurance, if a policy is required at that time, and the intention to continue the policy or obtain a policy as required by this subsection; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-021__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>comply with other applicable statutes and regulations.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-021__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>At the time of application for registration or renewal of registration, the department shall provide the applicant written information explaining the state's financial responsibility law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-021__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An employee of the department who processes an application for registration or renewal of registration, other than an application received by mail or an application for registration under
AS 28.10.152
, shall ask the applicant orally whether the applicant wishes to execute an anatomical gift. The department shall make known to all applicants the procedure for executing an anatomical gift under
AS 13.52
(Health Care Decisions Act) by displaying posters in the offices in which applications are taken, by providing a brochure or other written information to each person who applies in person or by mail, and, if requested, by providing oral advice. The department shall inform each applicant in writing that, if the applicant executes a gift under
AS 13.52
and if the gift is made with the registration application, the department will transmit the information on the registration to a donor registry created under
AS 13.50.110
. The department shall also direct the applicant to notify a procurement organization or the department under
AS 13.50.140
if the registration is destroyed or mutilated or the gift is revoked under
AS 13.52.183
. The department shall carry out the requirements of
AS 13.50.100
 13.50.190.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-031">
            <num>28.10.031</num>
            <heading>Temporary permits.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-031__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When application, accompanied by the proper fee and tax, has been made for the registration of a vehicle, the vehicle may be driven pending the issuance of a certificate of registration by displaying a temporary permit issued by the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-031__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A licensed vehicle dealer may issue to the purchaser of a vehicle sold by the dealer a temporary permit to drive the vehicle. A permit is effective for a period not to exceed 60 days. The commissioner shall adopt regulations governing the issuance of permits under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-031__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not operate a vehicle under an expired permit issued under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-041">
            <num>28.10.041</num>
            <heading>Grounds for refusing registration.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-041__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may refuse to register a vehicle if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-041__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the application contains a false or fraudulent statement;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-041__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the applicant fails to furnish information required by the department;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-041__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the applicant is not entitled to the issuance of a certificate of title or registration under this chapter;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-041__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the vehicle is determined to be mechanically unsafe to be driven or moved on a highway, vehicular way or area, or other public property in the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-041__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the department has reasonable grounds to believe that the vehicle was stolen or fraudulently acquired or that the granting of registration would be a fraud against the rightful owner or other person having a valid lien on the vehicle;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-041__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the registration of the vehicle has been suspended or revoked for any reason under the laws of the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-041__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the required fees or taxes have not been paid;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-041__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the vehicle or applicant fails to comply with this chapter or regulations implementing this section;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-041__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the vehicle is without a certificate of inspection required under
AS 19.10.310
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-041__subsec_a__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>except for a vehicle to be registered under
AS 28.10.152
, the vehicle is subject to a state-approved emission inspection program adopted under
AS 46.14.400
or 46.14.510, and the vehicle does not meet the standards of that program;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-041__subsec_a__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the applicant fails to certify to the department the existence of a motor vehicle liability policy that complies with
AS 28.22.101
for the vehicle being registered unless the owner of the vehicle qualifies as a self-insurer under
AS 28.20.400
or is exempted from obtaining liability insurance under
AS 28.22.011
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-041__subsec_a__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the applicant is a commercial motor carrier prohibited from operating by a federal agency.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-041__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the department refuses to register a vehicle, it shall immediately notify the applicant stating the reasons for the action and informing the applicant of the right to a hearing under
AS 28.05.131
  28.05.141.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-041__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except for a vehicle to be registered under
AS 28.10.152
, the department shall refuse to register a vehicle subject to the federal heavy vehicle use tax required by 26 U.S.C. 4481 (Internal Revenue Code of 1954) if the applicant fails to furnish proof, in the form prescribed by the United States Secretary of the Treasury, that the tax has been paid.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-041__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall refuse to register a vehicle if the applicant fails to register the vehicle using the applicant's full first, middle, and last name or a business name.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-051">
            <num>28.10.051</num>
            <heading>Department may suspend or revoke registration.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-051__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may suspend or revoke the registration of a vehicle, the certificate of registration or registration plates for a vehicle, or a special permit when</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-051__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the department determines that the registration or certificate, plate, or permit was fraudulently procured or erroneously issued;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-051__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the department determines that a registered vehicle is mechanically unsafe to be driven or moved on a highway, vehicular way or area, or other public property in this state and the vehicle has been seized or impounded under
AS 28.05.091
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-051__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a registered vehicle has been scrapped, dismantled, or destroyed beyond repair;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-051__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the department determines that a required fee or tax has not been paid and the fee or tax is not paid upon reasonable notice and demand;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-051__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a registration plate, permit, or certificate is knowingly displayed on a vehicle other than the vehicle for which issued;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-051__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the department determines that the owner of a vehicle has committed an offense under this chapter involving the registration or the certificate, plate, or permit to be suspended or revoked;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-051__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the vehicle has been reported to the department as stolen or unlawfully converted;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-051__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the department is otherwise required to do so under the laws of this state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-051__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the department determines that the vehicle owner has violated the requirements of
AS 28.10.146
or 28.10.147;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-051__subsec_a__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the department determines that a repair to a commercial motor vehicle, ordered by the Department of Transportation and Public Facilities or the Department of Public Safety under regulations adopted under
AS 19
, was not completed after the owner or operator represented to the Department of Transportation and Public Facilities, the Department of Public Safety, or the Department of Administration that the repair had been completed;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-051__subsec_a__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the owner or operator of a commercial motor vehicle has placed a commercial motor vehicle back in service after it has been placed out of service by the Department of Transportation and Public Facilities or the Department of Public Safety without having it reinspected as required under regulations adopted under
AS 19
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-051__subsec_a__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the owner or operator is a commercial motor carrier prohibited from operating by a federal agency; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-051__subsec_a__subsec_13">
                <num>(13)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the commercial motor vehicle is subject to an out-of-service order issued by a state or federal agency.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-051__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless the owner qualifies as a self-insurer under
AS 28.20.400
, or is exempted from obtaining liability insurance under
AS 28.22.011
, the department may suspend or revoke the registration of a vehicle that is not insured by a motor vehicle liability policy that complies with
AS 28.22.101
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-061">
            <num>28.10.061</num>
            <heading>Registration of vehicles with altered or missing identification number.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.10.061.   Registration of vehicles with altered or missing identification number.
When the vehicle identification number required to be registered under this chapter has been altered, removed, or defaced, or is not on the vehicle, the owner shall, immediately upon discovery, apply to the department for replacement of the identification number and for a new registration.  The department shall search all available sources to determine the identification number originally assigned and, if the number is determined, shall replace it. If efforts to determine the original identification number fail, the owner shall furnish information to show that the owner is entitled to ownership of the vehicle and have it inspected by the department. The department, when satisfied as to the ownership of the vehicle, shall assign an identification number to the vehicle and have the number placed upon the vehicle to which it is assigned. The vehicle shall then be registered under the replaced or assigned identification number.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-065">
            <num>28.10.065</num>
            <heading>Custom collector vehicle registration and identification.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.10.065.   Custom collector vehicle registration and identification.
When the department is satisfied as to the ownership of a replica of a custom collector vehicle and the vehicle does not have an identification number, the department shall assign a vehicle identification number to the vehicle and have the number stamped on the vehicle. A custom collector replica vehicle shall be registered as a vehicle constructed during the period represented by the replica.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-071">
            <num>28.10.071</num>
            <heading>Registration records and statistics; stolen vehicles.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-071__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall review each application for registration received and, when satisfied that it is correct, register the vehicle and keep a record of the registration in suitable books, index cards, or electronic or photographic recording and storage media, or in any combination of them. The vehicles are referred to as registered vehicles. The department may compile a record of the number and types of vehicles registered in this state and may make statistical data available to the public for a fee as prescribed in regulations adopted by the commissioner. The department may also provide vehicle registration lists to the public for a fee as an electronic service or product under
AS 40.25.115
. The commissioner may prescribe, by regulation, fees relating to the provision of vehicle registration lists.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-071__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Records under this section shall be maintained</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-071__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>by a distinctive registration number assigned to the vehicle;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-071__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>by the vehicle identification number, including but not limited to a record of identification numbers replaced or assigned under
AS 28.10.061
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-071__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>by the name and residence and mailing address of the owner; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-071__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>as otherwise required by the department.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-071__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall keep a record of the registrations of vehicles used in law enforcement work when secrecy is necessary. This record is separate from the record required by (a) of this section and may be disclosed only to and upon the request of the chief peace officer of a municipality, a state trooper district commander, the chief federal law enforcement officer assigned to the state, or to a court upon an appropriate order.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-071__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall maintain and appropriately index cumulative records of stolen, converted, recovered, and unclaimed vehicles reported to it.  The department may make and distribute weekly lists of these vehicles to peace officers and to other departments upon their request without charge and to the public for a reasonable fee as prescribed by the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-081">
            <num>28.10.081</num>
            <heading>Issuance of certificate of registration; certificate to be signed, carried, and displayed.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-081__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall mail or deliver the certificate of registration to the owner.  The certificate of registration must contain the assigned registration number, the name, the residence and mailing addresses of the owner, the vehicle identification number, the fees paid, and as much of the vehicle description appearing on the title as the commissioner considers necessary.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-081__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Every certificate of registration shall, except when used to apply for renewal of registration or to transfer the registration, be carried in the vehicle to which it refers. The driver of a vehicle shall display the original certificate of registration or a legible photocopy if the original is on file at the address shown on the certificate of registration to a peace officer or an officer or employee of the department acting in an official capacity upon the request of that officer or employee.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-091">
            <num>28.10.091</num>
            <heading>Lost or mutilated certificates of registration or registration plates.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.10.091.   Lost or mutilated certificates of registration or registration plates.
If a certificate of registration or a registration plate is lost, stolen, mutilated, or becomes illegible, the owner or legal representative or successor in interest of the owner of the vehicle for which the certificate or plate was issued as shown by the records of the department shall, immediately upon discovering the fact, apply for a duplicate or substitute certificate of registration or registration plate and shall return to the department all parts of the original certificate of registration or registration plates that the applicant possesses.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-108">
            <num>28.10.108</num>
            <heading>Registration procedures.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-108__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except for a vehicle registered under
AS 28.10.152
or 28.10.155, a vehicle required to be registered under this chapter shall be registered under the procedures set out in this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-108__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 29 ch 6 FSSLA 1996.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-108__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 29 ch 6 FSSLA 1996.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-108__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A registered vehicle retains the same biennial expiration date regardless of the ownership of the vehicle.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-108__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The registration of a vehicle expires on the last day of the month to which the vehicle is assigned.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-108__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon request of the owner and payment of the proportionate prorated applicable fees, a vehicle registered under this section shall have its registration period extended in monthly increments to allow biennial registration to occur in the month of the owner's choice, except that registration may not extend beyond the expiration of an emissions inspection and maintenance certificate required for the vehicle. Notwithstanding the other provisions of this chapter, upon request of the owner, payment of the annual fee set out in
AS 28.10.421
(h), payment of any annual vehicle registration tax due under
AS 28.10.431
(l), and, if applicable, payment of one-half of the biennial emission control inspection program fee imposed under
AS 28.10.423
, the department shall register a vehicle used for commercial purposes for a one-year period.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-108__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall issue to the registered owner, upon receipt of the proper application and fees, one registration plate, tabs, and a registration form displaying the month and year in which the registration expires.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-108__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall mail or deliver notice of registration expiration to the registered owner of record at the owner's mailing address or electronic mail address as shown in the records of the department. An owner of a vehicle subject to registration who has received notice under this subsection may renew registration of the vehicle on the department's Internet website or by returning the notice form, together with appropriate fees, to the department by mail postmarked not later than the fifth day of the registration renewal period shown on the vehicle's current registration or notice form. Upon receipt of a timely registration renewal application and the appropriate fees and taxes, the department shall renew the registration and mail the current registration card and registration plate or tabs to the owner at the owner's mailing address as shown in the department's records.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-108__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a vehicle is held for sale by a dealer, the requirement of registration and payment of fees and taxes does not apply until the vehicle is sold to a party other than another dealer.  The exemption from payment of fees and taxes under this subsection applies only if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-108__subsec_i__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the dealer is registered with the state; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-108__subsec_i__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the vehicle for which the exemption is sought can be shown to be part of the dealer's inventory at the time of exemption.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-108__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The purchaser of a vehicle for which registration and taxes have been held in abeyance under (i) of this section shall register the vehicle within five working days of purchase and pay the prorated fees and taxes required by the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-108__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall prorate fees in monthly increments to allow for registration of vehicles in more or less than one-year periods when required by any provision of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-108__subsec_l">
              <num>(l)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding the other provisions of this section, the following vehicles are not required to be registered biennially and shall be registered one time only:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-108__subsec_l__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a vehicle qualifying for registration under
AS 28.10.181</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-108__subsec_l__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a vehicle owned by a person who is 65 years of age or older; this paragraph applies to only one vehicle owned by the person who is 65 years of age or older.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-111">
            <num>28.10.111</num>
            <heading>Renewal of registration.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-111__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Application for the renewal of vehicle registration shall be made by completing the proper form and paying any required fee and tax.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-111__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may receive an application for the renewal of vehicle registration and issue a new certificate of registration at any time before the expiration of the biennial registration as prescribed in regulations adopted by the commissioner. Nothing in this section prevents the commissioner from providing for a longer registration period; however, a person may not display the new registration plates on a vehicle before a date which may be set by the commissioner.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-121">
            <num>28.10.121</num>
            <heading>Vehicles of nonresidents.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-121__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A nonresident owner of a noncommercial vehicle registered outside the state is exempt from the registration provisions of this chapter for 60 days after entry into the state if the vehicle at all times when driven in this state is registered in and has displayed upon it a currently valid registration plate issued for it by another jurisdiction. However, if the person becomes gainfully employed in the state or takes action that indicates an intention to acquire residence in the state, the person shall comply with the licensing and registration provisions of this chapter within 10 days of commencement of employment or of taking action that indicates the person's intention to acquire residence. If the vehicle is a commercial vehicle, the vehicle must be registered when its commercial use begins except as provided in
AS 28.10.011
, 28.10.131(c), and 28.10.152.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-121__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A vehicle owned by a nonresident and of a type subject to registration under this chapter, that is leased or rented to a person having an established place of business, a residence, or employment in this state, is subject to registration under this chapter either by the owner or lessee.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-121__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A vehicle under (a) of this section that is owned and driven by a full-time student pursuing a course of study beyond the high school level and upon which current, valid registration by another jurisdiction is maintained need not be registered in this state unless the student establishes residence or accepts full-time employment in the state.  This exemption applies only to the extent that the jurisdiction in which the vehicle is registered grants the same exemptions and privileges to a vehicle registered in this state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-121__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>It is the responsibility of the person claiming exemption under this section to provide proof of qualification for the exemption.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-131">
            <num>28.10.131</num>
            <heading>Vehicles previously registered in another jurisdiction.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-131__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except for a vehicle to be registered under
AS 28.10.152
, if a vehicle to be registered under this chapter is previously registered outside the state, the jurisdiction of registry shall be stated in the application, and the owner shall surrender to the department all evidence of out-of-state registration in the owner's possession or control except as provided in this section, and the department may require verification of the vehicle identification number.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-131__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the owner is unable to provide the necessary evidence of ownership, the department, when satisfied that the applicant is the lawfully registered owner of the vehicle, may register the vehicle without issuing a title and shall type or stamp on the face of the State of Alaska certificate of registration No Title Issued.  The issuance of the Alaska certificate of title shall be withheld until the registered or legal owner provides for the surrender of the out-of-state title, or in the case of a nontitle state, documents that satisfy the department of ownership and any liens on the vehicle, or until the posting of a vehicle surety bond equal to the market value of the vehicle, which bond shall be maintained for two years.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-131__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in
AS 28.10.152
, if the owner of a commercial vehicle desires to maintain title in another jurisdiction, the department, when satisfied that the applicant is temporarily operating in-state and is the lawfully registered owner of the commercial vehicle, may register the commercial vehicle without issuing a title and shall type or stamp on the face of the State of Alaska certificate of registration No Title Issued.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-146">
            <num>28.10.146</num>
            <heading>Registration of interstate rental trucks.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-146__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding any other registration requirement of this chapter, a fleet rental truck owner or authorized representative shall register a percentage of the total fleet as determined under this subsection, and shall pay the fees and taxes required by this chapter.  The percentage of fleet rental trucks required to be registered is equal to the total number of miles that all trucks in the rental fleet were driven in this state during a calendar year or other period established by the department by regulation, divided by the total number of miles that all trucks in the rental fleet were driven in all states and the District of Columbia during that period.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-146__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When applying for registration under (a) of this section, the fleet rental owner or authorized representative shall file with the department a certified report containing verifiable data, reporting</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-146__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the total number of miles operated by all of the trucks in the rental fleet in all states and the District of Columbia during the preceding calendar year or other period specified by the department;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-146__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the total number of miles operated in this state by all of the trucks in the rental fleet during the preceding calendar year or other period specified by the department; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-146__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>other fleet rental truck registration information that the department may require.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-146__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A fleet rental owner or authorized representative whose application for registration under this section has been accepted by the department shall preserve records of the period on which the application was based for four years. Upon request of the department, the fleet rental owner or authorized representative shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-146__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide records preserved under this subsection to the department for audit; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-146__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>pay the cost of an audit conducted by a representative of the department at the office of the owner.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-146__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After compliance with this section, all trucks identified as part of the rental fleet, and currently registered in any state or in the District of Columbia, may operate in this state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-146__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the department determines that the fleet rental owner or authorized representative has not registered fleet rental trucks as required by this section, the department may suspend or revoke a registration previously issued, and may deny future fleet rental registration under (a) of this section, until the owner or authorized representative has complied with this section.  If registration under (a) of this section has been suspended, revoked, or denied, all the owner's fleet rental trucks present in the state must be registered under applicable state law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-146__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A fee or tax paid as a result of registration required under this section does not satisfy or offset other fees or taxes levied by the state or a political subdivision in connection with the ownership or operation of fleet rental trucks.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-146__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, fleet means a fleet of 10 or more rental trucks that are rented or offered for rent without a driver.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-147">
            <num>28.10.147</num>
            <heading>Registration of interstate rental trailers.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-147__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding any other registration requirement of this chapter, a fleet rental trailer owner or authorized representative shall register the average number of trailers present in this state as calculated under this subsection, and shall pay the fees and taxes required by this chapter.  The average number of trailers is equal to the total number of trailers in the fleet that were present at any time in the state during a calendar year or other period established by the department by regulation, divided by the number of calendar months in the period.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-147__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When applying for registration of trailers as required under (a) of this section, the fleet rental owner or authorized representative shall file with the department a certified report containing verifiable data as to the average number of trailers that were present at any time in the state for the previous calendar year or other period specified by the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-147__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A fleet rental owner or authorized representative whose application for registration under this section has been accepted by the department shall preserve records of the period on which the application was based for four years. Upon request of the department, the fleet rental owner or authorized representative shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-147__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide records preserved under this subsection, to the department at its office for audit; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-147__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>pay the cost of an audit conducted by a representative of the department at the office of the owner.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-147__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After compliance with this section, all trailers identified as part of the rental fleet, and currently registered in any state or in the District of Columbia, may operate in this state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-147__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the department determines that the fleet rental owner or authorized representative has not registered fleet rental trailers as required by this section, the department may suspend or revoke a registration previously issued, and may deny future registration under (a) of this section, until the owner has complied with this section. If registration under (a) of this section has been suspended, revoked, or denied, all the owner's fleet rental trailers present in the state must be registered under applicable state law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-147__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A fee or tax paid as a result of registration required under this section does not satisfy or offset other fees or taxes levied by the state or a political subdivision in connection with the ownership or operation of fleet rental trailers.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-147__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, fleet means a fleet of 10 or more rental trailers that are rented or offered for rent for personal use, not for the transportation of persons or property for hire or other commercial use, and includes a boat trailer, baggage trailer, box trailer, utility trailer, house trailer, or travel trailer.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-151">
            <num>28.10.151</num>
            <heading>Vehicles transported under special permits.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-151__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When moved or driven under a special permit to be designed and issued by the department, the registration required by this chapter is not required of</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-151__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a vehicle under construction and that is not completed;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-151__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a vehicle while being moved from one place to another for the purpose of inspection, weighing, or meeting other requirements of the department;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-151__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a vehicle while being moved or driven from one location to another for the purpose of rebuilding, dismantling, or permanently removing the vehicle from the highways and vehicular ways and areas of the state; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-151__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an unladen commercial vehicle making a single continuous trip by a noncircular route for a period of time not exceeding 10 days.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-151__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A special permit issued under this section shall be prominently displayed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-152">
            <num>28.10.152</num>
            <heading>Certificates of temporary registration for certain commercial vehicles.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-152__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a commercial vehicle registered outside the state enters the state and is not to be registered under
AS 28.10.121
, 28.10.131, or another provision of this chapter, it must be temporarily registered under the provisions of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-152__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For a commercial vehicle to be registered under this section, the operator of the vehicle must provide proof of valid registration of the vehicle in another jurisdiction and any other documentation required by the department by regulation. Upon receipt of the proof of registration, any other required documentation, and payment of the applicable fee under (d) of this section, the department or the department's designee may issue a certificate of temporary registration, valid for 30 days, for the commercial vehicle. The certificate of temporary registration must state the date of issuance and the expiration date.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-152__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A certificate of temporary registration under this section may be issued for a commercial vehicle even if a certificate of temporary registration has previously been issued for the vehicle and has expired.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-152__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The fee for a certificate of temporary registration under this section is</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-152__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for a truck or a truck tractor, $350;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-152__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for a commercial bus, $350;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-152__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for all other commercial vehicles, including a trailer or a semi-trailer, $10.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-152__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Fees collected under this section may be appropriated by the legislature to the Department of Transportation and Public Facilities for programs related to commercial vehicles, including the administration and operation of weigh stations and commercial vehicle safety programs.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-155">
            <num>28.10.155</num>
            <heading>Permanent motor vehicle registration.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-155__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The owner of a motor vehicle, other than a commercial motor vehicle, that is required to be registered under this chapter may elect to register the motor vehicle permanently in lieu of registration under
AS 28.10.108
if the vehicle is at least eight years old and the owner resides in the unorganized borough or in a municipality that elects, by passage of an appropriate ordinance, to allow the permanent registration of motor vehicles. The permanent registration expires when the owner transfers or assigns the owner's title or interest in the vehicle. A permanent registration may not be renewed. Upon receiving the proper application and fees, the department shall issue to the registered owner one registration plate, tabs, and a permanent registration form.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-155__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The fees for permanent registration must equal the fees that would be applicable if the motor vehicle were registered under
AS 28.10.108
, plus a permanent registration fee of $25. The motor vehicle registration tax for a permanently registered vehicle is the rate established for permanent motor vehicle registration under
AS 28.10.431
(j). If a municipality has not established a tax for a permanently registered motor vehicle, the biennial rate established in
AS 28.10.431</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-155__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or (j), if any, is levied upon the vehicle and is payable only once at the time a motor vehicle is permanently registered. Except as provided in
AS 28.10.423
(b), the owner of a permanently registered motor vehicle is not required to pay other registration fees or taxes under this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-161">
            <num>28.10.161</num>
            <heading>Registration plates to be furnished by department.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-161__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except for a vehicle registered under
AS 28.10.152
, the department, upon registering a vehicle, shall issue the owner one fully reflectorized registration plate for the vehicle. Except as specifically provided in
AS 28.10.181
, the plate must remain with the vehicle as long as the vehicle is subject to registration under this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-161__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Every passenger vehicle registration plate, except as specifically provided in
AS 28.10.181
, shall have displayed on it</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-161__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>one of the following designs:
(A) the Alaska flag design, consisting of the Alaska flag, the traditional colors of yellow-gold and blue, and the slogan The Last Frontier;
(B) the bear design, consisting of a standing grizzly bear in the center of the plate; the bear design shall be modeled after the 1976 bicentennial plate without the bicentennial symbol; or
(C) the design celebrating the arts chosen by the commissioner through consultation with the Alaska State Council on the Arts; the commissioner shall choose a new design for the plates celebrating the arts every four years and discontinue issuance of the previous design;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-161__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the registration number assigned to the vehicle for which it is issued;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-161__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name of this state, which may be abbreviated; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-161__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the registration year number or expiration date for which time it is validated; the registration year number or expiration date may be part of the license plate or contained on a suitable sticker or tab device issued by the department; however, only one sticker or tab device may be issued for each plate or pair of plates, and the sticker or tab device must be affixed to the
(A) rear plate for noncommercial vehicles; or
(B) front plate for commercial vehicles.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-161__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may not adopt a new or altered passenger vehicle registration plate, except as specifically provided in
AS 28.10.181
, unless it substantially embodies the specifications of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-161__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall produce registration plates in each of the designs described in (b)(1) of this section. Upon registering a passenger vehicle, the owner shall select the plate design described in (b)(1) of this section that is to be issued by the department for the vehicle.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-161__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person or organization owning a vehicle that is issued two registration plates by the department may elect to return one registration plate to the department. The registration plate that is not returned to the department shall be attached to the</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-161__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>rear of the vehicle for which it is issued for a noncommercial vehicle; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-161__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>front of the vehicle for which it is issued if the vehicle is a commercial vehicle.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-171">
            <num>28.10.171</num>
            <heading>Display of registration plates.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-171__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When two registration plates are issued for a vehicle, they shall be attached to the vehicle for which issued, one in front and the other in the rear. When one registration plate is issued, it shall be attached to the</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-171__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>rear of the vehicle for which issued for a noncommercial vehicle; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-171__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>front of the vehicle for which issued if the vehicle is a commercial vehicle; in this paragraph, commercial vehicle has the meaning given to commercial motor vehicle in
AS 19.10.399
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-171__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Every registration plate issued under this chapter shall be securely fastened to the vehicle to which it is assigned, with the upper edge of the plate horizontal, at a height of not less than 12 inches from the ground measuring from the bottom of the plate, and maintained in a location and condition so as to be clearly legible.  However, when considered necessary to insure legibility, the commissioner may provide by regulation for another method of installation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-181">
            <num>28.10.181</num>
            <heading>Registration of unique and special vehicles and vehicles used for special purposes; special registration plates.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-181__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall register unique and special vehicles and vehicles used for special purposes and issue registration plates as provided in this section. Notwithstanding other provisions of this chapter, registration plates issued under this section remain with the person or organization to whom they are issued when vehicle ownership is transferred or title or interest in the vehicle is assigned, except for plates issued under (b), (h) and (i) of this section. Registration plates issued under this section may not be used on, or transferred to, a vehicle other than the vehicle for which the plates are issued without the approval of the department and payment of any required fees and taxes prescribed in
AS 28.10.421
(d),  28.10.431, and  28.10.441. Registration plates issued under this section to which a person is no longer entitled or the transfer of the plates to another vehicle that the department does not approve shall be returned immediately to the department by the person or organization to whom the plates were originally issued.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-181__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Historic vehicles. The owner of a historic vehicle may make application for special registration under this subsection. The department, when satisfied that the vehicle meets the requirements for historic vehicle registration under regulations adopted by the commissioner, shall register the vehicle and (1) issue one permanent registration plate of distinctive design and color bearing no date; a vehicle qualifying for registration under this paragraph shall be issued a registration plate numbered in a separate numerical series beginning with Historic Vehicle No. 1; or (2) allow the vehicle to use a registration plate of this state supplied by the vehicle owner that corresponds to the year the vehicle was manufactured if the vehicle was manufactured 30 or more years before the year of application. A registration plate issued under this subsection remains with the vehicle as long as the vehicle is registered under this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-181__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Special request plates. Upon application by the owner of a motor vehicle, the department shall design and issue registration plates containing a series of not more than six letters or numbers or combination of letters and numbers as requested by the owner. The department may, in its discretion, disapprove the issuance of registration plates under this subsection when the requested symbols are a duplication of an existing registration or when the symbols are considered unacceptable by the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-181__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Vehicles owned by veterans with disabilities, including persons disabled in the line of duty while serving in the Alaska Territorial Guard, or other persons with disabilities. Upon the request of a person with a disability that limits or impairs the ability to walk, as defined in 23 C.F.R. 1235.2, the department shall (1) register one motor vehicle in the name of the person without charge; and (2) issue a specially designed registration plate that displays (A) recognition of the disabled veteran if the applicant's disability originated from the applicant's service with the Alaska Territorial Guard or the armed forces of the United States; (B) the international symbol of accessibility (the wheelchair logo); and (C) if the applicant is a veteran, the Alaska and United States flags and red, white, and blue colors. A person who is not otherwise qualified under this subsection, but who meets the qualifications of a disabled veteran under
AS 29.45.030
(i), may register one motor vehicle without charge, and the department shall issue a specially designed registration plate that displays recognition of the disabled veteran that does not display the international symbol of accessibility and does not carry with it special parking privileges. A disabled veteran who otherwise qualifies for a registration plate under this subsection may elect to receive a plate under (p) or (q) of this section for which the person is otherwise qualified that does not display the international symbol of accessibility and does not carry with it special parking privileges. A disabled person who otherwise qualifies for a registration plate under (2)(B) of this subsection may elect to receive a plate under another provision of this section for which the person is otherwise qualified that does not display the international symbol of accessibility and does not carry with it special parking privileges. For purposes of this subsection, proof of disability may be provided by a person licensed as a speech-</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-181__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Vehicles owned by the state, municipalities, and charitable organizations of the state.  Every certificate of registration and registration plate issued to the state, a municipality, or charitable organization of the state is in effect until the vehicle for which the registration certificate and plate were issued is no longer owned and operated by the state, the municipality, or the charitable organization of the state or until the department, in its discretion, declares its expiration. The state, municipality, or charitable organization of the state shall maintain a current listing of all vehicles registered to it in the order of the registration number assigned to each vehicle, and shall provide a copy of the listing to the department upon request. The listing must include a description of each vehicle and other identifying information required by the department. Registration plates issued under this subsection must be of a distinctive design and numbering system.  For the purposes of this subsection, charitable organization means a nonprofit association, corporation, society, or other entity organized, incorporated, or headquartered in the state for educational, cultural, scientific, or other charitable purposes, as prescribed in regulations of the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-181__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Vehicles owned by elected state officials. The department shall issue special registration plates to each incumbent elected state official for display on motor vehicles owned and driven by the official except that the plates may not be displayed on a vehicle that is visually identifiable as a commercial vehicle. The department shall number or design the plates so that registration by an elected state official is indicated upon the plates. The registration plates issued under this subsection may remain on the vehicle only during the official's term of office.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-181__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 9 ch 20 SLA 1990.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-181__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Vehicles owned by ranchers, farmers, and dairymen. A vehicle not exceeding an unladen total gross weight of 20,000 pounds, owned by a person deriving the person's primary source of livelihood from the operation of a ranch, farm, or dairy where the person resides full-time, and that is used exclusively to transport (1) the person's own ranch, farm, or dairy products, or greenhouse or nursery products, including vegetables, plants, grass seed, sod, or tree seedlings, to and from the market, or (2) supplies, commodities, or equipment to be used on the person's ranch, farm, or dairy, or in the person's greenhouse or nursery, may be registered under this subsection and may be issued registration plates of a distinctive design or system of numbering.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-181__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Amateur mobile radio station vehicles.  A validly licensed amateur radio operator who presents satisfactory proof that the owner holds an unexpired Federal Communications Commission amateur radio operator's license of any renewable class, and who presents satisfactory proof that the vehicle contains or carries an amateur radio transmitter and receiving unit of a type applicable to the license class applied for, and who is permitted by law to operate a fixed station, may register one amateur mobile radio station vehicle for each radio license issued by the federal government and may receive for the vehicle distinctive registration plates instead of regular registration plates.  The number on the plates must be the radio call sign of the owner.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-181__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Vehicles owned by dealers. A state-registered and bonded vehicle dealer may apply for a dealer registration plate. A plate issued under this subsection may be used only on dealer-owned vehicles during the routine and normal course of the dealer's business, excluding service vehicles, or for transporting an unregistered vehicle from a port of entry to the dealer's facilities or from one dealer to another or, in the case of a house trailer, from the retail facility to a trailer space. A vehicle permitted to have a dealer plate must be affixed with one plate issued under this subsection. If the dealer sells or transfers the vehicle, the dealer plate may be used on the vehicle by the new owner or transferee for a period of not more than five days after the sale or transfer. The department may seize the dealer plate if it has reason to believe that the plate is being used to defeat the purposes of, or is in violation of, this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-181__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 3 ch 8 SLA 1993.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-181__subsec_l">
              <num>(l)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Vehicles owned by Pearl Harbor survivors, former prisoners of war, Medal of Honor recipients, and relatives of members of the United States armed forces killed in the line of duty. The department, upon receipt of written proof, shall issue without charge special registration plates for one noncommercial motor vehicle to a person who was on active military duty in Pearl Harbor on December 7, 1941, who has been a prisoner of war during a declared war or other conflict, as determined by the Department of Defense under federal regulations, who is the recipient of the Medal of Honor awarded by the President of the United States in the name of the United States Congress, or the spouse, parent, guardian, brother, sister, or dependent of a member of the United States armed forces killed in the line of duty. The design and color of the Pearl Harbor survivor, prisoner of war, Medal of Honor awarded by the President of the United States in the name of the United States Congress recipient, or relative of a member of the United States armed forces killed in the line of duty plates shall be solely within the discretion of the commissioner.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-181__subsec_m">
              <num>(m)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Special request plates for Alaska National Guard personnel. Upon application by the owner of a motor vehicle who presents satisfactory proof of current membership in the Alaska National Guard, the department may design and issue registration plates that identify the vehicle as registered to a member of the Alaska National Guard.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-181__subsec_n">
              <num>(n)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 9 ch 20 SLA 1990.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-181__subsec_o">
              <num>(o)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Special request university plates. Upon application by the owner of a motor vehicle, the department may design and issue registration plates representing the University of Alaska Anchorage, University of Alaska Fairbanks, University of Alaska Southeast, or Prince William Sound Community College. The department may disapprove the issuance of registration plates under this subsection when the requested plates are a duplication of an existing registration.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-181__subsec_p">
              <num>(p)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Vehicles owned by veterans. The department, upon receipt of written proof that the veteran is a sole or joint owner of a motor vehicle, shall issue special registration plates for the motor vehicle to a requesting person who is a veteran or retired veteran of the armed forces of the United States. The commissioner, after consulting with the person in the Department of Military and Veterans' Affairs in charge of veterans' affairs, shall determine the design and color of the veteran or retired veteran plates.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-181__subsec_q">
              <num>(q)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Vehicles owned by recipients of the Purple Heart. The department, upon receipt of written proof that the person is the sole or joint owner of a motor vehicle, shall issue special registration plates for the motor vehicle to a requesting person who has received the Purple Heart medal awarded for wounds suffered in action against an armed enemy or as a result of the hostile action of an armed enemy. The commissioner, after consulting with the person in the Department of Military and Veterans' Affairs in charge of veterans' affairs, shall determine the design and color of the Purple Heart medal recipient plates.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-181__subsec_r">
              <num>(r)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Special request custom collector plates. Upon application by the owner of a custom collector vehicle, the department may design and issue registration plates appropriate for custom collector vehicles. The department may disapprove the issuance of registration plates under this subsection when the requested plates are a duplication of an existing registration.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-181__subsec_s">
              <num>(s)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Special request dog mushing plates. Upon application by the owner of a motor vehicle, the department may design and issue registration plates representing the sport of dog mushing in the state. The department may disapprove the issuance of registration plates under this subsection when the requested plates are a duplication of an existing registration.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-181__subsec_t">
              <num>(t)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Special request Alaska children's trust plates. Upon application by the owner of a motor vehicle, the department may design and issue registration plates representing the Alaska children's trust under
AS 37.14.200
. The department may disapprove the issuance of registration plates under this subsection when the requested plates are a duplication of an existing registration.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-181__subsec_u">
              <num>(u)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 8 ch 70 SLA 2018.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-181__subsec_v">
              <num>(v)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 4 ch 11 SLA 2002.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-181__subsec_w">
              <num>(w)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Special request plates commemorating Alaska veterans. Upon application by the owner of a motor vehicle, the department may issue registration plates commemorating Alaska veterans. The commissioner shall determine the design and color of plates commemorating Alaska veterans. The department may disapprove the issuance of registration plates under this subsection when the requested plates are a duplication of an existing registration.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-181__subsec_x">
              <num>(x)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Special request plates commemorating and supporting troops. Upon application by the owner of a motor vehicle, the department may issue registration plates commemorating and supporting troops. The commissioner, in consultation with Support Our Troops, Inc., shall determine the design and color of the plates. The department may disapprove the issuance of registration plates under this subsection when the requested plates are a duplication of an existing registration. Support Our Troops shall appear at the bottom of the plate and may be alternated with Support Our Heroes if Support Our Troops, Inc., approves the use of terms and agrees to be responsible for any costs incurred from lack of sale of plates.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-181__subsec_y">
              <num>(y)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Special request Iditarod race finisher plates. Upon application by the owner of a motor vehicle, the department may design and issue Iditarod race finisher registration plates to a person who has finished the Iditarod race. The owner shall supply written proof, verified by the Iditarod Trail Committee, that the owner has successfully finished the race. The department may disapprove the issuance of registration plates under this subsection when the requested plates are a duplication of an existing registration.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-181__subsec_z">
              <num>(z)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Special request firefighter and emergency medical service provider plates. On application by the owner of a motor vehicle, the department may issue registration plates for firefighters and emergency medical service providers. The commissioner shall determine the design and color of the plates. The department may disapprove the issuance of registration plates under this subsection when the requested plates are a duplication of an existing registration. To be eligible for a firefighter and emergency medical service provider plate, a person shall present satisfactory proof that the person is</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-181__subsec_z__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an active member of
(A) a fire department in this state and the fire department is recognized as a fire department by the state fire marshal; or
(B) an out-of-hospital emergency medical service certified by the Department of Health; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-181__subsec_z__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a former firefighter or emergency medical service provider who was an active member of
(A) a fire department in this state for a minimum of five years; or
(B) an out-of-hospital emergency medical service certified by the Department of Health for a minimum of five years.
(aa) Special request fraternal organization member plates. On the request of a fraternal organization, the department may design a registration plate for the members of that fraternal organization. On application by the owner of a motor vehicle who is a member of that fraternal organization, the department may issue the fraternal organization registration plates to the person. The commissioner shall determine the design and color of the fraternal organization plates in consultation with the fraternal organization. The department may disapprove the issuance of registration plates under this subsection when the requested plates are a duplication of an existing registration. To be eligible for a fraternal organization member registration plate, a person must present evidence satisfactory to the department of the person's membership in the fraternal organization. In this subsection, fraternal organization means a civic, service, or charitable organization in the state, except a college and high school fraternity, not for pecuniary profit, that is a branch, lodge, or chapter of a national organization and exists for the common business, brotherhood, or other interest of its members.
(bb) Special request United States flag In God We Trust plates. Upon application by the owner of a motor vehicle, the department may issue registration plates with a design incorporating the flag of the United States and the motto In God We Trust on the plate. The commissioner shall determine the design and color of the plates. The department may disapprove the issuance of registration plates under this subsection when the requested plates are a duplication of an existing registration.
(cc) Special request Lao veteran pl</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-181__subsec_z__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>(A) provide that the entity requesting the issuance of the plates (A) submit an application on a form provided by the department;
(B) pay an application fee set by the department for issuance of the new registration plates;
(C) pay the entire cost of developing and issuing the specialty plate;
(D) may not be offensive in purpose, nature, activity, or name;
(E) may charge a fee for issuance of a specialty registration plate in addition to any registration fees set by statute or regulation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-181__subsec_z__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide for notice to the entity sponsoring the plate not later than six months before a proposed cancellation of the specialty organization plate;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-181__subsec_z__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establish procedures for owners of vehicles to purchase specialty organization registration plates under this subsection.
(mm) Special request plates commemorating peace officers killed in the line of duty. Upon application by the owner of a motor vehicle, the department may issue registration plates commemorating peace officers killed in the line of duty. The commissioner, after consulting with representatives of peace officers killed in the line of duty, shall determine the design and color of the plates. The department may disapprove the issuance of registration plates under this subsection when the requested plates are a duplication of an existing registration. In this subsection, peace officer means</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-181__subsec_z__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an officer of the state troopers;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-181__subsec_z__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a member of the police force of a municipality;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-181__subsec_z__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a correctional officer;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-181__subsec_z__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a village public safety officer;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-181__subsec_z__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an officer assigned to a court to serve warrants and court orders, provide court security and judicial protection, and transport prisoners; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-181__subsec_z__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>any other public servant vested by law with a duty to maintain public order or to make arrests, whether the duty extends to all offenses or is limited to a specific class of offenses or offenders.
(nn) Vehicles owned by women veterans. The department, upon receipt of written proof that the woman veteran is a sole or joint owner of a motor vehicle, shall issue special registration plates for the motor vehicle to a requesting person who is a woman veteran or retired woman veteran of the armed forces of the United States.
(oo) Special request plates for United States Space Force personnel. Upon application by the owner of a motor vehicle who presents satisfactory proof of current membership in the Unites States Space Force, the department may design and issue registration plates that identify the vehicle as registered to a member of the United States Space Force. The department may disapprove the issuance of registration plates under this subsection when the requested plates are a duplication of an existing registration.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-201">
            <num>28.10.201</num>
            <heading>Mandatory and permissive vehicle titles.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-201__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as otherwise provided in (b) of this section or in
AS 28.10.131
, 28.10.152, and 28.10.181(hh), every owner of a vehicle subject to registration in this state shall apply for a certificate of title under this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-201__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The owner of a vehicle described in
AS 28.10.011
as being exempt from registration and the owner of a snowmobile or off-highway vehicle may not apply for, nor may the department issue, a certificate of title for the vehicle. However, the department</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-201__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>may issue a certificate of title to the owner of a vehicle exempt from registration under
AS 28.10.011
(3), (6), (7), or (10) only upon application by that owner; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-201__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>except as provided in (e) of this section, shall issue a certificate of title to the owner of a manufactured home upon application, display of evidence of ownership satisfactory to the department, and payment of a fee of $100 by the owner; a certificate of title issued under this paragraph must comply with
AS 28.10.231
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-201__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The certificate of title issued may, when there is more than one owner, state the name of each owner in the conjunctive or in the disjunctive in order to indicate that the owners own the vehicle together or in the alternative.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-201__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except for vehicles registered under
AS 28.10.131</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-201__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or (c) or 28.10.152, the department may not register a vehicle unless the applicant for registration at the same time applies for and obtains a certificate of title under this chapter or presents satisfactory evidence that a certificate of title was previously issued to the applicant. The department may not accept the application for the original certificate of registration or title to a vehicle unless the vehicle is in the state at the time of application. However, the department may accept an application for registration and certificate of title for a vehicle that is not in the state when the application is made by a registered and bonded dealer or by a resident of the state when the application is accompanied by a manufacturer's statement of origin or, in the case of a used vehicle, when the application is accompanied by a certificate of title issued in another jurisdiction.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-201__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may not issue a certificate of title to a manufactured home if an application for the manufactured home has been filed under
AS 28.10.262
 28.10.264.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-211">
            <num>28.10.211</num>
            <heading>Application for title.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-211__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The owner of a vehicle required to be titled under this chapter shall apply for title by properly completing and surrendering the forms prescribed by the commissioner and by complying with all applicable laws and regulations, after which the department shall issue a certificate of title.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-211__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An application for title or transfer of title must contain</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-211__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the signature of the owner, or if there is more than one owner, the signature of at least one of the owners and the name of each owner stated in the conjunctive or in the disjunctive; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-211__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>any other information reasonably required by the department.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-211__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When an application for title refers to a new vehicle, the application must be accompanied by a manufacturer's certificate of origin and other information reasonably required by the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-211__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An applicant for title to a vehicle transferred by court action on a lien or encumbrance shall surrender to the department a certified copy of the court order involuntarily transferring the vehicle.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-211__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a vehicle to be titled is a specially constructed or reconstructed vehicle, the fact shall be noted on the application for title.  The department may require evidence of prior registration of, or issuance of title for, the vehicle and may require the applicant to furnish additional information as it considers necessary to establish ownership, including bills of sale, invoices for vehicle equipment, or a surety bond.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-211__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The holder of a manufacturer's certificate of origin for a manufactured home may deliver the certificate to any person to facilitate conveying or encumbering the manufactured home, and a person who receives the manufacturer's certificate of origin holds it in trust for the person delivering it.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-216">
            <num>28.10.216</num>
            <heading>Inadequate evidence of ownership.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-216__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the department is not satisfied as to the ownership of a vehicle or believes that there may be undisclosed security interests in it, the department may register the vehicle but shall either</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-216__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>withhold issuance of a certificate of title until the applicant presents documents sufficient to satisfy the department
(A) as to the ownership of the vehicle by applicant; and
(B) that there are no undisclosed security interests in the vehicle; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-216__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>require the applicant, as a condition of the issuance of a certificate of title, to file with the department either
(A) a bond in the form prescribed by the department and executed by the applicant; or
(B) a deposit of cash.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-216__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A bond or cash deposit filed under (a)(2) of this section must be equal in amount to one and one-half times the value of the vehicle as determined by the department and be conditioned to indemnify former owners, secured parties, and subsequent purchasers of the vehicle and their successors against loss resulting from a defect in or undisclosed security interest on the title of the applicant.  An injured party may sue on the bond for a breach of its conditions, but the liability of the surety or the department may not exceed the amount of the bond or deposit.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-216__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The bond or deposit shall be returned (1) at the end of three years from its filing, or (2) when the vehicle is no longer registered in the state if (2) is earlier and if the certificate of title is surrendered to the department. Service on the department of notice that action is pending to recover on the bond or the deposit extends the periods established in this subsection until 45 days after a final decision in the action on the bond or on the deposit.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-221">
            <num>28.10.221</num>
            <heading>Refusal, suspension, and revocation of title.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-221__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may refuse to issue a certificate of title and may suspend or revoke a previously issued certificate of title when</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-221__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the certificate of title was fraudulently procured or erroneously issued or required information or fees have not been provided;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-221__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the vehicle has been scrapped, dismantled, or destroyed beyond repair;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-221__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the vehicle has been reported to the department as stolen or unlawfully converted, until the department learns of the recovery of the vehicle or that the report of its theft or conversion was false or erroneous; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-221__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>authorized by any other provision of law.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-221__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Suspension or revocation of a certificate of title under (a) of this section does not affect the rights of a lienholder named on the certificate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-221__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A certificate of title that is suspended or revoked shall be returned immediately to the department by the owner or other person lawfully entitled to possession of the certificate of title.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-221__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in
AS 28.10.263
, the department may not suspend or revoke a certificate of title to a manufactured home based on the fact that the manufactured home is affixed in any manner to real property.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-231">
            <num>28.10.231</num>
            <heading>Certificate of title contents.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-231__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A certificate of title issued by the department must contain</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-231__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the date issued;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-231__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name and residence and mailing address of the owner;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-231__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name and address of the primary lienholder, if any;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-231__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a description of the vehicle including its make, year of manufacture, identification number; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-231__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>other information the department may reasonably require.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-231__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The certificate of title must contain a space for the assignment and warranty of title by the owner or dealer selling the vehicle and a space for the assignment or release of the security interest of a lienholder, and may contain forms for application for title by a transferee, and for the naming of a primary lienholder.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-231__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may not indicate on a certificate of title more than the primary lienholder and the primary registered owner when indicating lienholders and registered owners.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-241">
            <num>28.10.241</num>
            <heading>Delivery and judicial process against certificate of title.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-241__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall deliver the certificate of title to the primary lienholder named in the certificate.  Otherwise, delivery shall be to the registered owner.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-241__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A certificate of title for a vehicle is not subject to attachment, execution or other judicial process, but this section does not prevent a lawful levy upon the vehicle.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-251">
            <num>28.10.251</num>
            <heading>Lost, stolen, or mutilated certificate of title.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-251__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a certificate of title is lost, stolen, mutilated, destroyed, or becomes illegible, the first lienholder or, if none, the owner or legal representative of the owner named in the title as shown by the records of the department shall apply for and obtain a duplicate title upon furnishing information satisfactory to the department and payment of the prescribed fee.  The duplicate title must indicate that it is a duplicate title, and it shall be mailed or delivered to the first lienholder named in it or, if none, to the registered owner.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-251__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who recovers an original title for which a duplicate has been issued shall immediately surrender the duplicate to the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-261">
            <num>28.10.261</num>
            <heading>Evidence.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-261__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In a civil or criminal proceeding, when the title or right to possession of a vehicle is involved, the record of registrations and certificates of title as they appear in the files and records of the department are prima facie evidence of the ownership or right to possession. Proof of ownership or right to possession of a vehicle shall be made by a copy of the record certified by the department or by an original certificate of registration or title issued by the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-261__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Lien information indicated upon the title shall be accepted as prima facie evidence of legal ownership and the filing of a lien.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-261__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding another provision of law to the contrary, a certificate of title to a manufactured home issued by the department is prima facie evidence of the facts appearing on it, even if the manufactured home is affixed in any manner to real property.
Article 3. Manufactured Homes.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-262">
            <num>28.10.262</num>
            <heading>Cancellation of manufacturer's certificate of origin for manufactured home.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-262__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a manufactured home is permanently affixed to real property under
AS 34.85.150
, or if the owner intends to permanently affix the manufactured home to real property under
AS 34.85.150
, the owner may submit to the department an application requesting that the department cancel the manufacturer's certificate of origin for a manufactured home and update the department's records under
AS 28.05.061
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-262__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The application under (a) of this section must comply with
AS 28.10.266
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-262__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subject to
AS 28.05.041
, if the department is satisfied that the application filed under (a) of this section complies with (b) of this section, the department shall cancel the manufacturer's certificate of origin for the manufactured home, update the department's records under
AS 28.05.061
, and issue a written acknowledgment that the department has cancelled the certificate of origin under this section. The department shall deliver the written acknowledgment to the owner of the manufactured home and to a person identified under
AS 28.10.266</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-262__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the department has cancelled the manufacturer's certificate of origin under (c) of this section, the manufactured home is not subject to this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-263">
            <num>28.10.263</num>
            <heading>Cancellation of certificate of title to manufactured home.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-263__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a manufactured home is permanently affixed to real property under
AS 34.85.150
, or if the owner intends to permanently affix the manufactured home to real property under
AS 34.85.150
, the owner may submit to the department an application requesting that the department cancel the certificate of title to a manufactured home and update the department's records under
AS 28.05.061
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-263__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The application under (a) of this section must comply with
AS 28.10.266
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-263__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subject to
AS 28.05.041
, if the department is satisfied that the application filed under (a) of this section complies with (b) of this section and that there are no outstanding liens or encumbrances filed against the manufactured home under
AS 28.10.381
, the department shall cancel the certificate of title to the manufactured home, update the department's records under
AS 28.05.061
, and issue a written acknowledgment that the department has cancelled the certificate of title under this section. The department shall deliver the written acknowledgment to the owner of the manufactured home and to a person identified under
AS 28.10.266</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-263__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the department has cancelled a certificate of title under (c) of this section, the manufactured home is not subject to this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-264">
            <num>28.10.264</num>
            <heading>Confirmation of nonapplication of chapter.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-264__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The owner of a manufactured home may submit an application to the department requesting that the department indicate on the department's records that the manufactured home is not subject to this chapter if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-264__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the manufactured home is permanently affixed to real property under
AS 34.85.150
, or the owner intends to permanently affix the manufactured home to real property under
AS 34.85.150
; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-264__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the manufactured home
(A) is not covered by a manufacturer's certificate of origin or a certificate of title;
(B) is covered by a manufacturer's certificate of origin, but the owner of the manufactured home, after diligent search and inquiry, is unable to produce the certificate of origin; or
(C) is covered by a certificate of title, but the owner of the manufactured home, after diligent search and inquiry, is unable to produce the certificate of title.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-264__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The application under (a) of this section must comply with
AS 28.10.266
and be accompanied by a bond or cash deposit described in (c) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-264__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The bond that accompanies the application under (b) of this section must be in the form prescribed by the department and executed by the applicant. The amount of the bond or cash deposit that accompanies the application under (b) of this section must be equal to one and one-half times the value of the manufactured home as determined by the department and must be conditioned to indemnify former owners, secured parties, and subsequent purchasers of the manufactured home and their successors against loss resulting from a defect in or undisclosed security interest on the title of the applicant. An injured party may bring a court action against the bond or cash deposit for a breach of the conditions of the bond or cash deposit, but the liability of the bond surety or the department may not exceed the amount of the bond or cash deposit. The department shall return the bond or cash deposit at the end of three years after the submission under (b) of this section, except that service on the department of notice that an action is pending against the bond or cash deposit extends that period until 45 days after a final decision in the action on the bond or cash deposit.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-264__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the department is satisfied that the application filed under (a) of this section complies with (b) of this section, the department shall, subject to
AS 28.05.041
, indicate under
AS 28.05.061
on the department's records that the manufactured home is not subject to this chapter and shall provide to the owner a written confirmation that the owner of the manufactured home has submitted an application that complies with (b) of this section and that the manufactured home is not subject to this chapter. The department shall deliver the written confirmation to the owner of the manufactured home and to a person identified under
AS 28.10.266</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-264__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the department has provided a written confirmation under (d) of this section, the manufactured home is not subject to this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-265">
            <num>28.10.265</num>
            <heading>Certificate of title to severed manufactured home.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-265__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The owner of a manufactured home may submit an application to the department requesting that the department issue a certificate of title to a manufactured home and update the department's records under
AS 28.05.061
if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-265__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the manufactured home was permanently affixed to real property under
AS 34.85.150
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-265__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an affixation affidavit was recorded for the manufactured home under
AS 40.17.125
; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-265__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>after the occurrence of (1) and (2) of this subsection, the manufactured home was severed from the real property to which it was affixed.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-265__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The application under (a) of this section must comply with
AS 28.10.266
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-265__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subject to
AS 28.05.041
, if the department is satisfied that the application filed under (a) of this section complies with (b) of this section, the department shall issue a certificate of title to the manufactured home under
AS 28.10.231
 28.10.241, update the department's records under
AS 28.05.061
, and issue to the owner and to a person identified under
AS 28.10.266</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-265__subsec_c__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a written acknowledgment that the department has issued a certificate of title under this section.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-265__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the department has issued a certificate of title under (c) of this section, the manufactured home is subject to this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-266">
            <num>28.10.266</num>
            <heading>Application provisions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.10.266.   Application provisions.
An application under
AS 28.10.262
 28.10.265 must provide
(1) the name, residence, and mailing address of the owner of the manufactured home;
(2) a description of the manufactured home, including the name of the manufacturer, the make, the model name, the model year, the manufacturer's serial number for the manufactured home, and other information required by the department about the manufactured home;
(3) whether the manufactured home is new or used;
(4) for an application under
AS 28.10.262
 28.10.264, the date of purchase by the owner of the manufactured home and the name and address of the person from whom the home was acquired;
(5) for an application under
AS 28.10.262
 28.10.264, the name and address of any person who holds a lien or an encumbrance against the manufactured home and the order of apparent priority;
(6) a statement signed by the owner, stating
(A) any facts or information known to the owner that could reasonably affect the validity of the title to the manufactured home or the existence or nonexistence of a lien or encumbrance on it; or
(B) that the owner does not know any facts or information that could reasonably affect the validity of the title to the manufactured home or the existence or nonexistence of a lien or encumbrance on the manufactured home;
(7) subject to
AS 28.10.268
, for an application under
AS 28.10.262
 28.10.264, a certified copy of an affixation affidavit that complies with
AS 34.85.060
and that has been recorded under
AS 40.17.125
for the manufactured home;
(8) for an application under
AS 28.10.265
, a certified copy of a severance affidavit that complies with
AS 34.85.120
and that has been recorded under
AS 40.17.125
for the manufactured home;
(9) for an application under
AS 28.10.262
, the original manufacturer's certificate of origin;
(10) for an application under
AS 28.10.263
, the original certificate of title;
(11) for an application under
AS 28.10.264
or 28.10.265, a declaration that complies with
AS 28.10.267
;
(12) if desired by the applicant, the name and mailing address of one person, in addition to the owner, to receive a written acknowledgment from the department under
AS 28.10.262
, 28.10.263, or 28.10.265 or a written confirmation under
AS 28.10.264
; and
(13) other information and documents the department reasonably requires
(A) to identify the owner of the manufactured home;
(B) to determine the existence or nonexistence of liens or encumbrances on the manufactured home;
(C) for an application under
AS 28.10.262
 28.10.264, to enable the department to determine whether the owner satisfied the applicable requirements of
AS 34.85.010
; and
(D) for an application under
AS 28.10.265
, to enable the department to determine whether the owner of the manufactured home is entitled to a certificate of title.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-267">
            <num>28.10.267</num>
            <heading>Declaration.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-267__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The declaration required by
AS 28.10.266</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-267__subsec_a__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>must be made under oath or affirmation by an attorney authorized under
AS 08.08
to practice law in the state or an agent of a title insurance company entitled under
AS 21.66
to transact a title insurance business in this state.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-267__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The declaration must state that the manufactured home is free and clear of all liens and encumbrances and</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-267__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>any facts or information known to the attorney or agent that could reasonably affect the validity of the title to the manufactured home or the existence or nonexistence of a lien or encumbrance on the manufactured home; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-267__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>that the attorney or agent does not know any facts or information that could reasonably affect the validity of the title to the manufactured home or the existence or nonexistence of a lien or encumbrance on the manufactured home.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-268">
            <num>28.10.268</num>
            <heading>Time of satisfaction.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.10.268.   Time of satisfaction.
If a person delivers an application under
AS 28.10.262
 28.10.264 for a manufactured home to the department within 30 days after an affixation affidavit for the manufactured home is recorded under
AS 40.17.125
, and if the application is accepted by the department, the requirements of
AS 28.10.262
 28.10.264 are considered to be satisfied on the date the affixation affidavit is recorded, and, if the manufactured home is conveyed or encumbered on and after that date, the manufactured home shall be conveyed and encumbered as real property.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-269">
            <num>28.10.269</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.10.269.   Definitions.
In
AS 28.10.201
 28.10.269, unless the context indicates otherwise,
(1) affixation affidavit means an affixation affidavit under
AS 34.85.060
;
(2) severance affidavit means a severance affidavit under
AS 34.85.120
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-271">
            <num>28.10.271</num>
            <heading>Transfer of vehicle by owner.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-271__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the owner of a registered vehicle transfers or assigns the owner's title or interest in the vehicle, the registration of the vehicle expires; however, the registration plates remain on the vehicle except as otherwise provided in
AS 28.10.181
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-271__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The owner shall, at the time of delivery of the vehicle, endorse an assignment and warranty of title to the transferee in the space provided on the certificate of title. The owner shall deliver the certificates of title and registration to the transferee at the time of delivery of the vehicle, except as otherwise provided in
AS 28.10.291
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-271__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The owner shall notify the department of the transfer or assignment of the owner's title or interest in the vehicle within 10 days following transfer or assignment.  This notification shall constitute a valid transfer under
AS 28.10.321
and 28.10.361.  The notice form to be provided by the department must include the following information:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-271__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>name and address of owner;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-271__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>name and address of transferee;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-271__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>date of transfer or assignment; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-271__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>description and license number of vehicle.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-271__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An emissions inspection and maintenance certificate</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-271__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall be obtained when ownership of a vehicle subject to registration under this chapter is transferred if the
(A) transferee resides in an area designated by the Department of Environmental Conservation as an emissions inspection and maintenance area;
(B) vehicle would be subject to an emissions inspection and maintenance program; and
(C) vehicle</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-271__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>has not been inspected for emissions, or the existing emissions inspection occurred more than two years ago; or
(ii) has a certificate of inspection, but the certificate shows that the vehicle is not in compliance with program requirements;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-271__subsec_i__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>need not be obtained under (1) of this subsection if, when ownership of vehicle is transferred,
(A) the transferor surrenders the vehicle's registration plates and all evidence of registration in the transferor's possession or control to the department; or
(B) the vehicle has a valid, existing emissions inspection and maintenance program seasonal waiver and the purchaser signs a seasonal waiver transfer acknowledgment form approved by the department.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-281">
            <num>28.10.281</num>
            <heading>Transfer to dealer.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-281__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the owner of a registered vehicle transfers or assigns the owner's title or interest to a vehicle dealer under
AS 28.10.271
, the dealer is not required to present the certificates of registration and title to the department as provided in
AS 28.10.321
and 28.10.361 until the vehicle is transferred by the dealer.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-281__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A vehicle transferred to a dealer may not be driven unless it is reregistered under this chapter or is driven under dealer registration plates issued under
AS 28.10.181
(j).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-291">
            <num>28.10.291</num>
            <heading>Transfer from dealer.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-291__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A vehicle dealer, upon transferring a vehicle, shall execute an assignment and a warranty of title to the transferee as provided in
AS 28.10.271
and furnish proof of the sale of the vehicle to the transferee.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-291__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The dealer shall, within 30 days of the transfer of the vehicle, forward to the department the transferee's completed application for new certificates of title and registration except as provided in (c) of this section.  The application must contain the vehicle dealer's license number and must be accompanied by any required fees and taxes.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-291__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the transferee indicates in a sworn affidavit that the transferee does not intend to use the vehicle in a manner requiring registration in this state, the dealer may deliver the certificate of title to the transferee directly.  The dealer shall mail or deliver the affidavit to the department within five days of the transfer.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-301">
            <num>28.10.301</num>
            <heading>Transfer of motor vehicle to minor.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-301__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An agreement for the purchase of a motor vehicle by a minor who has not been emancipated is void unless a parent or guardian of the minor is also a party to the agreement.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-301__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a vehicle is improperly transferred to a minor, the title to and registration of the vehicle remains with the owner and does not transfer to the minor or the parent or guardian of the minor.  However, if the certificate of title and registration for the vehicle has been delivered to the minor or the parent or guardian of the minor, that person shall immediately deliver the certificate of title and registration to the department.  The department shall reissue title to the previous owner of record.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-301__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, emancipated means that a minor to whom the term refers is a resident of this state and is at least 16 years of age, is living separate and apart from the minor's parents or guardian, and is capable of self-support and of managing the minor's own financial affairs.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-311">
            <num>28.10.311</num>
            <heading>Transfer by operation of law.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-311__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the title to, or interest in, a registered vehicle passes to another person other than by a voluntary transfer, the registration of that vehicle expires.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-311__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person holding a certificate of title to a vehicle whose interest in the vehicle has been extinguished or transferred other than by voluntary transfer shall mail or deliver the certificates of title and registration to the department upon request of the department.  The delivery of the certificates of title and registration to the department upon its request does not affect the rights of the person surrendering the certificate of title, and the action of the department in issuing a new certificate of title or registration as provided in this chapter is not conclusive upon the rights of an owner or lienholder named in the surrendered certificate of title.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-321">
            <num>28.10.321</num>
            <heading>New owner to secure transfer of registration and new title.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-321__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided under
AS 28.10.281
and 28.10.291, the new owner shall, within 30 days, present the certificates of title and registration properly endorsed to the department, apply for a new title, and register the vehicle as upon an original registration.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-321__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An application for certificates of title and registration must be accompanied by any required registration fees and taxes, transfer of title and lien fees, and by the previous certificates of title and registration, if any.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-331">
            <num>28.10.331</num>
            <heading>Department to issue new certificates of title and registration.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.10.331.   Department to issue new certificates of title and registration.
The department, upon receipt of the certificate of title properly endorsed, the certificate of registration, the registration plates, if any, the application for new title and registration, and all required fees and taxes, shall issue a certificate of title and a certificate of registration to the transferee or the lienholder lawfully entitled to the certificates.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-341">
            <num>28.10.341</num>
            <heading>Duty of lienholder in possession of title to transferred vehicle.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.10.341.   Duty of lienholder in possession of title to transferred vehicle.
Upon request of an owner or transferee, a lienholder in possession of the certificate of title to a transferred vehicle shall, unless the transfer is in breach of a security agreement, deliver the certificate to the transferee. The delivery of the certificate of title does not affect the rights of the lienholder under the lienholder's security agreement.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-351">
            <num>28.10.351</num>
            <heading>Dismantling or wrecking vehicle.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.10.351.   Dismantling or wrecking vehicle.
A person who dismantles, scraps, or destroys a registered vehicle shall immediately forward to the department the certificates of title and registration and the registration plates for the vehicle.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-361">
            <num>28.10.361</num>
            <heading>When transfer effective.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.10.361.   When transfer effective.
A transfer by an owner or dealer is not effective until all applicable provisions of this chapter have been complied with.  However, an owner or dealer who has delivered possession of a vehicle to the transferee and has endorsed an assignment and warranty of title on the certificate of title and delivered the certificates of title and registration to the transferee or, in the case of a transfer from a dealer, delivered proof of the sale to the transferee, is not liable as the owner for any liabilities resulting from the driving or movement of the vehicle after the transfer.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-371">
            <num>28.10.371</num>
            <heading>Filing documents evidencing liens or encumbrances.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-371__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A conditional sales contract, chattel mortgage, or other lien or encumbrance or title retention document on a registered vehicle, other than a lien dependent upon possession, is not valid against a vehicle owner's creditor who acquires a lien dependent upon possession, or by levy or attachment, or against a subsequent purchaser or encumbrancer without notice, until the requirements of
AS 28.10.371
 28.10.401 are satisfied.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-371__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (a) of this section, a lien on a manufactured home for the purchase of the manufactured home is valid against judicial lien creditors and execution creditors on and after the date the lien attaches under
AS 45.29
against the manufactured home.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-371__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (a) of this section, the holder of a lien on a manufactured home may deliver a lien release document to a person to facilitate conveying or encumbering the manufactured home. A person receiving the lien release document holds the document in trust for the lienholder.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-375">
            <num>28.10.375</num>
            <heading>Effect of terminal rental adjustment clauses.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.10.375.   Effect of terminal rental adjustment clauses.
Notwithstanding other provisions of law, a transaction involving a motor vehicle or trailer does not create a sale or security interest merely because the transaction provides that the rental price is permitted or required to be adjusted under the agreement either upward or downward by reference to the amount realized upon the sale or other disposition of the motor vehicle or trailer.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-381">
            <num>28.10.381</num>
            <heading>Filing a lien or encumbrance.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-381__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A lien or other encumbrance on a vehicle may be filed by delivering to the department</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-381__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a manufacturer's certificate of origin or an existing certificate of title;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-381__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an application for a new certificate of title, signed by the registered owner and containing the name and address of any lienholder and the date of the lienholder's interest;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-381__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>applicable filing fees required by law; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-381__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>other documents or information required by the department.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-381__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon approval of the application, the department shall send to the person holding a lien or other encumbrance a new certificate of title which displays the name of the owner and indicates the existence of the lien or other encumbrance.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-381__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as otherwise provided in
AS 28.10.262
, 28.10.263, and
AS 34.85
, after a certificate of title to a manufactured home has been issued and while the manufactured home is subject to a lien or encumbrance under (a) of this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-381__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the department may not cancel the manufacturer's certificate of origin for the manufactured home under
AS 28.10.262
, or cancel the certificate of title to the manufactured home under
AS 28.10.263
; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-381__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the validity and priority of the lien or encumbrance continues.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-391">
            <num>28.10.391</num>
            <heading>Filing and date of notice.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-391__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The filing of the application and documents under
AS 28.10.381
and the issuance of a new certificate of title are constructive notice of any liens or encumbrances against the vehicle described in the certificate to a creditor of the owner, or to a subsequent purchaser or encumbrancer. However, a mortgage, conditional sale contract, or similar lien or encumbrance on the vehicle is subordinate to a lien under
AS 28.10.502
and is subject to the procedure provided in that section. A lien or encumbrance on a vehicle for labor, material, transportation, storage, or similar activity, other than a lien under
AS 28.10.502
, whether or not dependent on possession for its validity, is subordinate only to a mortgage, conditional sale contract, or similar lien or encumbrance on the vehicle properly filed on or before the time that the vehicle is subject to, or comes into possession of, the lien or encumbrance claimant for the labor, material, transportation, storage, or similar activity.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-391__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the documents referred to in
AS 28.10.371
 28.10.401 are received and filed in the central office of the department within 10 days after the date that the documents were executed, the constructive notice dates from the time of the execution of the documents. Otherwise, constructive notice dates from the time of receipt and filing of the documents by the department as shown in its endorsement on the documents.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-391__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Filing as provided in
AS 28.10.371
 28.10.401 is the exclusive method of giving constructive notice of a lien or encumbrance on a registered vehicle, except as to a lien dependent upon possession.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-391__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A lien or encumbrance or a document creating and evidencing a lien or encumbrance is exempt from the other provisions of law that require or relate to the recording or filing of a document creating and evidencing a lien or encumbrance upon a vehicle of a type subject to registration under this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-391__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding another provision of this section, the creation or termination of a lien or encumbrance with respect to a manufactured home that has been converted to real property under
AS 34.85.010
is governed by the laws that apply to real property.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-401">
            <num>28.10.401</num>
            <heading>Assignment or release by lienholder.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-401__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person holding a lien or encumbrance upon a vehicle, other than a lien dependent solely upon possession, may assign that person's title to or interest in the vehicle to a person other than the owner without the consent of the owner and without affecting the interest of the owner or the registration of the vehicle.  The person assigning the interest shall give written notice of the assignment to the owner.  Upon receiving a certificate of title assigned by the holder of a lien or encumbrance shown on the certificate and the name and address of the assignee, accompanied by the title fee required under
AS 28.10.441
, the department shall issue a new certificate of title.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-401__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person holding a lien or encumbrance upon a vehicle, as shown on a certificate of title, may release the lien or encumbrance or assign that person's interest to the owner of the vehicle without affecting the registration of the vehicle. Upon receiving a certificate of title upon which a lienholder has released or assigned the lienholder's interest to the owner, or upon receipt of a certificate not endorsed but accompanied by a legal release from a lienholder of the lienholder's interest to a vehicle, and upon payment of the title fee required under
AS 28.10.441
, the department shall issue a new certificate of title.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-411">
            <num>28.10.411</num>
            <heading>Registration fees levied.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-411__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For every year during any part of which a vehicle is subject to registration under this chapter, a registration fee shall be paid to the department at the time of original registration and at each biennial renewal of registration after that time.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-411__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, 1983 Initiative Proposal No. 2, § 6.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-411__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 6 ch 70 SLA 1986.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-411__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 41 ch 37 SLA 1986.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-411__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 3 ch 89 SLA 1987.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-411__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A resident 65 years of age or older on the date the registration fee is due or a resident with a disability that limits or impairs the ability to walk and who provides proof of that disability as provided in 23 C.F.R. 1235.2 is entitled to an exemption from the registration fee required under this section for one vehicle subject to registration under
AS 28.10.421
(b)(1)(A), (b)(2), (b)(4), or (j). An exemption may not be granted except upon written application for the exemption on a form prescribed by the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-411__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who presents satisfactory proof of current membership in the Alaska National Guard is entitled to an exemption from the registration fee required under this section for one vehicle subject to registration under
AS 28.10.421
(b)(1)(A), (b)(2), or (b)(4). An exemption may not be granted except upon written application for the exemption on a form prescribed by the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-421">
            <num>28.10.421</num>
            <heading>Registration fee rates.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-421__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless otherwise provided by law,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-421__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the fees prescribed in this section shall be paid to the department at the times provided under
AS 28.10.108
and  28.10.111;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-421__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an additional fee of $10 shall be added to the registration fee set out in this section for registration not conducted by mail, on the department's Internet website, or at an emissions inspection station or contract office offering vehicle registration services; the department may waive this additional fee for a good cause based on criteria established in regulations adopted by the department; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-421__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an additional fee in an amount not to exceed $50 shall be added to the registration fee set out in this section for a vehicle registration plate celebrating the arts under
AS 28.10.161</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-421__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The biennial registration fees under this subsection are imposed within the following classifications for</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-421__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a vehicle not exceeding 10,000 pounds unladen weight as established by the manufacturer's advertised weight or on the actual weight, which the owner shall furnish, subject to the approval of the commissioner or the commissioner's representative that is a
(A) passenger vehicle, low-speed vehicle, pick-up truck, truck, or van not used or maintained for the transportation of persons or property for hire or for other commercial use and not registered in the name of a company or business   .....  $100;
(B) taxicab   .....  $160;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-421__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a motor home not used or maintained for the transportation of persons or property for hire or for other commercial use and not registered in the name of a company or business   .....  $100;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-421__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a motor bus with a seating capacity of
(A) less than 20 persons and used exclusively for commercial purposes in the transporting of visitors or tourists   .....  $100;
(B) 20 or more persons and used exclusively for commercial purposes in the transporting of visitors or tourists   .....  $300;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-421__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a motorcycle or a motor-driven cycle   .....  $60.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-421__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The biennial registration fees under this subsection are imposed for a vehicle not subject to registration under (b) of this section and are based on the actual unladen weight as established by the manufacturer's advertised weight or on the actual weight, which the owner shall furnish, subject to the approval of the commissioner or the commissioner's representative, as follows:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-421__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>up to and including 5,000 pounds   .....  $180;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-421__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>more than 5,000 pounds to and including 12,000 pounds   .....  $268;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-421__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>more than 12,000 pounds to and including 18,000 pounds   .....  $516;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-421__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>more than 18,000 pounds   .....  $662.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-421__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The special registration fees under this subsection are imposed biennially, unless otherwise specified, for</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-421__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a historic vehicle registered under
(A)
AS 28.10.181</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-421__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>.....  $10;
(B)
AS 28.10.181
(b)(2) .....  $30 plus the fee required for that vehicle under (b) of this section, unless the historic vehicle is eligible for the fee described under (C) of this paragraph; the fee required by this subparagraph shall be collected only on the first issuance and on the replacement of the historic plates;
(C)
AS 28.10.181
(b)(2) and that is driven or moved on a highway for the primary purpose of historical exhibition or similar activity, one time only upon initial registration under
AS 28.10.181</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-421__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>.....  $10;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-421__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>special request plates for
(A) Alaska National Guard or United States Space Force personnel   .....  $30;
(B) veterans, retired veterans, women veterans, retired women veterans, or Lao veterans   .....  $30;
(C) recipients of the Purple Heart   .....  none;
(D) recipients of the Bronze Star awarded for valor, Silver Star, Navy Cross, Distinguished Service Cross, Air Force Cross, Coast Guard Cross, or other award reflecting valor  .....   $30;
(E) owners of custom collector vehicles   .....  $50;
(F) Iditarod race finishers   .....  $50;
(G) other special request plates   .....  $30;
plus the fee required for that vehicle under (b) of this section; the fee required by this paragraph shall be collected only on the first issuance and on the replacement of special request plates;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-421__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a vehicle owned by a person with a disability and registered under
AS 28.10.181</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-421__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a vehicle owned by the state   ...... none;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-421__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a vehicle owned by an elected state official   .....  the fee required for that vehicle under (b), (c), (h), or (i) of this section;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-421__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a vehicle owned by a rancher, farmer, or dairy-man and registered under
AS 28.10.181
.....  $68;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-421__subsec_b__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a snowmobile or off-highway vehicle   .....  $10;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-421__subsec_b__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an amateur mobile radio station vehicle,
(A) with a transceiver capable of less than 5-band operation .... the fee required for that vehicle under (b) or (c) of this section;
(B) in recognition of service to the public a mobile amateur radio station owned by an amateur with general class or higher license, provided the station must be satisfactorily proved capable of operating on at least five bands from 160 through 10 meters, must have an antenna, and must have a power supply and wiring as a permanent part of the vehicle; the transmitting unit may be removed from the car for service or dry storage  .... none for a mobile amateur radio station vehicle included in (b)(1)(A) of this section;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-421__subsec_b__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>dealer registration plates
(A) the initial plate   .....  $88;
(B) each subsequent plate   .....  $50;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-421__subsec_b__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a vehicle owned by a municipality or charitable organization meeting the requirements of
AS 28.10.181</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-421__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>.....  $10;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-421__subsec_e__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a vehicle owned by a Pearl Harbor survivor, a former prisoner of war, a recipient of the Medal of Honor awarded by the President of the United States in the name of the United States Congress, or the spouse, parent, guardian, brother, sister, or dependent of a member of the United States armed forces killed in the line of duty   .....  none;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-421__subsec_e__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>special request university plates   .....  $50  plus the fee required for that vehicle under (b), (c), (h), or (i) of this section; the fee required by this paragraph shall be collected only on the first issuance and on the replacement of special request plates; the commissioner shall separately account by university campus designation for the fees received under this paragraph that the department deposits in the general fund; the annual estimated balance in the accounts that is in excess of the cost of issuing special request university plates may be appropriated by the legislature for the support of programs at each campus;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-421__subsec_e__subsec_13">
                <num>(13)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>special request dog mushing plates   .....  $50  plus the fee required for that vehicle under (b), (c), (h), or (i) of this section; the fee required by this paragraph shall be collected only on the first issuance and on the replacement of special request plates; the commissioner shall separately account for the fees received under this paragraph that the department deposits in the general fund; notwithstanding (g) of this section, the annual estimated balance in the account that is in excess of the cost of issuing special request plates may be appropriated by the legislature for the support of programs benefiting dog mushing;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-421__subsec_e__subsec_14">
                <num>(14)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>special request Alaska children's trust plates   .....  $100  plus the fee required for that vehicle under (b), (c), (h), or (i) of this section; the fee required by this paragraph shall be collected only on the first issuance and the replacement of special request plates; the commissioner shall separately account for the fees received under this paragraph that the department deposits in the general fund; notwithstanding (g) of this section, the annual estimated balance in the account that is in excess of the cost of issuing special request plates may be appropriated by the legislature into the Alaska children's trust grant account established in
AS 37.14.205
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-421__subsec_e__subsec_15">
                <num>(15)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>[Repealed, § 8 ch 70, SLA 2018.]</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-421__subsec_e__subsec_16">
                <num>(16)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>special request plates commemorating Alaska veterans   .....  $100  plus a fee of $35 and the fee required for that vehicle under (b), (c), (h), or (i) of this section; the $100 fee required by this paragraph shall be collected only on the first issuance of and the replacement of the commemorative veterans' plates; the $35 fee required by this paragraph shall be collected biennially in the same manner as the fee required under (b), (c), (h), or (i) of this section; the commissioner shall separately account for the fees received under this paragraph that the department deposits in the general fund; notwithstanding (g) of this section, the annual estimated balance in the account that is in excess of the cost of issuing special request plates may be appropriated by the legislature to the Alaska veterans' cemetery fund created under
AS 37.05.600
and for the support of programs benefiting Alaska veterans;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-421__subsec_e__subsec_17">
                <num>(17)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>special request plates commemorating and supporting troops   .....  $40  plus the fee required for that vehicle under (b), (c), (h), or (i) of this section; the $40 fee required by this paragraph shall be collected on issuance and biennial renewal in the same manner as the fee required under (b), (c), (h), or (i) of this section; the commissioner shall separately account for the fees received under this paragraph that the department deposits in the general fund; notwithstanding (g) of this section, the annual estimated balance in the account that is in excess of the cost of issuing special request plates may be appropriated by the legislature to the organization for which the specialty license plate was purchased for the benefit of Alaska troops and their families;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-421__subsec_e__subsec_18">
                <num>(18)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>special request plates for firefighter and emergency medical service provider   .....  $30;  plus the fee required for that vehicle under (b), (c), (h), or (i) of this section; the fee required by this paragraph shall be collected only on the first issuance of and the replacement of the plates;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-421__subsec_e__subsec_19">
                <num>(19)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>special request fraternal organization member plates   .....  $50  plus the fee required for that vehicle under (b), (c), (h), or (i) of this section; the $50 fee required by this paragraph shall be collected only on the first issuance of and the replacement of the plates;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-421__subsec_e__subsec_20">
                <num>(20)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>special request United States flag In God We Trust plates   .....  $30  plus the fee required for that vehicle under (b), (c), (h), or (i) of this section; the fee required by this paragraph shall be collected biennially in the same manner as the fee required under (b), (c), (h), or (i) of this section;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-421__subsec_e__subsec_21">
                <num>(21)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>special request National Rifle Association plates   .....  $50  plus the fee required for that vehicle under (b), (c), (h), or (i) of this section; the $50 fee required by this paragraph shall be collected only on the first issuance and the replacement of the special request plates; a $30 fee shall be collected biennially there- after in the same manner as the fee required under (b), (c), (h), or (i) of this section; the commissioner shall separately account for the fees received under this paragraph that the department deposits into the general fund; notwithstanding (g) of this section, the annual estimated balance in the account that is in excess of the cost of issuing special request plates may be appropriated by the legislature to establish and maintain a scholastic clay target program and for other youth shooting programs;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-421__subsec_e__subsec_22">
                <num>(22)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>special request breast cancer awareness plates   .....  $50  plus the fee required for that vehicle under (b), (c), (h), or (i) of this section; the $50 fee required by this paragraph shall be collected only on the first issuance and the replacement of the special request plates; the commissioner shall separately account for the fees received under this paragraph that the department deposits into the general fund; notwithstanding (g) of this section, the annual estimated balance in the account that is in excess of the cost of issuing special request plates may be appropriated by the legislature to programs that provide screening for breast and cervical cancer;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-421__subsec_e__subsec_23">
                <num>(23)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>special request Choose Life plates   .....  $30  plus the fee required for that vehicle under (b), (c), (h), or (i) of this section; the fee required by this paragraph shall be collected biennially in the same manner as the fee required under (b), (c), (h), or (i) of this section; the commissioner shall separately account for the fees received under this paragraph that the department deposits in the general fund; the annual estimated balance in the account that is in excess of the cost of issuing special request Choose Life plates may be appropriated by the legislature to programs supporting or benefiting adoption;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-421__subsec_e__subsec_24">
                <num>(24)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>special request Pro-Family, Pro-Choice plates   .....  $30  plus the fee required for that vehicle under (b), (c), (h), or (i) of this section; the fee required by this paragraph shall be collected biennially in the same manner as the fee required under (b), (c), (h), or (i) of this section; the commissioner shall separately account for the fees received under this paragraph that the department deposits in the general fund; the annual estimated balance in the account that is in excess of the cost of issuing special request Pro-Family, Pro-Choice plates may be appropriated to the Alaska Children's Trust (
AS 37.14.200
);</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-421__subsec_e__subsec_25">
                <num>(25)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>special request Blood Bank of Alaska plates   .....  $50  plus the fee required for that vehicle under (b), (c), (h), or (i) of this section; the fee required by this paragraph shall be collected biennially in the same manner as the fee required under (b), (c), (h), or (i) of this section; the commissioner shall separately account for the fees received under this paragraph that the department deposits in the general fund; notwithstanding (g) of this section, the annual estimated balance in the account that is in excess of the cost of issuing special request plates may be appropriated by the legislature to the Blood Bank of Alaska.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-421__subsec_e__subsec_26">
                <num>(26)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>special request specialty organization plates under
AS 28.10.181
(ll) .....  $100 plus the fee required for that vehicle under (b), (c), (h), or (i) of this section; the fee required by this paragraph shall be collected biennially in the same manner as the fee required under (b), (c), (h), or (i) of this section; the commissioner shall separately account for the fees received under this paragraph that the department deposits in the general fund; notwithstanding (g) of this section, the annual estimated balance in the account that is in excess of the cost of issuing special request plates may be appropriated by the legislature to the Blood Bank of Alaska.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-421__subsec_e__subsec_27">
                <num>(27)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>special request plates commemorating peace officers killed in the line of duty  .....  $30 plus the fee required for that vehicle under (b), (c), (h), or (i) of this section; the fee required by this paragraph shall be collected biennially in the same manner as the fee required under (b), (c), (h), or (i) of this section.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-421__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A vehicle registered under this section which, by the removal of seats, a camper unit, a canopy or other equipment, may be converted into a vehicle on which the registration fee is computed on a different basis or in a different amount may not be driven or moved with seats, camper unit, canopy or other equipment removed unless the other applicable registration fee is paid.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-421__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to the fees imposed under (b) and (d) of this section, the following special biennial registration fee is imposed upon renewal of registration for a passenger vehicle, motor home, pick-up truck, or a van with special request Winter Olympics commemorative plates   .....  $60.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-421__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The fees collected by the department under this section shall be deposited in the general fund. The department shall separately account for three percent of the fees collected under this section and deposited in the general fund. The annual estimated balance in the account may be used by the legislature to make appropriations for administration of
AS 28.10.021</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-421__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and
AS 28.22
(Alaska Mandatory Automobile Insurance Act).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-421__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The annual registration fees under this subsection for vehicles, including low-speed vehicles, used for commercial purposes are imposed and are based upon the actual unladen weight as established by the manufacturer's advertised weight or upon the actual weight, which the owner shall furnish, subject to the approval of the commissioner or the commissioner's representative, as follows:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-421__subsec_h__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>up to and including 5,000 pounds   .....  $90;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-421__subsec_h__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>more than 5,000 pounds to and including 12,000 pounds   .....  $134;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-421__subsec_h__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>more than 12,000 pounds to and including 18,000 pounds   .....  $258;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-421__subsec_h__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>more than 18,000 pounds   .....  $331.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-421__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A one-time registration fee of $20 is imposed upon initial registration for a trailer or semi-trailer used for commercial purposes.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-421__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When a person registers a trailer not used or maintained for the transportation of persons or property for hire or for other commercial use, including a boat trailer, baggage trailer, box trailer, utility trailer, house trailer, travel trailer, or trailer rented or offered for rent, the person may choose to pay a biennial registration fee of $30 or, if the person resides within the unorganized borough or in a municipality that elects, by passage of an appropriate ordinance, to allow the permanent registration of motor vehicles, to register the trailer permanently. If the person permanently registers the trailer, the person shall pay the biennial registration fee plus a permanent registration fee of $25. If the person permanently registers the trailer, no additional registration fees are required if the same person who initially registered the trailer continues to own the trailer. A new owner of a trailer previously registered under this subsection shall register and pay the biennial registration fee or the permanent registration fee as provided in this subsection. The motor vehicle registration tax for a permanently registered trailer is the rate established for permanent trailer registration under
AS 28.10.431
(j). If a municipality has not established a tax for a permanently registered trailer, the biennial rate established in
AS 28.10.431</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-421__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or (j), if any, is levied upon the trailer and is payable only once at the time a trailer is permanently registered. If the person pays the registration tax as required by this subsection and
AS 28.10.431
, no additional registration taxes are required if the same person who initially registered the trailer continues to own the trailer.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-423">
            <num>28.10.423</num>
            <heading>Emission control inspection program fees.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-423__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to the biennial registration fee specified in
AS 28.10.421
, a $2 fee is imposed upon every vehicle required to be inspected under an emission control program established under
AS 46.14.400
or 46.14.510. This fee shall be collected at the same time and in the same manner as the registration fee.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-423__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to the permanent registration fee established in
AS 28.10.155
, a $2 fee is imposed on the owner of each permanently registered motor vehicle required to be inspected under an emission control program established in
AS 46.14.400
or 46.14.510. That fee shall be collected biennially.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-431">
            <num>28.10.431</num>
            <heading>Biennial motor vehicle registration tax.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-431__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>There is levied a motor vehicle registration tax within each municipality that elects, by passage of an appropriate ordinance, to come under this section. A municipality shall file a written notice of election with the department and may not rescind the notice for a subsequent fiscal year. The notice must be filed on or before January 1 of the year preceding the year election under this section is to become effective. If a municipality has, before October 15, 1978, levied a motor vehicle registration or ad valorem tax that has been repealed by a vote of the people at any regular or special municipal election, then the election provided for in this subsection is not effective until the ordinance passed by the local governing body has been approved by the people at the next regularly scheduled general or special municipal election.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-431__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The biennial tax is levied upon motor vehicles subject to the registration fee under
AS 28.10.411
and 28.10.421 and is based on the age of vehicles as determined by model year in the first year of the biennial period, according to the following schedule:
Tax According to Age of Vehicle Since Model Year:
1st2nd3rd4th5th6th7th8th or over
Motor Vehicle</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-431__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>motorcycle$ 17$ 15$ 13$ 10$ 7$ 5$ 4$ 4</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-431__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>vehicles specified
in
AS 28.10.421</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-431__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>vehicles specified
in
AS 28.10.421</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-431__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>vehicles specified
in
AS 28.10.421</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-431__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>vehicles specified
in
AS 28.10.421</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-431__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>vehicles specified
in
AS 28.10.421</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-431__subsec_b__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>vehicles specified
in
AS 28.10.421</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-431__subsec_b__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>vehicles eligible
for dealer
plates under
AS 28.10.421</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-431__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The registration tax shall be levied, collected, enforced, and otherwise administered in the same manner as provided for the registration fees in this chapter. Only one registration tax may be collected with respect to the same motor vehicle in the year for which the tax is paid.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-431__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a person has paid both the registration fee levied in
AS 28.10.411
and 28.10.421 and the registration tax levied in this section, and the department determines that the payor is entitled to a refund in whole or in part of the registration tax, the department shall make the refund to which the person is entitled. A refund may not be made unless application for a refund is filed with the department by December 31 of the year following the year for which the refund is claimed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-431__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall refund money collected under this section, less eight percent as collection costs, to a municipality for which the money was collected, as determined by (1) the address of residence of an individual required to pay the tax, or (2) the situs of the vehicle if the vehicle is not owned by an individual; the tax situs is the location at which the motor vehicle is usually, normally, or regularly kept or used during the registration period. For the first year in which the tax is levied within a municipality, the department may retain actual costs of collection of the tax within the municipality as determined by the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-431__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Money received by an organized borough under this section shall be allocated by the borough by ordinance for city, area outside city, and service area purposes within the borough.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-431__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Payment of the registration tax is in lieu of all local use taxes and ad valorem taxes on motor vehicles subject to the tax. A municipality which elects to come under the provisions of this section may not levy use or ad valorem taxes on motor vehicles subject to the registration tax during a fiscal year in which the election is in effect.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-431__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A vehicle owned by a former prisoner of war exempted from registration fees under
AS 28.10.421
(d)(11) is subject to a motor vehicle registration tax under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-431__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 28 ch 90 SLA 1991.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-431__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality that imposes a motor vehicle registration tax as described under (a) of this section may also, by passage of an appropriate ordinance, increase the scheduled amount of tax described under (b) or (l) of this section, establish a tax for a motor vehicle that is permanently registered under
AS 28.10.155
, or establish a tax for a trailer that is permanently registered under
AS 28.10.421
(j). A municipality that chooses to change the tax imposed under (b) or (l) of this section or establishes a tax for permanently registered motor vehicles or trailers shall file a written notice of the change with the department by January 1 of the year preceding the year in which the change in tax is to take effect. A municipality may not change the amount of the tax imposed under this section more than once every two years. The department may charge a municipality a one-time fee to cover the cost to the department of implementing a change under this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-431__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A vehicle registration application and renewal application for vehicles subject to a municipal vehicle registration tax shall itemize the total amount due in a manner that separately shows the amount of vehicle registration tax imposed by the municipality.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-431__subsec_l">
              <num>(l)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (b) of this section, an annual tax is levied upon vehicles specified in
AS 28.10.421</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-431__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and subject to the registration fee under
AS 28.10.411
and 28.10.421 if the owner elects to register the vehicle annually as allowed under
AS 28.10.108
(f). The tax is based on the age of the vehicle as determined by model year according to the following schedule:
Tax According to Age of Vehicle Since Model Year:
1st 2nd3rd4th5th6th7th8thor over
Motor Vehicle
5,000 pounds or less$ 66$ 55$ 44$ 33$ 22$ 17$ 11$ 8
5,001-12,000 pounds11088665544332211
12,001-18,000 pounds24020718516314111910797
18,001 pounds or over29525121818516114111997.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-441">
            <num>28.10.441</num>
            <heading>Schedule of other fees and charges.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.10.441.   Schedule of other fees and charges.
The following fees and charges are imposed by the department for the stated services that it provides:
(1) title fee, including transfer of title$15;
(2) lien filing fee$15;
(3) replacement of any registration plate, including a special request plate$5;
(4) duplicate of original certificate of title$15;
(5) duplicate of certificate of registration$2;
(6) temporary preregistration permit issued under
AS 28.10.031
none;
(7) special transport permit issued under
AS 28.10.151
$5;
(8) special permit for vehicle used for transport of a person with a disability issued under
AS 28.10.495
none.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-451">
            <num>28.10.451</num>
            <heading>Unlawful to violate provisions requiring registration and title.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.10.451.   Unlawful to violate provisions requiring registration and title.
A person may not wilfully attempt to defeat the provisions of this chapter or wilfully fail to title or register a vehicle as required by this chapter, or otherwise wilfully fail to comply with the requirements of this chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-461">
            <num>28.10.461</num>
            <heading>Driving vehicle without evidence of registration.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.10.461.   Driving vehicle without evidence of registration.
Except as otherwise expressly permitted in this chapter, a person may not drive or move, nor may an owner knowingly permit to be driven or moved, on a highway or vehicular way or area, a vehicle required to be registered under this chapter unless valid registration plates, decals, or permits for the current registration period are attached to and displayed on the vehicle in the manner required by this chapter, and unless a valid certificate of registration for the current registration period is carried, as required by this chapter, in the vehicle and is available for inspection by a peace officer or an authorized representative of the Department of Public Safety.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-471">
            <num>28.10.471</num>
            <heading>Driving vehicle when registration suspended or revoked or permit expired.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.10.471.   Driving vehicle when registration suspended or revoked or permit expired.
A person may not drive or move, nor may an owner knowingly permit to be driven or moved, on a highway or vehicular way or area, a vehicle for which the registration or permit has been suspended or revoked or has expired.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-481">
            <num>28.10.481</num>
            <heading>Improper use of evidence of registration or certificate of title.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.10.481.   Improper use of evidence of registration or certificate of title.
A person may not lend to another, or knowingly permit the use by another of, a certificate of registration or title, registration plate, decal, special plate, or permit issued under this chapter if the person to whom it is loaned or whose use is permitted is not entitled to its use, nor may a person display in or upon a vehicle a certificate of registration, registration plate, decal, special plate, or permit not issued for that vehicle or not otherwise lawfully used on that vehicle.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-491">
            <num>28.10.491</num>
            <heading>Felonies relating to title, registration, identification number, and removal and representation of vehicles.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-491__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon conviction, a person is guilty of a felony who</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-491__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>alters, forges, or counterfeits a certificate of title or registration, or a registration plate, decal, tab, or sticker of this or another jurisdiction;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-491__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>alters or forges an assignment of a certificate of title or an assignment or release of a security interest on a certificate of title of this or another jurisdiction or on a form the department prescribes;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-491__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has possession of or uses a certificate of title or registration, registration plate, decal, tab, or sticker of this or another jurisdiction knowing it to have been altered, forged, or counterfeited;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-491__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>wilfully removes or falsifies a vehicle identification number;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-491__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>wilfully conceals or misrepresents the identity of a vehicle or vehicle equipment;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-491__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>buys, receives, possesses, sells, or disposes of a vehicle or vehicle equipment, knowing that a vehicle identification number or equipment has been unlawfully removed or falsified;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-491__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>removes from the state a vehicle that is the subject of a security interest created under
AS 28.01
 28.35 or under
AS 45.01
 45.08,
AS 45.12
,
AS 45.14
, and
AS 45.29
without the written consent of the secured party, and with intent to defraud the secured party or the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-491__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>represents a motor vehicle or house trailer to be a new vehicle and who sells or procures the sale of that motor vehicle as a new vehicle without presenting a manufacturer's statement of origin; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-491__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>makes a false statement or otherwise conceals or withholds a material fact in an application for registration or certificate of title or falsely affirms with respect to a matter required to be sworn to, affirmed, or furnished under this chapter or regulations adopted under this chapter; except that a person who with criminal negligence as defined in
AS 11.81.900
, falsely certifies to the department the existence of a motor vehicle liability insurance policy under
AS 28.10.021</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-491__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person convicted of an offense under this section is punishable by imprisonment for not less than one year nor more than five years, or by a fine of not less than $500 nor more than $5,000, or by both.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-493">
            <num>28.10.493</num>
            <heading>Misdemeanors relating to transfers.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-493__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The owner of a vehicle who transfers a vehicle and fails to comply with the requirements of
AS 28.10.271
is guilty of a class B misdemeanor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-493__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A vehicle dealer who transfers a vehicle and fails to comply with the requirements of
AS 28.10.291
is guilty of a class B misdemeanor.
Article 8. General Provisions.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-495">
            <num>28.10.495</num>
            <heading>Parking permit for vehicle transporting a person with a disability.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-495__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon application by a person with a disability, or by an organization that transports persons with disabilities, the department or a person authorized by the department shall issue to the applicant, without charge, a special permit bearing the control number of the applicant. The permit issued under this section, when displayed in the front windshield of a parked or standing vehicle, shall provide for special consideration by the public with respect to the parking or standing in designated spaces of a vehicle that is being used for the transportation of a person with a disability.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-495__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person is not entitled to use the special permit provided for in (a) of this section except when providing transportation for a person with a disability. Upon the death of a person with a disability to whom a special permit has been issued, the special permit shall be returned to the department. If an organization to which a special permit has been issued ceases transporting persons with disabilities, or ceases operating, it shall return the special permit to the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-495__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Proof of disability, for the purpose of this section, shall be the same as that required for the purposes of
AS 28.10.181
(d).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-502">
            <num>28.10.502</num>
            <heading>Towing, transporting, and storage lien.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-502__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person engaged in the business of towing motor vehicles, who tows, transports, or stores a motor vehicle, has a possessory lien on the vehicle.  This lien attaches when the person acts under a contract with the owner or at the direction of a public officer acting lawfully or a person entitled to possession of the property upon which the motor vehicle is parked without consent. The lien remains in effect while the motor vehicle is in the possession of the person, and the vehicle may be sold, as provided in (c) of this section, to pay the charges for towing, transportation or storage.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-502__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A lien under this section is limited to towing and storage charges and associated mailing fees. Unless a vehicle has already been reclaimed by the owner, the person possessing the vehicle under this section shall notify the registered owner and primary lienholder, if any, of the towing, transporting, or storage of the vehicle, by certified letter, return receipt requested, mailed to the registered owner and primary lienholder, if any, within seven working days after the initial towing, transporting, or storage of the vehicle. The letter shall be sent to the addresses of record of the registered owner and primary lienholder, if any, on file with the department or the corresponding office in another jurisdiction in which the title to the motor vehicle and the lien on it are recorded. Storage charges cease to be part of the lien after 60 days unless the registered owner or primary lienholder, if any, has been given actual notice of the possessory lien within that time or unless the certified letter has been mailed within the time required in this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-502__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the motor vehicle remains unclaimed for a period of 30 days in the possession of the person who performed the towing, transportation or storage, it shall be sold on giving 20 days notice of the sale. The notice shall be delivered to the proper officer and personally served on the registered owner and all lienholders, if any, of the motor vehicle in the same manner as provided by law for service of summons.  If either of these persons cannot be located and served personally, notice of the sale shall be forwarded to the registered owner and all lienholders, if any, at their last known address by certified mail, return receipt requested.  This notice must contain a description of the motor vehicle, including its registration plate number and vehicle identification number, together with the time and place of sale, a statement of the amount due, and the name and address of the person to whom the charges are due.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-502__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The money realized from a sale made under this section shall be applied first to the payment of costs and expenses of the sale and secondly to the lawful charges of the person having a lien on the motor vehicle under this section. Remaining proceeds from the sale shall be retained by the department to be distributed to the registered and legal owner or lienholder entitled to the remaining proceeds. A purchaser in good faith of a titled motor vehicle sold under this section takes the motor vehicle free of any rights of prior lien.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-505">
            <num>28.10.505</num>
            <heading>Disclosure of personal information contained in motor vehicle records.</heading>
            <subsection eId="28-10-505__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding
AS 40.25.300
and except as provided in this section, the department may not disclose personal information contained in motor vehicle records maintained by the department under this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-505__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Personal information shall be disclosed for use in connection with matters of motor vehicle or driver safety or theft; motor vehicle emissions; motor vehicle product alterations, recalls, or advisories; performance monitoring of motor vehicles and dealers by motor vehicle manufacturers; and removal of nonowner records from the original owner records of motor vehicle manufacturers as required by federal law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-505__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Personal information may be disclosed if the requesting person demonstrates, in a form and manner the department prescribes, that the requesting person has obtained the written consent of the person who is the subject of the information.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-505__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Personal information may be disclosed by the department upon proof of the identity of the person requesting a record and representation by the requesting person that the use of the personal information is strictly limited to one or more of the following uses:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-505__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for use by a government agency, including a court or law enforcement agency, in carrying out its functions, or a private person or entity acting on behalf of a government agency in carrying out its functions;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-505__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for use in the normal course of business by a legitimate business or an agent, employee, or contractor of the business, but only
(A) to verify the accuracy of personal information submitted by an individual to the business or an agent, employee, or contractor of the business; and
(B) if the information submitted is not correct, to obtain the correct information, but only for the purposes of preventing fraud by pursuing legal remedies against, or recovering on a debt or security interest against, an individual;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-505__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for use in connection with a civil, criminal, administrative, or arbitration proceeding in a court or government agency or before a self-regulatory body, including service of process and the execution or enforcement of a judgment or court order;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-505__subsec_d__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for use in research activities, or in producing statistical reports, if the personal information is not published, redisclosed, or used to contact an individual;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-505__subsec_d__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for use by an insurer or insurance support organization, or by a self-insured entity, or an agent, employee, or contractor of an insurer, in connection with claims investigation activities, anti-fraud activities, rating, or underwriting;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-505__subsec_d__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for use in providing notice to the owners of towed or impounded vehicles;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-505__subsec_d__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for use by an employer or an agent or insurer of an employer to obtain or verify information relating to a holder of a commercial driver's license that is required under 49 U.S.C. 31101  31162 (Commercial Motor Vehicle Safety Act);</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-505__subsec_d__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for use in connection with the operation of private toll transportation facilities;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-505__subsec_d__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for use in connection with a legitimate business operating under a contract with the department;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-505__subsec_d__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for bulk distribution for surveys, marketing, or solicitations if the person who is the subject of the information has provided written consent to the release; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-505__subsec_d__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for any other purpose specifically authorized by law that is related to the operation of a motor vehicle or related to public safety.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-505__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Personal information contained in an individual record may be disclosed, without regard to the intended use of the personal information, if the person who is the subject of the information has provided written consent to the release.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="28-10-505__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-505__subsec_f__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>disclose means to engage in a practice or conduct that makes available or makes known personal information contained in records of the department about a person to another person, organization, or entity by any means of communication;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-505__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>individual record means a record containing personal information about a designated person who is the subject of the record, as identified in a request for information;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="28-10-505__subsec_f__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>personal information means information that identifies a person, including a name, address, telephone number, and medical or disability information, but does not include information on vehicular accidents, driving- or equipment-related violations, driver's license or registration status, or a zip code.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_28-10-661">
            <num>28.10.661</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 28.10.661.   Definitions.
In this chapter and in regulations adopted under this chapter, unless the context requires otherwise,
(1) dealer means a person engaged in the business of buying, selling, or exchanging vehicles of a type required to be registered under this chapter and who maintains a place of business or by word of mouth, advertising, or in any other manner represents to be in the business of buying, selling, or exchanging vehicles;
(2) manufactured home has the meaning given in
AS 45.29.102
;
(3) vehicle includes mobile homes for the purposes of provisions relating to certificates of title; in this paragraph, mobile home means a manufactured home.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>