<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-34/chapter-35"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-34/chapter-35"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="34.35"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-34/chapter-35/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-34/chapter-35/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-34/chapter-35/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-34/chapter-35/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_34">
        <num>34</num>
        <heading>Property</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_34__chp_35">
          <num>35</num>
          <heading>Liens</heading>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-005">
            <num>34.35.005</num>
            <heading>Action for foreclosure.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-005__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When an action is required to enforce a lien provided for in this chapter and the action falls within the monetary jurisdiction of the district court, the action shall be started in the district court in the judicial district in which venue lies.  An action that exceeds the monetary jurisdiction of the district court shall be started in the superior court in the judicial district in which venue lies. The procedure, except as otherwise provided in this chapter, is the same as in the trial of an action to secure property to hold it for the satisfaction of a lien against it.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-005__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In an action to enforce a lien, the court shall allow as part of the costs all money paid for drawing the lien and for filing and recording the lien claim, and a reasonable attorney fee for the foreclosure of the lien.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-005__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An action to enforce a lien created by
AS 34.35.005
 34.35.425 has preference upon the calendar of civil actions before the court and shall be tried without unnecessary delay.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-010">
            <num>34.35.010</num>
            <heading>Joinder of claimants in lien statement.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.010.   Joinder of claimants in lien statement.
Any number of persons who claim liens under
AS 34.35.005
 34.35.425 against the same property may join in one statement of lien.  The consolidated statement of lien shall be verified by the oath of one or more of the claimants having knowledge of the facts.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-015">
            <num>34.35.015</num>
            <heading>Joinder in foreclosure suit.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.015.   Joinder in foreclosure suit.
Any number of persons who claim liens against the same property may join in the same action, and when separate actions are commenced the court may consolidate them.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-020">
            <num>34.35.020</num>
            <heading>Sufficiency in lien notice or pleadings.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-020__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A mistake in formality or lack of statement in the lien notice or the pleadings is not ground for dismissal or unnecessary delay in an action to foreclose a lien.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-020__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Substantial compliance with the law relating to the contents of the lien notice is considered sufficient, if the notice satisfactorily shows the name of the claimant, the amount of the demand, the time of the employment, the property sought to be charged with the lien sufficient for identification, and the name of the owner or reputed owner of the property.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-020__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The inclusion of nonlienable items in the amount of the claimant's demand or error in the terms and conditions of the contract of employment, if there is a contract of employment, or other error in the lien notice, made in good faith, is not considered material, unless the error affects the substantial rights of the adverse party, acquired in good faith without notice.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-020__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The lien notice and pleadings may be amended at any time before judgment.  If a material statement or averment is omitted or misstated, this is ground for a reasonable delay or continuance to enable opposing parties to meet the amendment, and a nonsuit or dismissal may not be entertained in the action except upon the merits of the cause.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-025">
            <num>34.35.025</num>
            <heading>Parties to foreclosure.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.025.   Parties to foreclosure.
In an action to foreclose a lien created by
AS 34.35.005
 34.35.425, all persons personally liable and all lien holders whose claims have been recorded, and all other persons interested in the matter in controversy or the property sought to be charged with the lien may be made parties.  Persons who are not parties are not bound by the proceedings.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-030">
            <num>34.35.030</num>
            <heading>Lien claim against different properties.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.030.   Lien claim against different properties.
If a lien claim is filed for the same labor against two separate kinds of property owned or claimed by different persons, the court shall determine the liability of each kind of property and designate which shall be sold first to discharge the amount of the lien claim.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-035">
            <num>34.35.035</num>
            <heading>Several judgment for each claimant.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.035.   Several judgment for each claimant.
In an action to enforce a lien judgment shall be given in favor of each person having a lien for the amount due the person, and the court shall order property subject to the lien to be sold by the peace officer in the same manner that property is sold on execution, or in any manner that the court considers proper.  The proceeds of the sale shall be apportioned to the payment of each judgment pro rata, if the amount is insufficient to pay them in full.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-045">
            <num>34.35.045</num>
            <heading>Lienor's action on contract.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.045.   Lienor's action on contract.
Except as otherwise expressly provided, nothing in
AS 34.35.005
 34.35.425 may be construed to prevent a lienor under a contract from maintaining an action as if the lienor has no lien for the security of the debt and the bringing of this action does not prejudice rights under
AS 34.35.005
 34.35.425.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-050">
            <num>34.35.050</num>
            <heading>Lien for labor or materials furnished.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.050.   Lien for labor or materials furnished.
A person has a lien, only to the extent provided under this chapter, to secure the payment of the contract price if the person
(1) performs labor upon real property at the request of the owner or the agent of the owner for the construction, alteration, or repair of a building or improvement;
(2) is a trustee of an employee benefit trust for the benefit of individuals performing labor on the building or improvement and has a direct contract with the owner or the agent of the owner for direct payments into the trust;
(3) furnishes materials that are delivered to real property under a contract with the owner or the agent of the owner that are incorporated in the construction, alteration, or repair of a building or improvement;
(4) furnishes equipment that is delivered to and used upon real property under a contract with the owner or the agent of the owner for the construction, alteration, or repair of a building or improvement;
(5) performs services under a contract with the owner or the agent of the owner in connection with the preparation of plans, surveys, or architectural or engineering plans or drawings for the construction, alteration, or repair of a building or improvement, whether or not actually implemented on that property; or
(6) is a general contractor.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-055">
            <num>34.35.055</num>
            <heading>Land subject to lien.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-055__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The land upon which a building or other improvement described in
AS 34.35.050
is constructed, together with a convenient space about the building or other improvement or so much as is required for the convenient use and occupation of it (to be determined by the judgment of the court at the time of the foreclosure of the lien), and the mine on which the work is performed or for which the material is furnished is also subject to the lien created by
AS 34.35.050
  34.35.120 if, at the time the work is started or the materials for the building or other improvements are first furnished, the land belongs to the person who causes the building or other improvement to be constructed, altered, or repaired.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-055__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the person owns less than a fee simple estate in the land, then only the interest of the person in it is subject to the lien.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-055__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the interest is a leasehold interest, and the holder forfeits the rights of the holder to it, the purchaser of the building or improvement and leasehold term, or so much of it as remains unexpired at a sale under
AS 34.35.050
 34.35.120 is considered to be the assignee of the leasehold term, and may pay the lessor all arrears of rent or other money and costs due under the lease.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-055__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the lessor regains possession of the land and property, or obtains judgment for the possession of it before the commencement of the construction, alteration, or repair of the building or other improvement, the purchaser may only remove the building or other improvement within 30 days after the purchase, and the owner of the land shall receive the rent due payable out of the proceeds of the sale, according to the terms of the lease, down to the time of the removal.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-060">
            <num>34.35.060</num>
            <heading>Priorities.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-060__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (c) of this section, an encumbrance which is properly recorded shall be preferred to a lien created under
AS 34.35.050
  34.35.120 unless the claim of lien under
AS 34.35.070
or notice of right to lien under
AS 34.35.064
has been recorded before the encumbrance. The preference granted for a prior mortgage or deed of trust under this section applies without regard to when the sums are disbursed or whether the disbursements are required under the terms of a loan agreement.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-060__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 19 ch 175 SLA 1978.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-060__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A lien created by
AS 34.35.050
  34.35.120 in favor of an individual actually performing labor upon a building or other improvement in its original construction or of a trustee of an employee benefit trust for those individuals is preferred to a prior encumbrance upon the land on which the building or other improvement is constructed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-060__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In enforcing the lien, the building or other improvement may be sold separately from the land.  When sold separately, the purchaser may remove the building or other improvement within a reasonable time after the sale, not to exceed 30 days, upon the payment to the owner of the land of a reasonable rent for its use from the date of its purchase to the time of removal. If removal is prevented by legal proceedings, the 30 days does not begin to run until the final determination of the proceedings in the court of first resort, or in the appellate court if appeal is taken.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-062">
            <num>34.35.062</num>
            <heading>Construction financing.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-062__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A claimant to whom payment for the labor, material, service, or equipment furnished for a project is past due may give the lender a stop-lending notice.  The claimant shall at the same time give a copy of the notice to the owner and to each prime contractor with whom or through whom the claimant or the claimant's debtor has contracted.  A stop-lending notice must</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-062__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>instruct the lender to stop disbursing, advancing, or otherwise providing construction financing for the project;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-062__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>be verified by the claimant;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-062__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>state the claimant's name, address, and telephone number;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-062__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>describe the labor, material, service, or equipment furnished by the claimant and state the name of the person to whom furnished;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-062__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>describe the real property improved by the labor, material, service, or equipment and state the name of the person the claimant believes to be the owner of the real property;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-062__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>state the amount due and unpaid to the claimant for the labor, material, service, or equipment.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-062__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A stop-lending notice is binding upon a lender from the time the lender has received it and had a reasonable opportunity to act upon it until it expires or is revoked.  A notice expires on the 91st day after it is received by the lender unless the claimant has commenced an action on the claim that is the subject of the notice before that day and the lender has received written notification of the action.  A stop-lending notice may be revoked at any time in writing signed by the claimant.  Expiration or revocation of a notice extinguishes the liability of the lender to the claimant under (c) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-062__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A lender who disburses, advances, or otherwise provides construction financing for a project after it is the subject of a stop-lending notice is liable to the claimant in an amount equal to the lowest of the following amounts:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-062__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the amount of construction financing disbursed, advanced, or otherwise provided by the lender after receipt of the claimant's stop-lending notice; if there are two or more stop-lending notices when the disbursement occurs, the lender's liability to each claimant is based on the claimant's ranking under
AS 34.35.112
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-062__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the amount owed to the claimant, including interest, costs, and attorney's fees, for labor, material, service, or equipment furnished for the project by the claimant as established by a written agreement signed on or after the date of the stop-lending notice by the claimant, the owner and the prime contractor with whom or through whom the claimant or the claimant's debtor has contracted or by a final judgment in an action in which the owner, the claimant, and the claimant's debtor are named and, if necessary, served parties;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-062__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>150 percent of the amount stated in the stop-lending notice.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-062__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Within 10 days after receiving the written agreement or a certified copy of the judgment under (c)(2) of this section establishing the amount owed to a claimant from whom it has a binding stop-lending notice, a lender shall send to the claimant a verified statement showing, by date and amount, all construction financing provided by the lender for the project.  Except as provided in (e) of this section, the lender shall include with the statement payment in the amount of the lender's liability to the claimant under (c) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-062__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If there are two or more claimants to whom a lender is or may be liable under (c) of this section and the lender is uncertain as to the amount of its liability or possible liability to each, the lender may bring an action to require the claimants to interplead their claims.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-062__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A draw against construction financing may be made only after certification of job progress is delivered to the lender by the owner.  The form of the certification may be prescribed by the lender and must include</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-062__subsec_f__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a statement of the progress of the project, including the percentage of completion of the project;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-062__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name, address, and telephone number of each prime contractor who has furnished labor, material, service, or equipment for the project;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-062__subsec_f__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the amount owed by the owner to each listed prime contractor; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-062__subsec_f__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the portion of the draw that the owner will pay to each listed prime contractor.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-062__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The owner shall use each draw as indicated in the certificates given by the owner to the lender under (f) of this section. The lender may not be required to verify the information in a certificate and is not liable for an error in a certificate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-062__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An owner who intentionally fails to apply construction financing proceeds as indicated by the certificate required under (f) of this section is guilty of a class A misdemeanor. The penalty provided under this subsection does not replace any other penalty that may be provided for by law for the same conduct.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-062__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Within 10 days after being requested, a lender shall provide a person who has given the lender a stop-lending notice with a copy of</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-062__subsec_i__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>each certificate received by the lender under (f) of this section; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-062__subsec_i__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a verified certificate stating the amount of construction financing proceeds committed by the lender for the project that have not been disbursed by the lender.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-062__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The lender may not provide construction financing proceeds for payment of indebtedness of the owner that is not incurred for the project.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-064">
            <num>34.35.064</num>
            <heading>Notice of right to lien.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-064__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before furnishing labor, material, service, or equipment for a project, a person may give a notice of right to lien to the owner or owner's agent. If the notice is given in accordance with this section, the owner has the burden of proof to show that the owner did not know of or consent to the furnishing of the labor, material, service, or equipment by the claimant in an action to foreclose the claimant's lien on the property under
AS 34.35.050
 34.35.120.  Otherwise the claimant has the burden of proof to show that the owner knew of and consented to the furnishing of the labor, material, service, or equipment.  The notice of right to lien must be in writing, state that it is a notice of a right to assert a lien against real property for labor, materials, services, or equipment furnished in connection with a project, and contain</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-064__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a legal description sufficient for identification of the real property;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-064__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name of the owner;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-064__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name and address of the claimant;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-064__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name and address of the person with whom the claimant contracted;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-064__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a general description of the labor, materials, services, or equipment provided or to be provided;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-064__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a statement that the claimant may be entitled to record a claim of lien; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-064__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the following statement in type no smaller than that used in providing the information required by (1)  (6) of this subsection:
WARNING:  Unless provision is made for payment of sums that may be due to the undersigned, your above property may be subject to foreclosure to satisfy those sums even though you may pay a prime contractor or other person for the labor, material, service, or equipment furnished by the undersigned.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-064__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon request from an owner, lender, or prime contractor, a claimant who has given a notice of right to lien under this section shall disclose to the requester within five days the most recent accounting of the amount due and unpaid to that claimant under the terms of the contract and a description of labor, materials, services, or equipment that the claimant reasonably anticipates furnishing.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-065">
            <num>34.35.065</num>
            <heading>Notice of nonresponsibility.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-065__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A building or improvement mentioned in
AS 34.35.050
constructed with the knowledge of the owner of the land or the person having or claiming an interest in the land is considered to be constructed at the instance of the owner or person having or claiming the interest.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-065__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The interest owned or claimed is subject to a lien recorded under
AS 34.35.050
  34.35.120, unless</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-065__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the owner or person having or claiming an interest in the land gives notice within three days after the owner or other person obtains knowledge of the construction, alteration, or repair that the owner or other person will not be responsible for it, by posting a notice to that effect in writing in some conspicuous place upon the land or upon the building or other improvement located on the land;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-065__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the notice is signed by the owner or person having or claiming an interest in the land in the presence of two attesting witnesses or acknowledged by the owner or other person before a notary public;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-065__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the posting of notice is attested to by a witness; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-065__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an attested or notarized copy of the notice is recorded with the recorder of the recording district in which the land, building, or other improvement is located within three days after the posting of the notice.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-067">
            <num>34.35.067</num>
            <heading>Recording notice of right to lien.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.067.   Recording notice of right to lien.
A notice of right to lien may be recorded by a claimant at any time after the claimant enters into a contract for or first furnishes labor, material, service, or equipment in connection with a project.  The notice shall be recorded in the same manner as specified for the recording of a claim of lien under
AS 34.35.070
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-068">
            <num>34.35.068</num>
            <heading>Time periods for claiming liens.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-068__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a notice of completion is not recorded by the owner as provided in
AS 34.35.071
, a claim of lien shall be recorded not later than 120 days after the claimant</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-068__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>completes the construction contract; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-068__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>ceases to furnish labor, material, services, or equipment for the construction, alteration, or repair of the owner's property.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-068__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a notice of completion is recorded by the owner as provided in
AS 34.35.071
,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-068__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the following shall record a claim of lien or a notice of right to lien not later than 15 days after the notice of completion is recorded:
(A) a claimant who has received advance notification of the date that the notice of completion is recorded as provided in
AS 34.35.071</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-068__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the following shall record a claim of lien not later than the time specified in (a) of this section:
(A) a claimant who records a notice of right to lien before or within the period specified in (1) of this subsection;
(B) a claimant who has given a notice of right to lien but who has not received advance notice of the date that the notice of completion is recorded by the owner as provided in
AS 34.35.071</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-068__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A claim of lien is enforceable only if recorded by a claimant within the time specified in (a) or (b) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-070">
            <num>34.35.070</num>
            <heading>Claim of lien.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-070__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A claimant may record a claim of lien after entering into a contract for a project. A claim of lien may not be recorded later than the time specified under
AS 34.35.068
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-070__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 9 ch 61 SLA 1979.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-070__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The lien shall be verified by the oath of the claimant or another person having knowledge of the facts and state</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-070__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the real property subject to the lien, with a legal description sufficient for identification;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-070__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name of the owner;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-070__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name and address of the claimant;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-070__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name and address of the person with whom the claimant contracted;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-070__subsec_c__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a general description of the labor, materials, services, or equipment furnished for the construction, alteration, or repair, and the contract price of the labor, materials, services, or equipment;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-070__subsec_c__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the amount due to the claimant for the labor, materials, services, or equipment; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-070__subsec_c__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the date the last labor, materials, services, or equipment were furnished.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-070__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 19 ch 175 SLA 1978.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-070__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 19 ch 175 SLA 1978.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-070__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A violation of the provisions of this section places the violator in the position of guarantor regarding another person who suffers damages that are proximately caused by the violation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-071">
            <num>34.35.071</num>
            <heading>Notice of completion.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-071__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The owner of real property that may be subject to a lien under
AS 34.35.050
 34.35.120 may announce the date of completion of the project by</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-071__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>recording a notice of completion after completion of the project in the office of the recorder of the district in which the real property is situated; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-071__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>giving notice at least five days before the recording of the notice of completion to all claimants who have given a notice of right to lien or a stop-lending notice to the owner and the lender prior to 10 days before recording a notice of completion; the notice must include a copy of the notice of completion and a statement advising claimants that a notice of completion will be recorded not earlier than five days after the date of the notice.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-071__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The notice of completion shall be signed and verified by the owner, and must state</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-071__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the date of completion of the building or other improvement;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-071__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name and address of the owner;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-071__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the nature of the interest or estate of the owner;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-071__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the legal description of the property sufficient for identification; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-071__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name of the general contractor.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-071__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 9 ch 61 SLA 1979.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-071__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A notice of completion is not effective if recorded before completion.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-071__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Labor, materials, services, or equipment furnished after a notice of completion is recorded to satisfy warranty obligations or to remedy defective or unsatisfactory construction, alterations, or repairs for which no additional consideration is owed to the person furnishing the additional labor, materials, services, or equipment does not result in lien liability under
AS 34.35.050
  34.35.120.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-071__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After recording a common interest community declaration under
AS 34.08
, an owner may record a notice of completion under this section as to each unit after completion of the original construction of each unit of the common interest community.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-072">
            <num>34.35.072</num>
            <heading>Bond.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.072.   Bond.
If the owner of the property sought to be charged with a claim of lien under
AS 34.35.050
  34.35.120, or a prime contractor or subcontractor disputes the correctness or validity of the claim of lien brought under
AS 34.35.050
 34.35.120, the owner or contractor may record either before or after the commencement of an action to enforce the claim of lien, in the office of the recorder in which district the claim of lien was recorded, a bond executed by a person authorized to issue surety bonds in this state under
AS 21
, a financial institution licensed under
AS 06
, or a national bank authorized under the federal banking laws, in the penal sum equal to one and one-half times the amount of the claim of lien, which bond shall guarantee the payment of the sum that the lien claimant has claimed, together with the lien claimant's reasonable cost of suit in the action, if the claimant recovers on the claim of lien.  If the owner records a bond under this section, the property described in the bond is freed from the effect of a claim of lien under
AS 34.35.050
  34.35.120 and an action brought to foreclose the claim of lien.  The principal on the bond may be the owner of the property, the prime contractor, or a subcontractor who is affected by the claim of lien.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-074">
            <num>34.35.074</num>
            <heading>Civil suits.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-074__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person injured by a violation of
AS 34.35.050
 34.35.120 may bring a civil action</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-074__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>except as provided in
AS 34.35.062</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-074__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to enjoin the violation, and if the person prevails, the person shall be awarded costs, including reasonable attorney fees.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-074__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A claimant who gives a stop-lending notice or has a claim of lien recorded under
AS 34.35.075
and who fails to promptly revoke the stop-lending notice or remove the claim of lien from the record upon receiving payment in full on the claim or discovering that the stop-lending notice or claim of lien is in error, unjust, premature, or excessive is liable for actual and consequential damages caused by giving the stop-lending notice or improperly recorded claim of lien plus costs, including reasonable attorney fees.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-075">
            <num>34.35.075</num>
            <heading>Record and index of claim.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.075.   Record and index of claim.
The recorder shall record the claim in a book kept for that purpose.  The records shall be indexed as deeds and other conveyances are required by law to be indexed.  The recorder is entitled to the same fees allowed by law for recording deeds and other instruments.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-080">
            <num>34.35.080</num>
            <heading>Duration of lien.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-080__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A lien provided for in
AS 34.35.050
 34.35.120 does not bind real property for more than six months after the claim of lien is recorded, unless an action is commenced in the proper court to enforce the lien within</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-080__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>that time; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-080__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>six months after recording of an extension notice in the same recording office within the original six-month period showing the recording date and the book and page or instrument number or serial number of the initial claim of lien, and the balance owing.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-080__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 18 ch 102 SLA 1986.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-080__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A lien whose duration is extended by commencement of an action under (a) of this section is void as against a person who, after the commencement of the action and without knowledge or actual notice of its pendency, acquires an interest in the subject property in good faith for valuable consideration, unless a notice of the pendency of the action has been duly filed for record before the time the person's conveyance is duly filed for record.  Notice of the pendency of the action must conform to the requirements of
AS 09.45.940
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-085">
            <num>34.35.085</num>
            <heading>Lien for improving lot or street.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.085.   Lien for improving lot or street.
A person who, at the request of the owner of a lot in the state, grades, fills in, or improves the lot or the street in front of or adjoining the lot has a lien upon the lot for work done and materials furnished.  The provisions of
AS 34.35.050
 34.35.120 for securing and enforcing the mechanic's lien apply to the lien provided by this section.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-090">
            <num>34.35.090</num>
            <heading>Payment to contractor.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.090.   Payment to contractor.
A payment by the owner of a building or structure to a prime contractor or subcontractor, made before 120 days from the completion of the building, is not valid to defeat or discharge a lien created by
AS 34.35.050
 34.35.120 in favor of other claimants, unless the payment is distributed among the other claimants. If a payment is distributed in part only, then the payment is valid only to the extent it is distributed.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-095">
            <num>34.35.095</num>
            <heading>Amount of lien.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-095__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (c) of this section, a claimant may recover upon a lien recorded by the claimant only the amount due to the claimant according to the terms of the contract, after deducting all claims of other persons claiming through the claimant for work done and materials furnished.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-095__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 9 ch 61 SLA 1979.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-095__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An individual may recover upon a lien recorded by the individual only the amount due according to the terms of the employment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-100">
            <num>34.35.100</num>
            <heading>Action against contractor on lien.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-100__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Where a lien is recorded under
AS 34.35.050
 34.35.120 for work done or materials furnished to a prime contractor, the prime contractor shall defend an action at the expense of the prime contractor, and during the pendency of the action the owner may withhold from the prime contractor the amount of money for which the lien is recorded.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-100__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If judgment is given against the owner or the property of the owner upon the liens, the owner may deduct from the amount due or to become due by the owner to the prime contractor the amount of the judgment and costs.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-100__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the amount of the judgment and costs exceeds the amount due by the owner to the prime contractor, or if the owner settles with that contractor in full, the owner may recover back from the prime contractor an amount paid by the owner in excess of the contract price, and for which the prime contractor was originally liable.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-105">
            <num>34.35.105</num>
            <heading>Materials not subject to process.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.105.   Materials not subject to process.
When a mechanic, artisan, machinist, builder, lumber merchant, contractor, laborer, or other person furnishes or procures materials for use in the construction, alteration, or repair of a building or other improvement, the materials are not subject to attachment, execution, or other legal process to enforce a debt due by the purchaser of the materials except a debt due for the purchase money thereof, so long as the materials have been or are about to be applied in good faith to the construction, alteration, or repair of the building or other improvement.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-110">
            <num>34.35.110</num>
            <heading>Actions to enforce liens.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-110__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An action to enforce a lien created by
AS 34.35.050
 34.35.120 shall be brought in the superior court.  The pleadings, process, practice, and procedure are the same as in other cases.  Each claimant is entitled to execution for the balance due after distribution. The clerk of the superior court, upon demand, shall issue the execution after the return of the officer making the execution showing the balance due.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-110__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In an action under
AS 34.35.050
  34.35.120 the court shall, upon entering judgment for the plaintiff, allow as a part of the costs all money paid for the filing and recording of the lien and a reasonable amount as attorney fees.  An action to enforce a lien created by
AS 34.35.050
 34.35.120 has preference upon the calendar of civil actions of the court and shall be tried without unnecessary delay.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-110__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In an action to enforce a lien created by
AS 34.35.050
 34.35.120 all persons personally liable and all lienholders whose claims have been filed for record under
AS 34.35.070
shall be made parties; all other persons interested in the matter in controversy or in the property sought to be charged with the lien may be made parties. However, those persons who are not made parties are not bound by the proceedings.  The proceedings upon the foreclosure of a lien created by
AS 34.35.050
 34.35.120 shall, as nearly as possible, conform to the proceedings of a foreclosure of a mortgage lien upon real property.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-112">
            <num>34.35.112</num>
            <heading>Payment of claimant's liens.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-112__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If more than one lien created under
AS 34.35.050
  34.35.120 is claimed against property, the court in its judgment shall declare the rank of each lien or class of liens in the following order:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-112__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>all persons other than prime contractors or subcontractors with lien rights under
AS 34.35.050
(1);</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-112__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the trustees of employment benefit trusts for persons described in (1) of this subsection;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-112__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>all materialmen and subcontractors;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-112__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>persons described in
AS 34.35.050</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-112__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>and prime contractors, other than the general contractor;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-112__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the general contractor.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-112__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of
AS 34.35.050
  34.35.120, if the proceeds of the foreclosure sale of the property are insufficient to pay the lien claims of all persons who have recorded claims of lien, the</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-112__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>liens of all individuals with lien rights under
AS 34.35.050</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-112__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall first be paid in full, or pro rata if the proceeds are insufficient to pay them in full;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-112__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>liens of trustees of employment benefit trusts for persons described in (1) of this subsection shall be paid in full or pro rata if the proceeds are insufficient to pay them in full;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-112__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>liens of materialmen and subcontractors shall be paid in full or pro rata if the proceeds are insufficient to pay them in full;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-112__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>liens of persons described in
AS 34.35.050</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-112__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>and prime contractors other than the general contractor, shall be paid in full or pro rata if the remainder is insufficient to pay them in full; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-112__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>lien of the general contractor shall be paid out of the balance.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-112__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of
AS 34.35.050
 34.35.120, if the proceeds of the foreclosure sale of the property are sufficient to pay the lien claims of all persons who have recorded claims of lien, the balance shall be paid to the person who owned the property before the foreclosure sale.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-114">
            <num>34.35.114</num>
            <heading>Obligation of claimant and lender to provide information.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-114__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A prime contractor, on request, shall provide the following information within five days to any person entitled to claim a lien through the prime contractor:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-114__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a description of the real property being improved sufficient to identify the property;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-114__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name and address of the owner with whom the prime contractor contracted;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-114__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name and address of the lender providing construction financing; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-114__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>whether there is a payment bond and, if so, the name of the surety.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-114__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>At the request of any person who may claim a lien through a claimant other than a prime contractor, the claimant shall provide, within five days, the name of the person who contracted for the furnishing by the claimant of the labor, materials, services, or equipment from which a lien claim may arise.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-114__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who receives a stop-lending notice or notice of right to lien identifying a project for which the person is not the lender shall notify the claimant in writing within 10 days after receipt of the notice that the person is not the lender.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-114__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A claimant shall, within 10 days after receipt of a request, provide an owner or lender to whom the claimant has given a stop-lending notice or notice of right to lien a written statement of the amount due to the claimant and unpaid.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-114__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 18 ch 102 SLA 1986.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-115">
            <num>34.35.115</num>
            <heading>Persons considered agent of owner.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.115.   Persons considered agent of owner.
Every contractor, subcontractor, architect, builder, or other person having charge of the construction, alteration, or repair, in whole or in part, of a building or other improvement as provided in
AS 34.35.050
and 34.35.085, is considered to be the agent of the owner for the purposes of
AS 34.35.050
  34.35.120.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-117">
            <num>34.35.117</num>
            <heading>Waiver of lien rights.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-117__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided under (b) of this section, a written waiver of lien or stop-lending notice of rights created under
AS 34.35.050
 34.35.120 signed by a claimant requires no consideration and is valid and binding. A waiver permitted under this section may not relate to labor, materials, services, or equipment furnished after the date the waiver is signed by the claimant.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-117__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An individual described in
AS 34.35.120</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-117__subsec_b__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>may not waive right to claim a lien under
AS 34.35.050
 34.35.120.  A waiver that purports to waive the lien rights of that individual or class of individuals is void.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-119">
            <num>34.35.119</num>
            <heading>Waiver of liens on unsold common interest community units.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-119__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A lien created under
AS 34.35.050
 34.35.120 arising out of original construction that becomes subject to
AS 34.07
or
AS 34.08
before the first sale of a unit within a common interest community after commencement of construction shall be subject to the provisions of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-119__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subject to (c) of this section, a claimant who claims a lien against an entire common interest community shall release that portion of the lien claim that relates to a particular unit within a common interest community selected by the owner of the unsold common interest community units after the claimant receives a partial payment of the lien claim that is equal to 115 percent of the amount determined</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-119__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if the common interest community has been established under
AS 34.07
by
(A) dividing the surface area of the common areas and facilities attendant to the common interest community unit by the surface area of all common areas and facilities of the common interest community building; and
(B) multiplying the result obtained in (A) of this paragraph by the total amount of the claimant's lien claim;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-119__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>by the allocated interest in the common expenses if the common interest community has been established under
AS 34.08
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-119__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A lien claimant is not required to waive a portion of the lien claim under this section unless the amount of indebtedness secured by a prior encumbrance against the common interest community building held by a construction lender is also reduced by an amount calculated in the same manner as provided in (b) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-120">
            <num>34.35.120</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.120.   Definitions.
In
AS 34.35.050
  34.35.120,
(1) building or other improvement, includes a wharf, bridge, ditch, flume, tunnel, fence, well, land clearing, machinery, aqueduct to create hydraulic power, or for mining or other purposes, and all other structures and superstructures;
(2) completion means the cessation of the performance of labor or services or the furnishing of material or equipment on the building or other improvement to be constructed, altered, or repaired and includes, but is not limited to, the following:
(A) the occupation or use by the owner or an agent of the owner of the building or other improvement constructed, altered, or repaired accompanied by cessation of the furnishing of labor, services, material, or equipment on the building or improvement;
(B) the acceptance by the owner or an agent of the owner of the construction, alteration, or repair after labor, service, material, or equipment is furnished; or
(C) the issuance of a certificate of occupancy for a building by a municipality empowered to issue that certificate accompanied by cessation of the furnishing of labor, services, material, or equipment on the building or improvement;
(3) construction, alteration, or repair, includes partial construction, and all repairs done in and upon a building or other improvement;
(4) construction financing means money loaned or other credit extended to an owner secured by an encumbrance on real property to finance a project on that real property;
(5) contract price means the amount agreed upon by the contracting parties for furnishing services, labor, materials, or equipment covered by the contract, increased or diminished by the price of change orders, extras, or amounts attributable to altered specifications; if no price is agreed upon by the contracting parties, contract price means the reasonable value of all services, labor, materials, or equipment covered by the contract;
(6) draws means periodic disbursements of construction financing by a lender;
(7) encumbrance means a mortgage, deed of trust, or lien arising other than under
AS 34.35.050
  34.35.120;
(8) general contractor means a person who is a prime contractor and who has the responsibility for supervising all other contractors furnishing labor, materials, services, or equipment in connection with the construction, alteration, or repair of a building or other improvement;
(9) give notice means to mail a notice required under
AS 34.35.050
  34.35.120 by first-class mail and by using a form of mail requiring a signed receipt, or to deliver the notice and obtain a receipt signed by the person to whom it is directed or an agent of that person; a notice is effective when given or delivered to
(A) a lender at the address designated in the encumbrance securing that lender;
(B) an owner at the last known address of the owner;
(C) a prime contractor at the last known address of the prime contractor;
(D) a potential lien claimant at the address specified in a stop-lending notice or notice of right to lien or claim of lien;
(10) individual means a natural person who actually performs labor upon a building or other improvement as an employee of the owner or any contractor furnishing labor, materials, services, or equipment for the construction, alteration, or repair of a building or other improvement;
(11) lender means any person providing construction financing;
(12) materialman means a person who furnishes materials used in the construction, alteration, or repair of the owner's real property;
(13) owner means a person who owns real property or a possessory interest in real property and who enters into a contract, express or implied, for a project on that property;
(14) potential lien claimant or claimant means any person entitled to assert lien rights under
AS 34.35.050
  34.35.120;
(15) prime contractor means a person who enters into a contract directly with an owner to furnish labor, materials, services, or equipment for the construction, alteration, or repair of a building or other improvement on the owner's real property;
(16) project means construction, alteration, or repair of an improvement on real property or work done to enhance the real property itself;
(17) subcontractor means a person who enters into a contract with a prime contractor to furnish labor, services, or equipment for the construction, alteration, or repair of a building or other improvement on the owner's real property and does not include a materialman.
Article 3. Mines and Wells.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-125">
            <num>34.35.125</num>
            <heading>Liens on mines and oil wells.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.125.   Liens on mines and oil wells.
A person who, at the instance of the owner, performs work in, on, or about a mine, or mining claim, oil, gas, or other well, in opening up, developing, sinking, drilling, drifting, stoping, mucking, stripping, shoveling, mining, hoisting, firing, cooking, teaming, or performs any other class or kind of work necessary or convenient to the development, operation, working, or mining of the claim or well; or who performs work tending to or assisting in the development, extraction, separation, or reduction to a commercial value of the minerals; or who performs work on a water right, ditch, flume, pipe line, tramway, tram, road, or trail, used in connection with the opening up, or to facilitate the opening up, operation, or development of the claim or well, or the extraction of the minerals, has a lien on the mine or mining claim, oil, gas, or other claim or well as security for the payment of the work.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-130">
            <num>34.35.130</num>
            <heading>Lien on mill or machine.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.130.   Lien on mill or machine.
A person who, at the instance of the owner, performs work or labor on, in, or about a mill or machine, either in the alteration or repair of it, or in the operation or working of it, while the mill or machine is used in or about a mine, or mining claim, oil, gas, or other claim or well, as a means of opening up, developing, or mining, or as a means of separating, extracting, or reducing minerals to commercial value, has a lien on the mill or machine, to secure the payment of the amount due for the work.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-135">
            <num>34.35.135</num>
            <heading>Priority.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.135.   Priority.
A lien under
AS 34.35.125
and 34.35.130 is a preferred lien, prior and superior to a mortgage, conditional sale agreement, attachment, claim, or demand, unless the mortgage, conditional sale agreement, attachment, claim, or demand is in writing and recorded in the recorder's office of the recording district where the property is located before the work for which the lien is claimed is started. A sale, transfer, mortgage, assignment, or attachment made or filed for record after the work is started does not have the effect of postponing the lien.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-140">
            <num>34.35.140</num>
            <heading>Lien on dump or mass of mineral.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-140__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who, at the instance of another who has the right of possession of a mine, or mining claim, oil or gas well, performs upon, in, or about the mine or well any of the kinds of work mentioned in
AS 34.35.125
, or who performs any other kind of work in the production, piling up, or storing of a dump or mass of mineral, has a lien on the dump or mass, and the gold, gold dust, or other minerals contained in or extracted from it, to secure the amount due the laborer in the production of the minerals.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-140__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The lien attaches to the dump or mass, and to the gold, gold dust, or other mineral, whether they are deposited on the ground in a mass, or dumped into bunkers or hoppers, or stored in tanks or reservoirs, or placed in sluice boxes at the mine, and attaches to the gold, gold dust, and other minerals so long as they are in one mass and can be identified as being produced by the labor of the lienor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-140__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The lien provided for in this section is prior and preferred over a deed, mortgage, bill of sale, attachment, or other claim whether given before or after the work for which the lien is claimed is started.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-145">
            <num>34.35.145</num>
            <heading>Extent of liens.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.145.   Extent of liens.
Liens under
AS 34.35.125
, 34.35.130, and 34.35.140 are security for payment for the work performed within a period of nine months immediately before the cessation of the work.  The liens bind all the right, title, and interest in the property mentioned of the person at whose instance or request or for whom the work is performed, to the full extent of the interest that the person has at the beginning of the work for which the lien is claimed, or subsequently acquired in the property, up to the time of the foreclosure of the lien.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-150">
            <num>34.35.150</num>
            <heading>Labor deemed performed at instance of owner, mortgagee, or lien claimant.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-150__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the work mentioned in
AS 34.35.125
, 34.35.130, and 34.35.140 is performed at the instance of a person, who has the right of possession under a written or oral lease, license, or authority, expressed or implied, bond, option or other contract of sale from the owner, executed by the owner's authority, or who has possession with the knowledge of the owner, the work is considered to have been done at the instance of the owner, and at the instance of the mortgagee or lien claimant.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-150__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The owner's, mortgagee's, or claimant's interest in the property is subject to a lien filed in accordance with
AS 34.35.125
  34.35.170, unless the owner, mortgagee, or claimant, within 10 days after obtaining knowledge of the work, gives notice of nonresponsibility for the work, by posting notices to that effect in three conspicuous places on the mine, mining claim, or on or near the oil, gas, or other well, or in one conspicuous place on the dredge, steam shovel, derrick, mill, or machine.  A mortgagee or other lien claimant must also give additional notice of the nature of the lien, the amount due on it, and refer to the volume and page where the claim of lien is recorded.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-150__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The posting of notice is not required on a dragline, electric shovel, tractor, scraper, hoist, truck, or mobile equipment or machinery or personal property that is readily moved about from place to place or is required to be moved from place to place in the course of mining operations.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-155">
            <num>34.35.155</num>
            <heading>Liens not exclusive.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-155__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Liens under
AS 34.35.125
  34.35.170 are not exclusive of one another.  The lien shall attach and may be claimed by the same labor upon the mine, mining claim, mill, or machine used in mining or working, and the dump or mass of mineral, gold, or gold dust, if the facts relative to the labor warrant.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-155__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A lienor may claim a lien on one or more of the different classes of property subject to a lien for the same labor if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-155__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the amount claimed against each class of property is separately stated;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-155__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the property sought to be charged is described so that it can be identified; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-155__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name of the owner or reputed owner is given.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-160">
            <num>34.35.160</num>
            <heading>Claim of lien.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-160__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who claims the benefit of
AS 34.35.125
 34.35.170 shall, within 90 days after the performance of the services or the cessation of the work mentioned in
AS 34.35.125
 34.35.170, record the claim of lien in the recorder's office of the recording district in which the mine or mining claim, or other property on which the lien is claimed is located or used.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-160__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The claim of lien must contain</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-160__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a statement of the demand;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-160__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the amount of the demand, after deducting all credits and offsets;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-160__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name of the person by whom the claimant was employed;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-160__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a statement of the terms and conditions of the contract of employment;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-160__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the date of starting and stopping the work;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-160__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a description of the property on which the lien is claimed, sufficient for identification; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-160__subsec_b__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name of the owner or reputed owner.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-160__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The lien claim shall be verified by the oath of the lien claimant or someone on behalf of the lien claimant having personal knowledge of the facts.  If there is no express contract of employment, the claim must state the reasonable value of the work and services.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-165">
            <num>34.35.165</num>
            <heading>Duration of lien.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-165__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A lien under
AS 34.35.125
  34.35.170 does not bind a property for more than six months after notice of the lien is filed for record, unless suit is brought before the proper court to enforce the lien within that time, or if credit is given, with six months after the expiration of the credit.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-165__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A lien may not be continued in force for more than one year from the stopping of work by an agreement to give credit.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-170">
            <num>34.35.170</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-170__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In
AS 34.35.125
 34.35.170,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-170__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>dump or mass means the mineral-bearing sands, gravel, earth, ore, stone, coal, oil, gas, other fluids or minerals extracted, hoisted, and raised from a mine or mining claim, while in mass at the mine or on the mining claim or adjacent to it, whether it is deposited in dumps or piles, or placed in hoppers, tanks, or reservoirs, or in sluice boxes or bunkers or other receptacles and whether partially or wholly reduced from its primary state or not;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-170__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>mill or machine includes a dredge, steam, internal combustion or electric shovel, dragline, tractor, scraper, hoist, engine and boiler, derrick, drill, roasting or reduction works, stamp, roller or other mill, concentrator, conveyor, elevator, or other machinery used in or about a mine in digging, hoisting, conveying, washing, or blocking out mineral contents, or reducing the mineral contents to a commercial value, while the mill or machine is used in connection with the operation of the mine, and is not a fixture and included in the term mine as defined in this section;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-170__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>mine or mining claim means a block or parcel of mining ground, consisting of a part of a mining location, a mining location, or two or more contiguous mining locations, or an oil, gas, or other well or claim, possessed and held under one ownership, or mined under one management and worked through a common shaft, tunnel, incline, pit, well, or other opening, or over one tram; and all valuable mineral deposits, including coal, oil, gas, or other fluid, and all lodes, veins, or rock in place containing minerals; and all shafts, tunnels, stopes, ways, and other openings, roads, appliances, machinery, timbering, and structure below the surface of the ground; and all structures, buildings, mills, and machines on the surface of the ground and affixed to the ground and used in the working, mining, and development; and all ditches, water rights, pipelines, roads, trams, flumes, and other appurtenances;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-170__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>mineral includes coal, oil, gas, and inorganic substances subject to location, appropriation, acquisition, or enjoyment under the laws of the United States or the state.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-170__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the phrase different classes or kinds of property subject to lien is used, it refers to mines as defined in this section as one class; mills and machines as another class; and the dump or mass as a third class.
Article 4. Improvement of Chattels.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-175">
            <num>34.35.175</num>
            <heading>Improvement lien on personal property.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-175__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who makes, alters, repairs, or labors upon an article of personal property at the request of the owner or lawful possessor has a lien on the property for the just and reasonable charges for the labor performed and material furnished.  The person may keep possession of the article until the charges are paid.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-175__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the charges are not paid within three months after the labor or materials, or both, are performed or furnished, the person having the lien may sell the article at public auction and apply the proceeds of the sale, first, to the payment of the expenses of sale, second, to the discharge of lien, and third, the balance to the owner of the article.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-175__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The sale shall be held in the recording district where the article is left to be altered or repaired.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-175__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before the sale is made, notice of the sale shall be given to the debtor by registered letter directed to the last known place of residence of the debtor, if the residence is known, and also by posting notice of the sale in three public places in the recording district for 10 days before the day of sale. The notice must contain a particular description of the article to be sold, the name of the owner or reputed owner, the amount due on the lien, and the time and place of the sale.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-180">
            <num>34.35.180</num>
            <heading>Chattel lien; surrender of possession.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.180.   Chattel lien; surrender of possession.
A person who expends labor, skill, or materials upon a chattel, at the request of its owner, reputed owner, or authorized agent of the owner, or lawful possessor of the chattel, has a lien upon the chattel for the contract price of the expenditure, or in the absence of a contract price, for the reasonable worth of the expenditure, for a period of six months from the expenditure, notwithstanding the fact that the possession of the chattel is surrendered to the owner or lawful possessor.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-185">
            <num>34.35.185</num>
            <heading>Lien notice.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-185__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The lien claimant shall, before delivery of the chattel to the owner or the authorized agent of the owner, record a lien notice in the office of the recorder of the recording district where the chattel is situated and in which the labor, skill, and materials are expended on the chattel.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-185__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The notice must state the name of the claimant, the name of the owner, or reputed owner, a description of the chattel, sufficient for identification, upon which the claimant has expended labor, skill, and material, the amount for which the lien is claimed, and the date upon which the expenditure was completed. The notice shall be verified by the oath of the claimant, or by some one on behalf of the claimant, who has personal knowledge of the facts, and may be substantially in the following form:
....................................................., Claimant, v...................................................... DefendantNotice is hereby given that ..................................................... claims a lien upon ..................................................... (describe the property) for, and on account of labor, skill, and materials expended upon the ..................................................... (property); that the name of the owner, or reputed owner is, .....................................................; that the labor, skill, and materials were expended upon the property between the .......... day of .........., and the day of .........., and the rendition of the labor, skill, and materials so expended by the claimant above named was closed on the .......... day of ..........; that the amount claimant demands for labor, skill, and materials so expended is $..........; that no part of it has been paid except $.........., and there is now due and remaining unpaid on it, after deducting all just credits and offsets, the sum of $.........., in which amount a lien is claimed upon the property.State of Alaska..................................................... Judicial District  ss:..................................................... ClaimantI,....................................................., being first duly sworn, on oath say that I am ..................................................... named in the foregoing claim; that I have hea</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-190">
            <num>34.35.190</num>
            <heading>Duty of recorder.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.190.   Duty of recorder.
Upon the presentation of the notice to the recorder, the recorder shall record the notice and index it in a book or computer-readable medium kept for that purpose and called Index of Liens upon Chattels. The recorder is entitled to charge and receive from the person recording the notice of lien a fee provided for recording and indexing chattel mortgages.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-195">
            <num>34.35.195</num>
            <heading>Persons considered owner of chattel.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.195.   Persons considered owner of chattel.
The following persons are considered the owner of a chattel, or the authorized agent of the owner, for the purpose of
AS 34.35.175
 34.35.215:
(1) a person in possession of the chattel under an agreement to purchase it, whether the title to it is in the person or the vendor;
(2) a person in lawful possession of the chattel.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-200">
            <num>34.35.200</num>
            <heading>Priority.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.200.   Priority.
A lien under
AS 34.35.180
, when recorded in accordance with
AS 34.35.185
, is superior to and preferred to
(1) a lien, mortgage, or encumbrance that attaches to the chattel after the starting of labor or services or the furnishing of the material mentioned in that section;
(2) a lien, mortgage, or other encumbrance that attaches before that time, when the person furnishing the material or performing the services did not have notice of the prior lien, mortgage, or encumbrance, or the prior lien, mortgage, or encumbrance was not recorded or filed in the manner provided by law.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-205">
            <num>34.35.205</num>
            <heading>Duration of lien.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-205__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A lien does not bind a property for more than six months after the lien is recorded, unless suit is brought in the superior court to enforce the lien within that time, or if credit is given, within six months after the expiration of the credit.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-205__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A lien may not be continued in force for more than one year from stopping of work or services, or after the material is furnished, by an agreement of the parties.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-205__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The practice and procedure to enforce a lien shall be governed by the law applicable to the foreclosure of mechanics' and materialmen's liens.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-210">
            <num>34.35.210</num>
            <heading>Release or discharge of lien.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.210.   Release or discharge of lien.
A lien under
AS 34.35.175
  34.35.215 may be released and discharged by the lien claimant or the agent of the lien claimant by an entry upon the Index of Liens upon Chattels.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-215">
            <num>34.35.215</num>
            <heading>Penalty for refusal to discharge lien.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.215.   Penalty for refusal to discharge lien.
A person who refuses to discharge a lien after the lien is paid is guilty of a misdemeanor, and upon conviction is punishable by a fine of not more than $500 and in addition is liable in damages to the person injured by the refusal in an amount equal to three times the damage sustained.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-220">
            <num>34.35.220</num>
            <heading>Persons entitled to carrier, warehouse, and livestock liens.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.220.   Persons entitled to carrier, warehouse, and livestock liens.
The following persons have liens on personal property for their just and reasonable charges for the labor, care, and attention provided and the food furnished, and may retain possession of the property until the charges are paid:
(1) a person who is a common carrier, or who, at the request of the owner or lawful possessor of personal property, transports the property from one place to another;
(2) a person who safely keeps or stores personal property at the request of the owner or lawful possessor of the property; and
(3) a person who pastures or feeds livestock, or bestows labor, care, or attention on the livestock at the request of the owner or lawful possessor of the livestock.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-225">
            <num>34.35.225</num>
            <heading>Sale to enforce lien.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-225__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If just and reasonable charges are not paid within three months after the care, attention, and labor is performed or food is furnished, the person having the lien may proceed to sell at public auction, as provided in
AS 34.35.175
, the property mentioned in
AS 34.35.220
, or a part of it, sufficient to pay the just and reasonable charges.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-225__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing in this section may be construed to authorize a person to sell more of the property than is sufficient to pay charges due the person on the property.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-225__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who sells, loans, or otherwise disposes of property contrary to the provisions of
AS 34.35.220
and this section without the consent of the owner of the property shall, for each offense, forfeit and pay to the owner a sum equal to the market value of the property, and 50 percent of the market value in addition as a penalty. In this subsection, market value means the price the property bears at the time the owner makes demand on the person for it.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-225__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The remedies available under this section are in addition to any remedies available under
AS 45.07.210
.
Article 6. Timber and Lumber.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-230">
            <num>34.35.230</num>
            <heading>Construction.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.230.   Construction.
The purpose of
AS 34.35.230
 34.35.315 is remedial to secure laborers, contractors, and subcontractors the amount due them for labor performed in producing, or furnishing lumber.
AS 34.35.230
  34.35.315 shall be liberally construed to effect this purpose.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-235">
            <num>34.35.235</num>
            <heading>Persons entitled to timber lien.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-235__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The following persons shall have liens upon timber for the work done upon, or in obtaining or securing, or for services rendered in towing, transporting, hauling, or driving it:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-235__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a person who performs labor upon, or who assists in obtaining or securing timber;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-235__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the owner of a tugboat or towboat that tows or assists in towing timber from one place to another within the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-235__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the owner of a team or a logging or traction engine that hauls or assists in hauling timber from one place to another within the state; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-235__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the owner of a logging road over which timber is transported and delivered.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-235__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The lien attaches under (a) of this section whether the work or services are done, rendered, or performed at the instance of the owner of the timber or an agent of the owner.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-235__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The cook and other laborers in and about the logging or wood camp, the teamsters transporting the timber, and the laborers on roads and trails, not including public roads or trails, used for the transportation of the timber are considered persons who assist in obtaining, securing, and delivering the timber mentioned in this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-240">
            <num>34.35.240</num>
            <heading>Lien claim.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-240__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who claims a lien under
AS 34.35.235
within 60 days after the completion of the service or after the close of the work must record a claim with the recorder of the recording district in which the timber is cut.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-240__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The claim must contain (1) a statement of the demand and the amount of the demand, after deducting as nearly as possible all just credits and offsets; (2) the name of the person by whom the claimant was employed; (3) a statement of the terms and conditions of the contract, or if there is no contract, the reasonable value of the service or work; and (4) a description of the property charged with the lien sufficient for identification with reasonable certainty. The claim shall be verified by the oath of the claimant or another who has knowledge of the facts.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-240__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The claim must be substantially in the following form:
CLAIM OF LIEN..................................................... Claimant, v......................................................Notice is given by this claim that .................................., residing at .................................., State of Alaska, claims a lien upon a .................................. of .................................., being about .................................. in quantity, which were cut in .................................. recording district, State of Alaska, and are now lying or being at .................................., for labor performed and assistance provided in .................................. said ..................................; that the name of the owner or reputed owner is ..................................; that .................................. employed said .................................. to perform the labor and provide the assistance upon the following terms and conditions, to wit: That .................................. agreed to pay the .................................. for labor and assistance ..................................; that the contract has been faithfully performed and fully complied with on the part of .................................., who performed labor and assisted in .................................. for the period of ..................................; that the labor and assistance were so performed and provided upon .................................. between the .................................. day of .................................., and 45 days have not elapsed since that time; that the amount of the claimant's demand for the service is ..................................; that no part of the claim has been paid except ..................................; and there is now due and remaining unpaid on the claim, after deducting all just credits and offsets, the sum of .................................., and th</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-245">
            <num>34.35.245</num>
            <heading>Landowner's lien for timber.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.245.   Landowner's lien for timber.
A person who permits another to go upon the person's land and cut timber has a lien upon the timber for the price agreed to be paid for the privilege, or for the price the privilege would reasonably be worth if there is no express agreement fixing the price.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-250">
            <num>34.35.250</num>
            <heading>Landowner's lien claim.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-250__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who claims a lien under
AS 34.35.245
must record, within 90 days from the cutting of the timber, a claim with the recorder of the recording district in which the saw timber is cut.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-250__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The claim must be in substance the same as provided in
AS 34.35.240
and must be verified as provided in that section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-255">
            <num>34.35.255</num>
            <heading>Priority.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-255__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Liens under
AS 34.35.230
 34.35.315 are preferred liens and are prior to other liens.  A sale or transfer of timber does not divest a lien on it under
AS 34.35.230
  34.35.315.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-255__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>As between liens under
AS 34.35.230
  34.35.315 those for work and labor are preferred.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-255__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>As between liens for work claimed by several laborers on the same timber, the claim or claims for work done or performed on the identical timber proceeded against, to the extent that the timber can be identified, are preferred as against the general claim of liens for work recognized and provided for in
AS 34.35.230
 34.35.315.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-255__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The person performing the service or doing the work named in
AS 34.35.235
is only entitled to the liens provided in
AS 34.35.230
  34.35.315 for services or work for six calendar months or a shorter period preceding the recording of the claim.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-255__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The person granting the privilege mentioned in
AS 34.35.245
is only entitled to the lien under that section for timber cut during the six months preceding the recording of the claim as provided in
AS 34.35.240
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-260">
            <num>34.35.260</num>
            <heading>Duration of lien.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-260__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A lien under
AS 34.35.230
  34.35.315 does not bind property for more than six months after notice of the lien is recorded, unless suit is brought to enforce the lien in the proper court within that time or if credit is given, within six months after the expiration of the credit.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-260__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A lien may not be continued in force for more than one year from the stopping of the work or by an agreement to give credit.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-265">
            <num>34.35.265</num>
            <heading>Enforcement of lien against manufactured product.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-265__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The lien provided for saw logs and shingle bolts is not released or lost by the manufacture of the saw logs or shingle bolts into lumber or shingles, and the lien may be enforced against the lumber and shingles manufactured from them.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-265__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A lien may not be acquired upon or enforced against lumber or logs after the lumber or logs are used in the construction of a building or structure, or upon spars, piles, or other timber mentioned in
AS 34.35.230
 34.35.315 after they are put to the use for which they are intended.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-270">
            <num>34.35.270</num>
            <heading>Commissioner of public safety as receiver.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-270__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner of public safety or a peace officer designated by the commissioner shall be the receiver, when one is appointed, and the superior court, upon a showing made, shall appoint the receiver, without notice.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-270__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The receiver is entitled to fees which seem just to the court, and shall account for the fees in the same manner as other fees collected in an official capacity.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-270__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When property subject to a lien under
AS 34.35.230
 34.35.315 is in the custody of the receiver, a person who claims an interest in the property may deposit with the clerk of the court in which the action is pending a sum of money equal to the claim sued upon, together with $100 to cover costs and interest, unless the court makes an order fixing a different amount to cover the costs and interest, and may demand and receive the possession and custody of the property from the receiver immediately.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-275">
            <num>34.35.275</num>
            <heading>Bona fide purchasers.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.275.   Bona fide purchasers.
The court shall conclusively presume that a party purchasing the property liened upon within the 60 days given to claimants to record their liens is not an innocent third party and is not a bona fide owner of the property, unless it appears that
(1) the purchaser has paid full value for the property; and
(2) the purchase money has been applied to the payment of the bona fide claims that are entitled to liens upon the property under
AS 34.35.230
  34.35.315 according to the priorities established in those sections.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-280">
            <num>34.35.280</num>
            <heading>Enforceability.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-280__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The following persons may demand that a lien under
AS 34.35.230
  34.35.315 be enforced:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-280__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a person who brings an action to enforce the lien; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-280__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a person who has a lien under
AS 34.35.230
 34.35.315, and who is made a party to an action to enforce a lien under those sections.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-280__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The lien may be enforced against the whole, or a part of the lumber, when, during the six months preceding the recording of the lien,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-280__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the person has performed labor on it;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-280__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the person has assisted in securing or obtaining it; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-280__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>it has been cut on the person's land.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-280__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The lien demand recorded must be for</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-280__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>all the labor upon or all the assistance in obtaining or securing the lumber during the whole or a part of the six months mentioned in
AS 34.35.260
; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-280__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>timber cut during the whole or a part of the six months mentioned above.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-280__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The priority of the liens shall be determined under
AS 34.35.255
where</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-280__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>proceedings are started against a lot of lumber;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-280__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>some of the lienors claim liens against specific lumber to secure their claims for work and labor; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-280__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>other lienors claim liens against the lumber generally to secure their claims for work and labor.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-285">
            <num>34.35.285</num>
            <heading>Contractor's lien.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.285.   Contractor's lien.
A person who, as a contractor, supplies lumber under a contract is entitled to the lien under
AS 34.35.230
 34.35.315 to the amount due on the contract.  However, the lien is subject and subsequent to the liens of the laborers under
AS 34.35.230
  34.35.315 for the amounts due them for labor on the lumber.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-290">
            <num>34.35.290</num>
            <heading>Order of sale before judgment.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-290__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The court or judge may in vacation, upon motion supported by affidavit showing that the property is liable to loss or destruction, order that property subject to a lien under
AS 34.35.230
  34.35.315 be sold by the peace officer before judgment is rendered, as personal property is sold under execution.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-290__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The proceeds of the sale shall be paid into court to be applied as provided in
AS 34.35.230
  34.35.315.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-295">
            <num>34.35.295</num>
            <heading>Liability for injuring property or destroying identity.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-295__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who eloigns, injures, or destroys or who makes difficult, uncertain, or impossible the identification of timber upon which there is a lien under
AS 34.35.230
 34.35.315, without the express consent of the lienholder, is liable to the lienholder for the damages to the amount secured by the lien, together with costs and charges of drawing and recording the lien and reasonable attorney fees for the foreclosure of the lien.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-295__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If these facts are shown to the court in the action to enforce the lien, the court shall enter a personal judgment for the amount of the damages in the action against the person, if the person is a party to the action, or the damages may be recovered in a civil action against the person.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-300">
            <num>34.35.300</num>
            <heading>Lien for manufacturing.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-300__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who performs work or assists in manufacturing timber into lumber has a lien upon the lumber while it remains at the mill where it is manufactured, or in the possession or under the control of the manufacturer, whether the work is done at the instance of the owner of the logs or an agent of the owner, or a contractor or subcontractor of the owner.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-300__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section lumber means logs or other timber sawed or split for use, including beams, joists, planks, bolts, shingles, rails, stays, hoops, and every article manufactured from timber.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-305">
            <num>34.35.305</num>
            <heading>Manufacturing lien claim.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-305__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who desires to claim the benefit of
AS 34.35.300
shall, within 60 days after the close of the service mentioned in that section, record with the recorder of the recording district where the lumber is manufactured, a notice of claim of lien.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-305__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The notice must contain a statement of the demand and the amount of the demand in substance and form similar to that provided for in
AS 34.35.240
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-305__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The provisions of
AS 34.35.230
  34.35.315 relative to the liens of persons performing labor upon, or assisting, obtaining, and securing timber apply in all respects, where applicable, to the liens of persons who perform work in manufacturing lumber, as set out in
AS 34.35.300
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-310">
            <num>34.35.310</num>
            <heading>Release upon filing bond.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-310__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After a lien attaches to property mentioned in
AS 34.35.230
  34.35.315, the owner of the property or a person on behalf of the owner may file with the clerk of the superior court in the judicial district in which the property is located a bond (1) in a sum double the amount claimed in the lien notice; (2) executed by two sureties who have the qualifications of bail upon arrest; (3) to be approved by the clerk of the court; (4) running to the claimant in the lien notice; and (5) conditioned for the payment of the damages, costs, charges, and disbursements recovered by the lien claimant against the owner, or found to be a lien upon the property described in the lien notice.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-310__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The clerk shall issue to the owner or other person a certificate stating that the bond is substituted in place of the property and that the lien on the property is released and discharged.  A marginal entry of the release and substitution of bond shall be made in the lien docket in the office of the recorder where the lien statement is recorded.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-310__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the lien claimant establishes the lien by a suit to enforce it, the claimant is entitled to judgment or decree against the principal and sureties on the bond.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-310__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing in this section deprives a person of a defense that the person would have had if the bond had not been given.  The filing of the bond does not affect the time within which the foreclosure suit shall be started.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-315">
            <num>34.35.315</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.315.   Definitions.
In
AS 34.35.230
  34.35.315,
(1) lumber includes timber, or lumber or shingles manufactured from it;
(2) timber includes saw logs, piles, spars, cordwood, fuelwood, shingle bolts, or other timber.
Article 7. Fish Packers and Processors.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-320">
            <num>34.35.320</num>
            <heading>Packer's and processor's lien.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-320__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who contributes to the preparation of fish or aquatic animals for food, fish, meal, fertilizer, oil, or other article of commerce by furnishing material or labor for it has a lien for the value of the labor and material upon (1) the product or output of the cannery, saltery, or other plant or establishment, for which material or labor was furnished; and (2) the plant or establishment itself, including the houses, wharves, machinery, and equipment of the plant or establishment, for the value of labor and material.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-320__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This provision may not be construed to give a lien to (1) an officer of a corporation or of an association for labor or material furnished by the officer to the corporation or association; (2) a superintendent, manager, foreman, contractor, or subcontractor in charge of a cannery, saltery, or other plant or establishment for labor or material that the person has furnished to the plant or establishment; or (3) the owner or lessor of a plant or the equipment of the plant for the use or rental of the plant or equipment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-325">
            <num>34.35.325</num>
            <heading>Time limit.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.325.   Time limit.
The person performing the service or doing the work or furnishing the material mentioned in
AS 34.35.320
is only entitled to a lien under
AS 34.35.320
 34.35.390 for service, work, or material furnished for the six months, or a shorter period, preceding the recording of a claim under
AS 34.35.330
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-330">
            <num>34.35.330</num>
            <heading>Lien claim.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-330__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who claims the benefit of
AS 34.35.320
  34.35.390 shall, within 90 days after the completion of the work or the furnishing of material mentioned in
AS 34.35.320
, record a claim of lien in the recorder's office of the recording district where</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-330__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the product or output of the plant, cannery, saltery, or other establishment for which the material or labor is furnished is located; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-330__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the cannery, saltery, or other plant or establishment on which the lien is claimed is located.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-330__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The claim of lien must contain a statement of</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-330__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the claimant's demand and the amount of the demand after deducting credits and offsets;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-330__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name of the person by whom the claimant is employed or at whose request the material is furnished;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-330__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the terms and conditions of the contract of employment or under which the material was furnished;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-330__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a description of the property sufficient for identification on which the lien is claimed; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-330__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name of the owner or reputed owner thereof.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-330__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The lien claim shall be verified by the oath of the lien claimant or someone on behalf of the lien claimant who has knowledge of the facts.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-330__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If there is no express contract of employment or for furnishing the material the claim shall state the reasonable value of the work, labor, or material.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-335">
            <num>34.35.335</num>
            <heading>Extent of lien.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.335.   Extent of lien.
A lien under
AS 34.35.320
 34.35.390 binds all the right, title, and interest of the person at whose instance or request or for whom the work is performed or material furnished, to the full extent of the interest that the person has at the commencement of the work or at the time the material is furnished, for which the lien is claimed, or subsequently acquired up to the time of foreclosure of the lien, in (1) all of the product or output of the cannery, saltery, or other plant or establishment for which the material or work was furnished; and (2) the plant or establishment itself, including the houses, wharves, machinery, and equipment.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-340">
            <num>34.35.340</num>
            <heading>Priority.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-340__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A lien under
AS 34.35.320
 34.35.390 is preferred, prior, and superior to a mortgage, attachment, claim, or demand made or recorded in the recorder's office of the recording district where the property subject to the lien is located after</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-340__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the commencement of the work for which the lien is claimed;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-340__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the material is furnished for which the lien is claimed.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-340__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A sale, transfer, mortgage, assignment, or attachment recorded after the commencement of the work or furnishing of the material does not postpone the lien.  A lien under
AS 34.35.320
 34.35.390 is not prior or paramount to a valid prior lien for labor performed or material furnished in the construction, alteration, or repair of the houses, wharves, or other shore property.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-345">
            <num>34.35.345</num>
            <heading>Duration of lien.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-345__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A lien under
AS 34.35.320
  34.35.390 does not bind the property for more than six months after the lien is recorded, unless suit is brought before the proper court within that time to enforce the lien or if credit is given, within six months after the expiration of the credit.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-345__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A lien does not continue in force for more than one year from the cessation of the work or the furnishing of the material, by an agreement to give credit.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-350">
            <num>34.35.350</num>
            <heading>Commissioner of public safety as receiver.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-350__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner of public safety or a peace officer designated by the commissioner is the receiver, when one is appointed, and the superior court upon a showing made may appoint the receiver without notice.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-350__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The receiver is entitled to the fees that seem just to the court and the receiver shall account for the fees collected under this subsection in the same manner other fees collected in an official capacity are accounted for.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-350__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When property subject to a lien under
AS 34.35.320
 34.35.390 is in the custody or about to be taken into the custody of the receiver, a person who claims an interest in the property may deposit with the clerk of the court in which the action is pending a sum of money equal to the value of the property, but not greater than the amount of the claims sued upon together with $100 to cover costs and interest, unless the court makes an order fixing a different amount to cover costs and interest, and may demand and receive the possession and custody of the property from the receiver immediately.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-355">
            <num>34.35.355</num>
            <heading>Bona fide purchasers.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.355.   Bona fide purchasers.
The court shall conclusively presume that a party who purchases property on which a lien is claimed, within the time allowed for the filing of the lien, is not an innocent purchaser for value and is not a bona fide owner of the property subject to the lien, unless it appears that
(1) the purchaser paid the reasonable value of the property; and
(2) the purchase price for the property is applied to the payment of the bona fide claimants who are entitled to liens upon the property under
AS 34.35.320
  34.35.390.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-360">
            <num>34.35.360</num>
            <heading>Enforcement against whole or part of property.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-360__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who brings a suit to enforce the lien, or a person having a lien, who is made a party to the action, may demand that the lien be enforced against the whole or a part of the property upon which the person performs labor or for which the person furnishes material.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-360__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Where there are several lien claims against the same property or partly against the same property and partly against separate property, and it appears to the court that the property that may legally be held for the claims is insufficient to satisfy all the claims, the court shall, as nearly as practicable, determine what particular item of the property subject to the lien is the product in whole or in part of the labor or material furnished by each of the several claimants and for which each claims a lien, and shall give preference accordingly.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-365">
            <num>34.35.365</num>
            <heading>Property to be sold before judgment.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.365.   Property to be sold before judgment.
When it appears, during the term or in vacation, that the property is liable to loss or destruction, the court shall order it sold, free of the lien, by a peace officer, in the manner provided for the sale of personal property under execution, before judgment is rendered.  The proceeds of sale shall be paid into court to be applied as directed in the judgment.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-370">
            <num>34.35.370</num>
            <heading>Liability for injuring property or destroying identity.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-370__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who eloigns, injures, or destroys, or who makes difficult, uncertain, or impossible the identification of a property on which there is a lien under
AS 34.35.320
 34.35.390, without the written consent of the lienholder, is liable to the lienholder for the damages to the amount secured by the lien together with costs and charges of drawing and recording the lien and reasonable attorney fees for the foreclosure of the lien.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-370__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If these facts are shown to the court in the suit to enforce the lien, the court shall enter a personal judgment for the amount of the damages in the action against the person, if the person is a party to the action, or the damages may be recovered in a civil action against the person.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-375">
            <num>34.35.375</num>
            <heading>Release upon filing bond.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-375__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After a lien attaches upon property mentioned in
AS 34.35.320
  34.35.390, the owner of the property or a person on behalf of the owner may file with the clerk of the superior court in the judicial district in which the property is located, a bond (1) in a sum double the amount claimed in the lien notice; (2) executed by two sureties who have the qualifications of bail upon arrest; (3) to be approved by the clerk of the court; (4) running to the claimant in the lien notice; and (5) conditioned for the payment of all damages, costs, charges, and disbursements recovered by the lien claimant against the owner, or found to be a lien upon or against the property described in the lien notice.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-375__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The clerk shall issue to the owner a certificate stating that the bond is substituted in place of the property and that the lien on the property is released and discharged.  A marginal entry of the release and substitution of bond shall be made in the lien docket in the office of the recorder where the lien statement is recorded.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-375__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the lien claimant establishes the lien by a suit to enforce it, the lien claimant is entitled to judgment against the principal and sureties on the bond.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-375__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing in this section deprives a person of a defense that the person would have had if the bond had not been given.  The filing of the bond does not affect the time within which the foreclosure suit must be started.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-380">
            <num>34.35.380</num>
            <heading>Misdemeanor to remove lien property from state.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.380.   Misdemeanor to remove lien property from state.
A person who removes or has removed from the state fish, fish products, or the products of an aquatic animal, or fishing appliances, upon which there is a lien or right of lien under
AS 34.35.320
  34.35.390, unless a bond under
AS 34.35.375
is filed, is guilty of a misdemeanor, and upon conviction is punishable by a fine of not more than $2,000, or by imprisonment for not more than six months, or by both.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-385">
            <num>34.35.385</num>
            <heading>Embezzlement of lien property.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-385__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who sells or otherwise disposes of fish or the products of fish or aquatic animals or other property upon which there is a lien under
AS 34.35.320
 34.35.390 is a trustee for the lien claimant of the consideration received or promised to be paid for the property and shall account to the lien claimant for it.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-385__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If it appears, in a prosecution under this section, that the defendant has paid all claims of lien upon the property removed from the state or that the full value of the property has been distributed among the persons entitled to the lien, the defendant shall be discharged and further proceedings may not be brought against the defendant.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-385__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A trustee who refuses or fails to account for the trust fund, or refuses or fails to apply it in payment of the lien claim is guilty of embezzlement, and upon conviction is punishable accordingly.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-390">
            <num>34.35.390</num>
            <heading>Written statements to employees.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-390__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When a person employs another to work at a cannery, saltery, or other plant or establishment in this state for the catching or preparation of fish or aquatic animals for food, fish meal, fertilizer, oil, or other articles of commerce, and the plant or establishment, at the time of employment, is subject to a lien, mortgage, encumbrance, or the provisions of a transfer or conditional sale, or the employer is not the owner of the plant or establishment, or of the boats or fishing gear connected with it, the employer shall furnish to each employee at the time of employment, or in any event, not later than the time the employee is brought within the state boundaries, a written statement showing</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-390__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name of the owner of the plant or establishment at or in connection with which the employee is to work;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-390__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a general description of the plant or establishment as to buildings, boats, and other gear and material;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-390__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>whether any of the property is subject to a lien, mortgage, encumbrance, assignment, or conditional sale and, if so, the amount of it.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-390__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In a prosecution under this section, the defendant may show in defense that the claims for labor of the employees to whom the statements were not furnished have been paid in full.  A defendant who does so shall be discharged.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-390__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Failure to furnish a statement required by this section is a misdemeanor and a person who violates this section is punishable by a fine of not more than $2,000 or by imprisonment for not more than six months or by both.
Article 8. Fishermen's Lien.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-391">
            <num>34.35.391</num>
            <heading>Fishermen's lien.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-391__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who sells fish to a fish processor as defined in
AS 16.10.296
, or to a primary fish buyer as defined in
AS 16.10.296
, or to a cooperative corporation organized under
AS 10.15
, and receives a fish ticket or a record of purchase as described in
AS 16.05.690
has a lien upon the property of the fish processor, primary fish buyer, or cooperative corporation for the value of the fish.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-391__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who claims the benefit of this section shall, within 90 days of the date the fish are sold, record a claim of lien in the recorder's office of the recording district where the fish were sold.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-391__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The lien provided in this section is preferred, prior, and superior to a mortgage, attachment, claim, or demand made or recorded in the recording district in which the property is located after the date on which the fish are delivered to the buyer of the fish.
Article 9. Watchmen.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-395">
            <num>34.35.395</num>
            <heading>Watchman's lien.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.395.   Watchman's lien.
A person employed as watchman for real or personal property has a lien upon the property for the wages or salary earned as a watchman for the property.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-400">
            <num>34.35.400</num>
            <heading>Services or work covered by lien.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.400.   Services or work covered by lien.
The person performing the services or doing the work named in
AS 34.35.395
is only entitled to a lien under
AS 34.35.395
  34.35.425 for services or work for the nine months or a shorter period preceding the recording of the claim of lien under
AS 34.35.405
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-405">
            <num>34.35.405</num>
            <heading>Lien claim.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-405__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who claims a lien under
AS 34.35.395
 34.35.425 shall, within 90 days after the completion of the services or the cessation of the labor, record a claim of lien in the recorder's office of the recording district in which the property is located.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-405__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The lien claim must contain a true statement of</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-405__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the demand and the amount of the demand after deducting all just credits and offsets;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-405__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name of the person by whom the claimant is employed and a statement of the terms and conditions of the contract of employment;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-405__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a description of the property sufficient for identification on which the lien is claimed; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-405__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name of the owner or reputed owner of the property.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-405__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The lien claim shall be verified by the oath of the claimant or someone on behalf of the lien claimant who has personal knowledge of the facts.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-405__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If there is no express contract of employment the claim must state the reasonable value of the work or services.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-410">
            <num>34.35.410</num>
            <heading>Recording and indexing claim.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-410__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The recorder shall record the lien claim in a record book or computer-readable medium kept for that purpose. The record book shall be indexed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-410__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The recorder is entitled to receive the same fees allowed by law for recording deeds and other instruments.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-415">
            <num>34.35.415</num>
            <heading>Duration of lien.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-415__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A lien under
AS 34.35.395
  34.35.425 does not bind property for more than six months after the lien is recorded, unless suit is brought before the proper court to enforce the lien within that time or if credit is given, within nine months after the expiration of the credit.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-415__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A lien does not continue in force for more than one year from the stopping of the work or services by an agreement to give credit.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-420">
            <num>34.35.420</num>
            <heading>Extent of lien.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.420.   Extent of lien.
The lien provided in
AS 34.35.395
  34.35.425 binds all the right, title, and interest of the person at whose instance or request or for whom the work or services are performed, to the full extent of the interest that the person has at the commencement of the work or services for which the lien is claimed or that is subsequently acquired up to the time of the foreclosure of the lien, in the property where the work or services are performed.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-425">
            <num>34.35.425</num>
            <heading>Priority.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-425__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A lien under
AS 34.35.395
  34.35.425 is preferred, prior, and superior to a mortgage, attachment, claim, or demand made or recorded in the recorder's office of the recording district in which the property is located, after the commencement of the work or services for which the lien is claimed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-425__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A sale, transfer, mortgage, assignment, or attachment recorded after the commencement of the work or services does not postpone the lien, except that the lien is of equal rank with other liens recorded or claimed against the property for work or services performed or furnished in the erection, construction, repair, or preservation of the property.
Article 10. Attorneys.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-430">
            <num>34.35.430</num>
            <heading>Attorney's lien.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-430__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An attorney has a lien for compensation, whether specially agreed upon or implied, as provided in this section</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-430__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>first, upon the papers of the client that have come into the possession of the attorney in the course of the professional employment;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-430__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>second, upon money in the possession of the attorney belonging to the client;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-430__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>third, upon money in the possession of the adverse party in an action or proceeding in which the attorney is employed, from the giving of notice of the lien to that party;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-430__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>fourth, upon a judgment to the extent of the costs included in the judgment or, if there is a special agreement, to the extent of the compensation specially agreed on, from the giving of notice of the lien to the party against whom the judgment is given and filing the original with the clerk where the judgment is entered and docketed.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-430__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The lien described in (a) of this section is superior to all subsequent liens except tax liens. The lien is a charge on the action, and the parties to the action may not extinguish or affect the attorney's lien by any means, including settlement, other than by satisfying the underlying claim of the attorney for the fees and costs incurred in connection with the action. Nothing in this subsection precludes a party from contesting an attorney's lien under applicable law.
Article 11. Wages.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-435">
            <num>34.35.435</num>
            <heading>Lien for wages.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.435.   Lien for wages.
When a clerk, accountant, bookkeeper, waiter, waitress, cook, maid, porter, servant, employee, artisan, craftsman, factory operator, mill operator, mechanic, quarryman, common laborer, or farmhand labors or performs a service in an office, store, hotel, rooming house, boardinghouse, restaurant, cafe, shop, newspaper plant, factory, quarry, or mill, of any character, or upon a farm, under or by virtue of a contract or agreement, written or oral, with a person or employer, or an agent, receiver, or trustee of the person or employer, in order to secure the payment of the amount due or owing under the contract or agreement, written or oral, the employee has a first lien upon all products, machinery, tools, fixtures, appurtenances, goods, wares, merchandise, chattels, wagons, carts, or things of value, of whatsoever character, that are created in whole or in part by the labor or that may be used or useful by the person or may be necessarily connected with the performance of the labor or service, which may be owned by the employer, or an agent, receiver, or trustee of the employer.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-440">
            <num>34.35.440</num>
            <heading>Fixing the lien.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-440__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When a person or an agent, receiver, or trustee of the person, fails or refuses to make wage payments as prescribed by law or agreement between the parties, the employee who has performed the service shall make an account of service, showing the amount due the employee for the service, and present to the employer or an agent, receiver, or trustee of the employer one of the duplicate accounts within 30 days after the indebtedness accrues.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-440__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Within 90 days after termination of the performance of services the claimant shall record with the recorder of the recording district in which the services were performed a lien notice verified by the claimant.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-440__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The lien notice shall be indexed in a book or computer-readable medium kept for that purpose.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-440__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The lien claim must contain a description of the property charged with the lien sufficient for identification, and shall be verified by the oath of the lien claimant or of some other person having knowledge of the facts.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-440__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A compliance with the requirements in this section is necessary to fix and preserve the lien given under
AS 34.35.435
  34.35.445.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-440__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The liens of different persons of the same class have equal priority with each other.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-440__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person claiming the benefit of
AS 34.35.435
 34.35.445 has six months from the date of recording the lien within which to bring suit to foreclose the lien, or, if a credit is given, then six months after the expiration of the credit.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-440__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A substantial compliance with this section is sufficient diligence to fix and secure the lien, except that a purchaser of products covered by the lien from the owner of the products acquires good title to them unless at the time of the purchase, the purchaser has actual or constructive notice of the claim of the lienholder upon the products.  The purchaser has constructive notice if the claim is recorded and indexed or if an action is on file.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-445">
            <num>34.35.445</num>
            <heading>Duration of lien.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-445__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The lien created by
AS 34.35.435
  34.35.445 is not operative for more than six months after the lien is recorded and indexed, unless suit to enforce the lien is brought before the proper court within that time or if a credit is given, six months after the expiration of the credit.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-445__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A lien does not continue in force for more than one year from the stopping of the work by an agreement to give credit.
Article 12. Hospitals, Physicians, and Nurses.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-450">
            <num>34.35.450</num>
            <heading>Hospital's, physician's, and nurse's lien.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-450__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An operator of a hospital in the state, a licensed special nurse in a hospital in the state, or a physician who furnishes service to a person who has a traumatic injury has a lien upon any sum awarded to the injured person or the personal representative of the injured person by judgment or obtained by a settlement or compromise to the extent of the amount due the hospital, nurse, or physician for the reasonable value of the service furnished before the date of judgment, settlement, or compromise, together with costs and reasonable attorney fees that the court allows, incurred in the enforcement of the lien.
AS 34.35.450
 34.35.480 do not apply to a claim, right of action, or money accruing under
AS 23.30
(Workers' Compensation Act).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-450__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the person receiving hospitalization has a contract providing for indemnity or compensation for the sum incurred for hospitalization, the hospital has a lien upon the amount payable under the contract.  The party obligated to make reimbursement under the contract may pay the sum due under it directly to the hospital, and this payment is a full release of the party making the payment under the contract in the amount of the payment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-455">
            <num>34.35.455</num>
            <heading>Limitation on extent of lien.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.455.   Limitation on extent of lien.
Except as otherwise provided, a lien under
AS 34.35.450
 34.35.480 may not be allowed for hospitalization or the services of a physician or licensed special nurse furnished after a settlement is made by or on behalf of the person causing the injury unless the settlement is made within 20 days from the date of the injury. A lien is not allowed for necessary attorney fees, costs, and expenses incurred by the injured person in securing a settlement, compromise, or judgment.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-460">
            <num>34.35.460</num>
            <heading>Notice of lien.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-460__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To perfect the lien described in
AS 34.35.450
 34.35.480, the hospital or the owner or operator of the hospital, or the physician or licensed special nurse, shall, not later than 90 days after the date of injury, or in no event later than 90 days after the discharge of the injured person from the hospital or the provision of the physician's services, file a notice of lien substantially in the form prescribed in
AS 34.35.465
, containing a general description of the services rendered and a statement of the amount claimed, with a recorder's office, and shall, after the 90-day period, before the date of judgment, settlement, or compromise, serve a copy of the notice of lien by registered mail, at the last known address, upon the person alleged to be responsible for causing the injury and from whom damages are claimed, and upon the insurance carrier that has insured against the liability, if the insurance carrier is known.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-460__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A hospital or the owner or operator of a hospital, or a physician or licensed special nurse who files a notice of lien under (a) of this section for hospitalization or services provided to a recipient of medical assistance under
AS 47
shall mail a copy of the notice of lien to the unit of the Department of Health that administers medical assistance for needy persons under
AS 47
. The copy must be sent by certified mail no later than 30 days after the filing of the notice of lien under (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-465">
            <num>34.35.465</num>
            <heading>Form of notice.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.465.   Form of notice.
The form of notice required by
AS 34.35.450
  34.35.480 shall be substantially as follows:
NOTICE is hereby given that .................................. has rendered services for hospitalization, physician services, or special nurses' services for .................................., a person who was injured on the .......... day of .......... at .......... in the state, and the ..................................................... (claimant) hereby claims a lien upon any money due or owing or any claim for compensation, damages, contribution, settlement, or judgment from ..................................................... alleged to have caused the injuries and any other person liable for the injury or obligated to compensate the injured person on account of the injuries; the hospitalization, physician services, or special nurses' services were rendered to the injured person between the .......... day of .......... and .....................................................:General Description of Services Rendered and  Statement of Amount Due...................and that 90 days have not elapsed since that time; that the claimant's demands for care and service is in the sum of $.......... and that no part of the demands has been paid, except $.........., and that there is now due and owing and remaining unpaid thereof, after deducting all credits and offsets, the sum of $.........., in which amount lien is hereby claimed.United States of AmericaState of Alaska ss.......... Judicial DistrictI, ....................................................., being first duly sworn on oath say: That I am ..................................................... named in the foregoing claim of lien; that I have read the same and know the contents thereof and believe the same to be true.Subscribed and sworn to before me this .......... day of .........., 2...............................................................</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-475">
            <num>34.35.475</num>
            <heading>Settlement after notice.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-475__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person or insurer is liable to a hospital, physician, or nurse, in the amount that the hospital, physician, or nurse is entitled to receive, for 180 days after the date of a payment to the injured person, the heirs of the injured person, personal representatives, or the attorney of them, when the person or insurer</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-475__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>receives a copy of notice of lien, or the lien is recorded as provided in
AS 34.35.460
and 34.35.465;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-475__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>makes the payment after receipt of notice or the recording of the lien as compensation for the injury suffered; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-475__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>does not pay the hospital, physician, or the licensed special nurse for the reasonable value of the services rendered to the injured person and claimed in the notice of lien, or so much of the value of the services as can be satisfied out of a judgment, settlement, or compromise, after paying the attorney fees, costs, and expenses incurred in connection with it.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-475__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The hospital, physician, or nurse has a cause of action, during the 180 days, against the person or insurer.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-480">
            <num>34.35.480</num>
            <heading>Enforcement of lien.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-480__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A lien under
AS 34.35.450
  34.35.480 may be foreclosed or enforced by an action brought by the claimant, a representative, or assignee within one year after the filing of the lien.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-480__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In the action, upon entering a decree for the plaintiff, the court shall allow as part of the costs, all money paid for the filing and recording of the lien notice, together with a reasonable attorney fee.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-481">
            <num>34.35.481</num>
            <heading>Priority of liens.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.481.   Priority of liens.
A lien perfected by the Department of Health under
AS 47.05.075
has priority immediately after a lien perfected by a hospital, nurse, or physician under
AS 34.35.450
 34.35.480.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-482">
            <num>34.35.482</num>
            <heading>Definition.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.482.   Definition.
In
AS 34.35.450
 34.35.482, physician means a person licensed as a chiropractor under
AS 08.20
or a person licensed as a doctor of medicine under
AS 08.64
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-510">
            <num>34.35.510</num>
            <heading>Hotel and boardinghouse operator's liens.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.510.   Hotel and boardinghouse operator's liens.
The operator of a hotel or boardinghouse has a lien upon, and may retain, all baggage and other property lawfully in the possession of a guest for all proper charges owed by the guest to the hotel or boardinghouse operator.  However, this section does not apply when the baggage or other property is not owned by the guest and the hotel or boardinghouse operator has actual notice of this fact.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-520">
            <num>34.35.520</num>
            <heading>Disposition of property to satisfy liens.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-520__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a lien under
AS 34.35.510
is not satisfied within 60 days after the charges become due, the hotel or boardinghouse operator may proceed to sell the baggage or other property held under the lien at public auction.  Ten days before the sale the hotel or boardinghouse operator shall give notice of the time and place of sale by posting notice in three public places in the town or city where the hotel or boardinghouse is located and by mailing notice of the time and place to the owner of the baggage or other property at the place of residence as set out in the hotel or boardinghouse register. If the guest failed to register or to give sufficient address, the required notice shall be mailed to the guest at the city or town where the hotel or boardinghouse is located.  When the notice requirements of this section have been complied with, the sale of the baggage or other property is a perpetual bar to an action against the hotel or boardinghouse operator for recovery of baggage, property, or their value.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-520__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After satisfaction of the lien and payment of all legal charges for storage and expenses incurred in selling the property, the remaining proceeds of the sale shall, within one year, be paid to the guest upon demand.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-530">
            <num>34.35.530</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.530.   Definitions.
In
AS 34.35.510
  34.35.530,
(1) guest includes every person who is a member of the family of, or dependent upon, a guest, boarder, or lodger in a hotel or boardinghouse;
(2) hotel or boardinghouse includes any building held out to the public to be an inn, motel, hotel, or public lodginghouse, or place where sleeping accommodations, whether with or without meals, are furnished for hire to transient guests;
(3) operator includes innkeeper, proprietor, keeper, owner, lessee, or manager of a hotel or boardinghouse.
Article 14. Miscellaneous Provisions.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-900">
            <num>34.35.900</num>
            <heading>Acknowledgment of satisfaction.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-900__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When a lien is satisfied by payment, an acknowledgment of satisfaction suitable for recordation shall be delivered to all parties to the lien by the lien claimant. The acknowledgment of satisfaction shall be delivered immediately upon payment by tender of cash in satisfaction of the claim or within 10 days after payment when satisfaction is obtained in some other manner. A certificate of discharge of a lien for nonpayment of a state tax or license fee recorded under
AS 43.10.042
shall be delivered within 15 days after tender of cash in satisfaction of the claim or within 30 days when satisfaction is obtained in some other manner. The acknowledgment must identify all parties to the lien and any property subject to the lien using the same name or description contained in the claim of record, if a claim was made, and the book and page of the official record containing the claim or the serial number assigned to the claim by the recorder.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-900__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A lien claimant or assignee who, after payment in full of the lien claim and after written demand by a person liable upon the lien, fails without just cause for a period of 30 days to execute and file or record an acknowledgment of satisfaction in the recording district in which the claim of lien is filed or recorded is liable to the person making the demand or the grantees or heirs of that person for all damages that they may sustain by reason of that failure and shall also forfeit to them the sum of $100.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-910">
            <num>34.35.910</num>
            <heading>Employment considered continuous.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-910__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The fact that a lien claimant is employed at different kinds of labor or at different rates of wages during the period of general employment is not considered an interruption of the continuity of employment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-910__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A temporary cessation of employment of the lien claimant under an understanding of resumption of employment within a reasonable time is not considered an interruption of the continuity of employment so as to cause the time to run within which the notice of the lien is required to be filed for record.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-920">
            <num>34.35.920</num>
            <heading>Waiver of lien.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.920.   Waiver of lien.
Except as provided under
AS 34.35.117
and 34.35.119, an agreement by a person mentioned in
AS 34.35.010
 34.35.425 to waive the right to acquire a lien provided in
AS 34.35.010
  34.35.425 is invalid.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-930">
            <num>34.35.930</num>
            <heading>Liberal construction of chapter.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 34.35.930.   Liberal construction of chapter.
The intent of this chapter is remedial and its provisions shall be liberally construed.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_34-35-950">
            <num>34.35.950</num>
            <heading>Nonconsensual common law liens.</heading>
            <subsection eId="34-35-950__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A nonconsensual common law lien is invalid unless the lien is authorized by an order of a court of competent jurisdiction recognized under state or federal law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-950__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not submit a nonconsensual common law lien under
AS 40.17
to the recorder in order to record the lien unless the lien is accompanied by a specific order authorizing the recording of the lien issued by a court of competent jurisdiction recognized under state or federal law. When a nonconsensual common law lien is submitted for recording under this subsection, the court order accompanying the lien shall be recorded with the lien.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-950__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not submit a nonconsensual common law lien under a law authorizing the filing of a lien against personal property in order to file the lien unless the lien is accompanied by a specific order authorizing the filing of the lien issued by a court of competent jurisdiction recognized under state or federal law. When a nonconsensual common law lien is submitted for filing under this subsection, the court order accompanying the lien shall be filed with the lien.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="34-35-950__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-950__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>filed means the acceptance of a document by a department or person having responsibility for the receipt and filing of documents that may be filed and that are presented for filing in the place of filing designated by law, whether or not under applicable law the department or person is directed to file the document;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-950__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>nonconsensual common law lien means a lien on real or personal property that
(A) is not provided for by a specific state or federal statute or municipal ordinance;
(B) does not depend on the consent of the owner of the property affected for its existence; and
(C) is not an equitable, constructive, or other lien imposed by a court recognized under state or federal law;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-950__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>record means the acceptance of a document by the recorder that the recorder has determined is recordable under
AS 40.17
and that is presented for recording in the place of recording designated for the recording district where affected property is located whether or not the place of recording is in that district and whether or not under applicable law the recorder is directed to record the document;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="34-35-950__subsec_d__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>recorder means the commissioner of natural resources or the person designated by the commissioner of natural resources to perform the duties set out in
AS 40.17
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>