<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-47/chapter-05"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-47/chapter-05"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="47.05"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-47/chapter-05/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-47/chapter-05/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-47/chapter-05/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-47/chapter-05/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_47">
        <num>47</num>
        <heading>Welfare, Social Services, and Institutions</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_47__chp_05">
          <num>05</num>
          <heading>Administration of Welfare, Social Services, and Institutions</heading>
          <section eId="sec_47-05-010">
            <num>47.05.010</num>
            <heading>Duties of Department of Health.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.05.010.   Duties of Department of Health.
The Department of Health shall
(1) administer adult public assistance, the Alaska temporary assistance program, and all other assistance programs, and receive and spend money made available to it;
(2) adopt regulations necessary for the conduct of its business and for carrying out federal and state laws granting adult public assistance, temporary cash assistance, diversion payments, or self-sufficiency services for needy families under the Alaska temporary assistance program, and other assistance;
(3) establish minimum standards for personnel employed by the department and adopt necessary regulations to maintain those standards;
(4) require those bonds and undertakings from persons employed by it that, in its judgment, are necessary, and pay the premiums on them;
(5) cooperate with the federal government in matters of mutual concern pertaining to adult public assistance, the Alaska temporary assistance program, and other forms of public assistance;
(6) make the reports, in the form and containing the information, that the federal government from time to time requires;
(7) cooperate with the federal government in adopting state plans to make the state eligible for federal matching in appropriate categories of assistance, and in all matters of mutual concern, including adoption of the methods of administration that are found by the federal government to be necessary for the efficient operation of welfare programs;
(8) adopt regulations, not inconsistent with law, defining need, prescribing the conditions of eligibility for assistance, and establishing standards for determining the amount of assistance that an eligible person is entitled to receive; the amount of the assistance is sufficient when, added to all other income and resources available to an individual, it provides the individual with a reasonable subsistence compatible with health and well-being; an individual who meets the requirements for eligibility for assistance shall be granted the assistance promptly upon application for it;
(9) grant to a person claiming or receiving assistance and who is aggrieved because of the department's action or failure to act, reasonable notice and an opportunity for a fair hearing by the office of administrative hearings (
AS 44.64.010
), and the department shall adopt regulations relative to this;
(10) enter into reciprocal agreements with other states relative to public assistance that are considered advisable;
(11) establish the requirements of residence for public assistance that are considered advisable, subject to the limitations of other laws of the state, or law or regulation imposed as conditions for federal financial participation;
(12) establish the divisions and local offices that are considered necessary or expedient to carry out a duty or authority assigned to it and appoint and employ the assistants and personnel that are necessary to carry on the work of the divisions and offices, and fix the compensation of the assistants or employees, except that a person engaged in business as a retail vendor of general merchandise, or a member of the immediate family of a person who is so engaged, may not serve as an acting, temporary, or permanent local agent of the department, unless the commissioner of health certifies in writing to the governor, with relation to a particular community, that no other qualified person is available in the community to serve as local welfare agent; for the purposes of this paragraph, a member of the immediate family includes a spouse, child, parent, brother, sister, parent-in-law, brother-in-law, or sister-in-law;
(13) provide education and health-related services and referrals designed to reduce the number of out-of-wedlock pregnancies and the number of induced pregnancy terminations in the state;
(14) investigate reports of abuse, neglect, or misappropriation of property by certified nurse aides in facilities licensed by the department under
AS 47.32
;
(15) establish state policy relating to and administer federal programs subject to state control as provided under 42 U.S.C. 3001  3058ee (Older Americans Act of 1965), as amended, and related federal regulations;
(16) administer the older Alaskans service grants under
AS 47.65.010
 47.65.050 and the adult day care and family respite care grants under
AS 47.65.100
;
(17) establish an electronic application process for all assistance programs administered by the department and allow an applicant to submit either a written or an electronic application; the electronic application must inform an applicant that a false statement made on the application will be investigated and is punishable under
AS 11.56.210
; in this paragraph, electronic application means an application for benefits or renewal of benefits, whether the department exclusively administers the benefits or administers the benefits in coordination with another state agency or federal agency, electronically completed and submitted through the department's Internet website.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-05-012">
            <num>47.05.012</num>
            <heading>Material incorporated by reference.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.05.012.   Material incorporated by reference.
Under
AS 44.62.245
(a)(2), in adopting or amending a regulation that incorporates a document or other material by reference, the department may incorporate future amended versions of the document or other material if the document or other material is one of the following:
(1) a document that is published, compiled, or prepared by the United States Department of Health and Human Services and is included in the following list:
(A) the international classification of diseases, clinical modifications;
(B) the common procedure coding system;
(C) the specifications for national uniform billing data elements;
(D) the federal poverty guidelines for the state;
(E) the Indian Health Service encounter rates; or
(F) the relative value units used in the Medicare program for determination of fee schedules;
(2) the current procedural terminology for physicians published by the American Medical Association;
(3) the diagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders published by the American Psychiatric Association;
(4) the length of stay in hospitals by diagnosis and operation for the western region of the United States, published by Solucient;
(5) the relative value guide published by the American Society of Anesthesiologists;
(6) the consumer price index published by the United States Department of Labor;
(7) the health plan employer data and information set published by the National Committee for Quality Assurance;
(8) practice standards adopted by the American Academy of Pediatrics, American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, American Diabetes Association, American Cancer Society, American Academy of Family Physicians, American College of Physicians, United States Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality, or the National Asthma Education and Prevention Program;
(9) the compendium of animal rabies prevention and control published by the United States Centers for Disease Control and Prevention;
(10) the control of communicable diseases manual published by the American Public Health Association;
(11) the standards manual and interpretative guidelines for behavioral health, employment and community support services, and for medical rehabilitation published by the Commission on Accreditation of Rehabilitative Facilities;
(12) consumer assessment of health plans published by the Agency for Health Care Policy and Research;
(13) resources for optimal care of the injured patient published by the Committee on Trauma, American College of Surgeons;
(14) a document related to a resuscitation protocol that is published, compiled, or prepared based on the recommendations from the International Liaison Committee on Resuscitation;
(15)  the preferred drug list adopted by the department under
AS 47.07.065
(b); or
(16)  a prior authorization medications list under a state program permitted under 42 U.S.C. 1396r-8 (Title XIX, Social Security Act).</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-05-015">
            <num>47.05.015</num>
            <heading>Contracts.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-05-015__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may contract with a person or local government for the delivery of services to be provided by the department under
AS 47.05.010
if the commissioner determines the service will be provided at less cost to the state or will be provided in a more effective manner.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-015__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Services that may be provided by contract under this section include accepting applications for assistance, conducting interviews, making eligibility determinations, and issuing benefits, but do not include adoption of program standards or other matters involving the exercise of agency discretion.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-015__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A contract authorized under this section is exempt from the competitive bid requirements of
AS 36.30
(State Procurement Code). In awarding a contract under this section the department shall request proposals in accordance with regulations of the Department of Administration under
AS 36.30
(State Procurement Code).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-015__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This section does not limit the authority provided by law for the department to contract for the delivery of services other than those provided under
AS 47.05.010
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-05-017">
            <num>47.05.017</num>
            <heading>Home care providers.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-05-017__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>State money may not be used for a home care provider unless criminal history record information as permitted by P.L. 105-277 and
AS 12.62
is requested for the provider within 10 business days after the provider is hired to provide the care and is reviewed within five business days after it is received. The department shall require the grantee or contractor to do the information request and review required under this subsection for a home care provider employed by a person who has a grant or contract from the department to provide home care services.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-017__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall adopt regulations identifying actions that it will take, in addition to those otherwise required under
AS 47.17
and
AS 47.24
, when a report of harm is made under
AS 47.17
or
AS 47.24
that might relate to harm caused by actions or inactions of a public home care provider. The regulations must</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-017__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>address circumstances under which the department will, or will require a contractor or grantee to, reassign, suspend, or terminate a person alleged to have perpetrated harm;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-017__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>include appropriate procedural safeguards to protect the due process rights of public home care providers who may be reassigned, suspended, or terminated under the circumstances described in (1) of this subsection; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-017__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if the home care provider is a certified nurse aide, include procedures under which the department shall notify the Board of Nursing if the nurse aide is suspected of abuse, neglect, or misappropriation of property.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-017__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, public home care provider means a person who is paid by the state, or by an entity that has contracted with the state or received a grant from state funds, to provide homemaker services, chore services, personal care services, home health care services, or similar services in or around a client's private residence or to provide respite care in either the client's residence or the caregiver's residence or facility.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-05-020">
            <num>47.05.020</num>
            <heading>Regulations concerning records; disclosure of information.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-05-020__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The power of the department to adopt regulations includes the power to adopt and enforce reasonable regulations governing the custody, use, and preservation of the records, papers, files, and communications of the department. The regulations must provide that financial information concerning an eligibility determination of a person applying for or receiving cash assistance, a diversion payment, or self-sufficiency services under the Alaska temporary assistance program shall be disclosed to a legislator on request of the legislator in connection with official purposes within the scope of the legislator's legislative functions and related to the administration of the program consistent with federal law. When, under the law, names and addresses of recipients of public assistance are furnished to or held by another agency or department of government, the agency or department of government shall adopt regulations necessary to prevent the publication of the lists or their use for purposes not directly connected with the administration of public assistance and legislative functions. A legislator to whom information relating to the Alaska temporary assistance program is disclosed under this section may not further disclose the information except to another legislator and then only in connection with official purposes within each legislator's legislative functions and related to the administration of the program consistent with federal law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-020__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to any access to public assistance records authorized under (a) of this section, the department shall provide a copy of a public assistance record prepared or maintained by or on behalf of the department to the child support services agency created in
AS 25.27.010
, or the child support enforcement agency of another state, upon the request of the respective agency. If the record is in an electronic data base, the department shall provide the requesting agency with either access to the data base, or a copy of the information in the data base and a statement certifying its contents. The agency receiving the information under this subsection may use the information only for child support purposes authorized under law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-05-030">
            <num>47.05.030</num>
            <heading>Misuse of public assistance lists and records.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-05-030__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (b) and (c) of this section and for purposes directly connected with the administration of general assistance, adult public assistance, the child care assistance program authorized under
AS 47.25.001
 47.25.095, or the Alaska temporary assistance program, and in accordance with the regulations of the department, a person may not solicit, disclose, receive, make use of, or authorize, knowingly permit, participate in, or acquiesce in the use of, a list of or names of, or information concerning, persons applying for or receiving the assistance directly or indirectly derived from the records, papers, files, or communications of the department or subdivisions or agencies of the department, or acquired in the course of the performance of official duties.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-030__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>It is not a violation of (a) of this section for the department or an employee of the department to disclose to a legislator, or for a legislator to solicit, receive, or make use of, financial information concerning an eligibility determination of a person applying for or receiving cash assistance, a diversion payment, or self-sufficiency services under the Alaska temporary assistance program if the disclosure, solicitation, receipt, and use are for official purposes in connection with the legislator's official functions and related to the administration of the program consistent with federal law. Information provided to a legislator under this subsection shall remain confidential and may not be further disclosed except as provided in
AS 47.05.020
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-030__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>It is not a violation of (a) of this section for the department or an employee of the department to disclose information to the child support services agency created in
AS 25.27.010
, or the child support enforcement agency of another state, if the receiving agency requests the information only for purposes authorized under
AS 47.05.020
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-05-032">
            <num>47.05.032</num>
            <heading>Disclosures to legislators.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.05.032.   Disclosures to legislators.
A legislator to whom confidential information is disclosed under
AS 47.05.020
 47.05.030 is not subject to a penalty for further disclosure of the information unless, at the time the information was provided to the legislator, the legislator was given written notification that the material was confidential.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-05-040">
            <num>47.05.040</num>
            <heading>Consent to conditions of federal programs.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.05.040.   Consent to conditions of federal programs.
In order to take advantage of the training grants provisions of 42 U.S.C. 301  1397f (Social Security Act), as amended, the state, through the department, consents and agrees to all conditions required by federal statute and regulation necessary for the state to participate fully in the training grants or other programs.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-05-050">
            <num>47.05.050</num>
            <heading>Cooperation with federal government.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.05.050.   Cooperation with federal government.
It is the public policy of the state to cooperate and coordinate with the United States government and its agencies in providing for and administering federal and state laws for adult public assistance and the other assistance that is provided for or extended to the people of the state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-05-055">
            <num>47.05.055</num>
            <heading>Certified nurse aides.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-05-055__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the department has reason to believe that a certified nurse aide employed in a facility licensed by the department under
AS 47.32
as a hospital or nursing home has committed abuse, neglect, or misappropriation of property in connection with the person's duties as a certified nurse aide at the facility, the department shall investigate the matter. The department shall conduct proceedings to determine whether a finding of abuse, neglect, or misappropriation of property should be made. These proceedings shall be conducted under
AS 44.62.330
 44.62.630. A finding under this subsection that a certified nurse aide has committed abuse, neglect, or misappropriation of property shall be reported by the department to the Board of Nursing.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-055__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the certified nurse aide is employed in a skilled nursing facility or nursing facility, other than an intermediate care facility for persons with intellectual and developmental disabilities, that is participating in the Medicaid or Medicare program, only the state survey and certification agency may make, and report to the Board of Nursing, a finding that a certified nurse aide has committed abuse, neglect, or misappropriation of property in connection with the nurse aide's employment at the facility.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-05-070">
            <num>47.05.070</num>
            <heading>Third party liability subrogation.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-05-070__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may not pay medical claims that are payable by a third party payor. Medical providers shall attempt collection from the third party payor before billing Medicaid. Before payment by Medicaid, evidence of third-party denial or partial payment shall be presented with the claim.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-070__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the department provides or pays for medical assistance for injury or illness under this title, the department is subrogated to not more than the part of an insurance payment or other recovery by the recipient that is for medical expenses provided by the department. Notwithstanding the assertion of any action or claim by the recipient of medical assistance, the department may bring an action in the superior court against an alleged third-party payor to recover an amount subrogated to the department for medical assistance provided on behalf of a recipient.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-070__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a recipient of medical assistance under this title settles a claim or obtains an award or judgment arising from the injury or illness for which the medical assistance was received, the amount of the claim to which the department is entitled under (b) of this section shall be reduced by a pro rata share of the attorney fees and litigation costs. Regardless of the manner in which the amount of the attorney fees is derived in the particular case, the pro rata reduction of the subrogated claim for reimbursement of attorney fees shall be calculated in accordance with the applicable rules of court governing the award of attorney fees in civil matters.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-070__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department is authorized to enter into contracts for the collection of medical expenses already paid by Medicaid from potential third-party payors. The department may pay, from the funds recovered by the contractor, any amounts owing to the federal government as its share of the Medicaid paid claim, and the costs of collecting the funds.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-070__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 9 ch 96 SLA 2006.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-070__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may adopt regulations to interpret and implement this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-05-071">
            <num>47.05.071</num>
            <heading>Duty of a medical assistance recipient.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-05-071__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A medical assistance recipient shall cooperate with and assist the department in identifying and providing information concerning third parties who may be liable to pay for care and services received by the recipient under the medical assistance program.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-071__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>As a condition of medical assistance eligibility, a person who applies for medical assistance shall, at the time of application,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-071__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>assign to the department the applicant's rights of payment for care and services from any third party to the extent the department has paid medical assistance for care and services;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-071__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>cooperate with and assist the department in identifying and providing information concerning third parties who may be liable to pay for care and services received by the recipient under the medical assistance program; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-071__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>agree to make application for all other available third-party resources that may be used to provide or pay for the cost of care or services received by the medical assistance recipient or that may be used to finance reimbursement to the state for the cost of care or services received by the medical assistance recipient; a medical assistance recipient is under no duty to file a civil or other action for the purpose of reimbursing the state for the cost of care or services.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-05-072">
            <num>47.05.072</num>
            <heading>Duty of attorney for medical assistance recipient.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-05-072__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An attorney representing a medical assistance recipient shall notify the attorney general's office.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-072__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The notice to the attorney general's office required under (a) of this section includes submission of the following:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-072__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>identification of the medical assistance recipient's name, last known address, and telephone number, and the date of the injury or illness giving rise to the action or claim;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-072__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>copies of the pleadings and other papers related to the action or claim;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-072__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the identification of each potentially liable third party, including that party's name, last known address, and telephone number;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-072__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the identification of any insurance policy potentially responsive to the action or claim; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-072__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a description of the facts and circumstances supporting the action or claim.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-072__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An attorney who represents a medical assistance recipient shall give the attorney general's office notice within 30 days of any judgment, award, or settlement in an action or claim by the medical assistance recipient to recover damages for an injury or illness that has resulted in the department's providing or paying for medical assistance.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-072__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a medical assistance recipient is handling the action or claim on a pro se basis, the provisions of this section apply as if the medical assistance recipient were an attorney representing the medical assistance recipient.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-05-073">
            <num>47.05.073</num>
            <heading>Judgment, award, or settlement of a medical assistance lien.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-05-073__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A medical assistance recipient may not maintain any rights to payment for medical costs as a result of a judgment, award, or settlement of an action or claim for which another person may be legally obligated to pay without first making repayment to the department for costs of past medical assistance services provided to or paid for on behalf of the medical assistance recipient that relate to that action or claim.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-073__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A medical assistance recipient may not place any payment as a result of a judgment, award, or settlement of an action or claim for which another person was legally obligated to pay because of injury or illness into any trust for the purpose of maintaining public assistance or medical assistance eligibility without first making repayment to the department for costs of past medical assistance services provided to the medical assistance recipient related to that action or claim.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-073__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The attorney general may only discharge a medical assistance lien under
AS 47.05.075
if the discharge complies with federal law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-073__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (a)  (c) of this section, a third-party payor shall have no further liability if it settles or compromises a dispute in good faith and without knowledge that the individual is a recipient of medical assistance.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-05-074">
            <num>47.05.074</num>
            <heading>Conflict with federal requirements.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.05.074.   Conflict with federal requirements.
If any provision of this chapter related to subrogation, assignment, or lien conflicts with federal law concerning the Medicaid program or receipt of federal money to finance the medical assistance program, the provision does not apply to the extent of the conflict.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-05-075">
            <num>47.05.075</num>
            <heading>Medical assistance lien.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-05-075__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department has a lien upon any sum that may be due to the recipient of medical assistance from a third-party payor. The lien is in the amount of the medical assistance paid for medical services under this title, together with reasonable attorney fees and litigation costs incurred in the enforcement of the lien.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-075__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A lien against a sum due from a third-party payor for medical services provided to a recipient of medical assistance under this title attaches and is effective upon filing with a recorder's office in any recording district in the state. However, a lien filed under this subsection is not perfected and has no effect unless notice of filing of the lien is served by the department upon the third-party payor, personally or by registered, certified, or insured mail, return receipt requested.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-075__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a recipient of medical assistance under this title settles a claim or obtains an award or judgment arising from the injury or illness for which the medical assistance was received, the amount of the lien to which the department is entitled under (a) of this section shall be reduced by a pro rata share of the attorney fees and litigation costs. Regardless of the manner in which the amount of the attorney fees is derived in the particular case, the pro rata reduction of the lien shall be calculated in accordance with the applicable rules of court governing the award of attorney fees in civil matters.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-075__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A perfected lien under this section has priority over all other liens except tax liens and a lien perfected for attorney fees and costs.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-05-080">
            <num>47.05.080</num>
            <heading>Recovery of overpayments.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-05-080__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except for overpayments recovered under
AS 47.07
that cover the value of services paid from federal sources, benefit overpayments collected by the department in administering public assistance programs under
AS 47.05.010
shall be remitted to the Department of Revenue under
AS 37.10.050
(a).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-080__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The permanent fund dividend of a former recipient of a public assistance program listed under (a) of this section may be taken under
AS 43.23.140
(b)(6) and 43.23.170 to satisfy the balance due on a defaulted overpayment claim.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-05-085">
            <num>47.05.085</num>
            <heading>Subpoena power.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-05-085__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner or the commissioner's designee at the director level may issue subpoenas to compel the production of books, papers, correspondence, memoranda, and other records considered necessary as evidence in connection with an investigation under or the administration of
AS 47.07
(medical assistance),
AS 47.08
(assistance for catastrophic illnesses and acute or chronic medical conditions),
AS 47.25
(child care assistance, child care grants, general relief, adult public assistance, and food stamps), and
AS 47.27
(Alaska temporary assistance program).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-085__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In case of refusal to obey a subpoena issued to any person under (a) of this section, the superior court may, upon application by the department, issue an order requiring the person to appear before the department to produce evidence if ordered. Failure to obey the order of the court is punishable as contempt.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-085__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who, without just cause, fails or refuses to produce books, papers, correspondence, memoranda, and other records, if it is in the person's power to do so, in obedience to a subpoena of the department or an authorized representative of it, upon conviction, is punishable by a fine of not more than $200, or by imprisonment for not more than 60 days, or by both. Each day the failure or refusal continues is a separate offense.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-05-090">
            <num>47.05.090</num>
            <heading>Authorization of the Interstate Compact on Adoption and Medical Assistance.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-05-090__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Health and the Department of Family and Community services may cooperate and, on behalf of the state, enter into the Interstate Compact on Adoption and Medical Assistance and supplementary agreements with agencies of other states for the provision of adoption and medical assistance under
AS 47.07
and other provisions of this title for eligible children with special needs.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-090__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, state includes a state, territory, possession, or commonwealth of the United States.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-05-105">
            <num>47.05.105</num>
            <heading>Enhanced computerized eligibility verification system.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-05-105__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall establish an enhanced computerized income, asset, and identity eligibility verification system for the purposes of verifying eligibility, eliminating duplication of public assistance payments, and deterring waste and fraud in public assistance programs administered by the department under
AS 47.05.010
. Nothing in this section prohibits the department from verifying eligibility for public assistance through additional procedures or authorizes the department or a third-party vendor to use data to verify eligibility for a federal program if the use of that data is prohibited by federal law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-105__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall enter into a competitively bid contract with a third-party vendor for the purpose of developing a system under this section to prevent fraud, misrepresentation, and inadequate documentation when determining an applicant's eligibility for public assistance before the payment of benefits and for periodically verifying eligibility between eligibility redeterminations and during eligibility redeterminations and reviews. The department may also contract with a third-party vendor to provide information to facilitate reviews of recipient eligibility and income verification.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-105__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The annual savings to the state resulting from the use of the system under this section must exceed the cost of implementing the system. A contract under this section must require the third-party vendor to report annual savings to the state realized from implementing the system. Payment to the third-party vendor may be based on a fee for each applicant and may include incentives for achieving a rate of success established by the department for identifying duplication, waste, and fraud in public assistance programs.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-105__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To avoid a conflict of interest, the department may not award a contract to provide services for the enrollment of public assistance providers or applicants under this title to a vendor that is awarded a contract under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-05-110">
            <num>47.05.110</num>
            <heading>Alaska Tribal Child Welfare Compact.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.05.110.   Alaska Tribal Child Welfare Compact.
The state may participate in a tribal child welfare compact with Alaska tribes and tribal organizations for the administration of child welfare services by the tribes or tribal organizations. The compact is a written agreement between the state and Alaska tribes and tribal organizations that affirms the government-to-government relationship between the state and tribes.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-05-115">
            <num>47.05.115</num>
            <heading>Access to identifiable health information.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.05.115.   Access to identifiable health information.
Notwithstanding a contrary provision of law, the Department of Health and the Department of Family and Community Services shall share identifiable health information, regardless of the confidential nature of the information, between and within the departments as necessary to enable administration or operation of the sending or receiving department. Information shared in accordance with this section shall be acquired, used, disclosed, and stored in a confidential manner that safeguards the security of the information in a physically, administratively, and technologically secure environment. In this section, identifiable health information has the meaning given in
AS 18.15.395
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-05-190">
            <num>47.05.190</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.05.190.   Definitions.
In
AS 47.05.010
- 47.05.190,
(1) commissioner means the commissioner of the Department of Health;
(2) department means the Department of Health.
Article 2. Oversight of Medical Care Programs.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-05-200">
            <num>47.05.200</num>
            <heading>Annual audits.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-05-200__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall annually contract for independent audits of a statewide sample of all medical assistance providers in order to identify overpayments and violations of criminal statutes. The audits conducted under this section may not be conducted by the department or employees of the department. The number of audits under this section may not be less than 50 each year. The audits under this section must include both on-site audits and desk audits and must be of a variety of provider types. The department may not award a contract under this subsection to an organization that does not retain persons with a significant level of expertise and recent professional practice in the general areas of standard accounting principles and financial auditing and in the specific areas of medical records review, investigative research, and Alaska health care criminal law. The contractor, in consultation with the commissioner, shall select the providers to be audited and decide the ratio of desk audits and on-site audits to the total number selected. In identifying providers who are subject to an audit under this section, the department shall attempt to minimize concurrent state or federal audits.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-200__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Within 90 days after receiving each audit report from an audit conducted under this section, the department shall begin administrative procedures to recoup overpayments identified in the audits and shall allocate the reasonable and necessary financial and human resources to ensure prompt recovery of overpayments unless the attorney general has advised the commissioner in writing that a criminal investigation of an audited provider has been or is about to be undertaken, in which case, the commissioner shall hold the administrative procedure in abeyance until a final charging decision by the attorney general has been made. The commissioner shall provide copies of all audit reports to the attorney general so that the reports can be screened for the purpose of bringing criminal charges. The department may assess interest and penalties on any identified overpayment. Interest under this subsection shall be calculated using the statutory rates for postjudgment interest accruing from the date of the issuance of the final agency decision to recoup overpayments identified in the audit. In this subsection, the date of issuance of the final agency decision is the later of the date of</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-200__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the department's written notification of the decision and the provider's appeal rights; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-200__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if timely appealed by the provider, a final agency decision under
AS 44.64.060
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-200__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each fiscal year, the state's share of recovered overpayments obtained because of the required contract audits under this section shall be deposited with the commissioner of revenue under
AS 37.10.050
and separately accounted for by the commissioner of administration under
AS 37.05.142
. The legislature may appropriate a portion of the estimated balance in the account to the department to pay for the annual audits described in this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-200__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>As a condition of obtaining payment under
AS 47.07
and
AS 47.08
and for purposes of this section, a provider shall allow</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-200__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the department reasonable access to the records of medical assistance recipients and providers; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-200__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>audit and inspection of the records by state and federal agencies.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-200__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This section does not preclude the department from performing audits that are allowed or required under other laws.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-05-210">
            <num>47.05.210</num>
            <heading>Medical assistance fraud.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-05-210__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person commits the crime of medical assistance fraud if the person</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-210__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>knowingly submits or authorizes the submission of a claim to a medical assistance agency for property, services, or a benefit with reckless disregard that the claimant is not entitled to the property, services, or benefit;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-210__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>knowingly prepares or assists another person to prepare a claim for submission to a medical assistance agency for property, services, or a benefit with reckless disregard that the claimant is not entitled to the property, services, or benefit;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-210__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>except as otherwise authorized under the medical assistance program, confers, offers to confer, solicits, agrees to accept, or accepts property, services, or a benefit
(A) to refer a medical assistance recipient to a health care provider; or
(B) for providing health care to a medical assistance recipient if the property, services, or benefit is in addition to payment by a medical assistance agency;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-210__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>does not produce medical assistance records to a person authorized to request the records;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-210__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>knowingly makes a false entry in or falsely alters a medical assistance record;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-210__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>knowingly destroys, mutilates, suppresses, conceals, removes, or otherwise impairs the verity, legibility, or availability of a medical assistance record knowing that the person lacks the authority to do so; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-210__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>violates a provision of
AS 47.07
or
AS 47.08
or a regulation adopted under
AS 47.07
or
AS 47.08
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-210__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Medical assistance fraud under (a)(1), (2), or (3) of this section is</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-210__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a class B felony if the portion of the claim or claims submitted in violation of (a)(1) or (2) of this section, or the value of the property, services, or benefit that is in violation of (a)(3) of this section, is $25,000 or more;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-210__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a class C felony if the portion of the claim or claims submitted in violation of (a)(1) or (2) of this section, or the value of the property, services, or benefit that is in violation of (a)(3) of this section, is $500 or more but less than $25,000;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-210__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a class A misdemeanor if the portion of the claim or claims submitted in violation of (a)(1) or (2) of this section, or the value of the property, services, or benefit that is in violation of (a)(3) of this section, is less than $500.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-210__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Medical assistance fraud under (a)(4), (5), or (6) of this section is a class A misdemeanor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-210__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Medical assistance fraud under (a)(7) of this section is a class B misdemeanor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-05-220">
            <num>47.05.220</num>
            <heading>Notice of charges.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.05.220.   Notice of charges.
Upon the filing of a complaint, information, presentment, or indictment charging a medical assistance provider with a crime under
AS 47.05.210
, the attorney general shall, in writing, notify the commissioner of the filing. Upon receiving notice from the attorney general under this section, the commissioner shall immediately undertake a review of all unpaid claims or requests for reimbursements attributable to services claimed to have been provided by the person charged.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-05-230">
            <num>47.05.230</num>
            <heading>Determination of value; aggregation of amounts.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.05.230.   Determination of value; aggregation of amounts.
In
AS 47.05.210
, whenever it is necessary to determine the value of property, that value shall be determined in accordance with
AS 11.46.980
. In determining the degree or classification of a crime described under
AS 47.05.210
, amounts involved in criminal acts committed under one course of conduct, whether from the same person or several persons, shall be aggregated.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-05-235">
            <num>47.05.235</num>
            <heading>Duty to identify and repay self-identified overpayments.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-05-235__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless a provider is being audited under
AS 47.05.200
(a), an enrolled medical assistance provider shall conduct a biennial review or audit of a statistically valid sample of claims submitted to the department for reimbursement. If overpayments are identified, the medical assistance provider shall report the overpayment to the department not later than 10 business days after identification of the overpayment. The report must also identify how the medical assistance provider intends to repay the department. After the department receives the report, the medical assistance provider and the department shall enter into an agreement establishing a schedule for repayment of the identified overpayment. The agreement may authorize repayment in a lump sum, in a payment plan, or by offsetting future billings, as approved by the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-235__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may not assess interest or penalties on an overpayment identified and repaid by a medical assistance provider under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-05-240">
            <num>47.05.240</num>
            <heading>Exclusion from medical assistance programs.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-05-240__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner may exclude an applicant to or disenroll a medical assistance provider in the medical assistance program in
AS 47.07
or
AS 47.08
, or both, for a period of up to 10 years after unconditional discharge on a conviction</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-240__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for medical assistance fraud under
AS 47.05.210
or misconduct involving a controlled substance under
AS 11.71
; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-240__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in a court of the United States or a court of another state or territory, for a crime with elements similar to the crimes included under (1) of this subsection.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-240__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After a period of exclusion under (a) of this section, an applicant may not participate in a medical assistance program under
AS 47.07
or
AS 47.08
until the applicant establishes to the commissioner by clear and convincing evidence that the applicant possesses all required licenses and certificates and is qualified to participate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-05-250">
            <num>47.05.250</num>
            <heading>Civil penalties.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-05-250__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may assess a civil penalty against a provider who violates this chapter,
AS 47.07
, or regulations adopted under this chapter or
AS 47.07
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-250__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall adopt regulations establishing a range of civil penalties that the department may assess against a provider under this section. In establishing the range of civil penalties, the department shall take into account appropriate factors, including the seriousness of the violation, the service provided by the provider, and the severity of the penalty. The regulations may not provide for a civil penalty of less than $100 or more than $25,000 for each violation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-250__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The provisions of this section are in addition to any other remedies available under this chapter,
AS 47.07
, or regulations adopted under this chapter or
AS 47.07
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-250__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A provider against whom a civil penalty of less than $2,500 is assessed may appeal the decision assessing the penalty to the commissioner or the commissioner's designee. The commissioner shall, by regulation, establish time limits and procedures for an appeal under this subsection. The decision of the commissioner or the commissioner's designee may be appealed to the office of administrative hearings established under
AS 44.64
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-250__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A provider against whom a civil penalty of $2,500 or more is assessed may appeal the decision assessing the penalty to the office of administrative hearings established under
AS 44.64
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-05-270">
            <num>47.05.270</num>
            <heading>Medical assistance reform program.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-05-270__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall adopt regulations to design and implement a program for reforming the state medical assistance program under
AS 47.07
. The reform program must include</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-270__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>referrals to community and social support services, including career and education training services available through the Department of Labor and Workforce Development under
AS 23.15
, the University of Alaska, or other sources;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-270__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>electronic distribution of an explanation of medical assistance benefits to recipients for health care services received under the program;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-270__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>expanding the use of telehealth for primary care, behavioral health, and urgent care;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-270__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>enhancing fraud prevention, detection, and enforcement;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-270__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>reducing the cost of behavioral health, senior, and disabilities services provided to recipients of medical assistance under the state's home and community-based services waiver under
AS 47.07.045
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-270__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>pharmacy initiatives;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-270__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>enhanced care management;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-270__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>redesigning the payment process by implementing fee agreements that include one or more of the following:
(A) premium payments for centers of excellence;
(B) penalties for hospital-acquired infections, readmissions, and outcome failures;
(C) bundled payments for specific episodes of care; or
(D) global payments for contracted payers, primary care managers, and case managers for a recipient or for care related to a specific diagnosis;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-270__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>stakeholder involvement in setting annual targets for quality and cost-effectiveness;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-270__subsec_a__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to the extent consistent with federal law, reducing travel costs by requiring a recipient to obtain medical services in the recipient's home community, to the extent appropriate services are available in the recipient's home community;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-270__subsec_a__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>guidelines for health care providers to develop health care delivery models supported by evidence-based practices that encourage wellness and disease prevention.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-270__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall, in coordination with the Alaska Mental Health Trust Authority, efficiently manage a comprehensive and integrated behavioral health program that uses evidence-based, data-driven practices to achieve positive outcomes for people with mental health or substance abuse disorders and children with severe emotional disturbances. The goal of the program is to assist recipients of services under the program to recover by achieving the highest level of autonomy with the least dependence on state-funded services possible for each person. The program must include</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-270__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a plan for providing a continuum of community-based services to address housing, employment, criminal justice, and other relevant issues;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-270__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>services from a wide array of providers and disciplines, including licensed or certified mental health and primary care professionals; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-270__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>efforts to reduce operational barriers that fragment services, minimize administrative burdens, and reduce the effectiveness and efficiency of the program.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-270__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall identify the areas of the state where improvements in access to telehealth would be most effective in reducing the costs of medical assistance and improving access to health care services for medical assistance recipients. The department shall make efforts to improve access to telehealth for recipients in those locations. The department may enter into agreements with Indian Health Service providers, if necessary, to improve access by medical assistance recipients to telehealth facilities and equipment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-270__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>On or before November 15 of each year, the department shall prepare a report and submit the report to the senate secretary and the chief clerk of the house of representatives and notify the legislature that the report is available. The report must include</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-270__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>realized cost savings related to reform efforts under this section;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-270__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>realized cost savings related to medical assistance reform efforts undertaken by the department other than the reform efforts described in this section;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-270__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a statement of whether the department has met annual targets for quality and cost-effectiveness;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-270__subsec_d__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>recommendations for legislative or budgetary changes related to medical assistance reforms during the next fiscal year;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-270__subsec_d__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>changes in federal laws that the department expects will result in a cost or savings to the state of more than $1,000,000;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-270__subsec_d__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a description of any medical assistance grants, options, or waivers the department applied for in the previous fiscal year;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-270__subsec_d__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the results of demonstration projects the department has implemented;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-270__subsec_d__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>legal and technological barriers to the expanded use of telehealth, improvements in the use of telehealth in the state, and recommendations for changes or investments that would allow cost-effective expansion of telehealth;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-270__subsec_d__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the percentage decrease in costs of travel for medical assistance recipients compared to the previous fiscal year;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-270__subsec_d__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the percentage decrease in the number of medical assistance recipients identified as frequent users of emergency departments compared to the previous fiscal year;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-270__subsec_d__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the percentage increase or decrease in the number of hospital readmissions within 30 days after a hospital stay for medical assistance recipients compared to the previous fiscal year;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-270__subsec_d__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the percentage increase or decrease in state general fund spending for the average medical assistance recipient compared to the previous fiscal year;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-270__subsec_d__subsec_13">
                <num>(13)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the percentage increase or decrease in uncompensated care costs incurred by medical assistance providers compared to the percentage change in private health insurance premiums for individual and small group health insurance;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-270__subsec_d__subsec_14">
                <num>(14)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the cost, in state and federal funds, for providing optional services under
AS 47.07.030</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-270__subsec_d__subsec_15">
                <num>(15)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the amount of state funds saved as a result of implementing changes in federal policy authorizing 100 percent federal funding for services provided to American Indian and Alaska Native individuals eligible for Medicaid, and the estimated savings in state funds that could have been achieved if the department had fully implemented the changes in policy.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-270__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, telehealth means the practice of health care delivery, evaluation, diagnosis, consultation, or treatment, using the transfer of health care data through audio, visual, or data communications, performed over two or more locations between providers who are physically separated from the recipient or from each other or between a provider and a recipient who are physically separated from each other.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-05-290">
            <num>47.05.290</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.05.290.   Definitions.
In
AS 47.05.200
 47.05.290,
(1) benefit has the meaning given in
AS 11.81.900
;
(2) claim includes a request for payment for medical assistance services under applicable state or federal law or regulations, whether the request is in an electronic format or paper format or both;
(3) commissioner means the commissioner of health;
(4) department means the Department of Health;
(5) falsely alters has the meaning given in
AS 11.46.580
;
(6) knowingly has the meaning given in
AS 11.81.900
;
(7) makes a false entry has the meaning given in
AS 11.56.820
;
(8) medical assistance agency means the department, an agency of the department, and an agent, contractor, or designee of the department or of one of its agencies that performs one or more of the activities of the department or an agency of the department;
(9) medical assistance program means a program under
AS 47.07
or
AS 47.08
;
(10) medical assistance provider or provider means a person or organization that provides, attempts to provide, or claims to have provided services or products to a medical assistance recipient that may qualify for reimbursement under
AS 47.07
or
AS 47.08
or a person or organization that participates in or has applied to participate in a medical assistance program as a supplier of a service or product;
(11) medical assistance recipient means a person on whose behalf another claims or receives a payment from a medical assistance agency, without regard to whether the individual was eligible for benefits under a medical assistance program;
(12) medical assistance record means records required to be kept by state or federal law or regulation regarding claims to a medical assistance agency;
(13) organization has the meaning given in
AS 11.81.900
;
(14) person has the meaning given in
AS 11.81.900
;
(15) property has the meaning given in
AS 11.81.900
;
(16) reckless disregard means acting recklessly, as that term is defined in
AS 11.81.900
;
(17) services or medical assistance services means a health care benefit that may qualify for reimbursement under
AS 47.07
or
AS 47.08
, including health care benefits provided, attempted to be provided, or claimed to have been provided to another, by a medical assistance provider, or services as defined in
AS 11.81.900
;
(18) unconditional discharge has the meaning given in
AS 12.55.185
.
Article 3. Criminal and Civil History.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-05-300">
            <num>47.05.300</num>
            <heading>Applicability.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-05-300__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The provisions of
AS 47.05.310
 47.05.390 apply to any individual or entity that is required by statute or regulation to be licensed or certified or that is eligible to receive payments, in whole or in part, from the Department of Health or the Department of Family and Community Services to provide for the health, safety, and welfare of persons who are served by the programs administered by those departments.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-300__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Those individual service providers subject to
AS 47.05.310
 47.05.390 under (a) of this section include</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-300__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>public home care providers described in
AS 47.05.017
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-300__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>providers of home and community-based waiver services financed under
AS 47.07.030</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-300__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>case managers to coordinate community mental health services under
AS 47.30.530
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-05-310">
            <num>47.05.310</num>
            <heading>Criminal history; criminal history check; compliance.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-05-310__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If an individual has been charged with, convicted of, found not guilty by reason of insanity for, or adjudicated as a delinquent for, a crime that is inconsistent with the standards for licensure or certification established by the department with licensing or certification authority for the individual by regulation, that individual may not own an entity, or be an officer, director, partner, member, or principal of the business organization that owns an entity. In addition, an entity may not</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-310__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>allow that individual to operate the entity;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-310__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>hire or retain that individual at the entity as an employee, independent contractor, or unsupervised volunteer of the entity;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-310__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>allow that individual to reside in the entity if not a recipient of services; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-310__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>allow that individual to be present in the entity if the individual would have regular contact with individuals who receive services from the entity, unless that individual is a family member of or visitor of an individual who receives services from the entity.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-310__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department with licensing or certification authority for an entity or individual may not issue or renew a license or a certification for an entity or an individual that is in violation of (a) of this section or that would be in violation based on the information received as part of the application process.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-310__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 25 ch 69 SLA 2018.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-310__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An entity or an individual shall provide to the department with licensing or certification authority for the entity or individual a release of information authorization for a criminal history check under this section for each individual who is not a recipient of services from the entity, who is not in the custody of the applicable department, and, after the entity applies for or has been issued a license, license renewal, certification, or certification renewal by the applicable department,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-310__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>who intends to become an owner of the entity, or an officer, director, partner, member, or principal of the business organization that owns the entity;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-310__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>whom the entity intends to hire or retain as the operator of the entity's business;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-310__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>whom the entity intends to hire or retain as an employee, independent contractor, or unsupervised volunteer of the entity; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-310__subsec_d__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>who will be present in the entity or at the places of operation of the entity, and would have regular contact with individuals who receive services from the entity, but who is not a family member or visitor of an individual who receives services from the entity.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-310__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An individual for whom a release of information authorization has been provided to the department with licensing or certification authority for the individual shall submit the individual's fingerprints to that department, with the fee established under
AS 12.62.160
, for a report of criminal justice information under
AS 12.62
and for submission by the Department of Public Safety to the Federal Bureau of Investigation for a national criminal history record check. The Department of Public Safety shall provide the report of criminal justice information and the results of the national criminal history record check to the applicable department for its use in considering an application for a license, license renewal, certification, or certification renewal, or in considering other approval or selection regarding an entity or individual, for compliance with the standards established in this section. The department with licensing or certification authority for the individual may waive the requirement for fingerprint submission if an individual is unable to provide fingerprints due to a medical or physical condition that is documented by a licensed physician.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-310__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The provisions of this section do not apply if the department with licensing or certification authority for the individual or entity grants an exception from a requirement of (a)  (e) of this section under a regulation adopted by that department or if the department with licensing or certification authority for the individual or entity grants a variance under
AS 47.05.360
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-310__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Health and the Department of Family and Community Services shall adopt regulations listing those criminal offenses that are inconsistent with the standards for licensure or certification by each department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-310__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of this section, in place of nonissuance or nonrenewal of a license or certification, an entity or individual that is not required to be licensed or certified by either department or a person wishing to become an entity or individual that is not required to be licensed or certified by either department is ineligible to receive a payment, in whole or in part, from the applicable department to provide for the health, safety, and welfare of persons who are served by the programs administered by that department if the entity or individual is in violation of this section or would be in violation of this section based on information received by the applicable department as part of an application, approval, or selection process.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-310__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 25 ch 69 SLA 2018.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-310__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An individual who possesses a valid teacher certificate issued under
AS 14.20.015
 14.20.025 and applies to work at a facility licensed or certified by the Department of Education and Early Development or who applies to work in a child care facility or residential child care facility in a position as a certificated teacher with supervised access may request that the individual's criminal justice information and national criminal history record check on file with the Department of Education and Early Development be used to satisfy the requirements of (d) and (e) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-310__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person is presumed to be acting in good faith and is immune from civil or criminal liability if the person</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-310__subsec_k__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>makes a report of medical assistance fraud, abuse, neglect, or exploitation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-310__subsec_k__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>submits information to a civil history database identified under
AS 47.05.330
; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-310__subsec_k__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>fails to hire or retain an employee or unsupervised volunteer because the employee or unsupervised volunteer is included in a civil history database identified under
AS 47.05.330
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-310__subsec_l">
              <num>(l)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Family and Community Services may issue or renew a foster home license under
AS 47.32
or provide payments under
AS 47.14.100</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-310__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or (d) to an entity, individual service provider, or person if the applicant or a person who resides in the home is barred from licensure or payment under (c), (i)(2), or (i)(3) of this section and</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-310__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a person in the home is an adult family member or family friend of a child in the custody or supervision of the state under
AS 47.10
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-310__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Department of Family and Community Services finds that placing the child with the entity, individual service provider, or person is in the best interests of the child; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-310__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the conduct that is the basis of the finding under (c), (i)(2), or (i)(3) of this section occurred at least 10 years before the date the Department of Family and Community Services receives the application for licensure or renewal or makes a payment to the entity, individual service provider, or person.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-310__subsec_m">
              <num>(m)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-310__subsec_m__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>adult family member has the meaning given in
AS 47.10.990
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-310__subsec_m__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>child care facility has the meaning given in
AS 47.25.095
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-310__subsec_m__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>foster home has the meaning given in
AS 47.32.900
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-310__subsec_m__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>residential child care facility has the meaning given in
AS 47.32.900
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-310__subsec_m__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>supervised access means that a supervisor maintains a prudent level of awareness of the whereabouts of the individual for whom supervised access is required to ensure the protection of recipients of services.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-05-320">
            <num>47.05.320</num>
            <heading>Criminal history use standards.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.05.320.   Criminal history use standards.
The Department of Health and the Department of Family and Community Services shall by regulation establish standards for the consideration and use by that department, an entity, or an individual service provider of the criminal history of an individual obtained under
AS 47.05.310
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-05-325">
            <num>47.05.325</num>
            <heading>Civil history; civil history check; compliance.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-05-325__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Health and the Department of Family and Community Services shall establish by regulation civil history standards for denial of issuance or renewal of a license or certification for an individual or for an entity within that department's licensing or certification authority if the individual who is applying for a license, license renewal, certification, or certification renewal is</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-325__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a biological or adoptive parent, guardian, custodian, or Indian custodian of a child who is or was the subject of a child-in-need-of-aid petition under
AS 47.10
and the individual had custody of the child at the time the child was the subject of a petition; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-325__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the subject of a finding or circumstance described in
AS 47.05.330</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-325__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If an individual is the subject of a petition or finding or circumstance described in (a) of this section, or a substantially similar provision in another jurisdiction, the individual may not own an entity or be an officer, director, partner, member, employee, or principal of the business organization that owns an entity. In addition, an entity may not</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-325__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>allow that individual to operate the entity;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-325__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>hire or retain that individual at the entity as an employee, independent contractor, or unsupervised volunteer of the entity;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-325__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>allow that individual to reside in the entity, unless that individual receives services from the entity or is in the custody of the state; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-325__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>allow that individual to be present in the entity if the individual would have regular contact with individuals who receive services from the entity, unless that individual is a family member of or visitor of an individual who receives services from the entity.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-325__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An entity or an individual shall provide to the department with licensing or certification authority for that entity or individual a release of information authorization for a civil history check under this section for each individual who is not a recipient of services from the entity, who is not in the custody of the applicable department, and, after the entity applies for or has been issued a license, license renewal, certification, or certification renewal by the applicable department,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-325__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>who intends to become an owner of the entity, or an officer, director, partner, member, or principal of the business organization that owns the entity;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-325__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>whom the entity intends to hire or retain as the operator of the entity's business;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-325__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>whom the entity intends to hire or retain as an employee, independent contractor, or unsupervised volunteer of the entity; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-325__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>who will be present in the entity or at the places of operation of the entity, and would have regular contact with individuals who receive services from the entity, but who is not a family member of or visitor of an individual who receives services from the entity.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-325__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of this section, in place of nonissuance or nonrenewal of a license or certification, an entity or individual that is not required to be licensed or certified by either department or a person wishing to become an entity or individual that is not required to be licensed or certified by either department is instead ineligible to receive a payment, in whole or in part, from the applicable department to provide for the health, safety, and welfare of persons who are served by the programs administered by that department if the entity or individual is in violation of this section or would be in violation of this section based on information received by the applicable department as part of an application, approval, or selection process.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-325__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Health and the Department of Family and Community Services shall by regulation identify other governmental agencies or political subdivisions of the state that can request from that department information that is required under this section for a similar purpose.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-325__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The provisions of this section do not apply if the applicable department grants an exception from the requirements of (a) or (b) of this section under a regulation adopted by that department or if that department grants a variance under
AS 47.05.360
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-325__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person is presumed to be acting in good faith and is immune from civil and criminal liability if the person</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-325__subsec_g__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>makes a report of medical assistance fraud, abuse, neglect, or exploitation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-325__subsec_g__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>submits information to a civil history database identified under
AS 47.05.330
; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-325__subsec_g__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>fails to hire or retain an employee or unsupervised volunteer because the employee or unsupervised volunteer is included in a civil history database identified under
AS 47.05.330
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-325__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Health and the Department of Family and Community Services shall by regulation establish standards for the consideration and use by that department, an entity, or an individual of the civil history of an individual obtained under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-05-330">
            <num>47.05.330</num>
            <heading>Identification of civil history databases for a civil history check; confidentiality.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-05-330__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Health and the Department of Family and Community Services shall by regulation identify each database that department will review when conducting a civil history check under
AS 47.05.325
to identify each individual</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-330__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>whom a court or the applicable department has found
(A) to have committed abuse, neglect, undue influence, or exploitation of a vulnerable adult;
(B) under
AS 47.32
or regulations adopted under
AS 47.32
, to have significantly adversely affected the health, safety, or welfare of an individual who is receiving a service from an entity licensed under
AS 47.32
; a finding described in this subparagraph includes a decision to revoke, suspend, or deny a license or license renewal, or the relinquishment of a license as part of a settlement agreement;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-330__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>who has been subject to criminal or civil penalties for a violation of
AS 09.58
,
AS 47.05
,
AS 47.06
,
AS 47.07
,
AS 47.08
, or regulations adopted under
AS 09.58
,
AS 47.05
,
AS 47.06
,
AS 47.07
, or
AS 47.08
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-330__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>about whom the applicable department or a court has made a substantiated finding of child abuse or neglect under
AS 47.10
or
AS 47.14
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-330__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>who was a biological or adoptive parent, guardian, custodian, or Indian custodian of a child at the time the child was the subject of a child-in-need-of-aid petition under
AS 47.10
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-330__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>who, in the course of employment with the state, has been terminated from employment or has had an allegation of assaultive, abusive, neglectful, or exploitive behavior or actions substantiated;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-330__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>who, in this state or another jurisdiction, for reasons related to abuse, neglect, undue influence, exploitation, or other reasons that are inconsistent with standards for the protection of public health, safety, or welfare, has had a professional license, certification, or similar professional designation revoked, suspended, or denied, or has had a request for renewal of a professional license, certification, or similar professional designation denied;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-330__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>whom another state or jurisdiction has identified on a civil registry or database substantially similar to the databases identified under this section for reasons substantially similar to the reasons identified in (1)  (6) of this subsection.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-330__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The information gathered under this section is not a public record under
AS 40.25.110
and is not subject to public inspection or copying under
AS 40.25.110
 40.25.125. However, information gathered under this section may be released to an entity, an individual who is included in a database, a governmental agency, and a political subdivision of the state in a manner provided under this section and regulations adopted under this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-05-340">
            <num>47.05.340</num>
            <heading>Regulations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.05.340.   Regulations.
The Department of Health and the Department of Family and Community Services shall adopt regulations to implement
AS 47.05.300
 47.05.390 for the entities and individuals for which that department has licensing or certification authority.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-05-350">
            <num>47.05.350</num>
            <heading>Use of information; immunity.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 47.05.350.   Use of information; immunity.
An entity that obtains information about an employee under a criminal history check under
AS 47.05.310
or a civil history check under
AS 47.05.325
may use that information only as provided for in regulations adopted by the department with licensing or certification authority for that entity under this chapter. However, if an entity reasonably relies on the information provided under the regulations adopted by the applicable department to deny employment to an individual who was selected for hire as an employee, including during a period of provisional employment, the entity is not liable in an action brought by the individual based on the employment determination resulting from the information.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-05-360">
            <num>47.05.360</num>
            <heading>Variance request; final decision.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-05-360__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An individual or entity subject to the provisions of
AS 47.05.310
or 47.05.325 may request a variance from the provisions of
AS 47.05.310
or 47.05.325 under procedures established by the department with licensing or certification authority for that individual or entity by regulation. The procedures must include the establishment of a variance committee to consider requests for variances. A request for a variance may include a request that the applicable department issue a written explanation of incorrect information contained in the civil history databases identified under
AS 47.05.330
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-360__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An individual or entity that is dissatisfied with a decision by a variance committee may, not more than 30 days after the committee issues the decision, apply to the commissioner of the department with licensing or certification authority for that individual or entity for reconsideration of the decision. A determination by the applicable commissioner is a final agency decision for purposes of appeal to the superior court.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="47-05-360__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department with licensing or certification authority for that individual or entity shall disclose information and records pertaining to a child subject to
AS 47.10
or
AS 47.17
to a variance committee as provided under
AS 47.10.093
(b).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_47-05-390">
            <num>47.05.390</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="47-05-390__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or (c) or an individual service provider as described in
AS 47.05.300
and includes an owner, officer, director, member, or partner of the entity;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-390__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>individual service provider means an individual described in
AS 47.05.300</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-390__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>license includes a provisional license;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="47-05-390__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>unsupervised means that an individual who is licensed under
AS 47.32
, after submitting a criminal history background check, is not physically present to observe the volunteer at the entity.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>