<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-39/chapter-27"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-39/chapter-27"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="39.27"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-39/chapter-27/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-39/chapter-27/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-39/chapter-27/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-39/chapter-27/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_39">
        <num>39</num>
        <heading>Public Officers and Employees</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_39__chp_27">
          <num>27</num>
          <heading>Pay Plan for State Employees</heading>
          <section eId="sec_39-27-011">
            <num>39.27.011</num>
            <heading>Salary schedule.</heading>
            <subsection eId="39-27-011__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The following monthly basic salary schedule is approved as the pay plan for classified and partially exempt employees in the executive branch of the state government who are not members of a collective bargaining unit established under the authority of
AS 23.40.070
 23.40.260 (Public Employment Relations Act) and for employees of the legislature under
AS 24
:
RangeStepStepStepStepStepStep
No.ABCDEF
52,455.002,523.002,595.002,669.002,749.002,820.00
62,595.002,669.002,749.002,820.002,902.002,989.00
72,749.002,820.002,902.002,989.003,080.003,178.00
82,902.002,989.003,080.003,178.003,269.003,369.00
93,080.003,178.003,269.003,369.003,477.003,575.00
103,269.003,369.003,477.003,575.003,686.003,793.00
113,477.003,575.003,686.003,793.003,922.004,045.00
123,686.003,793.003,922.004,045.004,184.004,326.00
133,922.004,045.004,184.004,326.004,476.004,636.00
144,184.004,326.004,476.004,636.004,799.004,980.00
154,476.004,636.004,799.004,980.005,140.005,333.00
164,799.004,980.005,140.005,333.005,525.005,719.00
175,140.005,333.005,525.005,719.005,917.006,119.00
185,525.005,719.005,917.006,119.006,308.006,548.00
195,917.006,119.006,308.006,548.006,753.006,999.00
206,308.006,548.006,753.006,999.007,211.007,477.00
216,753.006,999.007,211.007,477.007,707.007,986.00
227,211.007,477.007,707.007,986.008,246.008,541.00
237,707.007,986.008,246.008,541.008,825.009,156.00
248,246.008,541.008,825.009,156.009,461.009,781.00
258,825.009,156.009,461.009,781.0010,135.0010,513.00
269,156.009,461.009,781.0010,135.0010,513.0010,890.00
279,461.009,781.0010,135.0010,513.0010,890.0011,299.00
289,781.0010,135.0010,513.0010,890.0011,299.0011,692.00
2910,135.0010,513.0010,890.0011,299.0011,692.0012,105.00
3010,513.0010,890.0011,299.0011,692.0012,105.0012,531.00</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="39-27-011__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 38 ch 3 SLA 1980.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="39-27-011__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a state officer or employee is appointed a deputy department head or a division director and, at the time of appointment, the officer or employee is receiving a salary higher than that set for the position to which appointment has been made, the officer or employee is entitled to continue receiving the higher salary. This subsection does not apply to the salary of a person appointed to a position other than a deputy department head or a division director.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="39-27-011__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner of administration shall adopt the regulations required under
AS 22.05.140
(d),
AS 22.07.090
(c),
AS 22.10.190
(d), and
AS 22.15.220
(e). The regulations relate to the internal management of state agencies and their adoption is not subject to
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act). The regulations shall be published in the Alaska Administrative Register and Code for informational purposes.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="39-27-011__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 4 ch 50 SLA 2022.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="39-27-011__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 4 ch 50 SLA 2022.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="39-27-011__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 8 ch 2 TSSLA 2000.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="39-27-011__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Pay increments, computed at the rate of 3.25 percent of the employee's base salary, shall be provided after an employee has remained in the final step within a given range for two years, and every two years thereafter, if, at the time the employee becomes eligible for the increment, the employee's current annual rating by the employee's supervisors is designated as good or higher.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="39-27-011__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Pay increments provided for in (h) of this section are approved under
AS 39.25.150</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="39-27-011__subsec_i__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>as an amendment to the pay plan for employees of the state.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="39-27-011__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subsections (h) and (i) of this section apply to employees of the legislature only if the committee responsible for adopting employment policies concerning the employee adopts a written policy that (h) and (i) of this section apply. Subsections (h) and (i) of this section apply to the employees of the office of the ombudsman only if the ombudsman adopts a policy that (h) and (i) of this section apply. Subsections (h) and (i) of this section apply to the employees of the office of victims' rights only if the victims' advocate adopts a policy that (h) and (i) of this section apply.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="39-27-011__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (a)  (j) and (l) of this section, the governor or a designee of the governor may, on a case-by-case basis, authorize for a partially exempt employee in the executive branch a higher pay than Step F. The authorization must be based on a determination that the action serves a critical governmental interest of the state, the employee possesses exceptional qualifications, recruitment difficulties exist, or the action is necessary due to competitive salaries in the relevant labor market. A determination made under this subsection must be in writing.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="39-27-011__subsec_l">
              <num>(l)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The amounts set out in the salary schedule contained in (a) of this section are increased by 15 percent for positions within the Department of Law, the public defender agency, and the office of public advocacy that require admission to the practice of law in this state as a condition of employment, positions in the division of legal and research services within the Legislative Affairs Agency and any nonunion positions in the executive branch that require admission to the practice of law in this state as a condition of employment, and the chief administrative law judge and administrative law judges of the office of administrative hearings under
AS 39.25.120
(c)(20).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="39-27-011__subsec_m">
              <num>(m)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 4 ch 5 SLA 2024]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="39-27-011__subsec_n">
              <num>(n)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Effective July 8, 2024, the amounts set out in the salary schedule contained in (a) of this section are increased by 3.38 percent.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="39-27-011__subsec_o">
              <num>(o)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Effective July 1, 2025, the amounts set out in the salary schedule contained in (a) of this section, as increased under (n) of this section, are increased by three percent.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="39-27-011__subsec_p">
              <num>(p)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Effective July 1, 2026, the amounts set out in the salary schedule contained in (a) of this section, as increased under (n) and (o) of this section, are increased by 2.5 percent if the percentage of increase over the period beginning January 1, 2024, and ending December 31, 2024, in all items of the Consumer Price Index for all urban consumers for urban Alaska is less than four percent, and are increased by five percent if the percentage of increase over the period beginning January 1, 2024, and ending December 31, 2024, in all items of the Consumer Price Index for all urban consumers for urban Alaska is four percent or more.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="39-27-011__subsec_q">
              <num>(q)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Effective July 1, 2027, if the basic monthly salaries paid to members of the supervisory bargaining unit are increased under
AS 23.40.215
, the amounts set out in the salary schedule in (a) of this section are increased at the same time and by the same percentage of increase. The commissioner of administration shall, by regulation, establish the percentage at which the salary schedule is increased and the increased salary amount. The regulations relate to the internal management of state agencies, and their adoption is not subject to
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act). The regulations must be published in the Alaska Administrative Register and Code for informational purposes.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_39-27-012">
            <num>39.27.012</num>
            <heading>Temporary salary schedules.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 39.27.012.   Temporary salary schedules.
The director of the division of personnel may establish salary schedules providing lesser amounts than those in the basic salary schedule in order to meet salary limit requirements for receipt and expenditure of federal funds. Salary rates established under authority of this section do not affect the salaries of employees provided for by a collective bargaining agreement negotiated under the authority of
AS 23.40.070
 23.40.260 (Public Employment Relations Act).</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_39-27-020">
            <num>39.27.020</num>
            <heading>Geographic pay differentials.</heading>
            <subsection eId="39-27-020__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The following geographic pay differentials established as a percentage above the basic salary schedule provided in
AS 39.27.011
are approved as an amendment to the basic salary schedule provided in
AS 39.27.011
:
Duty StationGeographic PayDifferential
Anchor Point0
Anchorage0
Anchorage International Airport0
Aniak50
Anvik50
Auke Bay5
Barrow50
Bethel50
Camp Carroll0
Cantwell0
Chena River3
Chignik50
Chitina0
Cold Bay50
Coldfoot Camp37
Cooper Landing0
Cordova11
Craig0
Crown Point0
Deadhorse50
Delta Junction0
Denali0
Dillingham37
Douglas5
Dutch Harbor60
Eagle0
Eagle River0
Eielson Air Force Base3
Elfin Cove0
Elmendorf Air Force Base0
Emmonak50
Fairbanks3
Finger Lake0
Fort Richardson0
Fort Wainwright3
Fort Yukon37
Gakona0
Galena37
Girdwood0
Glennallen0
Gustavus0
Haines0
Harding Lake3
Healy0
Homer0
Hoonah0
Iliamna50
Juneau5
Kaltag50
Kenai0
Ketchikan0
King Cove50
King Salmon50
Klawock0
Kodiak11
Kotzebue60
Mackenzie Point0
Matanuska0
McGrath37
Mount Edgecumbe5
Nancy0
Nenana0
Nikiski0
Ninilchik0
Nome37
Northway0
Palmer0
Pelican0
Petersburg0
Port Alsworth50
Port Moller50
Saint Mary's50
Sand Point50
Selawik60
Seward0
Sitka5
Skagway0
Soldotna0
Sterling0
Sutton0
Talkeetna0
Tazlina0
Tenakee Springs0
Tok0
Trapper Creek0
Unalakleet50
Unalaska60
Valdez11
Wasilla0
Whittier0
Willow0
Wrangell0
Yakutat0
Other states0</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="39-27-020__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If an employee's duty station is not included in (a) of this section and is not in a foreign country, the commissioner of administration shall establish by regulation the appropriate geographic pay differential. The regulations are not subject to
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="39-27-020__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner of administration shall establish geographic pay differentials for positions in foreign countries. The differentials shall be adjusted annually, effective July 1, to maintain equity between salaries for positions in foreign countries and salaries for positions in the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_39-27-025">
            <num>39.27.025</num>
            <heading>Swing and graveyard shift differentials.</heading>
            <subsection eId="39-27-025__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Classified and partially exempt state employees who regularly work a swing shift beginning between 12:00 noon and 7:59 p.m. are entitled to a one-step increase over their normal pay established by this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="39-27-025__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Classified and partially exempt state employees who regularly work a graveyard shift beginning between 8:00 p.m. and 3:59 a.m. are entitled to a two-step increase over their normal pay established by this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_39-27-030">
            <num>39.27.030</num>
            <heading>Geographic pay differential survey.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 39.27.030.   Geographic pay differential survey.
Subject to appropriation, the director of the division of personnel shall conduct a survey, at least every five years, to review the geographic pay differentials under
AS 39.27.020
. The survey may address factors the director determines are relevant to review state salary schedules, entitlements for beneficiaries of state programs, and payments for state service providers. The survey must reflect the cost of living for duty stations in the state or outside of the state by using the cost of living in Anchorage, Alaska, as a base.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>