<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-43/chapter-82"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-43/chapter-82"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="43.82"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-43/chapter-82/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-43/chapter-82/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-43/chapter-82/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-43/chapter-82/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_43">
        <num>43</num>
        <heading>Revenue and Taxation</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_43__chp_82">
          <num>82</num>
          <heading>Alaska Stranded Gas Development Act</heading>
          <section eId="sec_43-82-010">
            <num>43.82.010</num>
            <heading>Purpose.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 43.82.010.   Purpose.
The purpose of this chapter is to
(1) encourage new investment to develop the state's stranded gas resources by authorizing establishment of fiscal terms related to that new investment without significantly altering tax and royalty methodologies and rates on existing oil and gas infrastructure and production;
(2) allow the fiscal terms applicable to a qualified sponsor or the members of a qualified sponsor group, with respect to a qualified project, to be tailored to the particular economic conditions of the project and to establish those fiscal terms in advance with as much certainty as the Constitution of the State of Alaska allows; and
(3) maximize the benefit to the people of the state of the development of the state's stranded gas resources.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_43-82-020">
            <num>43.82.020</num>
            <heading>Contracts for payments in lieu of other taxes and for royalty adjustments.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 43.82.020.   Contracts for payments in lieu of other taxes and for royalty adjustments.
The commissioner may, under this chapter, negotiate terms for inclusion in a proposed contract with a qualified sponsor or qualified sponsor group providing for
(1) periodic payment in lieu of one or more taxes that otherwise would be imposed by the state or a municipality on the qualified sponsor or members of the qualified sponsor group as a consequence of the sponsor's or group's participation in an approved qualified project under this chapter; and
(2) certain adjustments regarding royalty under
AS 43.82.220
.
Article 2. Qualification and Application Procedures.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_43-82-100">
            <num>43.82.100</num>
            <heading>Qualified project.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 43.82.100.   Qualified project.
Based on information available to the commissioner, the commissioner may determine that a proposal for new investment is a qualified project under this chapter if the project
(1) principally involves
(A) the transportation of natural gas by pipeline to one or more markets, together with any associated processing or treatment;
(B) the export of liquefied natural gas from the state to one or more other states or countries; or
(C) any other technology that commercializes the shipment of natural gas within the state or from the state to one or more other states or countries;
(2) would produce at least 500,000,000,000 cubic feet of stranded gas within 20 years from the commencement of commercial operations; and
(3) is capable, subject to applicable commercial regulation and technical and economic considerations, of making gas available to meet the reasonably foreseeable demand in this state for gas within the economic proximity of the project.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_43-82-110">
            <num>43.82.110</num>
            <heading>Qualified sponsor or qualified sponsor group.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 43.82.110.   Qualified sponsor or qualified sponsor group.
The commissioner may determine that a person or group is a qualified sponsor or qualified sponsor group if the person or a member of the group
(1) intends to own an equity interest in a qualified project, intends to commit gas that it owns to a qualified project, or holds the permits that the department determines are essential to construct and operate a qualified project; and
(2) meets one or more of the following criteria:
(A) owns a working interest in at least 10 percent of the stranded gas proposed to be developed by a qualified project;
(B) has the right to purchase at least 10 percent of the stranded gas proposed to be developed by a qualified project;
(C) has the right to acquire, control, or market at least 10 percent of the stranded gas proposed to be developed by a qualified project;
(D) has a net worth equal to at least 10 percent of the estimated cost of constructing a qualified project;
(E) has an unused line of credit equal to at least 15 percent of the estimated cost of constructing a qualified project.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_43-82-120">
            <num>43.82.120</num>
            <heading>Applications.</heading>
            <subsection eId="43-82-120__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A qualified sponsor or qualified sponsor group may submit to the department an application for development of a contract under
AS 43.82.020
evidencing that the requirements of
AS 43.82.100
and 43.82.110 are met. The application must be submitted in the manner and form and contain the information required by the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="43-82-120__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Along with an application submitted under (a) of this section, an applicant shall submit a proposed project plan for a qualified project that contains the following information based on the information known to the applicant at the time of application:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-120__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a description of the work accomplished as of the date of the application to further the project;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-120__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a schedule of proposed development activity leading to the projected commencement of commercial operations of the project;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-120__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a description of the development activity proposed to be accomplished under the proposed project plan;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-120__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a description of each lease or property that the applicant believes to contain the stranded gas that would be developed if the project was built;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-120__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a description of the methods and terms under which the applicant is prepared to make gas available to meet the reasonably foreseeable demand in this state for gas within the economic proximity of the project during the term of the proposed contract, including proposed pipeline transportation and expansion rules if pipeline transportation is a part of the proposed project;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-120__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a detailed description of options to mitigate the increased demand for public services and other negative effects caused by the project;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-120__subsec_b__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a detailed description of options for the safe management and operation of the project once it is constructed;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-120__subsec_b__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>other information that the commissioner of revenue, in consultation with the commissioner of natural resources, considers necessary to make a determination that
(A) the work accomplished as of the date of application, the schedule of proposed development activity, and the development activity proposed to be accomplished under the proposed project plan reflect a proposal for diligent development on the part of the applicant;
(B) the proposed project plan does not materially conflict with the obligations of a lessee to the state under a lease or under a pool, unit, or other agreement with the state; and
(C) the proposed project plan describes satisfactory methods and terms for accommodating reasonably foreseeable demand for gas in this state within the economic proximity of the project during the term of the proposed contract.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="43-82-120__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The requirements of (b) of this section do not diminish the obligations of a qualified sponsor or member of a qualified sponsor group to the state or restrict the authority of the commissioner of revenue or the commissioner of natural resources under any other law or agreement relating to a plan of development for a lease, pool, or unit.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_43-82-130">
            <num>43.82.130</num>
            <heading>Qualified project plan.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 43.82.130.   Qualified project plan.
A proposed project plan submitted under
AS 43.82.120
may be approved as a qualified project plan under
AS 43.82.140
if the proposed project plan
(1) reflects a proposal for diligent development of the project on the part of the applicant;
(2) does not materially conflict with the obligations of a lessee to the state under a lease or under a pool, unit, or other agreement with the state; and
(3) describes satisfactory methods and terms for making gas available to meet the reasonably foreseeable demand in this state for gas within the economic proximity of the project during the term of the proposed contract.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_43-82-140">
            <num>43.82.140</num>
            <heading>Review of applications and determination of qualifications.</heading>
            <subsection eId="43-82-140__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall review an application submitted under
AS 43.82.120
to determine whether the provisions of
AS 43.82.100
concerning a qualified project and
AS 43.82.110
concerning a qualified sponsor or qualified sponsor group have been met. The commissioner may approve an application only if those provisions have been met.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="43-82-140__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the commissioner approves an application under (a) of this section, the commissioner and the commissioner of natural resources shall review the proposed project plan submitted with the application to determine whether the provisions of
AS 43.82.130
have been met. The commissioner may approve the proposed project plan as a qualified project plan only if the commissioner of natural resources concurs in the approval.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="43-82-140__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall send to the applicant written notice of and the reasons for the determinations made under (a) and (b) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_43-82-150">
            <num>43.82.150</num>
            <heading>Actions challenging determinations on applications.</heading>
            <subsection eId="43-82-150__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Only an applicant under
AS 43.82.120
who is aggrieved by a determination of the commissioner of revenue or the commissioner of natural resources under
AS 43.82.140
may seek judicial review of the determination.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="43-82-150__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The only grounds for judicial review of a determination made under
AS 43.82.140
are</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-150__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>failure to follow the qualification and application procedures set out in
AS 43.82.100
 43.82.180; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-150__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>abuse of discretion that is so capricious, arbitrary, or confiscatory as to constitute a denial of due process.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_43-82-160">
            <num>43.82.160</num>
            <heading>Multiple applications for similar or competing qualified projects.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 43.82.160.   Multiple applications for similar or competing qualified projects.
Nothing in this chapter prohibits different qualified sponsors or different qualified sponsor groups from submitting applications under
AS 43.82.120
relating to similar or competing qualified projects or prohibits the commissioner of revenue or the commissioner of natural resources from reviewing and approving applications and proposed project plans under
AS 43.82.140
relating to similar or competing qualified projects.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_43-82-170">
            <num>43.82.170</num>
            <heading>Application deadline.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 43.82.170.   Application deadline.
The commissioner of revenue or the commissioner of natural resources may not act on an application for a contract submitted under
AS 43.82.120
unless the application is received by the Department of Revenue no later than March 31, 2005.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_43-82-180">
            <num>43.82.180</num>
            <heading>Withdrawal of applications.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 43.82.180.   Withdrawal of applications.
Subject to the terms of a reimbursement agreement under
AS 43.82.240
or other agreement with the Department of Revenue, the Department of Natural Resources, the commissioner of revenue, or the commissioner of natural resources affecting the withdrawal of an application, a qualified sponsor or qualified sponsor group may withdraw an application submitted under
AS 43.82.120
at any time before the date that the commissioner of revenue submits a contract to the governor under
AS 43.82.430
without further obligation under this chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_43-82-200">
            <num>43.82.200</num>
            <heading>Contract development.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 43.82.200.   Contract development.
If the commissioner approves an application and proposed project plan under
AS 43.82.140
, the commissioner may develop a contract that may include
(1) terms concerning periodic payment in lieu of one or more taxes as provided in
AS 43.82.210
;
(2) terms developed under
AS 43.82.220
relating to
(A) timing and notice of the state's right to take royalty in kind or in value; and
(B) royalty value;
(3) terms regarding the hiring of Alaska residents and contracting with Alaska businesses under
AS 43.82.230
;
(4) terms regarding periodic payment to, or an equity or other interest in a project for, municipalities under
AS 43.82.500
;
(5) terms regarding arbitration or alternative dispute resolution procedures;
(6) terms and conditions for administrative termination of a contract under
AS 43.82.445
; and
(7) other terms or conditions that are
(A) necessary to further the purposes of this chapter; or
(B) in the best interests of the state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_43-82-210">
            <num>43.82.210</num>
            <heading>Contract terms relating to payment in lieu of one or more taxes.</heading>
            <subsection eId="43-82-210__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the commissioner approves an application and proposed project plan under
AS 43.82.140
, the commissioner may develop proposed terms for inclusion in a contract under
AS 43.82.020
for periodic payment in lieu of one or more of the following taxes that otherwise would be imposed by the state or a municipality on the qualified sponsor or member of a qualified sponsor group as a consequence of participating in an approved qualified project:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-210__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>oil and gas production taxes and oil surcharges under
AS 43.55
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-210__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>oil and gas exploration, production, and pipeline transportation property taxes under
AS 43.56
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-210__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>[Repealed, § 6 ch 34 SLA 1999.]</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-210__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Alaska net income tax under
AS 43.20
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-210__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>municipal sales and use tax under
AS 29.45.650
 29.45.710;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-210__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>municipal property tax under
AS 29.45.010
 29.45.250 or 29.45.550  29.45.600;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-210__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>municipal special assessments under
AS 29.46
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-210__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a comparable tax or levy imposed by the state or a municipality after June 18, 1998;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-210__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>other state or municipal taxes or categories of taxes identified by the commissioner.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="43-82-210__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the commissioner chooses to develop proposed terms under (a) of this section, the commissioner shall, if practicable and consistent with the long-term fiscal interests of the state, develop the terms in a manner that attempts to balance the following principles:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-210__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the terms should, in conjunction with other factors such as cost reduction of the project, cost overrun risk reduction of the project, increased fiscal certainty, and successful marketing, improve the competitiveness of the approved qualified project in relation to other development efforts aimed at supplying the same market;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-210__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the terms should accommodate the interests of the state, affected municipalities, and the project sponsors under a wide range of economic conditions, potential project structures, and marketing arrangements;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-210__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the state's and affected municipalities' combined share of the economic rent of the approved qualified project under the contract should be relatively progressive; that is, the state's and affected municipalities' combined annual share of the economic rent of the approved qualified project generally should not increase when there are decreases in project profitability, or decrease when there are increases in project profitability;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-210__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the state's and affected municipalities' combined share of the economic rent of the approved qualified project under the contract should be relatively lower in the earlier years than in the later years of the approved qualified project;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-210__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the terms should allow the project sponsors to retain a share of the economic rent of the approved qualified project that is sufficient to compensate the sponsors for risks under a range of economic circumstances;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-210__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the terms should provide the state and affected municipalities with a significant share of the economic rent of the approved qualified project, when discounted to present value, under favorable price and cost conditions;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-210__subsec_b__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the method for calculating the periodic payment in lieu of certain taxes under the contract should be clear and unambiguous; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-210__subsec_b__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>while cost calculations for the approved qualified project under the contract should be based on amounts that closely approximate actual costs, agreed-upon formulas reflecting reasonable economic assumptions should be used if possible to promote administrative certainty and efficiency.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="43-82-210__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (b) of this section, the commissioner's discretion under this section in developing proposed terms for a contract under
AS 43.82.020
is not limited to consideration of the economic rent of the approved qualified project.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_43-82-220">
            <num>43.82.220</num>
            <heading>Contract terms relating to royalty.</heading>
            <subsection eId="43-82-220__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding any contrary provisions of
AS 38
, the commissioner of natural resources, with the concurrence of the commissioner of revenue and the affected parties holding a state lease or unit agreement, may develop proposed terms for inclusion in a contract under
AS 43.82.020
that modify the timing and notice provisions of the applicable oil and gas leases and unit agreements pertaining to the state's rights to receive its royalty on gas in kind or in value if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-220__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the viability of the approved qualified project depends on long-term gas purchase and sale agreements;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-220__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>certainty over time regarding the quantity of royalty gas that the state may be taking in kind is needed to secure the long-term purchase and sale agreements;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-220__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the specified period of the state's commitment to take its royalty share in value or in kind does not exceed the term of the purchase and sale agreements; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-220__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the modification does not impair the ability of the approved qualified project or the state to meet the reasonably foreseeable demand in this state for gas within economic proximity of the project during the term of the contract developed under
AS 43.82.020
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="43-82-220__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding any contrary provisions of
AS 38
, the commissioner of natural resources, with the concurrence of the commissioner of revenue and the affected parties holding a state lease or unit agreement, may develop proposed terms for inclusion in a contract under
AS 43.82.020
that establish a valuation method for the state's royalty share of the gas production from an approved qualified project.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="43-82-220__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner of revenue shall include any proposed terms relating to royalty developed in accordance with this section in the proposed contract under
AS 43.82.400
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="43-82-220__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing in this chapter permits modification of the state's rights that relate to timing, notice, and rights to receive oil royalty in kind or in value under oil and gas leases or unit agreements.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_43-82-230">
            <num>43.82.230</num>
            <heading>Contract terms relating to hiring of Alaska residents and contracting with Alaska businesses.</heading>
            <subsection eId="43-82-230__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall include in a contract under
AS 43.82.020
a term requiring the qualified sponsor or qualified sponsor group and contractors of the qualified sponsor or qualified sponsor group to comply with all valid federal, state, and municipal laws relating to hiring Alaska residents and contracting with Alaska businesses to work in the state on the approved qualified project and not to discriminate against Alaska residents or Alaska businesses. Within the constraints of law, the commissioner shall also include in a contract under
AS 43.82.020
a term that requires the qualified sponsor or qualified sponsor group and contractors of the qualified sponsor or qualified sponsor group to employ Alaska residents and to contract with Alaska businesses to work in the state on the approved qualified project to the extent the residents and businesses are available, competitively priced, and qualified.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="43-82-230__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall include in a contract under
AS 43.82.020
a term requiring the qualified sponsor or qualified sponsor group and contractors of the qualified sponsor or qualified sponsor group to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-230__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>advertise for available positions in newspapers in the location where the work is to be performed and in other publications distributed throughout the state, including in rural areas; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-230__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>use Alaska job service organizations located throughout the state and not just in the location where the work is to be performed in order to notify Alaskans of work opportunities on the approved qualified project.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="43-82-230__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subject to the voluntary agreement of the qualified sponsor, the commissioner may include a term in the contract providing for incentives to encourage training and hiring of Alaska residents.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="43-82-230__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This section does not create or abridge individual rights and does not create a private right of action for any person.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="43-82-230__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-230__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Alaska business means a firm or contractor that
(A) has held an Alaska business license for the preceding 12 months;
(B) maintains, and has maintained for the preceding 12 months, a place of business in the state that competently and professionally deals in supplies, services, or construction of the nature required for the approved qualified project; and
(C) is</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="43-82-230__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>a sole proprietorship and the proprietor is an Alaska resident;
(ii) a partnership and more than 50 percent of the partnership interest is held by Alaska residents;
(iii) a limited liability company and more than 50 percent of the membership interest is held by Alaska residents;
(iv) a corporation that has been incorporated in the state or is authorized to do business in the state; or</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="43-82-230__subsec_v">
              <num>(v)</num>
              <content>
                <p>a joint venture and a majority of the venturers qualify as Alaska businesses under this paragraph;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-230__subsec_v__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Alaska job service organizations means those offices maintained by the state and recommended by the Department of Labor and Workforce Development whose functions are to aid the unemployed or underemployed in finding employment;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-230__subsec_v__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Alaska resident means a natural person who
(A) receives a permanent fund dividend under
AS 43.23
; or
(B) is registered to vote under
AS 15
and qualifies for a resident fishing, hunting, or trapping license under
AS 16
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-230__subsec_v__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>available, as applied to an Alaska resident or Alaska business, means that the resident or business is available for employment at the time required and is located anywhere in the state, not just in the area of the state where the work is to be performed;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-230__subsec_v__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>qualified, as applied to an Alaska resident or Alaska business, means that the resident or business possesses the requisite education, training, skills, certification, or experience to perform the work necessary for a particular position or to perform a particular service.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_43-82-240">
            <num>43.82.240</num>
            <heading>Use of an independent contractor.</heading>
            <subsection eId="43-82-240__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner may use independent contractors to assist in the evaluation of an application or in the development of contract terms under
AS 43.82.200
. The commissioner may condition the development of a contract under
AS 43.82.020
on an agreement by the applicant to reimburse the state for the reasonable expenses of independent contractors under this section. A reimbursement of expenses that is required in an agreement authorized by this subsection may not exceed $1,500,000 for each application.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="43-82-240__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An independent contractor selected under this section must sign an agreement regarding confidentiality and disclosures consistent with the determinations made under
AS 43.82.310
before the contractor may review information that is determined confidential under
AS 43.82.310
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="43-82-240__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Selection of an independent contractor under this section is not subject to
AS 36.30
(State Procurement Code).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_43-82-250">
            <num>43.82.250</num>
            <heading>Term of contract; effective date.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 43.82.250.   Term of contract; effective date.
The term of a contract developed under
AS 43.82.020
may be for no longer than is necessary to develop the stranded gas that is subject to the contract; however, the term of the contract may not exceed 35 years from the commencement of commercial operations of the approved qualified project.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_43-82-260">
            <num>43.82.260</num>
            <heading>Change of parties to an application or a contract; assignment of interests.</heading>
            <subsection eId="43-82-260__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A qualified sponsor or member of a qualified sponsor group may assign an interest in or add or withdraw a party to an application under
AS 43.82.120
only if the commissioner has</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-260__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>made a finding that the assignment, addition, or withdrawal is consistent with the requirements of
AS 43.82.110
; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-260__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>given prior written approval for the assignment, addition, or withdrawal.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="43-82-260__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A contract developed under this chapter may provide for the assignment to or withdrawal of a qualified sponsor or member of a qualified sponsor group.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="43-82-260__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon being added to an application under this section, a party becomes a qualified sponsor or a member of a qualified sponsor group, as appropriate, for the relevant project.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="43-82-260__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner may not unreasonably withhold approval under (a) of this section, but may condition the approval in any way reasonably necessary to protect the fiscal interests of the state and to further the purposes of this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="43-82-260__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of this section, an assignment includes a transfer of stock or a partnership interest in a manner that changes control of a qualified sponsor or member of a qualified sponsor group.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_43-82-270">
            <num>43.82.270</num>
            <heading>Project plans and work commitments.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 43.82.270.   Project plans and work commitments.
A contract under
AS 43.82.020
must include the qualified project plan approved under
AS 43.82.140
and provisions for updating the plan at reasonable intervals until the commencement of commercial operations of the approved qualified project. The commissioner of revenue, in consultation with the commissioner of natural resources, may, as a term in a contract under
AS 43.82.020
, include work commitments or other obligations in the contract to be accomplished before the commencement of commercial operations of the approved qualified project.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_43-82-300">
            <num>43.82.300</num>
            <heading>Requests for information.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 43.82.300.   Requests for information.
The commissioner of revenue or the commissioner of natural resources may request from an applicant information that the respective commissioner determines is necessary to perform the respective commissioner's responsibilities under
AS 43.82.140
. If the application is approved under
AS 43.82.140
, the respective commissioner shall require the successful applicant to provide financial, technical, and market information regarding the qualified project that the respective commissioner determines is necessary for the purpose of developing contract terms for the qualified project under
AS 43.82.200
. If requested information is not provided, the commissioner of revenue may not continue to review the application under
AS 43.82.140
or develop the contract under
AS 43.82.200
 43.82.270, as applicable.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_43-82-310">
            <num>43.82.310</num>
            <heading>Disclosure of information; confidentiality.</heading>
            <subsection eId="43-82-310__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An applicant may request confidential treatment of information that the applicant provides under
AS 43.82.300
by clearly identifying the information and the reasons supporting the request for confidential treatment. The commissioner of revenue or the commissioner of natural resources, as appropriate, shall keep the information confidential until the commissioner determines whether the requirements of (b) of this section are met. If the commissioner of revenue or the commissioner of natural resources has not made a determination under (b) of this section within 14 days after receiving a request for confidential treatment, the request is considered denied. If the appropriate commissioner determines that the information does not meet the requirements of (b) of this section or if the commissioner fails to make a determination within 14 days, the commissioner shall return the information and any copies of it at the request of the applicant. If the commissioner of revenue or the commissioner of natural resources, as appropriate, returns information under this subsection, the commissioner shall cease review of the application or cease contract development under
AS 43.82.200
 43.82.270, as appropriate, unless the commissioner determines that the returned information is unnecessary to make a determination on the application or to develop contract terms under
AS 43.82.200
 43.82.270.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="43-82-310__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If requested by the applicant, information provided to the commissioner of revenue or the commissioner of natural resources under
AS 43.82.300
shall be kept confidential if the commissioner receiving the information determines, upon an adequate showing by the applicant, that the information</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-310__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is a trade secret or other proprietary research, development, or commercial information that the applicant treats as confidential;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-310__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>affects the applicant's competitive position; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-310__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has commercial value that may be significantly diminished by public disclosure or that public disclosure is not in the long-term fiscal interests of the state.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="43-82-310__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Information determined to be confidential under (b) of this section is confidential under that subsection only so long as is necessary to protect the competitive position of the applicant, to prevent the significant diminution of the commercial value of the information, or to protect the long-term fiscal interests of the state. The commissioner of revenue or the commissioner of natural resources, as appropriate, may not release information that the commissioner has previously determined to be confidential under (b) of this section without providing the applicant notice and an opportunity to be heard.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="43-82-310__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding the limitation in (c) of this section, the Department of Revenue and the Department of Natural Resources may provide to one another, to the Department of Law, to the legislature, and to the Office of the Governor any information provided under
AS 43.82.300
relevant to the implementation of this chapter or to the enforcement of state or federal laws. Information that is exchanged under this subsection that was determined to be confidential under (b) of this section remains confidential except as provided in (c) of this section. The portions of the records and files of the Department of Revenue, the Department of Natural Resources, the Department of Law, the legislature, and the Office of the Governor that reflect, incorporate, or analyze information that is determined to be confidential under (b) of this section are not public records except as provided in (c) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="43-82-310__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding the limitation in (c) of this section, information that is determined to be confidential under (b) of this section shall be disclosed on request by the commissioner of revenue, the commissioner of natural resources, or the attorney general to a legislator; to the legislative auditor; and, as directed by the chair or vice-chair of the Legislative Budget and Audit Committee, to the director of legislative finance, to the permanent employees of those divisions who are responsible for evaluating a contract under
AS 43.82.020
, and to agents or contractors of the legislative auditor or the director of legislative finance who are engaged to evaluate a contract under
AS 43.82.020
. Information that is determined to be confidential under (b) of this section may also be disclosed by the commissioner of revenue or the commissioner of natural resources to an independent contractor under
AS 43.82.240
or to a municipal advisory group established under
AS 43.82.510
. Before confidential information is disclosed under this subsection, the person receiving the information must sign an appropriate confidentiality agreement.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="43-82-310__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the commissioner of revenue chooses to develop a contract under
AS 43.82.020
, the portions of the records and files of the Department of Revenue, the Department of Natural Resources, the Department of Law, and a municipal advisory group established under
AS 43.82.510
that reflect, incorporate, or analyze information that is relevant to the development of the position or strategy of the commissioner of revenue, the commissioner of natural resources, or the attorney general with respect to a particular provision that may be incorporated into the contract are not public records until the commissioner of revenue gives public notice under
AS 43.82.410
of the commissioner's preliminary findings and determination under
AS 43.82.400
. Nothing in this subsection</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-310__subsec_f__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>makes a record or file of the Department of Revenue, the Department of Natural Resources, or the Department of Law a public record that otherwise would not be a public record under
AS 40.25.100
 40.25.220;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-310__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>affects the confidentiality provisions of (a)  (e) of this section; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-310__subsec_f__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>abridges a privilege recognized under the laws of this state, whether at common law or by statute or by court rule.
Article 5. Contract Review, Approval, and Termination.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_43-82-400">
            <num>43.82.400</num>
            <heading>Preliminary findings and determination regarding the contract.</heading>
            <subsection eId="43-82-400__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the commissioner develops a proposed contract under
AS 43.82.200
 43.82.270, the commissioner shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-400__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>make preliminary findings and a determination that the proposed contract terms are in the long-term fiscal interests of the state and further the purposes of this chapter; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-400__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>prepare a proposed contract that includes those terms and shall submit the contract to the governor.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="43-82-400__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To make the preliminary findings and determination required by (a)(1) of this section, the commissioner shall compare the projected public revenue anticipated from the approved qualified project with the estimated operating and capital costs of the additional state and municipal services anticipated to arise from the construction and operation of the approved qualified project. The commissioner shall address the reasonably foreseeable effects of the proposed contract on the public revenue.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="43-82-400__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In conjunction with the making of preliminary findings and determination required by (a)(1) of this section, the commissioner shall describe the principal factors, including the projected price of gas, projected production rate or volume of gas, and projected recovery, development, construction, and operating costs, upon which the determination made under (a)(1) of this section is based. If the commissioner has previously submitted a proposed contract to the governor, the commissioner shall describe any material differences between the terms of the currently proposed contract and the previously proposed contract.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_43-82-410">
            <num>43.82.410</num>
            <heading>Notice and comment regarding the contract.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 43.82.410.   Notice and comment regarding the contract.
The commissioner shall
(1) give reasonable public notice of the preliminary findings and determination made under
AS 43.82.400
;
(2) make copies of the proposed contract, the commissioner's preliminary findings and determination, and, to the extent the information is not required to be kept confidential under
AS 43.82.310
, the supporting financial, technical, and market data, including the work papers, analyses, and recommendations of any independent contractors used under
AS 43.82.240
available to the public and to
(A) the presiding officer of each house of the legislature;
(B) the chairs of the finance and resources committees of the legislature; and
(C) the chairs of the special committees on oil and gas, if any, of the legislature;
(3) offer to appear before the Legislative Budget and Audit Committee to provide the committee a review of the commissioner's preliminary findings and determination, the proposed contract, and the supporting financial, technical, and market data; if the Legislative Budget and Audit Committee accepts the commissioner's offer, the committee shall give notice of the committee's meeting to the public and all members of the legislature; if the financial, technical, and market data that is to be provided must be kept confidential under
AS 43.82.310
, the commissioner may not release the confidential information during a public portion of a committee meeting; and
(4) establish a period of at least 30 days for the public and members of the legislature to comment on the proposed contract and the preliminary findings and determination made under
AS 43.82.400
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_43-82-420">
            <num>43.82.420</num>
            <heading>Coordination of public and legislative review.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 43.82.420.   Coordination of public and legislative review.
To the extent practicable, the commissioner shall coordinate the public comment opportunity provided under
AS 43.82.410
(4) with a review by the Legislative Budget and Audit Committee under
AS 43.82.410
(3).</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_43-82-430">
            <num>43.82.430</num>
            <heading>Final findings, determination, and proposed amendments; execution of the contract.</heading>
            <subsection eId="43-82-430__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Within 30 days after the close of the public comment period under
AS 43.82.410</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-430__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>prepare a summary of the public comments received in response to the proposed contract and the preliminary findings and determination;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-430__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>after consultation with the commissioner of natural resources, if appropriate, and with the pertinent municipal advisory group established under
AS 43.82.510
, prepare a list of proposed amendments, if any, to the proposed contract that the commissioner of revenue determines are necessary to respond to public comments;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-430__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>make final findings and a determination as to whether the proposed contract and any proposed amendments prepared under (2) of this subsection meet the requirements and purposes of this chapter.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="43-82-430__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After considering the material described in (a) of this section and securing the agreement of the other parties to the proposed contract regarding any proposed amendments prepared under (a) of this section, if the commissioner determines that the contract is in the long-term fiscal interests of the state, the commissioner shall submit the contract to the governor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="43-82-430__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner's final findings and determination under (a) of this section are final agency decisions under this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_43-82-435">
            <num>43.82.435</num>
            <heading>Legislative authorization.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 43.82.435.   Legislative authorization.
The governor may transmit a contract developed under this chapter to the legislature together with a request for authorization to execute the contract. A contract developed under this chapter is not binding upon or enforceable against the state or other parties to the contract unless the governor is authorized to execute the contract by law. The state and the other parties to the contract may execute the contract within 60 days after the effective date of the law authorizing the contract.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_43-82-440">
            <num>43.82.440</num>
            <heading>Judicial review.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 43.82.440.   Judicial review.
A person may not bring an action challenging the constitutionality of a law authorizing a contract enacted under
AS 43.82.435
or the enforceability of a contract executed under a law authorizing a contract enacted under
AS 43.82.435
unless the action is commenced within 120 days after the date that the contract was executed by the state and the other parties to the contract.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_43-82-445">
            <num>43.82.445</num>
            <heading>Administrative termination of a contract.</heading>
            <subsection eId="43-82-445__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall include terms in a contract developed under
AS 43.82.020
that provide for administrative termination of a party's rights under the procedures and conditions set out in this section if the party has</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-445__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>ceased to meet the requirements of
AS 43.82.110
as a qualified sponsor or qualified sponsor group;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-445__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>intentionally or fraudulently misrepresented, in whole or in part, material facts or circumstances upon which the contract was made;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-445__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>failed to comply with a condition or material term of the contract or a provision of this chapter; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-445__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>failed to comply with the approved qualified project plan or any updated project plan.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="43-82-445__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before administrative termination of a contract under this section, the commissioner shall give notice to the parties of the commissioner's intent to terminate the contract and an opportunity to be heard. The commissioner may also provide the parties an opportunity to cure any deficiency that is the basis for the termination if the commissioner determines that curing the deficiency is appropriate under the circumstances.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="43-82-445__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (a) and (b) of this section, the commissioner may not administratively terminate a contract after the party has committed full project funding except as provided in (e) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="43-82-445__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A party to a contract who is affected by the commissioner's action to terminate under (a) of this section may file an appeal with the superior court under the Alaska Rules of Appellate Procedure.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="43-82-445__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner may provide terms and conditions in a contract developed under
AS 43.82.020
upon which a party's rights under the contract may be administratively terminated after the party commits full project funding.
Article 6. Municipal Participation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_43-82-500">
            <num>43.82.500</num>
            <heading>Obligation to share payments with municipalities.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 43.82.500.   Obligation to share payments with municipalities.
If the commissioner develops a contract under
AS 43.82.020
that includes terms that exempt a party to the contract, and the property, gas, products, and activities associated with the approved qualified project that is subject to the contract, from a municipal tax or assessment in accordance with
AS 29.45.810
or
AS 29.46.010
(b), or
AS 43.82.200
and 43.82.210, the commissioner shall include a term in the contract that the party pay a portion of the periodic payments due under the contract to the revenue-affected municipality.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_43-82-505">
            <num>43.82.505</num>
            <heading>Payments to economically affected municipalities.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 43.82.505.   Payments to economically affected municipalities.
If the commissioner executes a contract under
AS 43.82.020
that will produce one or more economically affected municipalities, the commissioner shall include a term in the contract that provides for a portion of the periodic payments to the economically affected municipalities under the principles in
AS 43.82.520
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_43-82-510">
            <num>43.82.510</num>
            <heading>Municipal advisory group.</heading>
            <subsection eId="43-82-510__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the commissioner approves an application and proposed project plan under
AS 43.82.140
and decides to develop a contract under
AS 43.82.020
and 43.82.200, the commissioner shall notify each revenue-affected municipality and economically affected municipality.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="43-82-510__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The mayor of a municipality notified by the commissioner under (a) of this section may appoint one representative to a municipal advisory group in relation to the application.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="43-82-510__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each municipal advisory group serves until a final action is taken on the application for which the group was appointed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="43-82-510__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each municipal advisory group shall elect a chair.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_43-82-520">
            <num>43.82.520</num>
            <heading>Duties of the commissioner of revenue in relation to municipal participation.</heading>
            <subsection eId="43-82-520__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall meet with each municipal advisory group periodically to report on the development of the contract provisions that affect the municipalities.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="43-82-520__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In developing a contract under
AS 43.82.200
 43.82.270, the commissioner shall ensure that each revenue-affected municipality and economically affected municipality receives a fair and reasonable share of the payments provided under
AS 43.82.210
in accordance with the following principles:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-520__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the share of the payments to revenue-affected municipalities should be given priority over payments to economically affected municipalities with due regard to the anticipated size of the tax base that the contract would exempt from municipal taxation by revenue-affected municipalities;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-520__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the share of the payments to municipalities should be determined with due regard to the anticipated economic and social burdens that would be imposed on the municipality by construction and operation of the project;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-520__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the respective shares of the total payments to the state and to municipalities should be fixed in a manner to ensure that their respective interests are aligned;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-520__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to the extent practicable, the periodic amounts paid to each of the municipalities should be stable and predictable; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="43-82-520__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to the extent practicable, the provisions for sharing payments with municipalities should be consistent with the principles established in
AS 43.82.210</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="43-82-520__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In establishing the municipal shares under (b) of this section, the commissioner shall consult with the pertinent municipal advisory group.
Article 7. Miscellaneous Provisions.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_43-82-600">
            <num>43.82.600</num>
            <heading>Governing law.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 43.82.600.   Governing law.
If a provision of this chapter conflicts with another provision of state or municipal law, the provision of this chapter governs.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_43-82-610">
            <num>43.82.610</num>
            <heading>Regulations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 43.82.610.   Regulations.
The commissioner of revenue, the commissioner of natural resources, and the commissioner of labor and workforce development may adopt regulations to carry out their respective duties under this chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_43-82-620">
            <num>43.82.620</num>
            <heading>Procedures for collection of amounts due; security.</heading>
            <subsection eId="43-82-620__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner may adopt procedures for the collection of amounts due the state under a contract developed under
AS 43.82.020
, including the collection of interest and penalties.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="43-82-620__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner may require a party to a contract developed under
AS 43.82.020
to provide security sufficient to guarantee amounts due under the contract.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_43-82-630">
            <num>43.82.630</num>
            <heading>Reports and audits.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 43.82.630.   Reports and audits.
The commissioner may require periodic reports from and may at reasonable intervals conduct audits and inspect the books of a party that has entered into a contract developed under
AS 43.82.020
to ensure compliance with the provisions of this chapter and the regulations adopted under this chapter and of the terms of the contract.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_43-82-640">
            <num>43.82.640</num>
            <heading>Annual report of the commissioner of labor and workforce development.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 43.82.640.   Annual report of the commissioner of labor and workforce development.
On an annual basis, the commissioner of labor and workforce development shall prepare and present to the legislature a comprehensive report on each party to a contract with the state developed under
AS 43.82.020
, and its contractors, regarding the state residency of the employees working in this state on the approved qualified project that is subject to the contract. The commissioner of labor and workforce development shall use state data bases, including data from the quarterly reports by a party to the contract developed under
AS 43.82.020
and its contractors for unemployment insurance purposes, to determine state residency of employees regarding compliance with
AS 43.82.230
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_43-82-900">
            <num>43.82.900</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 43.82.900.   Definitions.
In this chapter, unless the context requires otherwise,
(1) affected municipality means an economically affected municipality or a revenue-affected municipality;
(2) commencement of commercial operations means the start of regular deliveries of marketable products from an approved qualified project;
(3) cubic foot of gas means the quantity of gas contained in a volume of one cubic foot at a standard temperature of 60 degrees Fahrenheit and a standard absolute pressure of 14.65 pounds per square inch;
(4) economic proximity means the distance within which a person may be willing to design, construct, and operate a gas line to provide service to a local consumer;
(5) economic rent means the estimated total gross revenue less estimated total costs for a qualified project over the term of a contract under
AS 43.82.020
, measured in undiscounted nominal dollars; for purposes of this paragraph, total costs do not include a rate of return on capital, financing costs, or any payments to governments;
(6) economically affected municipality means a municipality the commissioner of revenue determines will be reasonably required to provide additional public services under the terms proposed in an application approved under
AS 43.82.140
(a); the commissioner may consider historical data from construction of the Trans Alaska Pipeline System, and information submitted by a municipality in making the determination;
(7) full project funding means full approval by a party to a contract under
AS 43.82.020
for the expenditure of the capital necessary for construction and operation of the approved qualified project that is subject to the contract;
(8) gas has the meaning given in
AS 43.55.900
;
(9) group means two or more persons;
(10) lease or property has the meaning given in
AS 43.55.900
;
(11) periodic payment means payment made in lieu of one or more other taxes under a contract under
AS 43.82.020
;
(12) revenue-affected municipality means a municipality that the commissioner of revenue reliably expects will be restricted from imposing a tax, or a portion of a tax, as a result of implementation of a contract developed under this chapter;
(13) stranded gas means gas that is not being marketed due to prevailing costs or price conditions as determined by an economic analysis by the commissioner for a particular project.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_43-82-990">
            <num>43.82.990</num>
            <heading>Short title.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 43.82.990.   Short title.
This chapter may be cited as the Alaska Stranded Gas Development Act.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>