<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-41/chapter-37"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-41/chapter-37"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="41.37"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-41/chapter-37/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-41/chapter-37/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-41/chapter-37/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-41/chapter-37/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_41">
        <num>41</num>
        <heading>Public Resources</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_41__chp_37">
          <num>37</num>
          <heading>Citizens' Advisory Commission on Federal Areas in Alaska</heading>
          <section eId="sec_41-37-160">
            <num>41.37.160</num>
            <heading>Citizens' Advisory Commission on Federal Management Areas in Alaska.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.37.160.   Citizens' Advisory Commission on Federal Management Areas in Alaska.
The Citizens' Advisory Commission on Federal Management Areas in Alaska is established in the department for administrative purposes only. In the exercise of its responsibilities, the commission shall consider the views of citizens of the state and officials of the state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-37-170">
            <num>41.37.170</num>
            <heading>Membership and officers.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-37-170__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission is composed of 12 members appointed in accordance with this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-37-170__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The members of the commission who are not members of the legislature shall represent each judicial district, with not more than three members being from any one judicial district .</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-37-170__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The governor shall appoint six members of the commission.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-37-170__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The speaker of the house of representatives shall appoint one member of the commission from the membership of the state house of representatives and two members who are residents of the state who are not legislators.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-37-170__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The president of the senate shall appoint one member of the commission from the membership of the state senate and two members who are residents of the state who are not legislators.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-37-170__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each member of the commission serves at the pleasure of the appointing authority.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-37-170__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall select a presiding officer of the commission from its membership. The commission may elect other officers.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-37-180">
            <num>41.37.180</num>
            <heading>Qualifications of members.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-37-180__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and members appointed under
AS 41.37.170</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-37-180__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and (e) who are not members of the legislature shall be representative of the diversity of users and uses of federal land in the state. At least one member must be enrolled in and represent a federally recognized tribe. At least one other member must be a shareholder of and represent a corporation organized under 43 U.S.C. 1601 et seq. (Alaska Native Claims Settlement Act).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-37-190">
            <num>41.37.190</num>
            <heading>Term of members of the commission.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-37-190__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A member of the commission appointed by the governor serves for a term of four years or until a successor is appointed and qualifies.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-37-190__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A member of the commission appointed from the legislature serves for the person's term of office as a legislator or until a successor is appointed and qualifies.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-37-190__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (b) of this section, a member of the commission appointed by the speaker of the house of representatives or president of the senate serves for four years or until a successor is appointed and qualifies.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-37-200">
            <num>41.37.200</num>
            <heading>Compensation, expenses, and per diem.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-37-200__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A member of the commission who is a legislator or a full-time employee of the state or of a municipality of the state shall suffer no loss of compensation from the state or a municipality of the state as a result of service to the commission.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-37-200__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A member of the commission is entitled to per diem and travel expenses authorized for boards and commissions under
AS 39.20.180
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-37-210">
            <num>41.37.210</num>
            <heading>Staff of the commission.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.37.210.   Staff of the commission.
The commission may employ staff and contract for services relating to matters within its authority. Staff employed under this section are responsible to the commission.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-37-220">
            <num>41.37.220</num>
            <heading>Duties of the commission.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-37-220__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall consider, research, and hold hearings on the consistency with federal law and congressional intent on management, operation, planning, development, and additions to federal management areas in the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-37-220__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall consider, research, and hold hearings on the effect of federal regulations and federal management decisions on the people of the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-37-220__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission may, after consideration of the public policy concerns under (a) and (b) of this section, make a recommendation on the concerns identified under (a) and (b) of this section to an agency of the state or to the agency of the United States that manages federal land in the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-37-220__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall consider the views, research, and reports of advisory groups established by it under
AS 41.37.230
as well as the views, research, and reports of individuals and other groups in the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-37-220__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall establish internal procedures for the management of the responsibilities granted to it under this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-37-220__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall report annually to the governor and the legislature within the first 10 days of a regular legislative session.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-37-220__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall cooperate with each department or agency of the state or with a state board or commission in the fulfillment of its duties.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-37-220__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>All hearings of the commission are subject to
AS 44.62.310
. Hearings of the commission held under this section shall be noticed as provided in
AS 44.62.190
and 44.62.200, and the hearings shall be conducted in accordance with the provisions of
AS 44.62.210
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-37-220__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall determine which matters are considered, researched, heard, and recommended by the commission under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-37-220__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding another provision of this section, the commission may not consider, research, or hold hearings relating to public use on private land, including a highway with an easement onto private land or onto public land reserved for private use. In this subsection, highway has the meaning given in
AS 19.59.001
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-37-230">
            <num>41.37.230</num>
            <heading>Advisory groups of the commission.</heading>
            <subsection eId="41-37-230__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission may establish advisory groups in the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-37-230__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall invite nominations for the membership on the advisory groups and shall consider the nominations in making its appointments to the groups.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="41-37-230__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The membership of each advisory group shall be broadly representative of individuals involved in activities affected by the establishment or management of units of federal land within the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-37-240">
            <num>41.37.240</num>
            <heading>Suit.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.37.240.   Suit.
The commission may request the attorney general to file suit against a federal official or agency if the commission determines that the federal official or agency is acting in violation of an Act of Congress, congressional intent, or the best interests of the state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-37-250">
            <num>41.37.250</num>
            <heading>Agency cooperation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.37.250.   Agency cooperation.
Each state department, agency, board, and commission shall cooperate with the commission in the fulfillment of the duties of the commission under
AS 41.37.220
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_41-37-260">
            <num>41.37.260</num>
            <heading>Definition.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 41.37.260.   Definition.
In this chapter, commission means the Citizens' Advisory Commission on Federal Management Areas in Alaska.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>