<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-10/chapter-20"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-10/chapter-20"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="10.20"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-10/chapter-20/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-10/chapter-20/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-10/chapter-20/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-10/chapter-20/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_10">
        <num>10</num>
        <heading>Corporations and Associations</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_10__chp_20">
          <num>20</num>
          <heading>Alaska Nonprofit Corporation Act</heading>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-005">
            <num>10.20.005</num>
            <heading>Purposes.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.005.   Purposes.
Corporations may be organized under this chapter for any lawful purpose, including, but not limited to, one or more of the following: charitable; religious; benevolent; eleemosynary; educational; civic; cemetery; patriotic; political; social; fraternal; literary; cultural; athletic; scientific; agricultural; horticultural; animal husbandry; and professional, commercial, industrial, or trade association purposes.  Trade unions and other labor organizations may also be organized under this chapter, but cooperative corporations, electric and telephone cooperatives, and organizations subject to state insurance or banking laws may not be organized under this chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-007">
            <num>10.20.007</num>
            <heading>Corporations organized under Alaska Native Claims Settlement Act.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.007.   Corporations organized under Alaska Native Claims Settlement Act.
A village corporation organized under 43 U.S.C. 1601 et seq. (Alaska Native Claims Settlement Act) may be incorporated under and subject to this chapter except the name of the corporation may not contain the word village or otherwise imply that the corporation is a municipal corporation; however, the name of a village may be used in the corporate name.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-011">
            <num>10.20.011</num>
            <heading>General powers.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.011.   General powers.
A corporation may
(1) have perpetual succession by its corporate name unless its duration is limited by its articles of incorporation;
(2) sue and be sued, complain and defend, in its corporate name;
(3) adopt and use a corporate seal or a facsimile thereof, which may be altered at pleasure, and which may be impressed or affixed or in any manner reproduced;
(4) purchase, take, receive, lease, take by gift, devise or bequest, or otherwise acquire, own, hold, improve, use and otherwise deal in and with real or personal property, or any interest in the property, wherever situated;
(5) sell, convey, mortgage, pledge, lease, exchange, transfer and otherwise dispose of all or any part of its property and assets;
(6) lend money to its employees other than its officers and directors and otherwise assist its employees, officers and directors;
(7) purchase, take, receive, subscribe to, or otherwise acquire, own, hold, vote, use, employ, sell, mortgage, lend, pledge, or otherwise dispose of, and otherwise use and deal in and with, shares or other interests in, or obligations of, other domestic or foreign corporations, whether for profit or not for profit, associations, partnerships or individuals, or direct or indirect obligations of the United States, or of any other government, state, territory, governmental district or municipality or of any instrumentality thereof;
(8) make contracts, incur liabilities, borrow money at rates of interests the corporation may determine, issue its notes, bonds, and other obligations, and secure any of its obligations by mortgage or pledge of all or any of its property, franchises and income;
(9) lend money for its corporate purposes, invest and reinvest its funds, and take and hold real and personal property as security for the payment of funds so loaned or invested;
(10) transact its business, carry on its operations, have offices and exercise the powers granted by this chapter in any state, territory, district, or possession of the United States, or in any foreign country;
(11) elect or appoint officers and agents of the corporation, who may be directors or members, define their duties and fix their compensation;
(12) make and alter bylaws, not inconsistent with its articles of incorporation or with the laws of the state, for the administration and regulation of the affairs of the corporation;
(13) make donations for public welfare or for charitable, scientific or educational purposes; and in time of war make donations in aid of war activities;
(14) indemnify a director, officer or former director or officer of the corporation, or a person who has served at its request as a director or officer of another corporation in which it owns shares of capital stock or of which it is a creditor, against expenses actually and reasonably incurred by that person in connection with the defense of any action, suit or proceeding, civil or criminal, in which that person is made a party by reason of being or having been a director or officer, except in relation to matters in which that person was adjudged, in the action, suit or proceeding, to be liable for negligence or misconduct in the performance of corporate duties; and to make any other indemnification authorized by the articles of incorporation or bylaws, or resolution adopted after notice by the members entitled to vote;
(15) pay pensions and establish pension plans or pension trusts for its directors, officers and employees;
(16) cease its corporate activities and surrender its corporate franchise;
(17) have and exercise all powers necessary or convenient to effect the purposes for which the corporation is organized.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-016">
            <num>10.20.016</num>
            <heading>Defense of ultra vires.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-20-016__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An act of a corporation and a conveyance or transfer of real or personal property to or by a corporation is not invalid because the corporation did not have capacity or power to perform the act or to convey or receive the property. However, lack of capacity or power may be asserted as provided in this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-016__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The assertion may be made in a proceeding by a member or director against the corporation to enjoin the performance of an act or the transfer of real or personal property by or to the corporation.  If the unauthorized act or transfer sought to be enjoined is being or is to be performed or made under a contract to which the corporation is a party, the court may, if the parties to the contract are parties to the proceeding and if the court considers it equitable, set aside and enjoin the performance of the contract.  In so doing the court may allow compensation to the corporation or to the other parties to the contract for the loss or damage sustained by either of them resulting from the action of the court in setting aside and enjoining the performance of the contract.  The court may not award anticipated profits to be derived from the performance of the contract as a loss or damage sustained.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-016__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The assertion may be made in a proceeding by the corporation, whether acting directly or through a receiver, trustee, or other legal representative, or through members in a representative suit, against the incumbent or former officers or directors of the corporation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-016__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The assertion may be made in a proceeding by the attorney general to dissolve the corporation, or to enjoin the corporation from the transaction of unauthorized business.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-021">
            <num>10.20.021</num>
            <heading>Corporate name.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-20-021__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The name of a corporation may not contain a word or phrase that indicates or implies that it is organized for a purpose other than one or more of the purposes contained in the articles of incorporation of the corporation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-021__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The name of the corporation must be distinguishable on the records of the department from the name of any other organized entity and from a reserved or registered name. The department may adopt regulations under
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act) to implement this subsection. In this subsection, organized entity and reserved or registered name have the meanings given in
AS 10.35.040
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-026">
            <num>10.20.026</num>
            <heading>Registered office and registered agent.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.026.   Registered office and registered agent.
A corporation shall continuously maintain in the state a registered office which may be, but need not be, the same as its place of business, and a registered agent.  The registered agent may be either an individual resident of the state whose business office is the same as the registered office, or a domestic or foreign corporation authorized to transact business in the state whose business office is the same as the registered office.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-031">
            <num>10.20.031</num>
            <heading>Filing list of corporations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.031.   Filing list of corporations.
The department shall file a list of the name of each corporation, the address of the registered office and the name and address of the registered agent with each clerk of the superior court.  The department shall provide a periodic supplement to the list indicating additions, deletions and changes at least once every six months.  The commissioner shall make the list available to the public for a fee prescribed by the commissioner.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-036">
            <num>10.20.036</num>
            <heading>Change of registered office or agent.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-20-036__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A corporation, domestic or foreign, may change its registered office, agent, or both, by filing with the department a statement signed by the president or the vice-president setting out</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-036__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name of the corporation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-036__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the address of its registered office;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-036__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the address of its new registered office if the registered office is to be changed;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-036__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name of its registered agent;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-036__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name of its new registered agent if its registered agent is to be changed;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-036__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>that the change is authorized by resolution of its board of directors.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-036__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon finding that the statement complies with this chapter, the commissioner shall file it in the commissioner's office. The change becomes effective when the statement is filed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-041">
            <num>10.20.041</num>
            <heading>Change of location or resignation of registered agent.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-20-041__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the registered agent of a corporation, domestic or foreign, changes the location of an office from one address to another within a city or town, or from one city or town in the state to another, the agent may change the registered office for each corporation for whom the agent is acting as registered agent by filing in the office of the commissioner a statement setting out</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-041__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name of the agent;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-041__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the address of the office before change;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-041__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the address to which the office is changed; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-041__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a list of corporations for whom the agent is furnishing a registered office.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-041__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The statement in (a) of this section shall be executed by the registered agent in the agent's individual name and, if the agent is a corporation, domestic or foreign, it shall be executed by its president or a vice-president. The statement shall be delivered to the commissioner who, upon finding that it complies with this chapter, shall file it in the commissioner's office. The change becomes effective when the statement is filed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-041__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A registered agent may resign by filing a written notice, executed in duplicate, with the commissioner.  The commissioner shall immediately mail a copy of the notice to the corporation at its registered office.  The appointment of the agent terminates 30 days after receipt of the notice by the commissioner.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-046">
            <num>10.20.046</num>
            <heading>Service on corporation.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-20-046__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The registered agent of a corporation is an agent upon whom process, notice or demand required or permitted by law to be served upon the corporation may be served.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-046__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Whenever a corporation fails to appoint or maintain a registered agent in the state, the commissioner is an agent of the corporation upon whom the process, notice, or demand may be served.  Service is made upon the commissioner as agent by leaving with the commissioner, or with a clerk having charge of the corporation department of the commissioner's office, duplicate copies of the process, notice or demand.  When process, notice or demand is served on the commissioner, the commissioner shall immediately forward a copy of it by registered mail to the corporation at its registered office. Service on the commissioner is returnable in not less than 30 days.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-046__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall keep a record of processes, notices, and demands served on the commissioner.  The record must show the time of service and the commissioner's action with reference to the service.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-046__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This chapter does not limit or affect the right to serve process, notice or demand required or permitted by law to be served upon a corporation in any other manner permitted by law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-051">
            <num>10.20.051</num>
            <heading>Members and liability of directors, officers, employees, and members.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-20-051__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A corporation may have one or more classes of members or may have no members.  If the corporation has one or more classes of members, the designation of the class or classes, the manner of election or appointment, and the qualifications and rights of the members of each class shall be set out in the articles of incorporation or the bylaws. If the corporation has no members, that fact shall be set out in the articles of incorporation or the bylaws. A corporation may issue certificates evidencing membership.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-051__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The directors, officers, employees, and members of the corporation are not, as such, liable on its obligations.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-056">
            <num>10.20.056</num>
            <heading>Bylaws.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.056.   Bylaws.
The board of directors shall adopt the initial bylaws of a corporation.  The power to adopt, alter, amend or repeal bylaws is vested in the board of directors unless it is reserved to the members by the articles of incorporation. The bylaws may contain provisions for the regulation and management of the affairs of the corporation not inconsistent with law or the articles of incorporation.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-061">
            <num>10.20.061</num>
            <heading>Meetings of members.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-20-061__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Meetings of members may be held at a place, either inside or outside the state, which may be provided in the bylaws.  In the absence of such a provision, all meetings shall be held at the registered office of the corporation in the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-061__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An annual meeting of the members shall be held at a time provided in the bylaws.  Failure to hold the annual meeting at the designated time does not work a forfeiture or dissolution of the corporation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-061__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Special meetings of the members may be called by the president or by the board of directors.  Special meetings of the members may also be called by such other officers, persons or number or proportion of members as may be provided in the articles of incorporation or bylaws.  In the absence of a provision fixing the number or proportion of members entitled to call a meeting, a special meeting of members may be called by members having one-twentieth of the votes entitled to be cast at the meeting.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-066">
            <num>10.20.066</num>
            <heading>Notice of meetings.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.066.   Notice of meetings.
Unless otherwise provided in the articles of incorporation or bylaws, written notice stating the manner, place, if the meeting is to be held at a designated place, day, and hour of the meeting, and, in case of a special meeting, the purpose or purposes for which the meeting is called, shall be delivered not less than 10 nor more than 50 days before the date of the meeting, either personally or by mail, by or at the direction of the president, or the secretary, or the officers or persons calling the meeting, to each member entitled to vote at the meeting. If mailed, the notice shall be considered to be delivered when deposited in the United States mail addressed to the member at the member's address as it appears on the records of the corporation, with postage prepaid.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-071">
            <num>10.20.071</num>
            <heading>Voting; quorum.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-20-071__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The right of the members, or any class or classes of members, to vote may be limited, enlarged, or denied to the extent specified in the articles of incorporation or the bylaws. Unless limited, enlarged, or denied, each member, regardless of class, is entitled to one vote on each matter submitted to a vote of members.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-071__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A member entitled to vote may vote in person or, unless the articles of incorporation or the bylaws otherwise provide, may vote by remote communication, by proxy executed in writing by the member or by the attorney-in-fact for the member, or by proxy executed by electronic transmission by the member or by the authorized attorney-in-fact of the member. A proxy is not valid after 11 months from the date of its execution, unless otherwise provided in the proxy. If directors or officers are to be elected by members, the bylaws may provide that the elections may be conducted by mail.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-071__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The articles of incorporation or the bylaws may provide that in all elections for directors every member entitled to vote shall have the right to cumulate the member's vote and to give one candidate a number of votes equal to the member's vote multiplied by the number of directors to be elected, or by distributing the votes on the same principle among any number of the candidates.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-071__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a corporation has no members or its members have no right to vote, the directors shall have sole voting power.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-071__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The articles of incorporation or the bylaws may provide the number or percentage of members entitled to vote represented in person, by remote communication, or by proxy, or the number or percentage of votes represented in person, by remote communication, or by proxy, which constitute a quorum at a meeting of members. In the absence of any such provision, members holding one- tenth of the votes entitled to be cast on the matter to be voted on represented in person, by remote communication, or by proxy constitute a quorum. A majority of the votes entitled to be cast on a matter to be voted on by the members present or represented by proxy at a meeting at which the quorum is present is necessary for adoption unless a greater proportion is required by this chapter, the articles of incorporation or the bylaws.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-071__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A proxy executed by electronic transmission must</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-071__subsec_f__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>be directed to the person who will be the holder of the proxy or to a proxy solicitation person, including a proxy support service organization or similar agent that is authorized by the person who will be the holder of the proxy to receive the transmission; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-071__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>include information that demonstrates that the stockholder authorized the transmission.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-071__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, electronic transmission has the meaning given in
AS 10.06.990
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-076">
            <num>10.20.076</num>
            <heading>Quorum of members.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.076.   Quorum of members.
Unless otherwise provided in the articles of incorporation or the bylaws, members holding one-tenth of the votes entitled to be cast, represented in person, by remote communication, or by proxy, constitute a quorum at a meeting of members. However, in no event may a quorum consist of less than one-tenth of the votes entitled to vote at a meeting. If a quorum is present, the affirmative vote of a majority of the votes represented at the meeting and entitled to vote on the subject matter is the act of the members, unless the vote of a greater number is required by this chapter or the articles of incorporation or the bylaws.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-081">
            <num>10.20.081</num>
            <heading>Board of directors.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.081.   Board of directors.
The affairs of a corporation shall be managed by a board of directors.  Directors need not be residents of the state or members of the corporation unless the articles of incorporation or the bylaws so require. The articles of incorporation or the bylaws may prescribe other qualifications for directors.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-086">
            <num>10.20.086</num>
            <heading>Number of directors.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-20-086__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The number of directors of a corporation shall be at least three.  The number of directors shall be fixed by the bylaws, except that the number constituting the initial board of directors shall be fixed by the articles of incorporation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-086__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The number of directors may be increased or decreased from time to time by amendment to the bylaws, but a decrease may not have the effect of shortening the term of an incumbent director.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-086__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In the absence of a bylaw fixing the number of directors, the number shall be the same as that stated in the articles of incorporation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-091">
            <num>10.20.091</num>
            <heading>Membership and term of office of first board of directors.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.091.   Membership and term of office of first board of directors.
The names and addresses of the members of the first board of directors shall be stated in the articles of incorporation. Each member holds office until the first annual election of directors or for the period specified in the articles of incorporation.  If no term of office is specified, a director's term is one year.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-096">
            <num>10.20.096</num>
            <heading>Election and terms of directors.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.096.   Election and terms of directors.
At the first annual election of directors and at each annual meeting thereafter the members shall elect directors to hold office for the terms provided in the bylaws.  Each director holds office for the term for which elected and until a successor is elected and qualified. The terms of office of directors may be staggered.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-101">
            <num>10.20.101</num>
            <heading>Vacancies.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.101.   Vacancies.
A vacancy occurring in the board of directors and a directorship to be filled by reason of an increase in the number of directors may be filled by the affirmative vote of a majority of the remaining directors, though less than a quorum of the board of directors, unless the articles of incorporation or the bylaws provide that a vacancy or directorship so created shall be filled in some other manner. A director elected or appointed to fill a vacancy shall be elected or appointed for the unexpired term of the director's predecessor in office.  A directorship to be filled by reason of an increase in the number of directors shall be filled by the board of directors for a term of office which continues only until the next election of directors.  In no case may a vacancy continue for longer than six months or until the next annual meeting of the members, whichever occurs first.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-106">
            <num>10.20.106</num>
            <heading>Quorum of directors.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.106.   Quorum of directors.
A majority of the number of directors fixed by the bylaws, or, in the absence of a bylaw fixing the number of directors, the number stated in the articles of incorporation, constitutes a quorum for the transaction of business unless a greater number is required by the articles of incorporation or the bylaws. The act of the majority of the directors present at a meeting at which a quorum is present is the act of the board of directors, unless the act of a greater number is required by the articles of incorporation or the bylaws.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-111">
            <num>10.20.111</num>
            <heading>Executive committee.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.111.   Executive committee.
If the articles of incorporation or the bylaws so provide, the board of directors, by resolution adopted by a majority of the number of directors fixed by the bylaws, or, in the absence of a bylaw fixing the number of directors, the number stated in the articles of incorporation, may designate two or more directors to constitute an executive committee, which, to the extent provided in the resolution or in the articles of incorporation or the bylaws of the corporation, may exercise the authority of the board of directors in the management of the corporation.  The designation of the executive committee and the delegation of authority to it do not relieve the board of directors or any member of the board from responsibility imposed by law.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-116">
            <num>10.20.116</num>
            <heading>Place and notice of directors' meetings.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-20-116__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Regular or special meetings of the board of directors may be held at a designated place, by remote communication, or at a designated place and by remote communication. The designated place may be inside or outside the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-116__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Regular meetings of the board of directors may be held with or without notice as prescribed in the bylaws. Special meetings of the board of directors shall be held after the notice which shall be prescribed in the bylaws. Attendance of a director at a meeting constitutes a waiver of notice of the meeting, except when a director attends a meeting for the express purpose of objecting to the transaction of any business because the meeting is not lawfully called or convened.  The business to be transacted or the purpose of a regular or special meeting of the board of directors need not be specified in the notice of the meeting unless required by the bylaws.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-121">
            <num>10.20.121</num>
            <heading>Officers.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-20-121__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The officers of a corporation consist of a president, one or more vice presidents as prescribed by the bylaws, a secretary, and a treasurer.  Each of the officers shall be elected by the board of directors at the time and in the manner prescribed by the bylaws.  Other necessary officers and assistant officers and agents may be elected or appointed by the board of directors or chosen in the manner prescribed by the bylaws. Two or more offices may be held by the same person, except the offices of president and secretary.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-121__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The articles of incorporation or bylaws may provide that an officer is an ex officio member of the board of directors.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-121__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An officer may be designated by additional titles as provided in the articles of incorporation or bylaws.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-126">
            <num>10.20.126</num>
            <heading>Removal of officers.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.126.   Removal of officers.
An officer or agent may be removed by the board of directors, or by the executive committee, whenever in its judgment the best interests of the corporation will be served.  Removal is without prejudice to the contract rights of the person removed.  Election or appointment of an officer or agent does not of itself create contract rights.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-131">
            <num>10.20.131</num>
            <heading>Books and records; inspection.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-20-131__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A corporation shall keep correct and complete books and records of account and shall keep minutes of the proceedings of its members, board of directors and committees having any of the authority of the board of directors; and shall keep at its registered office or principal office in the state a record of the names and addresses of its members entitled to vote.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-131__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>All books and records of a corporation may be inspected by any member, or an agent or attorney for the member, for any proper purpose at any reasonable time.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-136">
            <num>10.20.136</num>
            <heading>Shares of stock and dividends prohibited; compensation, benefits, and distributions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.136.   Shares of stock and dividends prohibited; compensation, benefits, and distributions.
A corporation may not have or issue shares of stock.  No dividend may be paid and no part of the income or profit of a corporation may be distributed to its members, directors, or officers.  A corporation may pay compensation in a reasonable amount to its members, directors, or officers for services rendered, may confer benefits upon its members in conformity with its purposes, and upon dissolution or final liquidation may make distribution to its members as permitted by this chapter, and a payment, benefit, or distribution under this section may not be considered to be a dividend or a distribution of income or profit.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-141">
            <num>10.20.141</num>
            <heading>Loans to directors and officers prohibited.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.141.   Loans to directors and officers prohibited.
A corporation may not make loans to its directors or officers.  A director or officer who assents to or participates in the making of such a loan shall be liable to the corporation for the amount of the loan until its repayment.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-146">
            <num>10.20.146</num>
            <heading>Incorporators.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.146.   Incorporators.
Three or more natural persons at least 19 years of age may act as incorporators of a corporation by signing and delivering in duplicate to the commissioner articles of incorporation for the corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-151">
            <num>10.20.151</num>
            <heading>Articles of incorporation; relationship to bylaws; director liability.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-20-151__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The articles of incorporation must set out</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-151__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name of the corporation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-151__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the period of its duration, which may be perpetual;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-151__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the purpose or purposes for which the corporation is organized;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-151__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provisions, not inconsistent with law, which the incorporators elect to set out in the articles of incorporation for the regulation of the internal affairs of the corporation, including provision for distribution of assets on dissolution or final liquidation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-151__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the address of its initial registered office, and the name of its initial registered agent at the address;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-151__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the number of directors constituting the initial board of directors, and the names and addresses of the persons who are to serve as the initial directors;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-151__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name and address of each incorporator.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-151__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>It is not necessary to set out in the articles of incorporation any of the corporate powers enumerated in this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-151__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless the articles of incorporation provide that a change in the number of directors shall be made only by amendment to the articles of incorporation, a change in the number of directors made by amendment to the bylaws is controlling.  In all other cases, if a provision of the articles of incorporation is inconsistent with a bylaw, the provision of the articles of incorporation shall be controlling.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-151__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to the matters required to be set out in the articles of incorporation by (a) of this section, the articles of incorporation may also contain a provision eliminating or limiting the personal liability of a director to the corporation for monetary damages for the breach of fiduciary duty as a director. The articles of incorporation may not eliminate or limit the liability of a director for</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-151__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a breach of a director's duty of loyalty to the corporation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-151__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>acts or omissions not in good faith or that involve intentional misconduct or a knowing violation of law; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-151__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a transaction from which the director derives an improper personal benefit.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-151__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The provisions of (d) of this section do not eliminate or limit the liability of a director for an act or omission that occurs before the effective date of the articles of incorporation or of an amendment to the articles of incorporation authorized by (d) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-153">
            <num>10.20.153</num>
            <heading>Provisions considered to be in articles of incorporation by operation of law; option to exclude provision.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-20-153__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The articles of incorporation of every nonprofit corporation which is a private foundation, as defined in  26 U.S.C. 509 (Internal Revenue Code of 1954), are considered to contain provisions prohibiting the corporation from</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-153__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>engaging in an act of self-dealing, as defined in  26 U.S.C. 4941(d) (Internal Revenue Code of 1954), which would give rise to liability for the tax imposed by  26 U.S.C. 4941(a) (Internal Revenue Code of 1954);</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-153__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>retaining excess business holdings, as defined in  26 U.S.C. 4943(c) (Internal Revenue Code of 1954), which would give rise to liability for the tax imposed by  26 U.S.C. 4943(a) (Internal Revenue Code of 1954);</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-153__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>making an investment which would jeopardize the carrying out of any of its exempt purposes, within the meaning of  26 U.S.C. 4944 (Internal Revenue Code of 1954), so as to give rise to liability for the tax imposed by  26 U.S.C. 4944(a) (Internal Revenue Code of 1954); and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-153__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>making taxable expenditures, as defined in  26 U.S.C. 4945(d) (Internal Revenue Code of 1954), which would give rise to liability for the tax imposed by  26 U.S.C. 4945(a) (Internal Revenue Code of 1954).</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-153__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The articles of incorporation of every nonprofit corporation that is a private foundation, as defined in  26 U.S.C. 509 (Internal Revenue Code of 1954), are considered to contain a provision requiring the corporation to distribute, for the purposes specified in its articles of incorporation, for each taxable year, amounts at least sufficient to avoid liability for the tax imposed by  26 U.S.C. 4942(a) (Internal Revenue Code of 1954).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-153__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A nonprofit corporation may at any time amend its articles of incorporation or other instrument governing the corporation, by any amendment process open to it under the laws of this state, to provide that some or all provisions of (a) and (b) of this section do not apply to the corporation.  A nonprofit corporation formed after August 23, 1971 may provide in its articles of incorporation that some or all provisions of (a) and (b) of this section do not apply to the corporation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-153__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, references to provisions of the Internal Revenue Code of 1954 include future amendments to those provisions.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-156">
            <num>10.20.156</num>
            <heading>Filing of articles of incorporation.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-20-156__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Duplicate originals of the articles of incorporation shall be delivered to the commissioner.  Upon finding that the articles of incorporation conform to law, the commissioner shall, when all fees prescribed by this chapter have been paid,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-156__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>endorse on each duplicate original the word filed, and the date of the filing;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-156__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>file one duplicate original in the commissioner's office;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-156__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>issue a certificate of incorporation and affix the other duplicate original to it.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-156__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The certificate of incorporation, together with the duplicate original of the articles of incorporation affixed by the commissioner, shall be returned to the incorporators or their representative.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-161">
            <num>10.20.161</num>
            <heading>Effect of issuance of certificate of incorporation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.161.   Effect of issuance of certificate of incorporation.
Upon the issuance of the certificate of incorporation, the corporate existence begins.  The certificate of incorporation is conclusive evidence that all conditions precedent required to be performed by the incorporators have been complied with and that the corporation has been incorporated. The issuance of the certificate does not affect the right of the state to bring a proceeding to cancel or revoke the certificate of incorporation or for involuntary dissolution of the corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-166">
            <num>10.20.166</num>
            <heading>Organizational meeting of directors; first meeting of members.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-20-166__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After the issuance of the certificate of incorporation, an organizational meeting of the board of directors named in the articles of incorporation shall be held at a designated place, by remote communication, or at a designated place and by remote communication at the call of a majority of the incorporators, for the purpose of adopting bylaws, electing officers, and the transaction of other business as may come before the meeting. The designated place may be inside or outside the state. The incorporators calling the meeting shall give at least three days' notice of the meeting by mail to each director named, and the notice must state the time and place of the meeting.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-166__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A first meeting of the members may be held at the call of a majority of the directors for purposes stated in the notice of the meeting.
Article 3. Amendment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-171">
            <num>10.20.171</num>
            <heading>Right to amend articles of incorporation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.171.   Right to amend articles of incorporation.
A corporation may amend its articles of incorporation, from time to time, in any and as many respects as may be desired, so long as its articles of incorporation, as amended, contain only those provisions which might lawfully be contained in original articles of incorporation at the time the amendment is made.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-176">
            <num>10.20.176</num>
            <heading>Procedure to amend articles of incorporation.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-20-176__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Amendments to the articles of incorporation shall be made in the manner set out in this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-176__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If there are members entitled to vote, the board of directors shall adopt a resolution setting out the proposed amendment and directing that it be submitted to a vote at a meeting of members entitled to vote, which may be either an annual or a special meeting.  Written notice setting out the proposed amendment or a summary of the changes shall be given to each member entitled to vote within the time and in the manner provided in this chapter for the giving of notice of meetings of members.  The proposed amendment shall be adopted upon receiving at least two-thirds of the votes which members present at the meeting or represented by proxy are entitled to cast.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-176__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If there are no members, or no members entitled to vote, an amendment shall be adopted at a meeting of the board of directors upon receiving the vote of a majority of the directors in office.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-176__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Any number of amendments may be submitted and voted upon at any one meeting.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-181">
            <num>10.20.181</num>
            <heading>Articles of amendment.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.181.   Articles of amendment.
The articles of amendment shall be executed in duplicate by the corporation by its president or a vice president, and its secretary or an assistant secretary, and must set out
(1) the name of the corporation;
(2) the amendment adopted;
(3) if there are members entitled to vote on the amendment,
(A) a statement setting out the date of the meeting of members at which the amendment was adopted, that a quorum was present at the meeting, and that the amendment received at least two-thirds of the votes which members present at the meeting or represented by proxy were entitled to cast; or
(B) a statement that the amendment was adopted by a consent in writing signed by all members entitled to vote with respect to the amendment;
(4) if there are no members, or no members entitled to vote, a statement of that fact, the date of the meeting of the board of directors at which the amendment was adopted, and a statement of the fact that the amendment received the vote of a majority of the directors in office.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-186">
            <num>10.20.186</num>
            <heading>Filing of articles of amendment.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-20-186__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Duplicate originals of the articles of amendment shall be delivered to the commissioner.  Upon finding that the articles of amendment conform to law, the commissioner shall, when all fees prescribed in this chapter have been paid,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-186__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>endorse on each duplicate original the word filed, and the date of the filing;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-186__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>file one duplicate original in the commissioner's office;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-186__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>issue a certificate of amendment and affix the other duplicate original to it.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-186__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The certificate of amendment, together with the duplicate original of the articles of amendment affixed by the commissioner, shall be returned to the corporation or its representative.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-191">
            <num>10.20.191</num>
            <heading>Effect of certificate of amendment.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-20-191__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon the issuance of the certificate of amendment by the commissioner, the amendment becomes effective and the articles of incorporation are considered amended accordingly.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-191__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An amendment does not affect an existing cause of action in favor of or against the corporation, or a pending suit to which the corporation is a party, or the existing rights of persons other than members.  In the event the corporate name is changed by amendment, a suit brought by or against the corporation under its former name does not abate for that reason.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-196">
            <num>10.20.196</num>
            <heading>Restated articles of incorporation.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-20-196__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A domestic corporation may at any time restate its articles of incorporation as theretofore amended in the manner set out in this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-196__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If there are members entitled to vote, the board of directors shall adopt a resolution setting out the proposed restated articles of incorporation and directing that they be submitted to a vote at a meeting of members entitled to vote, which may be either an annual or a special meeting.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-196__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Written notice setting out the proposed restated articles or a summary of the provisions shall be given to each member entitled to vote within the time and in the manner provided in this chapter for giving notice of meetings to members.  If the meeting is an annual meeting, the proposed restated articles or a summary of the provisions may be included in the notice of the annual meeting.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-196__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>At the meeting a vote of the members entitled to vote shall be taken on the proposed restated articles.  The restated articles shall be adopted upon receiving the affirmative vote of a majority of the members entitled to vote who are present at the meeting or represented by proxy.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-196__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If there are no members, or no members entitled to vote, the proposed restated articles shall be adopted at a meeting of the board of directors upon receiving the affirmative vote of a majority of the directors in office.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-201">
            <num>10.20.201</num>
            <heading>Execution of restated articles of incorporation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.201.   Execution of restated articles of incorporation.
Upon approval, the restated articles of incorporation shall be executed in duplicate by the corporation by its president or a vice-president and by its secretary or assistant secretary.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-206">
            <num>10.20.206</num>
            <heading>Contents of restated articles of incorporation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.206.   Contents of restated articles of incorporation.
The restated articles of incorporation must set out
(1) the name of the corporation;
(2) the period of its duration;
(3) the purpose or purposes which the corporation is authorized to pursue;
(4) other provisions, not inconsistent with law, which are set out in the articles of incorporation as amended, except that it is not necessary to set out in the restated articles of incorporation the registered office of the corporation, its registered agent, its directors or its incorporators;
(5) a statement that the restated articles of incorporation correctly set out the provisions of the articles of incorporation as amended, and that they have been adopted as required by law and that they supersede the original articles of incorporation and all amendments.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-211">
            <num>10.20.211</num>
            <heading>Filing of restated articles of incorporation with commissioner.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-20-211__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Duplicate originals of the restated articles of incorporation shall be delivered to the commissioner. Upon finding that the restated articles of incorporation conform to law, the commissioner shall, when all fees prescribed in this chapter have been paid,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-211__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>endorse on each duplicate original the word filed, and the date of the filing;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-211__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>file one duplicate original in the commissioner's office;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-211__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>issue a restated certificate of incorporation and affix the other duplicate original to it.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-211__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The restated certificate of incorporation, together with the duplicate original of the restated articles of incorporation affixed by the commissioner, shall be returned to the corporation or its representative.
Article 4. Merger, Consolidation, and Disposition of Assets.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-216">
            <num>10.20.216</num>
            <heading>Merger.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.216.   Merger.
Two or more domestic nonprofit corporations may merge into one of the two or more corporations under a plan of merger approved in the manner provided in this chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-221">
            <num>10.20.221</num>
            <heading>Procedure for merger.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.221.   Procedure for merger.
The board of directors of each corporation shall, by resolution, approve a plan of merger setting out
(1) the names of the corporations proposing to merge and the name of the corporation into which they propose to merge, which is hereafter referred to as the surviving corporation;
(2) the terms and conditions of the proposed merger;
(3) a statement of changes in the articles of incorporation of the surviving corporation caused by the merger;
(4) other provisions with respect to the merger considered necessary or desirable.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-226">
            <num>10.20.226</num>
            <heading>Consolidation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.226.   Consolidation.
Two or more domestic corporations may consolidate into a new corporation under a plan of consolidation approved in the manner provided in this chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-231">
            <num>10.20.231</num>
            <heading>Procedure for consolidation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.231.   Procedure for consolidation.
The board of directors of each corporation shall, by a resolution, approve a plan of consolidation setting out
(1) the names of the corporations proposing to consolidate, and the name of the new corporation into which they propose to consolidate, which is hereafter referred to as the new corporation;
(2) the terms and conditions of the proposed consolidation;
(3) all of the statements with respect to the new corporation required to be set out in articles of incorporation for corporations organized under this chapter;
(4) other provisions with respect to the consolidation considered necessary or desirable.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-236">
            <num>10.20.236</num>
            <heading>Adoption of plan of merger or consolidation.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-20-236__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A plan of merger or consolidation shall be adopted in the manner set out in this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-236__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the members of a merging or consolidating corporation are entitled to vote, the board of directors of the corporation shall adopt a resolution approving the proposed plan and directing that it be submitted to a vote at a meeting of members entitled to vote, which may be either an annual or a special meeting.  Written notice setting forth the proposed plan or a summary shall be given to each member entitled to vote at the meeting within the time and in the manner provided in this chapter for the giving of notice of meetings of members.  The proposed plan shall be adopted upon receiving at least two-thirds of the votes which members present at the meeting or represented by proxy are entitled to cast.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-236__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a merging or consolidating corporation has no members, or no members entitled to vote, a plan of merger or consolidation shall be adopted at a meeting of the board of directors of the corporation upon receiving the vote of a majority of the directors in office.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-241">
            <num>10.20.241</num>
            <heading>Abandonment of plan of merger or consolidation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.241.   Abandonment of plan of merger or consolidation.
After approval by a vote of the members, or in the case of a corporation with no members or no members entitled to vote, after approval by its board of directors, of each corporation, and before the filing of the articles of merger or consolidation, the merger or consolidation may be abandoned under provisions, if any, set out in the plan of merger or consolidation.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-246">
            <num>10.20.246</num>
            <heading>Execution of articles of merger or consolidation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.246.   Execution of articles of merger or consolidation.
Upon approval of the plan of merger or consolidation, articles of merger or articles of consolidation shall be executed in duplicate by each corporation by its president or a vice-president and its secretary or an assistant secretary.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-251">
            <num>10.20.251</num>
            <heading>Contents of articles of merger or consolidation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.251.   Contents of articles of merger or consolidation.
The articles of merger or consolidation must set out
(1) the plan of merger or the plan of consolidation;
(2) if the members of any merging or consolidating corporation are entitled to vote, as to each such corporation
(A) a statement setting out the date of the meeting of members at which the plan was adopted, that a quorum was present at the meeting, and that the plan received at least two-thirds of the votes which members present at the meeting or represented by proxy were entitled to cast; or
(B) a statement that the plan was adopted by a consent in writing signed by all members entitled to vote;
(3) if a merging or consolidating corporation has no members, or no members entitled to vote, as to each corporation a statement of this fact, the date of the meeting of the board of directors at which the plan was adopted and a statement of the fact that the plan received the vote of a majority of the directors in office.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-256">
            <num>10.20.256</num>
            <heading>Filing of articles of merger or consolidation with commissioner.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-20-256__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Duplicate originals of the articles of merger or articles of consolidation shall be delivered to the commissioner.  Upon finding that the articles conform to law, the commissioner shall, when all fees prescribed in this chapter have been paid,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-256__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>endorse on each duplicate original the word filed, and the date of the filing;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-256__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>file one duplicate original in the commissioner's office;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-256__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>issue a certificate of merger or a certificate of consolidation and affix the other duplicate original to it.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-256__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The certificate of merger or certificate of consolidation, together with the duplicate original of the articles of merger or articles of consolidation affixed shall be returned to the surviving or new corporation or its representative.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-261">
            <num>10.20.261</num>
            <heading>Effective date and effect of merger or consolidation.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-20-261__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon the issuance of the certificate of merger or the certificate of consolidation, the merger or consolidation becomes effective.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-261__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Merger or consolidation has the following effect:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-261__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the merging or consolidating corporations are a single corporation, which, in the case of a merger, is the corporation designated in the plan of merger as the surviving corporation, and, in the case of a consolidation, is the new corporation provided for in the plan of consolidation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-261__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the separate existence of the corporations, except the surviving or new corporation, ceases;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-261__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the surviving or new corporation has the rights, privileges, immunities and powers and is subject to the duties and liabilities of a corporation organized under this chapter;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-261__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the surviving or new corporation possesses the rights, privileges, immunities and franchises, public and private, of the merging or consolidating corporations; all real, personal and mixed property, and all debts due, including subscriptions to shares, and all other choses in action, and every other interest of or belonging to or due to each of the corporations are transferred to and vested in the surviving or new corporation; the title to real estate, or interest in real estate, vested in the corporations does not revert nor is it in any way impaired because of the merger or consolidation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-261__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the surviving or new corporation is liable for the liabilities and obligations of each of the corporations merged or consolidated; a claim existing or action or proceeding pending by or against the corporations may be prosecuted as if the merger or consolidation had not taken place, or the surviving or new corporation may be substituted in its place; neither the rights of creditors nor liens upon the property of a merging or consolidating corporation are impaired by the merger or consolidation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-261__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in the case of a merger, the articles of incorporation of the surviving corporation are amended to the extent that changes in its articles of incorporation are stated in the plan of merger; in the case of a consolidation, the statements set out in the articles of consolidation which are required or permitted to be set out in the articles of incorporation of corporations organized under this chapter are the original articles of incorporation of the new corporation.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-266">
            <num>10.20.266</num>
            <heading>Merger or consolidation of domestic and foreign corporations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.266.   Merger or consolidation of domestic and foreign corporations.
One or more foreign corporations and one or more domestic corporations may be merged or consolidated in the manner provided in
AS 10.20.271
and 10.20.275 if the merger or consolidation is permitted by the laws of the state under which each foreign corporation is organized.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-271">
            <num>10.20.271</num>
            <heading>Law applicable when domestic and foreign corporations merge or consolidate.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-20-271__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each domestic corporation shall comply with the provisions of this chapter with respect to the merger or consolidation of domestic corporations and each foreign corporation shall comply with the applicable provisions of the laws of the state under which it is organized.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-271__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the surviving or new corporation is to be governed by the laws of a state other than this state, it shall comply with the provisions of this chapter with respect to foreign corporations if it is to transact business in this state and in every case it shall file with the commissioner</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-271__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an agreement that it may be served with process in this state in a proceeding for the enforcement of an obligation of a domestic corporation which is a party to the merger or consolidation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-271__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an irrevocable appointment of the commissioner as its agent to accept service of process in these proceedings.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-275">
            <num>10.20.275</num>
            <heading>Effect of merger or consolidation of foreign and domestic corporations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.275.   Effect of merger or consolidation of foreign and domestic corporations.
If the surviving or new corporation is to be governed by the law of this state, the effect of the merger or consolidation is the same as the merger or consolidation of domestic corporations.  If the surviving or new corporation is to be governed by the laws of another state, the effect of the merger or consolidation is the same as the merger or consolidation of domestic corporations except insofar as the laws of the other state provide otherwise.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-280">
            <num>10.20.280</num>
            <heading>Sale, lease, exchange, mortgage, or other disposition of assets.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-20-280__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A sale, lease, exchange, mortgage, pledge, or other disposition of all, or substantially all, the property and assets of a corporation may be made upon such terms and conditions and for such consideration, which may consist in whole or in part of money or property, real or personal, including shares of any corporation for profit, domestic or foreign, as may be authorized in the manner set out in this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-280__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If there are members entitled to vote, the board of directors shall adopt a resolution recommending the sale, lease, exchange, mortgage, pledge, or other disposition and directing that it be submitted to a vote at a meeting of members entitled to vote, which may be either an annual or a special meeting. Written notice stating that the purpose, or one of the purposes, of the meeting is to consider the sale, lease, exchange, mortgage, pledge, or other disposition of all or substantially all, the property and assets of the corporation shall be given to each member entitled to vote at the meeting, within the time and in the manner provided by this chapter for the giving of notice of meetings of members.  At the meeting the members may authorize the sale, lease, exchange, mortgage, pledge, or other disposition and may fix, or may authorize the board of directors to fix, the terms and conditions thereof and the consideration to be received by the corporation therefor. This authorization shall require at least two-thirds of the votes which members present at the meeting or represented by proxy are entitled to cast.  After authorization by a vote of members, the board of directors may abandon the sale, lease, exchange, mortgage, pledge, or other disposition of assets, subject to the rights of third parties under related contracts, without further action or approval by members.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-280__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If there are no members, or no members entitled to vote, a sale, lease, exchange, mortgage, pledge, or other disposition of all, or substantially all, the property and assets of a corporation shall be authorized upon receiving the vote of a majority of the directors in office.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-285">
            <num>10.20.285</num>
            <heading>Other transactions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.285.   Other transactions.
Under
AS 10.55
(Alaska Entity Transactions Act), a corporation may enter into mergers, interest exchanges, conversions, and domestications that are not covered by
AS 10.20.216
 10.20.280.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-290">
            <num>10.20.290</num>
            <heading>Voluntary dissolution.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-20-290__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A corporation may dissolve and wind up its affairs in the manner set out in (b) and (c) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-290__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If there are members entitled to vote, the board of directors shall adopt a resolution recommending that the corporation be dissolved, and directing that the question of the dissolution be submitted to a vote at a meeting of members entitled to vote, which may be either an annual or a special meeting. Written notice stating that the purpose, or one of the purposes, of the meeting is to consider the advisability of dissolving the corporation, shall be given to each member entitled to vote at the meeting, within the time and in the manner provided in this chapter for the giving of notice of meetings of members.  A resolution to dissolve the corporation shall be adopted upon receiving at least two-thirds of the votes which members present at the meeting or represented by proxy are entitled to cast.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-290__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If there are no members, or no members entitled to vote, the dissolution of the corporation shall be authorized at a meeting of the board of directors upon the adoption of a resolution to dissolve by the vote of a majority of the directors in office.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-290__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon the adoption of a resolution by the members, or by the board of directors if there are no members or no members entitled to vote, the corporation shall cease to conduct its affairs except as may be necessary to wind them up, shall immediately cause a notice of the proposed dissolution to be mailed to each known creditor of the corporation, and shall proceed to collect its assets and apply and distribute them as provided in this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-290__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Following the adoption of a resolution to dissolve, a copy of it executed by the corporation's president or vice-president and a secretary or assistant secretary shall be immediately filed with the commissioner. The resolution must state the number of members and the number of directors voting for and against it.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-290__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A corporation, which has filed a resolution of voluntary dissolution, which has not concluded its affairs and received a certificate of dissolution, within two years after the date of filing the resolution, shall be involuntarily dissolved by the commissioner.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-295">
            <num>10.20.295</num>
            <heading>Distribution of assets.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.295.   Distribution of assets.
The assets of a corporation in the process of dissolution shall be applied and distributed as follows:
(1) all liabilities and obligations of the corporation shall be paid and discharged, or adequate provision shall be made therefor;
(2) assets held by the corporation upon condition requiring return, transfer or conveyance, which condition occurs by reason of the dissolution, shall be returned, transferred or conveyed in accordance with the requirements;
(3) assets received and held by the corporation subject to limitations permitting their use only for charitable, religious, eleemosynary, benevolent, educational or similar purposes, but not held upon a condition requiring return, transfer or conveyance by reason of the dissolution, shall be transferred or conveyed to one or more domestic or foreign corporations, societies or organizations engaged in activities substantially similar to those of the dissolving corporation, under a plan of distribution adopted as provided in this chapter;
(4) other assets, if any, shall be distributed in accordance with the provisions of the articles of incorporation or bylaws to the extent that the articles of incorporation or bylaws determine the distributive rights of members, or any class or classes of members, or provide for distribution to others;
(5) any remaining assets may be distributed to persons, societies, organizations or domestic or foreign corporations, whether for profit or nonprofit, as may be specified in a plan of distribution adopted as provided in this chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-300">
            <num>10.20.300</num>
            <heading>Plan of distribution.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-20-300__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A plan providing for the distribution of assets, not inconsistent with the provisions of this chapter, may be adopted by a corporation in the process of dissolution and shall be adopted by a corporation for the purpose of authorizing a transfer or conveyance of assets for which this chapter requires a plan of distribution, in the manner set out in this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-300__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If there are members entitled to vote, the board of directors shall adopt a resolution recommending a plan of distribution and directing the submission to a vote at a meeting of members entitled to vote, which may be either an annual or a special meeting.  Written notice setting out the proposed plan of distribution or a summary shall be given to each member entitled to vote at the meeting, within the time and in the manner provided in this chapter for giving notice of meetings of members.  The plan of distribution shall be adopted upon receiving at least two-thirds of the votes which members present at the meeting or represented by proxy are entitled to cast.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-300__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If there are no members, or no members entitled to vote, a plan of distribution shall be adopted at a meeting of the board of directors upon receiving a vote of a majority of the directors in office.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-300__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A plan of distribution shall be immediately filed with the commissioner. The plan of distribution must state the number of members and the number of directors voting for and against it.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-305">
            <num>10.20.305</num>
            <heading>Revocation of voluntary dissolution proceedings.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-20-305__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A corporation may, at any time before the issuance of a certificate of dissolution by the commissioner, revoke the action taken to dissolve the corporation, in the manner set out in this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-305__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If there are members entitled to vote, the board of directors shall adopt a resolution recommending that the voluntary dissolution proceedings be revoked, and directing that the question of revocation be submitted to a vote at a meeting of members entitled to vote, which may be either an annual or a special meeting.  Written notice stating that the purpose, or one of the purposes, of the meeting is to consider the advisability of revoking the voluntary dissolution proceedings, shall be given to each member entitled to vote at the meeting, within the time and in the manner provided in this chapter for the giving of notice of meetings of members. A resolution to revoke the voluntary dissolution proceedings shall be adopted upon receiving at least two-thirds of the votes which members present at the meeting or represented by proxy are entitled to cast.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-305__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If there are no members, or no members entitled to vote, a resolution to revoke the voluntary dissolution proceedings shall be adopted at a meeting of the board of directors upon receiving the vote of a majority of the directors in office.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-305__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon the adoption of the resolution by the members, or by the board of directors where there are no members or no members entitled to vote on it, the corporation may again conduct its affairs.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-305__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon the adoption of the resolution, a copy shall immediately be filed with the commissioner.  The resolution must state the number of members and the number of directors voting for and against it.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-310">
            <num>10.20.310</num>
            <heading>Articles of dissolution.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.310.   Articles of dissolution.
If voluntary dissolution proceedings have not been revoked, then, after all debts, liabilities, and obligations of the corporation have been paid and discharged, or adequate provision made for payment, and all of the remaining property and assets of the corporation transferred, conveyed, or distributed in accordance with the provisions of this chapter, articles of dissolution shall be executed in duplicate by the corporation by its president or a vice-president and its secretary or an assistant secretary. The articles of dissolution must set out
(1) the name of the corporation;
(2) if there are members entitled to vote,
(A) a statement setting out the date of the meeting of members at which the resolution to dissolve was adopted, that a quorum was present at the meeting, and that the resolution received at least two-thirds of the votes that members present at the meeting or represented by proxy were entitled to cast; or
(B) a statement that the resolution was adopted by a consent in writing signed by all members entitled to vote;
(3) if there are no members, or no members entitled to vote, a statement of the fact, the date of the meeting of the board of directors at which the resolution to dissolve was adopted, and a statement of the fact that the resolution received the vote of a majority of the directors in office;
(4) that all debts, obligations, and liabilities of the corporation have been paid and discharged or that adequate provision has been made for the payment;
(5) a copy of the plan of distribution, if any, as adopted by the corporation, or a statement that no plan was adopted;
(6) that all the remaining property and assets of the corporation have been transferred, conveyed, or distributed in accordance with the provisions of this chapter;
(7) that there are no suits pending against the corporation in any court, or that adequate provision has been made for the satisfaction of a judgment, order, or decree that may be entered against it in a pending suit.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-315">
            <num>10.20.315</num>
            <heading>Filing of articles of dissolution.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-20-315__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Duplicate originals of the articles of dissolution shall be delivered to the commissioner.  Upon finding that the articles of dissolution conform to law, the commissioner shall, when all fees prescribed by this chapter have been paid:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-315__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>endorse on each of the duplicate originals the word filed, and the date of the filing;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-315__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>file one of the duplicate originals in the commissioner's office;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-315__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>issue a certificate of dissolution and affix the other duplicate original to it.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-315__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The certificate of dissolution, together with the duplicate original of the articles of dissolution affixed shall be returned to the representative of the dissolved corporation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-320">
            <num>10.20.320</num>
            <heading>Effect of certificate of dissolution.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.320.   Effect of certificate of dissolution.
Upon the issuance of the certificate of dissolution the existence of the corporation ceases, except for the purpose of suits, other proceedings and appropriate corporate action by members, directors, and officers as provided in this chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-325">
            <num>10.20.325</num>
            <heading>Grounds for involuntary dissolution.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.325.   Grounds for involuntary dissolution.
A corporation may be dissolved involuntarily by the commissioner when it is established that
(1) the corporation has failed to file its biennial report within the time required by this chapter;
(2) the corporation procured its articles of incorporation through fraud;
(3) the corporation has continued to exceed or abuse the authority conferred upon it by law;
(4) the corporation has failed for 30 days to appoint and maintain a registered agent in the state;
(5) the corporation has failed for 30 days after change of its registered office or registered agent to file in the office of the commissioner a statement of the change;
(6) the corporation has failed, within the time required by this chapter, to revoke or complete a plan of voluntary dissolution; or
(7) the corporation is 90 days delinquent in filing a notice of change of an officer or director as required by this chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-335">
            <num>10.20.335</num>
            <heading>Notice to corporation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.335.   Notice to corporation.
When the commissioner determines that a corporation has given any cause for involuntary dissolution, the commissioner shall mail to the corporation a notice, setting out the grounds for involuntary dissolution, 60 days before a certificate of dissolution is issued. The commissioner shall mail the notice and any subsequent certificate of dissolution in the same manner as required for notices and certificates of involuntary dissolution under
AS 10.06.633
(i).</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-345">
            <num>10.20.345</num>
            <heading>Removal of ground for dissolution.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.345.   Removal of ground for dissolution.
If the corporation, within the time required by this chapter, files its biennial report or appoints or maintains a registered agent as provided in this chapter, or files with the commissioner the required statement of change of registered office or registered agent, or revokes or concludes a plan of voluntary dissolution, the commissioner's authority to involuntarily dissolve the corporation ceases.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-355">
            <num>10.20.355</num>
            <heading>Jurisdiction of court to liquidate assets and business of corporation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.355.   Jurisdiction of court to liquidate assets and business of corporation.
The superior court may liquidate the assets and business of a corporation in the cases provided in
AS 10.20.360
 10.20.370.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-360">
            <num>10.20.360</num>
            <heading>Action by members for liquidation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.360.   Action by members for liquidation.
In an action by a member, the superior court may liquidate the assets and business of a corporation when it is established that
(1) the directors are deadlocked in the management of the corporate affairs, the members are unable to break the deadlock, and irreparable injury to the corporation is being suffered or is threatened by reason of the deadlock;
(2) the acts of the directors or those in control of the corporation are illegal, oppressive, or fraudulent;
(3) the members are deadlocked in voting power, and have failed, for a period which includes at least two consecutive annual meeting dates, to elect successors to directors whose terms have expired or would have expired upon the election of their successors; or
(4) the corporate assets are being misapplied or wasted.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-365">
            <num>10.20.365</num>
            <heading>Action by creditor for liquidation.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-20-365__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In an action by a creditor, the superior court may liquidate the assets and business of a corporation when</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-365__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the claim of the creditor has been reduced to judgment and an execution on the judgment has been returned unsatisfied and it is established that the corporation is insolvent; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-365__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the corporation has admitted in writing that the claim of the creditor is due and owing and it is established that the corporation is insolvent.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-365__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section insolvent means inability of a corporation to pay its debts as they become due in the usual course of its business.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-370">
            <num>10.20.370</num>
            <heading>Liquidation on application by corporation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.370.   Liquidation on application by corporation.
Upon application by a corporation that has filed a statement of intent to dissolve, as provided in this chapter, to have its liquidation continued under the supervision of the court, the superior court may liquidate the assets and affairs of the corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-380">
            <num>10.20.380</num>
            <heading>Joinder of members.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.380.   Joinder of members.
It is not necessary to make members parties to an action or proceeding for liquidation of the assets of a corporation unless relief is sought against them personally.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-385">
            <num>10.20.385</num>
            <heading>Procedure in liquidation of corporation by court.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.385.   Procedure in liquidation of corporation by court.
In a proceeding to liquidate the assets and business of a corporation the superior court may issue injunctions, appoint a receiver pendente lite with powers and duties as the court may direct, and take other proceedings necessary to preserve the corporate assets wherever situated and carry on the business of the corporation until a full hearing is had.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-390">
            <num>10.20.390</num>
            <heading>Appointment of receiver; powers.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.390.   Appointment of receiver; powers.
After a hearing held upon such notice as the court may direct to be given to all parties to the proceedings and to any other parties in interest designated by the court, the court may appoint a liquidating receiver with authority to collect the assets of the corporation, including amounts owing to the corporation by members.  The liquidating receiver may, subject to the order of the court, sell, convey, and dispose of all or a part of the assets of the corporation wherever situated, either at public or private sale.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-395">
            <num>10.20.395</num>
            <heading>Disposition of assets or proceeds.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.395.   Disposition of assets or proceeds.
The assets of the corporation or the proceeds resulting from a sale, conveyance, or other disposition of the assets shall be applied and distributed as follows:
(1) all costs and expenses of the court proceedings and all liabilities and obligations of the corporation shall be paid, satisfied, and discharged, or adequate provision shall be made for payment;
(2) assets held by the corporation upon condition requiring return, transfer, or conveyance, which condition occurs by reason of the dissolution or liquidation, shall be returned, transferred, or conveyed in accordance with these requirements;
(3) assets received and held by the corporation subject to limitations permitting their use only for charitable, religious, eleemosynary, benevolent, educational or similar purposes, but not held upon a condition requiring return, transfer or conveyance by reason of the dissolution or liquidation, shall be transferred or conveyed to one or more domestic or foreign corporations, societies or organizations engaged in activities substantially similar to those of the dissolving or liquidating corporation as the court may direct;
(4) other assets, if any, shall be distributed in accordance with the provisions of the articles of incorporation or the bylaws to the extent that the articles of incorporation or bylaws determine the distributive right of members, or any class or classes of members, or provide for distribution to others;
(5) any remaining assets may be distributed to persons, societies, organizations, or domestic or foreign corporations, whether for profit or not for profit, specified in the plan of distribution adopted as provided in this chapter, or where no plan of distribution has been adopted, as the court may direct.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-400">
            <num>10.20.400</num>
            <heading>Powers and duties of receiver.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.400.   Powers and duties of receiver.
The order appointing the liquidating receiver shall state the receiver's powers and duties.  The powers and duties may be increased or diminished at any time during the liquidation proceedings.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-405">
            <num>10.20.405</num>
            <heading>Compensation of receiver and attorneys.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.405.   Compensation of receiver and attorneys.
The court may allow from time to time, as expenses of the liquidation, compensation to the receiver and to attorneys in the proceeding, and direct the payment of compensation out of the assets of the corporation or the proceeds of a sale or disposition of assets.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-410">
            <num>10.20.410</num>
            <heading>Power of receiver to sue and defend.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.410.   Power of receiver to sue and defend.
A receiver of a corporation appointed under this chapter may sue and defend in all courts in the receiver's own name as receiver of the corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-415">
            <num>10.20.415</num>
            <heading>Exclusive jurisdiction of appointing court.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.415.   Exclusive jurisdiction of appointing court.
The court appointing the receiver has exclusive jurisdiction of the corporation and its property, wherever situated.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-420">
            <num>10.20.420</num>
            <heading>Qualifications of receivers.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.420.   Qualifications of receivers.
A receiver shall be a citizen of the United States or a corporation authorized to act as receiver, which corporation may be a domestic corporation or a foreign corporation authorized to transact business in the state.  A receiver shall give the bond the court directs with sureties the court requires.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-425">
            <num>10.20.425</num>
            <heading>Filing of claims in liquidation proceedings.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-20-425__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In a proceeding to liquidate the assets and business of a corporation the court may require creditors of the corporation to file with the clerk of the court or with the receiver, in the form the court prescribes, proof under oath of their respective claims.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-425__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the court requires the filing of claims it shall fix a date, not less than four months from the date of the order, as the last day for the filing of claims, and shall prescribe the notice to be given to creditors and claimants of the date fixed. Before the date fixed, the court may extend the time of the filing of claims.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-425__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A creditor who fails to file proof of a claim on or before the date fixed may be barred by order of the court from participating in the distribution of the assets of the corporation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-430">
            <num>10.20.430</num>
            <heading>Discontinuance of liquidation proceedings.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.430.   Discontinuance of liquidation proceedings.
The liquidation of the assets and business of a corporation may be discontinued at any time during the liquidation proceeding when it is established that cause for liquidation no longer exists.  In this event, the court shall dismiss the proceeding and direct the receiver to redeliver to the corporation its remaining property and assets.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-435">
            <num>10.20.435</num>
            <heading>Decree of involuntary dissolution.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.435.   Decree of involuntary dissolution.
In proceedings to liquidate the assets and business of a corporation, when the costs and expenses of the proceeding and the debts, obligations, and liabilities of the corporation have been paid and discharged or when the remaining property and assets are not sufficient to satisfy and discharge the costs, expenses, debts, and obligations, and all the property and assets have been applied to their payment, the court shall enter a decree dissolving the corporation.  Upon entry of the decree, the existence of the corporation ceases.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-440">
            <num>10.20.440</num>
            <heading>Filing of decree of dissolution.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.440.   Filing of decree of dissolution.
If the court enters a decree dissolving a corporation, the clerk of the court shall file a certified copy of the decree with the commissioner.  A fee may not be charged for this filing.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-445">
            <num>10.20.445</num>
            <heading>Deposit with commissioner of amount due creditors or members.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.445.   Deposit with commissioner of amount due creditors or members.
Upon the voluntary or involuntary dissolution of a corporation, the portion of the assets distributable to a creditor or member who is unknown or cannot be found, or who is under disability and there is no legally competent person to receive the distributive portion, shall be reduced to cash and deposited with the commissioner and shall be paid over to the creditor or member or the legal representative of the creditor or member upon proof satisfactory to the commissioner of a right to it.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-450">
            <num>10.20.450</num>
            <heading>Survival of remedy after dissolution.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.450.   Survival of remedy after dissolution.
The dissolution of a corporation either by (1) the issuance of a certificate of dissolution by the commissioner, or (2) a decree of the court when the court has not liquidated the assets and business of the corporation as provided in this chapter, or (3) by expiration of its period of duration, does not take away or impair a remedy available to or against the corporation, its directors, officers, or members, for a right or claim existing, or a liability incurred, before dissolution if an action or other proceeding is commenced within two years after the date of dissolution.  The action or proceeding by or against the corporation may be prosecuted or defended by the corporation in its corporate name.  The members, directors, and officers may take appropriate action to protect the remedy, right, or claim.  If the corporation was dissolved by the expiration of its period of duration, it may amend its articles of incorporation at any time during the two year period in order to extend its period of duration.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-452">
            <num>10.20.452</num>
            <heading>Continued existence for certain purposes.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.452.   Continued existence for certain purposes.
If a dissolved corporation is the owner of real or personal property, or claims an interest in or lien upon real or personal property, the corporation through its board of directors continues to exist for five years after the date of dissolution for the purpose of conveying, transferring, or releasing the real or personal property or interest in or lien upon the property. In addition, a dissolved corporation through its board of directors continues to exist for the purpose of being made a party in an action or proceeding arising before dissolution and involving the title to real or personal property or an interest in it.  The action or proceeding may be instituted and maintained in the same manner as before the dissolution of the corporation. This section does not affect or suspend a statute of limitations applicable to a claim.  For the purpose of service of process, notice, or demand within the prescribed time following dissolution, the commissioner is an agent of the dissolved corporation upon whom service may be made in the manner prescribed in
AS 10.06.175
(b).</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-455">
            <num>10.20.455</num>
            <heading>Certificate of authority required.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.455.   Certificate of authority required.
A foreign nonprofit corporation may not transact business in the state until it has procured a certificate of authority from the commissioner.  A foreign corporation may not procure a certificate of authority to transact business in the state that a corporation organized under this chapter is not permitted to transact.  A foreign corporation may not be denied a certificate of authority because the laws of the state or country under which it is organized governing its organization and internal affairs differ from the laws of the state.  Nothing in this chapter authorizes the state to regulate the organization or the internal affairs of a foreign corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-460">
            <num>10.20.460</num>
            <heading>Activities not constituting transacting business in the state.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.460.   Activities not constituting transacting business in the state.
Without excluding other activities which may not constitute transacting business in the state, a foreign corporation does not transact business in the state by carrying on any of the following activities:
(1) maintaining or defending any action or suit or an administrative or arbitration proceeding, or effecting its settlement or the settlement of claims or disputes;
(2) holding meetings of its directors, shareholders, or members or carrying on other activities concerning its internal affairs;
(3) maintaining bank accounts;
(4) securing or collecting debts, or enforcing rights in property securing debts;
(5) transacting business in interstate commerce;
(6) granting funds;
(7) distributing information to members;
(8) conducting an isolated transaction completed within a period of 30 days not in the course of a number of repeated transactions of like nature.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-465">
            <num>10.20.465</num>
            <heading>Equal status as domestic corporations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.465.   Equal status as domestic corporations.
A foreign corporation that has received a certificate of authority enjoys the same, but no greater, rights and privileges as a domestic corporation organized for the purposes set out in the application under which the certificate of authority is issued and, except as otherwise provided in this chapter, is subject to the duties, restrictions, penalties, and liabilities imposed upon a domestic corporation of like character.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-470">
            <num>10.20.470</num>
            <heading>Corporate name of foreign corporation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.470.   Corporate name of foreign corporation.
A certificate of authority may not be issued to a foreign corporation unless the corporate name of the corporation
(1) does not contain a word or phrase that indicates or implies that it is organized for any purpose other than the purpose contained in its articles of incorporation;
(2) is available for use by the foreign corporation under
AS 10.20.021
(b).</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-471">
            <num>10.20.471</num>
            <heading>Assumed corporate name.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.471.   Assumed corporate name.
When a foreign corporation, applying for a certificate of authority, has a name that is not available for use by the foreign corporation under
AS 10.20.021
(b), it shall
(1) select a name under which it elects to do business in the state;
(2) clearly identify on all advertising, contracts, and other legal documents its true corporate name as well as its assumed name.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-475">
            <num>10.20.475</num>
            <heading>Change of name by foreign corporation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.475.   Change of name by foreign corporation.
When a foreign corporation authorized to transact business in the state changes its name to one under which a certificate of authority would not be granted to it, the certificate of authority of the corporation is suspended and it may not transact business in the state until it has changed its name to a name available to it under the laws of the state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-480">
            <num>10.20.480</num>
            <heading>Application for certificate of authority.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.480.   Application for certificate of authority.
To procure a certificate of authority to transact business in the state, a foreign corporation shall file an application in duplicate with the commissioner.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-485">
            <num>10.20.485</num>
            <heading>Contents of application.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.485.   Contents of application.
The application must set out
(1) the name of the corporation and the state or country under the laws of which it is incorporated;
(2) the date of incorporation and the period of duration of the corporation;
(3) the address of the principal office of the corporation in the state or country under the laws of which it is incorporated;
(4) the address of the proposed registered office of the corporation in this state, and the name of its proposed registered agent in this state at that address;
(5) the purpose or purposes of the corporation that it proposes to pursue in conducting its affairs in the state;
(6) the names and addresses of the directors and officers of the corporation;
(7) additional information which may be necessary or appropriate in order to enable the commissioner to determine whether the corporation is entitled to a certificate of authority to conduct affairs in the state;
(8) the name and address of a person owning at least five percent of the shares, or five percent of any class of shares, and the percentage of the shares or class of shares owned by that person.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-490">
            <num>10.20.490</num>
            <heading>Form and execution of application.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.490.   Form and execution of application.
The application must be on forms prescribed and furnished by the commissioner and shall be executed in duplicate by the corporation by its president or vice-president and by its secretary or an assistant secretary.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-495">
            <num>10.20.495</num>
            <heading>Filing of application for certificate of authority.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-20-495__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon finding that the application conforms to law, the commissioner shall, when all fees prescribed in this chapter have been paid</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-495__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>endorse on each document the word filed, and the date of the filing;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-495__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>file one duplicate original of the application in the commissioner's office;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-495__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>issue a certificate of authority to transact business in the state and affix the other duplicate original application to it.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-495__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The certificate of authority, together with the duplicate original of the application affixed to it by the commissioner, shall be returned to the corporation or its representative.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-500">
            <num>10.20.500</num>
            <heading>Effect of certificate of authority.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.500.   Effect of certificate of authority.
Upon the issuance of a certificate of authority by the commissioner, the corporation may transact business in the state for the purpose set out in its application, subject, however, to the right of the state to suspend or revoke the authority as provided in this chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-505">
            <num>10.20.505</num>
            <heading>Registered office and registered agent of foreign corporation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.505.   Registered office and registered agent of foreign corporation.
Each foreign corporation authorized to transact business in the state shall have and continuously maintain in the state a registered
(1) office which may be, but need not be, the same as its place of business in the state;
(2) agent, who may be either an individual resident in the state whose business office is identical with the registered office or a domestic corporation, or a foreign corporation authorized to transact business in the state, which has a business office identical with the registered office.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-510">
            <num>10.20.510</num>
            <heading>List of foreign corporations and registered offices and agents.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.510.   List of foreign corporations and registered offices and agents.
The commissioner shall provide each clerk of the superior court with a current list of the names of all foreign corporations, the address of their registered office, and the name and address of their registered agent. The commissioner shall provide a supplement to the list indicating additions, deletions, and changes at least every six months.  The list shall be made available to the public by the commissioner for a fee prescribed by the commissioner.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-515">
            <num>10.20.515</num>
            <heading>Change of registered office or registered agent of foreign corporation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.515.   Change of registered office or registered agent of foreign corporation.
A foreign corporation authorized to transact business in the state may change its registered office or change its registered agent, or both, upon filing with the department a statement setting out
(1) the name of the corporation;
(2) the address of its registered office;
(3) if the address of its registered office is to be changed, the address of the proposed office;
(4) the name of its registered agent;
(5) if its registered agent is to be changed, the name of its successor registered agent;
(6) that the address of its registered office and the address of the business office or its registered agent, as changed, will be identical;
(7) that the change is authorized by resolution adopted by the board of directors.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-520">
            <num>10.20.520</num>
            <heading>Execution, filing, and effective date of statement.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.520.   Execution, filing, and effective date of statement.
The statement shall be executed by the corporation by its president or a vice-president and delivered to the commissioner. Upon finding that the statement conforms to the provisions of this chapter, the commissioner shall file the statement in the commissioner's office, and, upon filing the statement, the change of address of the registered office, or the change of registered agent, or both, becomes effective.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-525">
            <num>10.20.525</num>
            <heading>Service of process on foreign corporation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.525.   Service of process on foreign corporation.
The registered agent appointed by a foreign corporation authorized to transact business in the state shall be an agent of the corporation upon whom process, notice, or demand required or permitted by law to be served upon the corporation may be served.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-530">
            <num>10.20.530</num>
            <heading>Service on commissioner.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.530.   Service on commissioner.
When a foreign corporation authorized to transact business in the state, or not authorized to transact business in the state but doing so, fails to appoint or maintain a registered agent in the state, or when a registered agent cannot with reasonable diligence be found at the registered office, or when the certificate of authority of a foreign corporation is suspended or revoked, the commissioner is an agent upon whom process, notice, or demand may be served. Service on the commissioner shall be made by delivering to and leaving with the commissioner, or the commissioner's designee, duplicate copies of the process, notice, or demand, accompanied by a fee established by the department by regulation. The commissioner shall immediately have one copy forwarded by registered or certified mail, addressed to the corporation at its principal office in the state or country under whose laws it is incorporated. Service on the commissioner is returnable in not less than 30 days.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-535">
            <num>10.20.535</num>
            <heading>Records of commissioner.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.535.   Records of commissioner.
The commissioner shall keep a record of all processes, notices, or demands served under
AS 10.20.525
and 10.20.530, and shall record the time of service and the commissioner's action with reference to the service.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-540">
            <num>10.20.540</num>
            <heading>Procedure not exclusive.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.540.   Procedure not exclusive.
Nothing in
AS 10.20.525
  10.20.535 limits or affects the right to serve any process, notice, or demand required or permitted by law to be served upon a corporation in any other manner.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-545">
            <num>10.20.545</num>
            <heading>Amendment of articles of incorporation of foreign corporation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.545.   Amendment of articles of incorporation of foreign corporation.
When the articles of incorporation of a foreign corporation authorized to transact business in the state are amended, the foreign corporation shall, within 30 days after the amendment becomes effective, file with the department a copy of the amendment authenticated by the proper officer of the state or country under whose laws it is incorporated.  The filing of the amendment does not enlarge or alter the purpose that the corporation may pursue in the transaction of business in the state, nor authorize the corporation to transact business in the state under a name other than the name set out in its certificate of authority.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-550">
            <num>10.20.550</num>
            <heading>Merger of foreign corporation authorized to transact business in the state.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.550.   Merger of foreign corporation authorized to transact business in the state.
When a foreign corporation authorized to transact business in the state is a party to a statutory merger permitted by the laws of the state or country where it is incorporated, and the corporation is the surviving corporation, it shall, within 30 days after the merger becomes effective, file with the commissioner a copy of the articles of merger authenticated by the proper office of the state or country under whose laws the statutory merger was carried out.  It is not necessary for the corporation to procure either a new or amended certificate of authority to transact business in the state unless the name of the corporation is changed or unless the corporation desires to pursue in the state other or additional purposes than those that it is authorized to conduct in the state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-555">
            <num>10.20.555</num>
            <heading>When amended certificate of authority required.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.555.   When amended certificate of authority required.
A foreign corporation authorized to transact business in the state shall procure an amended certificate of authority if it changes its corporate name, or desires to pursue in the state other or additional purposes than those set out in its earlier application for a certificate of authority, by making application to the commissioner.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-560">
            <num>10.20.560</num>
            <heading>Withdrawal of foreign corporation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.560.   Withdrawal of foreign corporation.
A foreign corporation authorized to transact business in the state may withdraw from the state upon procuring from the commissioner a certificate of withdrawal.  To procure a certificate of withdrawal, the foreign corporation shall deliver to the commissioner an application for withdrawal.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-565">
            <num>10.20.565</num>
            <heading>Contents of application for withdrawal.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.565.   Contents of application for withdrawal.
The application for withdrawal must set out
(1) the name of the corporation and the state or country where it is incorporated;
(2) that the corporation is not transacting business in the state;
(3) that the corporation surrenders its authority to transact business in the state;
(4) that the corporation revokes the authority of its registered agent in the state to accept service of process and consents that service of process in an action, suit, or proceeding based upon a cause of action arising in the state during the time the corporation was authorized to transact business in the state may be made on the corporation by service on the commissioner;
(5) a post office address to which the commissioner may mail a copy of a process against the corporation that may be served on the commissioner;
(6) additional information necessary or appropriate to enable the commissioner to determine and assess unpaid fees payable as prescribed in this chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-570">
            <num>10.20.570</num>
            <heading>Form and execution of application for withdrawal.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.570.   Form and execution of application for withdrawal.
The application for withdrawal shall be made on forms prescribed and furnished by the commissioner and shall be executed by the corporation by its president or a vice-president and by its secretary or an assistant secretary, or, if the corporation is in the hands of a receiver or trustee, the application shall be executed on behalf of the corporation by the receiver or trustee.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-575">
            <num>10.20.575</num>
            <heading>Filing of application for withdrawal.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-20-575__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Duplicate originals of the application for withdrawal shall be delivered to the commissioner.  Upon finding that the application conforms to the provisions of this chapter, the commissioner shall, when all fees prescribed in this chapter have been paid,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-575__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>endorse on each duplicate original the word filed, and the date of the filing;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-575__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>file one duplicate original in the commissioner's office;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-575__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>issue a certificate of withdrawal and affix the other duplicate original to it.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-575__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The certificate of withdrawal, together with the duplicate original of the application for withdrawal affixed by the commissioner shall be returned to the corporation or its representative.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-580">
            <num>10.20.580</num>
            <heading>Effect of certificate of withdrawal.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.580.   Effect of certificate of withdrawal.
Upon the issuance of the certificate of withdrawal, the authority of the corporation to transact business in the state ceases.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-585">
            <num>10.20.585</num>
            <heading>Grounds for revocation of certificate of authority.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.585.   Grounds for revocation of certificate of authority.
The certificate of authority of a foreign corporation to transact business in the state may be revoked by the commissioner when
(1) the corporation fails to file its biennial report within the time required by this chapter, or fails to pay fees or penalties prescribed in this chapter when they are due and payable;
(2) the corporation fails to appoint and maintain a registered agent in this state;
(3) the corporation fails, after change of its registered office or registered agent, to file with the commissioner a statement of the change as required by this chapter;
(4) the corporation fails to file with the department an amendment to its articles of incorporation or articles of merger within the time prescribed by this chapter;
(5) a misrepresentation has been made of a material matter in an application, report, affidavit, or other document submitted under this chapter; or
(6) the corporation is 90 days delinquent in filing a notice of change of an officer or director as required by this chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-590">
            <num>10.20.590</num>
            <heading>Limitations on revocation of certificate of authority.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.590.   Limitations on revocation of certificate of authority.
The commissioner may not revoke a certificate of authority of a foreign corporation unless
(1) the commissioner has given the corporation at least 60 days' notice by mail addressed to its registered office in the state; and
(2) the corporation fails, before revocation, to file the biennial report, or pay the fees, or file the required statement of change of registered agent or registered office, or file the articles of amendment or articles of merger, or correct the misrepresentation.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-595">
            <num>10.20.595</num>
            <heading>Issuance of certificate of revocation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.595.   Issuance of certificate of revocation.
Upon revoking a certificate of authority, the commissioner shall
(1) issue a certificate of revocation in duplicate;
(2) file one of the certificates in the commissioner's office;
(3) mail to the corporation at its registered office in the state a notice of the revocation accompanied by one of the certificates.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-600">
            <num>10.20.600</num>
            <heading>Effect of certificate of revocation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.600.   Effect of certificate of revocation.
Upon the issuance of the certificate of revocation, the authority of the corporation to transact business in the state ceases.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-605">
            <num>10.20.605</num>
            <heading>Transacting business without certificate of authority as a bar to right to sue.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.605.   Transacting business without certificate of authority as a bar to right to sue.
A foreign corporation transacting business in the state without a certificate of authority may not maintain an action, suit, or proceeding in a court of the state until it obtains a certificate of authority. A successor or assignee of a foreign corporation transacting business without a certificate of authority may not maintain an action, suit, or proceeding in a court of the state on a right, claim, or demand arising out of the transaction of business by the corporation in the state until a certificate of authority is obtained by the corporation or by a corporation that has acquired all or substantially all of its assets.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-610">
            <num>10.20.610</num>
            <heading>Transacting business without certificate of authority not affecting validity of contract or act, and right to defend.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.610.   Transacting business without certificate of authority not affecting validity of contract or act, and right to defend.
The failure of a foreign corporation to obtain a certificate of authority to transact business in the state does not impair the validity of a contract or act of it, and does not prevent the corporation from defending an action, suit, or proceeding in a court of the state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-615">
            <num>10.20.615</num>
            <heading>Liability to state for transacting business without certificate of authority.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.615.   Liability to state for transacting business without certificate of authority.
A foreign corporation that transacts business in the state without a certificate of authority is liable to the state, for the years or portions of years during which it transacted business in the state without a certificate of authority, in an amount equal to all fees that would have been imposed by this chapter on the corporation if it had applied for and received a certificate of authority to transact business in the state as required by this chapter and filed all reports required by this chapter, plus all penalties imposed by this chapter for failure to pay the fees and a penalty of up to $5,000 per year or fraction of a year of operating without a certificate of authority.  The attorney general shall bring proceedings to recover amounts due the state under this section.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-620">
            <num>10.20.620</num>
            <heading>Biennial report of domestic and foreign corporations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.620.   Biennial report of domestic and foreign corporations.
Each domestic corporation and each foreign corporation authorized to transact business in the state shall file a biennial report within the time prescribed by this chapter. The information contained in the biennial report shall be given as of June 30 of the reporting year.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-625">
            <num>10.20.625</num>
            <heading>Contents of biennial report.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.625.   Contents of biennial report.
The biennial report must set out
(1) the name of the corporation and the state or country where it is incorporated;
(2) the address of the registered office of the corporation in the state, and the name of its registered agent in the state at that address, and, in the case of a foreign corporation, the address of its principal office in the state or country where it is incorporated;
(3) a brief statement of the character of the business in which the corporation is engaged in the state;
(4) the names and addresses of the directors and officers of the corporation;
(5) the real and personal property assets of the corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-630">
            <num>10.20.630</num>
            <heading>Filing of biennial report of domestic and foreign corporations.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-20-630__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The biennial report of a domestic or foreign corporation must be delivered to the commissioner before July 2 of the reporting year.  A domestic corporation filing its articles of incorporation and a foreign corporation receiving a certificate of authority during an even-numbered year must file the biennial report before July 2 of each even-numbered year.  A corporation filing its articles of incorporation or receiving its certificate of authority during an odd-numbered year must file the biennial report before July 2 of each odd-numbered year. The biennial report is delinquent if not filed before August 1 of each odd or even year as provided in this section.  Delinquent returns are subject to the penalty prescribed in
AS 10.20.325
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-630__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 48 ch 170 SLA 1976.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-630__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Proof to the satisfaction of the commissioner that before August 1 the report was deposited in the United States mail in a sealed envelope, properly addressed, with postage prepaid, is compliance with (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-630__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon finding that the report conforms to the requirements of this chapter, the commissioner shall file it. Upon finding that it does not conform to the requirements of this chapter, the commissioner shall return it promptly to the corporation for necessary corrections. If the report is corrected to conform to the requirements of this chapter and returned to the commissioner in sufficient time to be filed before October 1 of the year in which it is due, the penalties for failure to file the report provided in
AS 10.20.645
do not apply.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-631">
            <num>10.20.631</num>
            <heading>Filing notice of change of officers or directors.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-20-631__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In the event of a change of an officer or director during the year following the filing of the biennial report, the corporation must file a notice of change amending the report before July 2 of that year.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-631__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The notice must be filed in the office of the commissioner and must state the name and current address of a director or officer not stated in the corporation's last filed biennial report, and the name of the person replaced and the office held.  The notice must be signed by an officer of the corporation.
Article 8. Fees and Charges.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-635">
            <num>10.20.635</num>
            <heading>Department fees.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-20-635__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall establish by regulation and charge and collect fees for filing</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-635__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>articles of incorporation and issuing a certificate of incorporation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-635__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>articles of amendment and issuing a certificate of amendment;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-635__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>restated articles of incorporation and issuing a restated certificate of incorporation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-635__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>articles of merger or consolidation and issuing a certificate of merger or consolidation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-635__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a statement of change of address of registered office or change of registered agent, or both;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-635__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>articles of dissolution;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-635__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an application of a foreign corporation for a certificate of authority to conduct affairs in this state and issuing a certificate of authority;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-635__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an application of a foreign corporation for an amended certificate of authority to conduct affairs in this state and issuing an amended certificate of authority;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-635__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a copy of an amendment to the articles of incorporation of a foreign corporation holding a certificate of authority to conduct affairs in this state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-635__subsec_a__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a copy of articles of merger of a foreign corporation holding a certificate of authority to conduct affairs in this state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-635__subsec_a__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an application for withdrawal of a foreign corporation and issuing a certificate of withdrawal;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="10-20-635__subsec_a__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>any other statement or report, including a biennial report, of a domestic or foreign corporation.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-635__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may by regulation charge each corporation subject to this chapter a fixed fee in place of the various fees specified in this chapter and for routine administrative services rendered to the corporation by the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-640">
            <num>10.20.640</num>
            <heading>Fee for certified copies of instruments.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.640.   Fee for certified copies of instruments.
The fee for furnishing a certified copy of any instrument shall be established by the department by regulation.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-645">
            <num>10.20.645</num>
            <heading>Penalties imposed upon corporation.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-20-645__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A domestic or foreign corporation that fails or refuses to file its biennial report for any required reporting period within the time prescribed by this chapter is subject to a penalty of $5 to be assessed by the commissioner.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-645__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A domestic or foreign corporation that fails or refuses to answer truthfully and fully within the time prescribed by this chapter interrogatories propounded by the commissioner in accordance with the provisions of this chapter is guilty of a misdemeanor and upon conviction is punishable by a fine of not more than $500.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-650">
            <num>10.20.650</num>
            <heading>Penalties imposed upon officers and directors.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.650.   Penalties imposed upon officers and directors.
Each officer and director of a domestic or foreign corporation who fails or refuses within the time prescribed by this chapter to answer truthfully and fully interrogatories propounded by the commissioner in accordance with this chapter, or who signs any articles, statement, report, application, or other document filed with the commissioner that is known to the officer or director to be false in any material respect, is guilty of a misdemeanor, and upon conviction is punishable by a fine of not more than $500.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-655">
            <num>10.20.655</num>
            <heading>Interrogatories by commissioner; certification to attorney general regarding violation.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-20-655__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner may propound to a domestic or foreign corporation and to an officer or director of a domestic or foreign corporation those interrogatories reasonably necessary and proper for ascertaining whether the corporation has complied with the provisions of this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-655__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The interrogatories shall be answered within 30 days after mailing, or within the additional time fixed by the commissioner, and the answers shall be full and complete, in writing and under penalty of unsworn falsification in the second degree under
AS 11.56.210
. If the interrogatories are directed to an individual, they shall be answered by that individual and, if directed to a corporation, they shall be answered by the president, vice-president, secretary, or assistant secretary of the corporation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-655__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner need not file the document to which the interrogatories relate until the interrogatories are properly answered and need not then file the document if the answers disclose that the document does not conform to the provisions of this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-655__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall certify to the attorney general, for appropriate action, all interrogatories and answers that disclose a violation of this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-660">
            <num>10.20.660</num>
            <heading>Disclosure of interrogatories, answers, and information.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.660.   Disclosure of interrogatories, answers, and information.
Interrogatories and answers are not open to public inspection and the commissioner may not disclose facts or information obtained from the interrogatories except as an official duty of the commissioner requires or if the interrogatories or the answers are required for evidence in criminal proceedings or other action by the state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-665">
            <num>10.20.665</num>
            <heading>Notice of and appeal from disapproval of document.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.665.   Notice of and appeal from disapproval of document.
If the commissioner fails to approve articles of incorporation, amendment, merger, consolidation, or dissolution, or any other document required by this chapter to be approved, the commissioner, within 10 days after delivery of the document to the commissioner, shall give written notice of disapproval to the person or corporation, domestic or foreign, delivering the document, specifying the reasons for disapproval.  The person or corporation may appeal from the disapproval to the superior court by filing with the clerk of the court a petition setting out a copy of the document sought to be filed and a copy of the written disapproval.  The matter shall be tried de novo by the superior court, which shall either sustain the action of the commissioner or direct the commissioner to take action the court considers proper.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-670">
            <num>10.20.670</num>
            <heading>Appeal from revocation of certificate of authority.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.670.   Appeal from revocation of certificate of authority.
If the commissioner revokes the certificate of authority of a foreign corporation to transact business in the state under this chapter, the foreign corporation may appeal to the superior court by filing with the clerk of the court a petition setting out a copy of its certificate of authority and a copy of the notice of revocation given by the commissioner.  The matter shall be tried de novo by the superior court, and the court shall either sustain the action of the commissioner or direct the commissioner to take action the court considers proper.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-673">
            <num>10.20.673</num>
            <heading>Cancellation of filings.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.673.   Cancellation of filings.
The provisions in
AS 10.06
(Alaska Corporations Code) relating to the cancellation of certain corporate filings apply to nonprofit corporations.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-675">
            <num>10.20.675</num>
            <heading>Certificates and certified copies to be received in evidence.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.675.   Certificates and certified copies to be received in evidence.
Certificates issued by the commissioner in accordance with this chapter, and copies of documents filed in the commissioner's office in accordance with the provisions of this chapter when certified by the commissioner, are prima facie evidence of the facts stated.  A certificate by the commissioner under the seal of the state as to the existence or nonexistence of facts relating to corporations that do not appear from a certified copy of these documents or certificates is prima facie evidence of the existence or nonexistence of the facts stated.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-680">
            <num>10.20.680</num>
            <heading>Use of forms furnished by the commissioner.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.680.   Use of forms furnished by the commissioner.
All reports required by this chapter to be filed with the department or the commissioner must be on forms prescribed and furnished by the commissioner.  Forms for all other documents to be filed in the office of the department or the commissioner shall be furnished by the commissioner on request, but their use, unless required in this chapter, is not mandatory.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-685">
            <num>10.20.685</num>
            <heading>Greater voting or concurrence requirements.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.685.   Greater voting or concurrence requirements.
When, with respect to any action to be taken by the members or directors of a corporation, the articles of incorporation or bylaws require the vote or concurrence of a greater proportion of the directors or members or any class of members than required by this chapter, the provisions of the articles of incorporation or bylaws control.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-690">
            <num>10.20.690</num>
            <heading>Waiver of notice.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.690.   Waiver of notice.
When notice is required to be given to a member or director of a corporation under the provisions of this chapter or under the provisions of the articles of incorporation or bylaws of the corporation, a waiver of the notice in writing signed by the person entitled to notice, whether before or after the time stated for notice, is equivalent to the giving of notice.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-695">
            <num>10.20.695</num>
            <heading>Action by members or directors without a meeting.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-20-695__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Action required by this chapter to be taken at a meeting of the members or directors of a corporation, or action that may be taken at a meeting of the members or directors, may be taken without a meeting if a consent in writing, setting out the action so taken, shall be signed by all of the members entitled to vote with respect to the subject matter or all of the directors.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-695__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The consent has the same effect as a unanimous vote, and may be stated as such in articles or documents filed with the commissioner.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-700">
            <num>10.20.700</num>
            <heading>Unauthorized assumption of corporate powers.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.700.   Unauthorized assumption of corporate powers.
Persons who assume to act as a corporation without authority are jointly and severally liable for debts and liabilities incurred or arising as a result of that action.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-905">
            <num>10.20.905</num>
            <heading>Powers of commissioner.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.905.   Powers of commissioner.
The commissioner has the power and authority reasonably necessary for administering this chapter efficiently and performing the duties imposed by this chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-910">
            <num>10.20.910</num>
            <heading>Applicability to domestic and foreign corporations.</heading>
            <subsection eId="10-20-910__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The provisions of this chapter relating to domestic corporations apply to all corporations organized under this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="10-20-910__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The provisions of this chapter relating to foreign corporations apply to all foreign nonprofit corporations conducting affairs in this state for a purpose or purposes for which a corporation might be organized under this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-915">
            <num>10.20.915</num>
            <heading>Application to foreign and interstate commerce.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.915.   Application to foreign and interstate commerce.
This chapter applies to commerce with foreign nations and among the several states only as permitted under the Constitution of the United States.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-920">
            <num>10.20.920</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.920.   Definitions.
In this chapter, unless the context otherwise requires,
(1) articles of incorporation means the original or restated articles of incorporation or articles of consolidation and all amendments to them, including articles of merger;
(2) board of directors means the group of persons vested with the management of the affairs of the corporation irrespective of the name by which the group is designated;
(3) bylaws means the code or codes of rules adopted for the regulation or management of the affairs of the corporation irrespective of the name or names by which the rules are designated;
(4) commissioner means commissioner of commerce, community, and economic development;
(5) corporation or domestic corporation means a nonprofit corporation subject to the provisions of this chapter, except a foreign corporation;
(6) department means the Department of Commerce, Community, and Economic Development;
(7) foreign corporation means a nonprofit corporation organized under laws other than the laws of this state;
(8) member means one having membership rights in a corporation in accordance with the provisions of its articles of incorporation or bylaws;
(9) nonprofit corporation means a corporation no part of the income or profit of which is distributed to its members, directors, or officers.
(10) remote communication has the meaning given in
AS 10.06.990
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_10-20-925">
            <num>10.20.925</num>
            <heading>Short title.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 10.20.925.   Short title.
This chapter may be cited as the Alaska Nonprofit Corporation Act.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>