<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-37/chapter-15"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-37/chapter-15"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="37.15"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-37/chapter-15/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-37/chapter-15/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-37/chapter-15/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-37/chapter-15/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_37">
        <num>37</num>
        <heading>Public Finance</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_37__chp_15">
          <num>15</num>
          <heading>Bonding</heading>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-010">
            <num>37.15.010</num>
            <heading>Full faith and credit for general obligation bonds.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.010.   Full faith and credit for general obligation bonds.
The full faith, credit, and resources of the state are hereby pledged to the payment of the principal of and interest and redemption premium, if any, on all general obligation bonds of the state authorized pursuant to art. IX, § 8 of the constitution.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-011">
            <num>37.15.011</num>
            <heading>Alaska debt retirement fund.</heading>
            <subsection eId="37-15-011__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Alaska debt retirement fund is established as a separate fund in the general fund. The fund consists of all money appropriated to it.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-011__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Alaska debt retirement fund shall be invested by the Department of Revenue so as to yield competitive market rates, as provided in
AS 37.10.071
. Money in the fund may be appropriated</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-011__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for the purposes set out in
AS 37.15.012
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-011__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to reimburse municipalities for obligations authorized under
AS 14.11.100
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-011__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to finance the acquisition of state facilities through lease-purchase agreements; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-011__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if an unobligated balance remains, to finance the design and construction of capital projects.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-012">
            <num>37.15.012</num>
            <heading>Continuing debt service appropriation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.012.   Continuing debt service appropriation.
The amounts required annually to pay the principal, interest, and redemption premium on all issued and outstanding general obligation bonds of the state are appropriated each fiscal year from the Alaska debt retirement fund to the state bond committee to make all required payments of principal, interest, and redemption premium. If the balance of the Alaska debt retirement fund is insufficient to fully pay these amounts, the necessary additional amounts are appropriated from the general fund to the state bond committee to make all required payments of principal, interest, and redemption premium.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-015">
            <num>37.15.015</num>
            <heading>Notice before election.</heading>
            <subsection eId="37-15-015__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before a general or special election in which a bond issue is offered for ratification, the state bond committee shall publish a notice of existing state bonded indebtedness at least once a week for three consecutive weeks in a newspaper of general circulation in each of the four judicial districts of the state. The first notice shall be published at least 20 days before the date of the election. A notice must contain</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-015__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the current total bonded indebtedness of the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-015__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the cost of the debt service on the current indebtedness;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-015__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the projected amount of state general obligation debt principal that could be issued and paid for from the Alaska debt retirement fund;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-015__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the estimated debt service requirements for the bond issue offered for ratification; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-015__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>whether the bond issue offered for ratification will be repaid with amounts from the Alaska debt retirement fund.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-015__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Neither the failure to publish the notice of existing state bonded indebtedness nor a defect in the publication affects the validity of the bond issue offered for ratification or of a general or special election in which a bond issue is offered for ratification.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-020">
            <num>37.15.020</num>
            <heading>Manner and amounts of sale.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.020.   Manner and amounts of sale.
The state bond committee shall sell the bonds of each authorization in the amounts or series and at the times which it finds are for the best interests of the state and its inhabitants.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-030">
            <num>37.15.030</num>
            <heading>Interest rate and maturity.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.030.   Interest rate and maturity.
Each issue or series of bonds must bear interest at an effective rate over the life of the bonds not to exceed 11 percent a year or that rate of interest that is 110 percent of the rate of the Bond Buyer Index of 20 Municipal Bond Average Yields for the week previous to the date of sale of the bonds, whichever is higher.  The bonds must mature in not more than 30 years from date of issue, unless a longer period is specifically authorized by statute.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-040">
            <num>37.15.040</num>
            <heading>Sale of bonds.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.040.   Sale of bonds.
Before selling an issue or series of bonds, the state bond committee shall give notice inviting sealed bids in a manner that it may prescribe.  If satisfactory bids are received, the bonds offered for sale shall be awarded to the highest responsible bidder.  If the state bond committee determines that the bids received are not satisfactory as to price or responsibility of the bidders, it may reject all bids received.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-050">
            <num>37.15.050</num>
            <heading>Redemption.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.050.   Redemption.
The state bond committee may determine whether the bonds are subject to redemption before their fixed maturities and may fix the premium for and all other terms of the redemption.  A bond is not subject to redemption before its fixed maturity date unless the right to so redeem the bond is expressly mentioned on the face of the bond.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-060">
            <num>37.15.060</num>
            <heading>Form and registration of bonds.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.060.   Form and registration of bonds.
An issue or series of bonds may be issued in coupon form payable to bearer or in fully registered form, and bonds in coupon form may be made registrable as to principal or principal and interest, as determined by the state bond committee.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-070">
            <num>37.15.070</num>
            <heading>Place of payment.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.070.   Place of payment.
The state bond committee may fix the place or places of payment of the principal, interest and redemption premium, if any.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-080">
            <num>37.15.080</num>
            <heading>Signatures and seal.</heading>
            <subsection eId="37-15-080__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each bond shall be signed on behalf of the state by the governor and attested by the lieutenant governor, which signatures may be facsimile signatures.  The seal of the state shall be impressed, imprinted or otherwise reproduced on each bond.  Each interest coupon attached to the bond shall be signed by the facsimile signatures of the governor and lieutenant governor.  If an officer whose signature appears on the bonds or coupons ceases to be an officer before delivery of the bonds, the signature is, nevertheless, valid and sufficient for all purposes, as if the officer had remained in office until delivery.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-080__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A signature required on a bond issued by a political subdivision of the state may be a facsimile signature.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-090">
            <num>37.15.090</num>
            <heading>Terms and conditions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.090.   Terms and conditions.
Each issue or series of bonds shall be issued under and subject to the terms, conditions, and covenants providing for the payment of the principal and the interest and other terms, conditions, covenants, and protective provisions safeguarding the payment as found reasonably necessary by the state bond committee for the most advantageous sale.  The terms, conditions, and covenants may include the setting aside and maintaining of certain reserves to secure the payment of principal and interest.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-100">
            <num>37.15.100</num>
            <heading>Trustee.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.100.   Trustee.
If the state bond committee finds it necessary to accomplish the most advantageous sale of the bonds, the committee shall select a trustee for the owners and holders of the bonds or for the safeguarding and disbursement of the proceeds of the sale of the bonds for the use and purpose for which issued, and shall fix the rights, duties, powers, and obligations of the trustee.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-110">
            <num>37.15.110</num>
            <heading>Creation and membership of state bond committee.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.110.   Creation and membership of state bond committee.
There is created a committee known as the state bond committee, the members of which are the commissioner of commerce, community, and economic development, the commissioner of administration, and the commissioner of revenue.  If a member of the committee is absent or otherwise unable to act, the member's designee in the department shall act as a member of the committee in the member's place.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-120">
            <num>37.15.120</num>
            <heading>Regulations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.120.   Regulations.
The state bond committee may adopt regulations for the performance of its duties and may designate by resolution one of its members to perform any act necessary to effectuate its duties not required by statute to be performed by the state bond committee in meeting or by resolution, or by another officer of the state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-130">
            <num>37.15.130</num>
            <heading>Officers, records, and proceedings.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.130.   Officers, records, and proceedings.
The commissioner of commerce, community, and economic development is the chairman of the state bond committee and the commissioner of revenue is the secretary.  A majority of the members of the committee constitute a quorum.  The committee shall keep a full, complete, and permanent record of its proceedings.  All records and correspondence of the committee shall be kept in the office of the commissioner of revenue.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-140">
            <num>37.15.140</num>
            <heading>Duties of state bond committee.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.140.   Duties of state bond committee.
The state bond committee shall adopt the resolution and prepare the documents necessary for the issuance, sale, and delivery of bonds.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-150">
            <num>37.15.150</num>
            <heading>Committee may employ special services.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.150.   Committee may employ special services.
If the state bond committee considers it necessary and advisable, it may procure architectural or engineering, fiscal agent or municipal investment, legal and other expert or specialized services at reasonable and customary fees to assist it in accomplishing the most advantageous sale of the bonds. The fees may be paid from the proceeds of the sale or advanced from the contingency fund in the office of the governor or otherwise.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-155">
            <num>37.15.155</num>
            <heading>Prohibited bidding on bonds and anticipation notes.</heading>
            <subsection eId="37-15-155__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who provides financial programming or marketing assistance to the state bond committee in connection with the issuance or sale of general obligation bonds, revenue bonds, or bond anticipation notes of the state may not bid on the bonds.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-155__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The sale of general obligation bonds, revenue bonds, or bond anticipation notes of the state to a person who is prohibited from bidding on the bonds or notes under (a) of this section is against public policy and the sale is void.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-155__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section person means an individual, firm, agent, factor, intermediary, partnership, corporation, association, bond house, stockbroker, or bond broker.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-160">
            <num>37.15.160</num>
            <heading>Contents of resolution.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.160.   Contents of resolution.
The resolution adopted by the state bond committee must
(1) fix the principal amount, denominations, date, maturities, place of payment, terms, right of redemption if any, form, conditions, and covenants of the bonds;
(2) fix the date of sale and the form of the notice of sale; and
(3) provide if the notice is to be published elsewhere in addition to the publication required by
AS 37.15.040
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-170">
            <num>37.15.170</num>
            <heading>State bond committee to certify annual principal, interest, and reserve requirements.</heading>
            <subsection eId="37-15-170__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before December 1 of each year after bonds are issued, the state bond committee shall certify to the commissioner of administration the amount needed for the following calendar year to meet principal, interest, and reserve requirements on all bonds or issues or series of bonds then outstanding, including reimbursements authorized under
AS 14.11.100
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-170__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner of administration shall set aside these amounts or make the necessary provisions for the setting aside of these amounts so that there will be sufficient money to pay the principal and interest on the due date and to meet reserve requirements.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-170__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before December 1 of each year, the state bond committee shall report to the governor the current fund balance in the Alaska debt retirement fund. The report must contain an estimate of the amount of state general obligation debt principal that could be issued and paid for from the fund. The state bond committee shall notify the legislature that the report is available.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-180">
            <num>37.15.180</num>
            <heading>Remedies of bondholders.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.180.   Remedies of bondholders.
The owner and holder of each bond or the trustee may by appropriate proceeding require and compel the transfer and payment of money as directed by this chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-190">
            <num>37.15.190</num>
            <heading>Negotiability.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.190.   Negotiability.
General obligation bonds of the state and the coupons attached to the bonds are negotiable instruments.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-200">
            <num>37.15.200</num>
            <heading>Bonds as legal investments.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.200.   Bonds as legal investments.
General obligation bonds of the state are legal investments for all state funds, or for funds under state control, and for all funds of a political subdivision of the state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-210">
            <num>37.15.210</num>
            <heading>Refunding bonds.</heading>
            <subsection eId="37-15-210__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>All or a part of the general obligation bonds of the state, or all or a part of each outstanding issue or series of bonds, may be refunded at or before maturity by the issuance of general obligation refunding bonds of the state if, in the opinion of the state bond committee, refunding is advantageous to and in the best interest of the state and its inhabitants. Money set aside as reserve to secure the payment of the principal and interest of bonds being refunded may be used to pay the principal and interest on these bonds or may be retained by the state to secure the payment of the principal and interest on the refunding bonds to be issued.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-210__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Refunding bonds and the coupons attached to them are negotiable instruments.  The effective rate of interest over the life of refunding bonds may not exceed 11 percent a year or that rate of interest that is 110 percent of the rate of the Bond Buyer Index of 20 Municipal Bond Average Yields for the week previous to the date of sale of bonds, whichever is higher, and the amount of premium that is paid to effect the redemption of outstanding bonds may not be considered in determining the effective rate of interest.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-210__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Refunding bonds may be exchanged for the bonds being refunded or refunding bonds may be sold in the manner and at the prices that the state bond committee determines to be for the best interest of the state and its inhabitants either at public or private sale.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-210__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The issuance of refunding bonds need not be authorized by the qualified voters of the state.  The state bond committee shall adopt the resolution and prepare the documents necessary for the issuance, exchange or sale, and delivery of refunding bonds.  The provisions of this chapter relating to the terms, conditions, covenants, issuance, and sale of general obligation bonds of the state apply to refunding bonds except as otherwise specifically provided in this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-215">
            <num>37.15.215</num>
            <heading>Official statements.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.215.   Official statements.
To the extent practicable the official statements and other documentation issued in connection with an offering of state or local government securities must comply with the guidelines of the Municipal Finance Officers Association or other nationally recognized guidelines.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-220">
            <num>37.15.220</num>
            <heading>Short title.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.220.   Short title.
AS 37.15.010
 37.15.220 may be cited as the State Bonding Act.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-225">
            <num>37.15.225</num>
            <heading>Bond authorization.</heading>
            <subsection eId="37-15-225__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of financing a portion of the costs of the Knik Arm bridge and appurtenant facilities or other toll bridges as the legislature may designate, including the costs of bond issuance, the issuance and sale of bonds of the state by the committee is authorized as provided in
AS 37.15.225
 37.15.290. The net proceeds of the sale of the bonds remaining after payment of costs of issuance, capitalized interest, if any, and making deposits to the bond reserve fund under
AS 37.15.260
, shall be transferred to the Knik Arm construction fund established in
AS 37.15.230
or may be held by a trustee to be disbursed to pay the costs of a toll bridge under the terms and conditions set out in a trust agreement. Accrued interest paid on the bonds shall be paid into the bond redemption fund.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-225__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Prior to the issuance of bonds authorized under (a) of this section, the committee shall send notice of the issuance to the legislature.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-225__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The total unpaid principal amount of bonds, including refunding bonds, but excluding refunded bonds, is limited as provided in
AS 37.15.235
. The bonds do not constitute a general obligation of the state. Authorization by the voters of the state or the legislature is not required.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-225__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The committee may enter into agreements with other state agencies as necessary or convenient to implement
AS 37.15.225
 37.15.290.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-225__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The committee may contract for the services of underwriters, paying agents, trustees, bond printers, rating agencies, bond insurance, credit enhancement providers, accountants, financial advisors, and bond counsel, and other services as are necessary to accomplish the bond issuance and sale.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-225__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The state may not issue bonds under (a) of this section for financing the Knik Arm bridge and appurtenant facilities until the Federal Highway Administration, United States Department of Transportation, has approved a loan to the state of at least 30 percent of the total project cost for construction of the Knik Arm bridge and appurtenant facilities under 23 U.S.C. 601  609 (Transportation Infrastructure Finance and Innovation Act of 1998).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-230">
            <num>37.15.230</num>
            <heading>Knik Arm construction fund.</heading>
            <subsection eId="37-15-230__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Knik Arm construction fund is established in the general fund to receive the proceeds of the sale of bonds issued under
AS 37.15.225
, and other state or federal money that is appropriated for the same purpose for which the bonds are issued. The Department of Transportation and Public Facilities shall use money in the construction fund to pay the cost of acquiring, constructing, and equipping the Knik Arm bridge and appurtenant facilities. To the extent allowed by the bond resolution, money in the construction fund may also be used for the payment of interest on the bonds during the time of construction. Money in the construction fund may be transferred to the bond redemption fund, as permitted by the bond resolution.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-230__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The bond resolution may provide for the investment of money in the construction fund as the committee determines. The interest earned on the investment of money in the fund shall be retained in the fund.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-235">
            <num>37.15.235</num>
            <heading>Toll bridge revenue bond limit.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.235.   Toll bridge revenue bond limit.
The total unpaid principal amount of revenue bonds issued under
AS 37.15.225
 37.15.290, including refunding bonds but excluding refunded bonds, may not exceed $300,000,000.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-240">
            <num>37.15.240</num>
            <heading>Toll bridge revenue fund.</heading>
            <subsection eId="37-15-240__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The toll bridge revenue fund is established as a separate fund of the state. The revenue fund consists of all revenue, fees, charges, and rentals received by the state, by contract with the authority or otherwise, from the ownership or operation of toll bridges and facilities and improvements used in connection with the toll bridges and facilities. Contracts or other agreements with the authority may establish priorities for the payment of operation and maintenance costs of the authority. The money in the revenue fund may be used only</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-240__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to pay or secure payment of the principal of and interest on bonds;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-240__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to redeem bonds before their fixed maturities;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-240__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to pay indebtedness to the Federal Highway Administration, United States Department of Transportation; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-240__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>subject to appropriation by the legislature, for any other purpose for which federal funds may be obligated by the state under 23 U.S.C. 129(a).</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-240__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The investment of money in the revenue fund may be made in the manner that the committee or the committee's delegated representative may determine. The interest earned on or any profits derived from the sale of this investment shall be deposited in and become a part of the revenue fund.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-240__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>All references to the toll bridge revenue fund in this section include special accounts within the toll bridge revenue fund that may be created by resolution or trust agreement to secure the payment of particular bonds.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-245">
            <num>37.15.245</num>
            <heading>Toll bridge revenue bond redemption fund.</heading>
            <subsection eId="37-15-245__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The toll bridge revenue bond redemption fund is established as a special fund of the state. The bond redemption fund is a trust fund for paying and securing the payment of the principal of and interest and redemption premium, if any, on the bonds and shall be at all times completely segregated and set apart from all other funds of the state. The bond redemption fund shall be drawn on only for the purpose of paying the principal of and interest and redemption premium, if any, on the bonds, together with related trustee fees, if any.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-245__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Money in the bond redemption fund may be invested in the same manner and on the same conditions as permitted for investment of money belonging to the state or held in the treasury under
AS 37.10.070
; however, the committee may agree with the bondholders to further limit these investments. Earnings on investments must be retained in the bond redemption fund or a designated account in the bond redemption fund.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-245__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>All references to the bond redemption fund in this section include special accounts in the bond redemption fund that may be created by resolution or first agreement to secure the payment of particular bonds.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-250">
            <num>37.15.250</num>
            <heading>Bond terms.</heading>
            <subsection eId="37-15-250__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The bonds may be issued and sold at public or negotiated sale in the manner, in the amounts or series, and at the time or times that the committee or the committee's delegated representative determines. The bonds, or each series of them, shall be sold at the price and on the terms, conditions, and covenants set by the committee or the committee's delegated representative after considering market conditions. Interest rates may be fixed or variable.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-250__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The bonds mature at the time or times fixed by the committee or the committee's delegated representative. The bonds may be subject to redemption before their fixed maturities, as determined by the committee or the committee's delegated representative, with or without a premium or premiums. The bonds may be in denominations determined by the committee or the committee's delegated representative; may be issued in fully or partially registered form; must be payable as to principal and interest at the place or places determined by the committee; must be signed on behalf of the state in the manner provided by the committee; and must be issued under and subject to the terms, conditions, covenants, and protective features safeguarding payment of the bonds and relating to the funding of projects as found necessary by the committee or the committee's delegated representative.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-250__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the committee or the committee's delegated representative finds it reasonably necessary, the committee or the committee's delegated representative may select a trustee or trustees for the holders of the bonds, or any series of them, for the safeguarding and disbursement of any of the money in the bond redemption fund, or for duties with respect to the enforcement, authentication, delivery, payment, and registration of the bonds as the committee may determine. The committee or the committee's delegated representative shall fix the rights, duties, powers, and obligations of the trustee or trustees.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-250__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In its determination of all matters and questions relating to the issuance and sale of the bonds and the fixing of their maturities, terms, conditions, and covenants as provided in (a)  (c) of this section, the decisions of the committee shall be reasonably necessary for the best interests of the state and accomplish the most advantageous sale of the bonds. Decisions of the committee, as expressed in a bond resolution, are final and conclusively considered to comply with the requirements of
AS 37.15.225
 37.15.290.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-255">
            <num>37.15.255</num>
            <heading>Bond resolution.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.255.   Bond resolution.
The committee shall authorize the issuance of bonds by adopting a resolution and shall prepare all other documents and proceedings necessary for the issuance, sale, and delivery of the bonds or any part or series of them. The bond resolution may fix or the committee's delegated representative, subject to parameters set by the committee, may fix the principal amount, denominations, date, maturities, manner of sale, place or places of payment, rights of redemption, if any, terms, form, conditions, and covenants of the bonds or each series of bonds.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-260">
            <num>37.15.260</num>
            <heading>Bond reserve fund.</heading>
            <subsection eId="37-15-260__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The resolution authorizing the issuance of the bonds under
AS 37.15.225
 37.15.290 may provide for the establishment and maintenance of a special fund called the toll bridge revenue bond reserve fund in which there shall be deposited or transferred</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-260__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>all money appropriated by the legislature for the purpose of the fund including appropriations in accordance with (g) of this section; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-260__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>all proceeds of bonds required to be deposited in the fund by terms of the bond resolution or a trust agreement with respect to the proceeds of bonds.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-260__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subject to (h) of this section, money in the reserve fund shall be held and applied solely to the payment of the interest on and principal of bonds authorized under
AS 37.15.225
 37.15.290 as the interest and principal become due and payable to the retirement of bonds. Money may not be withdrawn if a withdrawal would reduce the amount in the reserve fund to an amount less than the required debt service reserve except for payment of interest then due and payable on bonds and the principal of bonds then maturing and payable and for the retirement of bonds in accordance with the terms of the bond resolution or trust agreement and for which payment is not then available.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-260__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Money in the reserve fund in excess of the required debt service reserve as defined in (b) of this section, whether because of investment or otherwise, may be withdrawn at any time or may be transferred to the bond redemption fund subject to (h) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-260__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Money in the reserve fund may be invested in the same manner and on the same conditions as permitted for investment of funds belonging to the state or held in the treasury under
AS 37.10.070
; however, the committee or the committee's delegated representative may agree with the bondholders to further limit these investments.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-260__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of valuation, investments in the reserve fund shall be valued at par or, if purchased at less than par, at cost, unless otherwise provided by resolution of the committee. Valuation on a particular date shall include the amount of interest then earned or accrued to that date on the money or investments in the reserve fund.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-260__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding any other provision of
AS 37.15.225
 37.15.290, bonds may not be issued under a trust agreement, indenture, or bond resolution unless there is in the reserve fund the required debt service reserve for all bonds then issued under a trust agreement, indenture, or bond resolution and outstanding and for the bonds to be issued; however, the committee may satisfy this requirement by depositing as much of the proceeds of the bonds to be issued, on their issuance, as is needed to meet the required debt service reserve. The committee may, at any time, issue bonds or notes for the purpose of increasing the amount in the reserve fund to the required debt service reserve, or to meet whatever higher or additional reserve that may be fixed by a bond resolution or trust agreement with respect to the fund.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-260__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To ensure the required debt service reserve is maintained in the reserve fund, the legislature may appropriate annually for deposit in the fund the sum, certified by the commissioner of revenue to the governor and to the legislature, that is necessary to restore the fund to an amount equal to the required debt service reserve. The commissioner of revenue annually, before January 30, shall make and deliver to the governor and to the legislature a certificate stating the sum required to restore the fund to that amount, and the certified sum may be appropriated during the then current state fiscal year. Nothing in this subsection creates a debt or liability of the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-260__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>All amounts received because of money appropriated to the reserve fund shall be held and applied in accordance with (b) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-260__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>All references to the reserve fund in this section include special accounts within the reserve fund that may be created by resolution or trust agreement to secure the payment of particular bonds.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-260__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner of revenue may, subject to appropriation, lend surplus money in the general fund for deposit to an account in the reserve fund in an amount equal to the required debt service reserve. The loans shall be made on the terms and conditions that may be agreed on by the commissioner of revenue and the trustee, including, without limitation, terms and conditions providing that the loans need not be repaid until the obligations of the state secured and to be secured by the account in the reserve fund are no longer outstanding.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-260__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, required debt service reserve means, on the date of computation, the amount required to be on deposit in the reserve fund as provided by resolution of the committee.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-265">
            <num>37.15.265</num>
            <heading>Enforcement by bond owner.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.265.   Enforcement by bond owner.
The holder of any bonds or the trustee for the holders of the bonds or any series of them, may, by appropriate proceedings in the superior court, compel the transfer, setting aside, and payment of money and the enforcement of all of the terms, conditions, and covenants as required and provided for in
AS 37.15.225
 37.15.290 and in the bond resolution or trust agreement.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-270">
            <num>37.15.270</num>
            <heading>Amounts required for payments.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.270.   Amounts required for payments.
The committee shall, before June 30 of each year or from time to time within the year, as appropriate, commencing with the year in which the bonds are issued, certify to the commissioners of revenue and administration the amounts required in the current fiscal year and the next ensuing fiscal year by the bond resolution or resolutions or trust agreements to be paid out of toll bridge revenue or capitalized amounts into the bond redemption fund and to be paid into and maintained in any reserve fund or account or other fund or account created by the bond resolution or resolutions. The committee shall also certify to the commissioners the last date or dates on which payments may be made.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-275">
            <num>37.15.275</num>
            <heading>Refunding.</heading>
            <subsection eId="37-15-275__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The committee may refund the bonds or any part of the bonds at or before their maturity or redemption dates by issuing refunding revenue bonds of the state if the committee determines the refunding to be advantageous to and in the best interest of the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-275__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The issuance of refunding bonds need not be authorized by the voters of the state or by an act of the legislature. The committee shall adopt the resolution or resolutions and prepare all other documents and proceedings necessary for the issuance, exchange or sale, and delivery of the refunding bonds. All provisions of
AS 37.15.225
 37.15.290 applicable to revenue bonds are applicable to the refunding bonds and to the issuance, sale, or exchange of the refunding bonds, except as otherwise provided in this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-275__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The committee may issue refunding bonds in a principal amount sufficient to provide money for the advance or current refunding of all bonds to be refunded and interest on the refunded bonds and to pay the costs of issuance and administration of the refunding bonds. These expenses also include the difference in amount between the par value of the refunding bonds and any amount less than par for which the refunding bonds are sold; the premium, if any, necessary to be paid in order to call or retire the outstanding bonds and the interest accruing on them to the date of the call or retirement; and other costs. The committee is authorized to incur the expenses.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-275__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The committee or the committee's delegated representative may contract with a refunding trustee to hold the proceeds of refunding bonds in trust until the proceeds, together with earnings on the proceeds, are applied to pay the principal of, premium, if any, and interest on the bonds to be refunded. Until the refunding bond proceeds are applied, the proceeds may be invested in direct obligations of, or obligations guaranteed by, the United States or an agency or corporation of the United States whose obligations constitute direct obligations of, or obligations guaranteed by, the United States.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-280">
            <num>37.15.280</num>
            <heading>Bonds as legal investments.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.280.   Bonds as legal investments.
The bonds are legal investments for all banks, trust companies, savings banks, savings and loan associations, and other persons carrying on a banking business, all insurance companies and other persons carrying on an insurance business, and all executors, administrators, trustees, and other fiduciaries. The bonds may be accepted as security for deposits of all money of the state and its political subdivisions.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-285">
            <num>37.15.285</num>
            <heading>Statutory construction.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.285.   Statutory construction.
AS 37.15.225
 37.15.290 shall be liberally construed in order to carry out the purposes for which they were enacted.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-290">
            <num>37.15.290</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.290.   Definitions.
In
AS 37.15.225
 37.15.290,
(1) authority means
(A) the Knik Arm Bridge and Toll Authority established in
AS 19.75.021
with respect to the Knik Arm bridge and its appurtenant facilities; or
(B) an authority established by the legislature for any other toll bridge project;
(2) bond redemption fund means the toll bridge revenue bond redemption fund established in
AS 37.15.245
;
(3) bond resolution means a resolution adopted by the committee under
AS 37.15.255
to authorize the issuance of bonds;
(4) bonds means the toll bridge revenue bonds authorized in
AS 37.15.225
 37.15.290;
(5) committee means the state bond committee created in
AS 37.15.110
, or any other committee, body, department, or officer of the state that succeeds to the rights, powers, duties, and obligations of the state bond committee by law;
(6) costs of issuance and administration means all costs associated with issuance and administration of toll bridge revenue bonds and refunding bonds, including costs of bond printing, official statements, financial advisors, travel costs, rating agencies, bond insurance, letters and lines of credit for credit enhancement, underwriters, legal services, paying agents, bond registrars, bond and escrow trustees, arbitrage rebate, and all other costs, including administrative costs, both direct and indirect;
(7) reserve fund means the toll bridge revenue bond reserve fund authorized in
AS 37.15.260
;
(8) revenue fund means the toll bridge revenue fund established in
AS 37.15.240
.
Article 3. Bond Anticipation Notes.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-300">
            <num>37.15.300</num>
            <heading>Borrowing in anticipation of sale of bonds permitted.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.300.   Borrowing in anticipation of sale of bonds permitted.
When the state bond committee considers it in the best interests of the state, it may borrow money in anticipation of the sale of general obligation and revenue bonds if money to be derived from the sale of the bonds has been appropriated by the legislature and
(1) in the case of revenue bonds, the bonds to be sold have been authorized by law; or
(2) in the case of general obligation bonds, the bonds to be sold have been
(A) authorized by law and ratified by a majority vote of the qualified voters of the state who vote on the question; or
(B) authorized by law for the purpose of meeting natural disasters, repelling invasion, suppressing insurrection, or defending the state in war.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-310">
            <num>37.15.310</num>
            <heading>Issuance of notes.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.310.   Issuance of notes.
The state bond committee shall issue notes for the amounts borrowed with a maturity date not to exceed one year from the date of issue.  All the notes are payable at a fixed place, on or before a fixed time, or at a fixed time, from the proceeds of the sale of bonds, in anticipation of which the original note or notes were issued, unless the bonds have not been sold by the maturity date of the notes.  Interest on the notes is payable at a fixed place, on or before a fixed time, out of appropriations made for the payment of interest on general obligation notes or bonds of the state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-330">
            <num>37.15.330</num>
            <heading>Repayment of notes.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.330.   Repayment of notes.
Every note shall be payable from the proceeds of the next succeeding sale of bonds or from the proceeds of the sale of new bond anticipation notes.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-340">
            <num>37.15.340</num>
            <heading>Security for repayment of general obligation bonds.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.340.   Security for repayment of general obligation bonds.
Notes issued in anticipation of the sale of general obligation bonds and the interest thereon are secured by the full faith, credit, and resources of the state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-350">
            <num>37.15.350</num>
            <heading>Security for repayment of revenue bonds.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.350.   Security for repayment of revenue bonds.
Notes issued in anticipation of the sale of revenue bonds and the interest thereon are secured in the same manner as are the revenue bonds in anticipation of which the notes are issued.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-360">
            <num>37.15.360</num>
            <heading>Limitation on issuance of notes.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.360.   Limitation on issuance of notes.
The total amount of such notes issued and outstanding shall at no time exceed the total amount of bonds authorized to be issued.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-370">
            <num>37.15.370</num>
            <heading>Use of proceeds from sale of notes.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.370.   Use of proceeds from sale of notes.
The proceeds from the sale of the notes shall be used only for the purposes for which the proceeds from the sale of bonds may be used or to meet payment of outstanding bond anticipation notes.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-380">
            <num>37.15.380</num>
            <heading>Sale of notes.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.380.   Sale of notes.
Notes issued under this chapter shall be sold by the state bond committee in the manner and at the price or prices as it shall determine, at either public or private sale; however, a note sold under this chapter may not be sold for less than par and accrued interest or at an interest rate exceeding 11 percent a year or that rate of interest that is 110 percent of the rate of Bond Buyer Index of 20 Municipal Bond Average Yields for the week previous to the date of sale of the notes, whichever is higher.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-390">
            <num>37.15.390</num>
            <heading>Execution of notes.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.390.   Execution of notes.
Notes for money borrowed in anticipation of receipts from the sale of bonds shall be signed by the governor and countersigned by the lieutenant governor. The governor's and lieutenant governor's signatures may be facsimile signatures.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-410">
            <num>37.15.410</num>
            <heading>Bond authorization.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.410.   Bond authorization.
For the purpose of providing part or all of the money to be used, with or without any grants or other money that may become available, the issuance and sale of revenue bonds of the state in a total principal sum not to exceed $812,500,000 is authorized to acquire, equip, construct, and install the additions, improvements, extensions, and facilities authorized in
AS 37.15.510
. The principal of and interest on these bonds shall be paid out of and secured by the gross revenue derived by the state from the ownership, lease, use, and operation of the airports, and of all the facilities of them, and out of any other money that may be appropriated for the purpose, excepting only proceeds of any customer facility charge, and unless otherwise contractually required any customer facility maintenance charge, set by the commissioner of transportation and public facilities under
AS 02.15.090
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-415">
            <num>37.15.415</num>
            <heading>Continuing revenue bond debt service appropriation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.415.   Continuing revenue bond debt service appropriation.
The amounts required annually to pay the principal, interest, and redemption premium on all issued and outstanding international airports revenue bonds of the state are appropriated each fiscal year from the international airports revenue fund to the state bond committee to make all required payments of principal, interest, and redemption premium.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-420">
            <num>37.15.420</num>
            <heading>International airports construction fund.</heading>
            <subsection eId="37-15-420__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>There is established the International Airports Construction Fund, into which shall be paid the proceeds of the sale of the bonds (except any accrued interest paid on them, which shall be paid into the bond redemption fund) and grant or other money that is legally provided for the same purposes for which the bonds are authorized. The money in the construction fund shall be used to pay the costs of acquiring, equipping, constructing, and installing additions and improvements to and extensions of and facilities for the airports and costs incidental thereto, including costs of the authorization, issuance, and sale of the bonds. To the extent provided in the bond resolution, money in the construction fund may also be used for the payment of interest on the bonds during the period of actual construction, and for a further period, not exceeding one year after the period of construction, that may be provided in the bond resolution. Money in the construction fund may also be transferred to the bond redemption fund, to the extent provided in the bond resolution, to establish a reserve for the payment of the principal of and interest on the bonds.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-420__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The bond resolution may provide for the investment of money in the construction fund in a manner that the committee may determine.  The interest earned upon or any profits derived from the sale of this investment shall be deposited in and become a part of the construction fund.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-420__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>By January 1 of each year, the commissioner of transportation and public facilities shall submit to the legislature an annual spending plan that contains information regarding the planned expenditure of money from the construction fund during the next fiscal year and information on certain expenditures made during the previous fiscal year. The spending plan must include</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-420__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the total amount of money to be spent from the construction fund;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-420__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a description of the work to be performed on airport facilities that will be financed with money from the construction fund;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-420__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the amount from the construction fund that will be spent under contracts with the private sector and a description of the goods or services to be provided to the state under each of the contracts;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-420__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the amounts that the state will spend from the construction fund for purposes other than contract payments and a description of each of those purposes, including financing costs, administrative and other overhead costs, and contingencies;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-420__subsec_c__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the amounts spent during the previous fiscal year for cost overruns on projects financed in whole or part with money from the construction fund and the sources of money used for those cost overruns;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-420__subsec_c__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>identification of time delays that occurred during the previous fiscal year on projects financed in whole or part with money from the construction fund and amounts spent as a result of the delays.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-430">
            <num>37.15.430</num>
            <heading>International airports revenue fund.</heading>
            <subsection eId="37-15-430__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>There is established an enterprise fund known as the International Airports Revenue Fund, into which shall be paid all revenue, fees, charges, and rentals derived by the state from the ownership, lease, use, and operation of the airports and all of the facilities and improvements of them and facilities and improvements used in connection with them, excepting only proceeds of any customer facility charge, and unless otherwise contractually required any customer facility maintenance charge, set by the commissioner of transportation and public facilities under
AS 02.15.090
. The revenue, charges, fees, and rentals may not include the proceeds of any state tax or license. The money in the revenue fund may only be used for the purpose of</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-430__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>paying or securing the payment of the principal of and interest on the bonds and of and on any other revenue bonds issued by authorization of the legislature to provide money to acquire, equip, construct, and install additions and improvements to, and extensions of and facilities for, the airports, and to be payable out of the revenue fund;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-430__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>paying the normal and necessary costs of maintaining and operating the airports and all of the improvements and facilities of them;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-430__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>paying the costs of renewals, replacements, and extraordinary repairs to the airports and all of the improvements and facilities of them;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-430__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>redeeming before their fixed maturities any and all revenue bonds issued for the purposes of the airports;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-430__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>providing money to acquire, construct, and install necessary additions and improvements to and extensions of and facilities for the airports and all of their facilities; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-430__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>providing money to pay any and all other costs relating to the ownership, use, and operation of the airports.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-430__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The investment of money in the revenue fund may be made in the manner that the committee may determine.  The interest earned upon or any profits derived from the sale of this investment shall be deposited in and become a part of the revenue fund.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-430__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For proceeds of a customer facility charge set by the commissioner of transportation and public facilities under
AS 02.15.090
but required to be collected from customers by occupants or users of, or persons under contract to occupy or use, all or a portion of a facility that is or will be acquired, constructed, equipped, installed, or improved for state ownership with the proceeds of indebtedness incurred other than by the state on behalf of the Department of Transportation and Public Facilities,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-430__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Department of Transportation and Public Facilities shall by regulation or contract require that the proceeds of the customer facility charge be remitted directly to a trustee or another third party designated to receive the proceeds and to use the proceeds as provided under
AS 02.15.090</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-430__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the proceeds are not revenue of the state securing any indebtedness other than the indebtedness described in
AS 02.15.090</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-430__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For proceeds of a customer facility maintenance charge set by the commissioner of transportation and public facilities under
AS 02.15.090
but required to be collected from customers by occupants or users of, or persons under contract to occupy or use, all or a portion of a facility that is or will be acquired, constructed, equipped, installed, or improved with proceeds of indebtedness incurred other than by the state on behalf of the Department of Transportation and Public Facilities,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-430__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Department of Transportation and Public Facilities shall by regulation or contract require that the proceeds of the customer facility maintenance charge be remitted directly to a trustee or another third party designated to receive the proceeds and to pay some or all of the costs, fees, and expenses as determined by the commissioner of transportation and public facilities under
AS 02.15.090</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-430__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the proceeds are not, unless otherwise contractually required, revenue of the state securing any indebtedness.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-440">
            <num>37.15.440</num>
            <heading>International airports revenue bond redemption fund.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.440.   International airports revenue bond redemption fund.
There is another special fund of the state, known as the International Airports Revenue Bond Redemption Fund, which is a trust fund for paying and securing the payment of the principal of and interest and redemption premium, if any, on the bonds and which shall be at all times completely segregated and set apart from all other funds of the state. The committee, on behalf of the state, shall obligate and bind the state to set aside and pay into the bond redemption fund any part or parts of, or all of, or a fixed proportion of, or a fixed amount of the money in the revenue fund sufficient to pay the principal of and interest and redemption premium, if any, on the bonds as the payments become due and, if it considers it necessary, to set aside and maintain reserves for this purpose.  The bond redemption fund shall be drawn upon for the purpose of paying the principal of and interest and redemption premium, if any, on the bonds, and the bonds do not constitute a general obligation of the state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-450">
            <num>37.15.450</num>
            <heading>Bond terms.</heading>
            <subsection eId="37-15-450__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The bonds may be sold at public or private sale in the manner, in the amounts or series, and at the time or times that the committee determines. However, the bonds, or each series of them, shall be sold at such a price so that the effective interest rate over the life of the bonds does not exceed 11 percent per year or that rate of interest that is 125 percent of the rate of the Bond Buyer Index of 20 Municipal Bond Average Yields for the week previous to the date of sale of the bonds, whichever is higher. Interest shall be payable annually or semiannually.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-450__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The bonds mature at the time or times fixed by the committee. The bonds may be subject to redemption before their fixed maturities as determined by the committee and with a premium or premiums fixed by the committee, but a bond is not subject to redemption before its fixed maturity date unless the right so to redeem that bond is expressly mentioned on the face of the bond.  The bonds may be in denominations determined by the committee; may be issued in coupon form or in fully registered form, and may be registrable as to principal or both principal and interest, all under regulations and conditions that the committee shall provide; shall be payable as to principal and interest at such place or places as may be determined by the committee; shall be signed on behalf of the state by the governor and shall be attested by the lieutenant governor, both of which signatures may be facsimile signatures; shall have the seal of the state impressed, printed, or lithographed on them, and each of the interest coupons attached to them shall be signed by the facsimile signatures of these officials; shall be issued under and subject to such terms, conditions, and covenants providing for the payment of the principal of them and interest on them and such other terms, conditions, covenants, and protective features safeguarding this payment and relating to the maintenance, operation, and improvement of the airports as found necessary by the committee, which covenants may include a provision requiring the setting aside and maintenance of certain reserves to secure the payment of this principal and interest.  The committee may provide that any additional bonds authorized after June 27, 1972 by the legislature to be payable out of the same source or sources as the bonds authorized as of that date may later be issued on a parity with the bonds authorized as of that date upon compliance with any conditions which the committee may prescribe.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-450__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If found reasonably necessary, the committee may select a trustee or trustees for the holders of the bonds or any series of them, for the safeguarding and disbursement of any of the money in any of the funds created by
AS 37.15.420
, 37.15.430, and 37.15.440, or for duties with respect to the authentication, delivery, and registration of the bonds as the committee may determine, and shall fix the rights, duties, powers, and obligations of the trustee or trustees.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-450__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In its determination of all of the matters and questions relating to the issuance and sale of the bonds and the fixing of the maturities, terms, conditions, and covenants of them as provided in (a), (b), and (c) of this section, the decisions of the committee shall be those found to be reasonably necessary for the best interests of the state and its inhabitants, and those that will accomplish the most advantageous sale of the bonds, with due regard, however, to necessary or normal costs of maintenance and operation, renewals, and replacements of and repairs to the airports and to all improvements to them and facilities of them owned, used, operated, or leased in connection with them, the future growth and expansion of the airports and all of such facilities, and the possibility of additional revenue bond financing for airports purposes.  Any such decisions of the committee, as expressed in any bond resolution, are final and conclusive when any bonds have been issued pursuant to the bond resolution.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-450__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A bond resolution may provide that the bonds issued must contain a recital that they are issued under
AS 37.15.410
 37.15.550, and a bond containing this recital shall be conclusively considered to be valid and to have been issued in conformity with
AS 37.15.410
 37.15.550.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-450__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The validity of the authorization and issuance of bonds is not affected by any proceedings for the acquisition or construction of the additions, improvements, extensions, or facilities for which the bonds have been issued or by any contracts in connection with the acquisition or construction.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-460">
            <num>37.15.460</num>
            <heading>Bond resolution.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.460.   Bond resolution.
The committee shall adopt the bond resolution and prepare all other documents and proceedings necessary for the issuance, sale, and delivery of the bonds or any part or series of them. The bond resolution must fix the principal amount, denomination, date, maturities, place or places of payment, rights of redemption, if any, terms, form, conditions, and covenants of the bonds or each series of them.  The committee shall also determine and provide for the date and manner of sale of the bonds, and shall provide whether the notice of sale is to be published elsewhere in addition to the publication required by
AS 37.15.450
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-470">
            <num>37.15.470</num>
            <heading>Enforcement by holder.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.470.   Enforcement by holder.
The holder of any bonds or the trustee for the holders of the bonds or any series of them may, by appropriate proceedings in the courts of record of the state, require and compel the transfer, setting aside, and payment of money and the enforcement of all of the terms, conditions, and covenants as required and provided in
AS 37.15.410
 37.15.550 and in the bond resolution.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-480">
            <num>37.15.480</num>
            <heading>Amounts required for payments.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.480.   Amounts required for payments.
The committee shall, before December 31 of each year, commencing with the year in which the bonds are issued, certify to the commissioners of revenue and transportation and public facilities the amounts required in the next ensuing calendar year by the bond resolution or resolutions to be paid out of the revenue fund into the bond redemption fund and to be paid into and maintained in any reserve fund or account or any other fund or account created by the bond resolution or resolutions, and shall also certify to the commissioners the last date or dates upon which payments may be made.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-490">
            <num>37.15.490</num>
            <heading>Bond negotiability.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.490.   Bond negotiability.
The bonds and the coupons attached to them are fully negotiable instruments under the laws of the state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-500">
            <num>37.15.500</num>
            <heading>Airport charges.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.500.   Airport charges.
As provided in
AS 02.15.090
(a), the commissioner of transportation and public facilities shall fix and collect the fees, charges, and rentals derived by the state from the ownership, lease, use, and operation of the airports and all of the facilities and improvements that will provide revenue sufficient to comply with all of the covenants of the bond resolution.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-510">
            <num>37.15.510</num>
            <heading>State improvements to airports.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.510.   State improvements to airports.
The state is authorized to acquire, equip, construct, and install additions and improvements to and extensions of the airports, facilities for the landing, parking, loading, storing, repairing, safety, and utility of aircraft at the airports and passenger, freight, and terminal facilities, including safety equipment and devices at the airports, found to be necessary by the commissioner of transportation and public facilities.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-520">
            <num>37.15.520</num>
            <heading>Refunding.</heading>
            <subsection eId="37-15-520__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The bonds or any part of them may be refunded at or before their maturity by the issuance of refunding revenue bonds of the state if in the opinion of the committee refunding is advantageous to and in the best interests of the state and its inhabitants.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-520__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The issuance of refunding bonds need not be authorized by an Act of the legislature, and the committee shall adopt the resolution or resolutions and prepare all other documents and proceedings necessary for the issuance, exchange, or sale, and delivery of such bonds.  All provisions of
AS 37.15.410
 37.15.550 applicable to revenue bonds are applicable to the refunding bonds and to the issuance, sale, or exchange of them, except as otherwise provided in this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-520__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Refunding bonds may be issued in a principal amount sufficient to provide funds for the payment of all bonds to be refunded by them, and, in addition, for the payment of all expenses incident to the calling, retiring, or paying of the outstanding bonds, and the issuance of the refunding bonds. These expenses include the difference in amount between the par value of the refunding bonds and any amount less than par for which the refunding bonds are sold, any amount necessary to be made available for the payment of interest upon the refunding bonds from the date of sale of them to the date of payment of the bonds to be refunded or to the date upon which the bonds to be refunded will be paid pursuant to the call of them or agreement with the holders of them, and the premium, if any, necessary to be paid in order to call or retire the outstanding bonds and the interest accruing on them to the date of the call or retirement.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-530">
            <num>37.15.530</num>
            <heading>Bonds as legal investments.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.530.   Bonds as legal investments.
The bonds are legal investments for all banks, trust companies, savings banks, savings and loan associations, and other persons carrying on a banking business, all insurance companies and other persons carrying on an insurance business, and all executors, administrators, trustees, and other fiduciaries.  The bonds may be accepted as security for deposits of all funds of the state and its political subdivisions.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-540">
            <num>37.15.540</num>
            <heading>Statutory construction.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.540.   Statutory construction.
AS 37.15.410
 37.15.550 shall be liberally construed in order to carry out the purposes for which they were enacted, and all existing laws in conflict with any of these sections are superseded insofar as necessary to accomplish the purposes of and carry out the provisions of these sections.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-550">
            <num>37.15.550</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.550.   Definitions.
In
AS 37.15.410
 37.15.550, unless the context otherwise requires,
(1) airports means the international airports owned and operated by the state and located at or near the cities of Anchorage and Fairbanks;
(2) bond redemption fund means the International Airports Revenue Bond Redemption Fund created by
AS 37.15.440
, including any accounts that are created in that fund after June 27, 1972;
(3) bond resolution means the resolution or resolutions authorizing the issuance of bonds, adopted by the committee under
AS 37.15.460
;
(4) bonds means the international airports revenue bonds authorized by
AS 37.15.410
 37.15.550;
(5) commissioner of revenue means the principal executive officer of the Department of Revenue of the state as provided in
AS 44.25.010
, or a successor;
(6) commissioner of transportation and public facilities means the principal executive officer of the Department of Transportation and Public Facilities of the state as provided in
AS 44.42.010
, or a successor;
(7) committee means the state bond committee created by
AS 37.15.110
, or any other committee, body, department, or officer of the state which or who succeeds to the rights, powers, duties, and obligations of the state bond committee by lawful Act of the legislature;
(8) construction fund means the International Airports Construction Fund created by
AS 37.15.420
;
(9) revenue fund means the International Airports Revenue Fund created by
AS 37.15.430
.
Article 5. Alaska Clean Water Fund and Drinking Water Fund Bonds.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-560">
            <num>37.15.560</num>
            <heading>Bond authorization.</heading>
            <subsection eId="37-15-560__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of providing part of the money to be used to provide financial assistance to municipalities and other qualified entities under
AS 46.03.032
and 46.03.036, including the costs of bond issuance and administration, the issuance and sale of revenue bonds of the state is authorized subject to (b) of this section. The bonds are to be issued by the state bond committee, as provided in
AS 37.15.560
 37.15.605, as part of the Alaska clean water fund and the Alaska drinking water fund revolving loan fund programs (
AS 46.03.032
and 46.03.036), public enterprises of the state. The net proceeds of the sale of the bonds remaining after any payment of costs of issuance and administration shall be paid into the Alaska clean water fund or the Alaska drinking water fund, as appropriate. Accrued interest paid on the bonds shall be paid into the Alaska clean water fund or the Alaska drinking water fund for transfer to the Alaska clean water fund revenue bond redemption fund or the Alaska drinking water fund revenue bond redemption fund (
AS 37.15.565
), as appropriate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-560__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The state bond committee may not issue more than $15,000,000 in revenue bonds under
AS 37.15.560
 37.15.605 during a fiscal year for each revolving loan fund program referred to in (a) of this section, excluding refunding bonds. The total unpaid principal amount of revenue bonds, including refunding bonds, but excluding refunded bonds, issued under
AS 37.15.560
 37.15.605 may not exceed $150,000,000 for each program.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-560__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The bonds do not constitute a general obligation of the state. Authorization by the voters of the state or the legislature is not required.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-560__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The state bond committee may enter into agreements with other state agencies as necessary or convenient to implement
AS 37.15.560
 37.15.605.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-560__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The state bond committee may contract for the services of underwriters, paying agents, trustees, bond printers, rating agencies, bond insurance, credit enhancement providers, accountants, financial advisors, and bond counsel, and other services as are necessary to accomplish the bond issuance and sale.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-565">
            <num>37.15.565</num>
            <heading>Bond redemption funds.</heading>
            <subsection eId="37-15-565__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>There are established special funds of the state, known as the Alaska clean water fund revenue bond redemption fund  and the Alaska drinking water fund revenue bond redemption fund, which are trust funds for paying and securing the payment of the principal of and interest and redemption premium, if any, on the bonds and which shall be at all times completely segregated and set apart from all other funds of the state. The committee, on behalf of the state, may obligate and bind the state to set aside and pay into the bond redemption funds, on a monthly or other periodic basis, any part or parts of, or all of, or a fixed proportion of, or a fixed amount of the money in the Alaska clean water fund (
AS 46.03.032
) or the Alaska drinking water fund (
AS 46.03.036
) sufficient to pay the principal of and interest and redemption premium, if any, on the bonds and, if it considers it necessary, to set aside and maintain reserves for this purpose. The bond redemption funds shall be drawn upon only for the purpose of paying the principal of and interest and redemption premium, if any, on the bonds, together with related trustee fees, if any.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-565__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Money in the bond redemption funds may be invested in the same manner and on the same conditions as permitted for investment of money belonging to the state or held in the treasury under
AS 37.10.070
; however, the committee may agree with the bondholders to further limit these investments. Earnings on investments must be retained in the bond redemption funds.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-565__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Separate accounts may be created in the bond redemption funds for the purposes of paying and securing the bonds. The accounts may be combined for purposes of investment and for financial support to achieve the purposes of
AS 37.15.570
(c).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-570">
            <num>37.15.570</num>
            <heading>Bond terms.</heading>
            <subsection eId="37-15-570__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The bonds may be issued and sold at public or negotiated sale in the manner, in the amounts or series, and at the time or times that the committee determines. The bonds, or each series of them, shall be sold at the price and upon the terms, conditions, and covenants set by the committee after considering market conditions. Interest rates may be fixed or variable.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-570__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The bonds mature at the time or times fixed by the committee. The bonds may be subject to redemption before their fixed maturities, as determined by the committee, with or without a premium or premiums. The bonds may be in denominations determined by the committee; may be issued in fully or partially registered form; must be payable as to principal and interest at the place or places determined by the committee; must be signed on behalf of the state in the manner provided by the committee; must be issued under and subject to the terms, conditions, covenants, and protective features safeguarding payment of the bonds and relating to the funding of projects as found necessary by the committee, including covenants requiring the setting aside and maintenance of certain reserves to secure the payment of principal and interest, all under regulations and conditions of the committee.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-570__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The committee may pledge to the payment of the principal of and interest on bonds issued by the committee part or all of the legally available money or other assets on hand in the Alaska clean water fund (
AS 46.03.032
) or the Alaska drinking water fund (
AS 46.03.036
); part or all of the revenue of the Alaska clean water fund or the Alaska drinking water fund, including federal capitalization grants, the proceeds of loan repayments, and interest on money in the funds; the proceeds of the sale of bonds; and money on hand in the bond redemption funds. Revenue of the Alaska clean water fund or the Alaska drinking water fund, if so pledged, must be paid into the Alaska clean water fund or the Alaska drinking water fund, as appropriate. The committee may provide for the issuance of additional bonds, secured by a pledge of such money and revenue, ranking junior to, senior to, or on a parity with, outstanding bonds, upon conditions prescribed in the bond resolution. A pledge of loan repayments securing bonds may be made applicable to specific loans from the Alaska clean water fund or the Alaska drinking water fund, or, on a pooled basis, to all loan repayments received.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-570__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the committee finds it reasonably necessary, the committee may select a trustee or trustees for the holders of the bonds, or any series of them, for the safeguarding and disbursement of any of the money in the bond redemption funds created by
AS 37.15.565
, or for duties with respect to the enforcement, authentication, delivery, payment, and registration of the bonds as the committee may determine. The committee shall fix the rights, duties, powers, and obligations of the trustee or trustees.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-570__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In its determination of all matters and questions relating to the issuance and sale of the bonds and the fixing of their maturities, terms, conditions, and covenants as provided in (a)  (d) of this section, the decisions of the committee shall be those that are reasonably necessary for the best interests of the state and its inhabitants and that will accomplish the most advantageous sale of the bonds, with due regard, however, for the continued funding under
AS 46.03.032
and
AS 46.03.036
of the categories of projects identified in
AS 46.03.032</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-570__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and 46.03.036(b). Decisions of the committee, as expressed in a bond resolution, are final and are conclusively considered to comply with the requirements of
AS 37.15.560
 37.15.605,
AS 46.03.032
, and 46.03.036.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-570__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A bond resolution may provide that the bonds issued must contain a recital that they are issued under
AS 37.15.560
 37.15.605 and under
AS 46.03.032
or 46.03.036, as appropriate, and a bond containing this recital is conclusively considered to be valid and to have been issued in conformity with
AS 37.15.560
 37.15.605 and with
AS 46.03.032
or 46.03.036, as appropriate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-573">
            <num>37.15.573</num>
            <heading>Bond resolution.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.573.   Bond resolution.
The committee shall authorize the issuance of bonds by adopting a resolution and shall prepare all other documents and proceedings necessary for the issuance, sale, and delivery of the bonds or any part or series of them. The bond resolution must fix the principal amount, denominations, date, maturities, manner of sale, place or places of payment, rights of redemption, if any, terms, form, conditions, and covenants of the bonds or each series of them. A bond resolution may state terms, conditions, amounts, and other limitations on loans to be made from the Alaska clean water fund (
AS 46.03.032
) or the Alaska drinking water fund (
AS 46.03.036
), as appropriate, from the relevant bond proceeds.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-575">
            <num>37.15.575</num>
            <heading>State aid intercept.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.575.   State aid intercept.
If a municipality is in default on the payment of principal or interest on a loan from the Alaska clean water fund (
AS 46.03.032
) or the Alaska drinking water fund (
AS 46.03.036
), the committee may provide written notice of default to any state agency that is the custodian of money that is payable to the municipality. If the committee determines to provide notice, a separate written notice shall be given in each instance of default. Notwithstanding any other provision of law, at any time after receipt of written notice of default, the agency head shall withhold payment of the money from the municipality. The agency head shall pay over the withheld money to the committee for deposit in the Alaska clean water fund or the Alaska drinking water fund, as appropriate, for the purpose of paying or securing the principal and interest on the loan.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-580">
            <num>37.15.580</num>
            <heading>Pledge of the state.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.580.   Pledge of the state.
The state pledges to and agrees with the holders of bonds issued by the committee under
AS 37.15.560
 37.15.605 and under
AS 46.03.032
or 46.03.036, as appropriate, that the state will not limit or alter the rights and powers vested in the committee by
AS 37.15.560
 37.15.605 and by
AS 46.03.032
or 46.03.036, as appropriate, to fulfill the terms of any contract made by the committee with the holders, or in any way impair the rights and remedies of the holders until the principal amount of the bonds, together with the interest on them with interest on unpaid installments of interest, are fully met and discharged. The committee may include this pledge and agreement of the state in a contract with the holders.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-583">
            <num>37.15.583</num>
            <heading>Enforcement by bond owner.</heading>
            <subsection eId="37-15-583__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The owner or owners of not less than 10 percent of the aggregate principal amount of any series or issue of bonds or the trustee for the owners of the bonds or any series of them may, by appropriate proceedings in state court, require and compel the transfer, setting aside, and payment of money and the enforcement of all of the terms, conditions, and covenants as required and provided in
AS 37.15.560
 37.15.605,
AS 46.03.032
or 46.03.036, as appropriate, and the bond resolution.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-583__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A proceeding under (a) of this section may be commenced and conducted only in the Superior Court for the State of Alaska, First Judicial District at Juneau.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-585">
            <num>37.15.585</num>
            <heading>Amounts required for payments.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.585.   Amounts required for payments.
The committee shall, before June 30 of each year or from time to time within the year, as appropriate, commencing with the year in which the bonds are issued, certify to the commissioners of revenue and environmental conservation the amounts required in the current fiscal year and the next ensuing fiscal year by the bond resolution or resolutions to be paid out of the Alaska clean water fund or the Alaska drinking water fund into the appropriate bond redemption fund and to be paid into and maintained in any reserve fund or account or other fund or account created by the bond resolution or resolutions, and shall also certify to the commissioners the last date or dates upon which payments may be made.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-587">
            <num>37.15.587</num>
            <heading>Purposes and sufficiency of revenue.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.587.   Purposes and sufficiency of revenue.
The proceeds of bonds may be used for the purposes described in
AS 46.03.032
or 46.03.036, as appropriate. Bonds may not be issued unless the committee first finds that revenue to be derived from repayment of loans from the Alaska clean water fund or the Alaska drinking water fund, as appropriate, will be sufficient, together with other available money, to comply with all covenants of the bond resolutions.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-590">
            <num>37.15.590</num>
            <heading>Refunding.</heading>
            <subsection eId="37-15-590__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The committee may refund the bonds or any part of them at or before their maturities or redemption dates by the issuance of refunding revenue bonds of the state if, in the opinion of the committee, refunding is advantageous to and in the best interest of the state and its inhabitants.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-590__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The issuance of refunding bonds need not be authorized by the voters of the state or by an act of the legislature. The committee shall adopt the resolution or resolutions and prepare all other documents and proceedings necessary for the issuance, exchange or sale, and delivery of the refunding bonds. All provisions of
AS 37.15.560
 37.15.605 and of
AS 46.03.032
and 46.03.036, as appropriate, applicable to revenue bonds are applicable to the refunding bonds and to the issuance, sale, or exchange of them, except as otherwise provided in this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-590__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Refunding bonds may be issued in a principal amount sufficient to provide money for the advance or current refunding of all bonds to be refunded and interest on the refunded bonds and, in addition, for the payment of all costs of issuance and administration of the refunding bonds. These expenses also include the difference in amount between the par value of the refunding bonds and any amount less than par for which the refunding bonds are sold; the premium, if any, necessary to be paid in order to call or retire the outstanding bonds and the interest accruing on them to date of the call or retirement; and other such costs. The committee is authorized to incur such expenses.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-590__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The committee may contract with a refunding trustee to hold the proceeds of refunding bonds in trust until the proceeds, together with earnings on the proceeds, are applied to pay the principal of, premium, if any, and interest on the bonds to be refunded. Until the refunding bond proceeds are applied, the proceeds may be invested in direct obligations of, or obligations guaranteed by, the United States or an agency or corporation of the United States whose obligations constitute direct obligations of, or obligations guaranteed by the United States.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-595">
            <num>37.15.595</num>
            <heading>Bonds as legal investments.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.595.   Bonds as legal investments.
The bonds are legal investments for all banks, trust companies, savings banks, savings and loan associations, and other persons carrying on a banking business, all insurance companies and other persons carrying on an insurance business, and all executors, administrators, trustees, and other fiduciaries. The bonds may be accepted as security for deposits of all money of the state and its political subdivisions.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-600">
            <num>37.15.600</num>
            <heading>Statutory construction.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.600.   Statutory construction.
AS 37.15.560
 37.15.605 shall be liberally construed in order to carry out the purposes for which they were enacted.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-603">
            <num>37.15.603</num>
            <heading>Regulations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.603.   Regulations.
The committee may adopt regulations necessary to implement the provisions of
AS 37.15.560
 37.15.605.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-605">
            <num>37.15.605</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.605.   Definitions.
In
AS 37.15.560
 37.15.605,
(1) bond redemption funds means the Alaska clean water fund revenue bond redemption fund and the Alaska drinking water fund revenue bond redemption fund established in
AS 37.15.565
, as applicable;
(2) bond resolution means the resolution or resolutions adopted by the committee under
AS 37.15.573
authorizing the issuance of bonds;
(3) bonds means the Alaska clean water fund revenue bonds or the Alaska drinking water fund revenue bonds authorized in
AS 37.15.560
 37.15.605, as applicable;
(4) commissioner of environmental conservation means the principal executive officer the Department of Environmental Conservation as provided in
AS 44.46.010
, or a successor;
(5) commissioner of revenue means the principal executive officer of the Department of Revenue as provided in
AS 44.25.010
, or a successor;
(6) committee means the state bond committee created in
AS 37.15.110
or any other committee, body, department, or officer of the state that succeeds to the rights, powers, duties, and obligations of the state bond committee by lawful act of the legislature;
(7) costs of issuance and administration means all costs associated with issuance and administration of Alaska clean water fund revenue bonds or the Alaska drinking water fund revenue bonds, as applicable, and refunding bonds, including costs of bond printing, official statements, financial advisors, travel costs, rating agencies, bond insurance, letters and lines of credit for credit enhancement, underwriters, legal services, paying agents, bonds registrars, bond and escrow trustees, arbitrage rebate, and all other costs, including administrative costs, both direct and indirect.
Article 6. Toll Facilities Revenue Bonds.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-610">
            <num>37.15.610</num>
            <heading>Bond authorization.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.610.   Bond authorization.
For the purpose of providing part or all of the money to be used, with or without any grants or other money that may become available, the issuance and sale of revenue bonds of the state in the total principal sum of not to exceed $500,000,000 is authorized to acquire, construct, equip, and install the additions, improvements, extensions, and facilities authorized in
AS 37.15.720
and 37.15.730. The principal of and interest on these bonds are paid out of and secured by the gross revenue derived by the state from the ownership, use, and operation of the toll facilities, and out of any other revenue or money that the state legislature may provide exclusive of any state tax or license.  Bonds may not be issued to assist in the acquisition, financing, or operation of projects without prior approval from the legislature.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-620">
            <num>37.15.620</num>
            <heading>Construction fund.</heading>
            <subsection eId="37-15-620__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The toll facilities construction fund is established for deposit of proceeds of the sale of the bonds authorized by
AS 37.15.610
and any grant or other money that is legally provided for the same purposes for which the bonds are authorized except for any accrued interest paid on the bonds by the purchaser.  The money in the construction fund is used to pay the cost of acquiring, constructing, and equipping facilities authorized in
AS 37.15.720
and 37.15.730 and costs incidental to those activities, including costs of the authorization, issuance, and sale of the bonds.  To the extent allowed in the bond resolution, money in the construction fund may also be used for the payment of interest on the bonds during the time of actual construction, and for any additional time, not exceeding one year after construction is completed. Money in the construction fund may also be transferred to the bond redemption fund, as permitted by the bond resolution, to establish a reserve for the payment of the principal and interest on the bonds.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-620__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The bond resolution may provide for the investment of money in the construction fund as the committee determines.  The interest earned upon or any profit derived from the sale of the investment is deposited in the construction fund.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-630">
            <num>37.15.630</num>
            <heading>Revenue fund.</heading>
            <subsection eId="37-15-630__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The toll facilities revenue fund is established and shall be set apart from all other money of the state.  The toll facilities revenue fund is a trust fund for the purposes under
AS 37.15.610
  37.15.760, where all revenue, fees, tolls, charges, and rentals are deposited that are derived by the state from the ownership, lease, use, and operation of the facilities authorized by
AS 37.15.720
and 37.15.730.  The revenue, fees, tolls, charges, and rentals may not include the proceeds of any state tax or license.  The money in the revenue fund may only be used to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-630__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>pay or secure the payment of the principal of and interest on the toll facilities bonds and principal of and interest on any other revenue bonds issued by authorization of the legislature to provide money to acquire, construct, and equip facilities authorized by
AS 37.15.720
and 37.15.730 and to be payable out of the revenue fund;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-630__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>pay the normal and necessary costs of maintaining and operating the facilities acquired, constructed, or equipped under
AS 37.15.610
  37.15.760;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-630__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>pay the costs of renewals, replacements, and extraordinary repairs to facilities acquired, constructed, or equipped under
AS 37.15.610
  37.15.760;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-630__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>redeem before their fixed maturities any and all revenue bonds issued for the purpose of acquiring, constructing, and equipping facilities authorized by
AS 37.15.720
and 37.15.730;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-630__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide money to acquire, construct, and equip necessary additions and improvements to facilities authorized by
AS 37.15.720
and 37.15.730; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-630__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide money to pay any and all other costs relating to the ownership, use, and operation of the facilities.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-630__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The investment of money in the revenue fund may be made as the committee determines.  The interest earned upon or any profits derived from the sale of an investment under this subsection shall be deposited in the revenue fund.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-640">
            <num>37.15.640</num>
            <heading>Bond redemption fund.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.640.   Bond redemption fund.
The toll facilities revenue bond redemption fund is established for deposit in trust of money for paying and securing the payment of principal of and interest and redemption premium, if any, on bonds and is set apart from all other money of the state.  The committee, on behalf of the state, shall obligate the state to set aside and pay into the bond redemption fund from the revenue fund an amount of money sufficient to pay the principal of and interest and redemption premium, if any, on the bonds as the payments become due and, if the committee considers it necessary, to set aside and maintain a reserve for this purpose.  The bond redemption fund is drawn upon for the purpose of paying the principal of and interest and redemption premium, if any, on the bonds, and the bonds do not constitute a general obligation of the state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-650">
            <num>37.15.650</num>
            <heading>Bond terms.</heading>
            <subsection eId="37-15-650__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The toll facilities bonds are sold in the amounts or series and at the time as determined by the committee. Before selling a series of bonds, the committee shall give notice inviting sealed bids.  If satisfactory bids are received, the bonds offered for sale are awarded to the highest responsible bidder.  If the committee determines that a bid received is not satisfactory as to price or responsibility of the bidder, the committee may reject the bid received.  Bonds, or a series of bonds, may not be sold if the effective interest rate over the life of the bonds exceeds 11 percent per year or that rate of interest that is 125 percent of the rate of the Bond Buyer Index of 20 Municipal Bond Average Yields for the week previous to the date of sale of the bonds, whichever is higher. Interest is payable annually or semiannually.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-650__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The bonds mature at the time fixed by the committee. The bonds may be subject to redemption before their fixed maturities as determined by the committee and with the premium fixed by the committee, but a bond may not be subject to redemption before its fixed maturity date unless the right to redeem that bond is expressly mentioned on the face of the bond. The bonds</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-650__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>may be in denominations determined by the committee;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-650__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>may be issued in coupon form or in fully registered form, and may be registrable as to principal or both principal and interest, all under regulations and conditions the committee provides;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-650__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>are payable as to principal and interest at the place determined by the committee;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-650__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall be signed on behalf of the state by the governor and shall be attested to by the lieutenant governor, both of which signatures may be facsimile signatures, and each of the interest coupons attached to them shall be signed by the facsimile signatures of these officials;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-650__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall have the seal of the state impressed, printed, or lithographed on them; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-650__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall be issued under and subject to the terms, conditions, and covenants providing for the payment of the principal of and interest on the bonds and the other terms, conditions, covenants, and protective features safeguarding this payment and relating to the maintenance, operation, and improvement of the toll facilities as found necessary by the committee, which covenants may include a provision requiring the setting aside and maintenance of certain reserves to secure the payment of the principal and interest.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-650__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If found reasonably necessary, the committee may select a trustee or trustees for the holders of the bonds or any series of the bonds, for the safeguarding and disbursement of any of the money in any of the funds created by
AS 37.15.620
, 37.15.630, and 37.15.640, or for the duties for authentication, delivery, and registration of the bonds as the committee may determine.  The committee shall also fix the rights, duties, powers, and obligations of the trustee or trustees.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-650__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In the committee's determination of all of the matters and questions relating to the issuance and sale of the bonds and the fixing of the maturities, terms, conditions, and covenants of the bonds as provided in (a)  (c) of this section, the decisions of the committee shall be those found to be reasonably necessary for the best interests of the state and its inhabitants, and those that will accomplish the most advantageous sale of the bonds, with due regard, however, (1) to necessary or normal costs of maintenance and operation; (2) to renewals and replacements of and repairs to the toll facilities; (3) to all improvements to toll facilities and property of toll facilities owned, used, operated, or leased in connection with toll facilities; and (4) to the future growth and expansion of all of the facilities and the possibility of additional revenue bond financing for toll facilities purposes.  A decision of the committee, as expressed in any bond resolution, is final when any bonds have been issued under the bond resolution.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-650__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A bond resolution may provide that the bonds issued contain a recital that they are issued under
AS 37.15.610
 37.15.760, and any bonds containing this recital are conclusively considered to be valid and to have been issued in conformity with
AS 37.15.610
  37.15.760.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-650__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The validity of the authorization and issuance of bonds is not affected by any proceeding for the acquisition or construction of the additions, improvements, or facilities for which the bonds have been issued or by any contract in connection with the acquisition or construction.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-660">
            <num>37.15.660</num>
            <heading>Bond resolution.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.660.   Bond resolution.
The committee is authorized and directed to adopt the bond resolution and prepare all other documents and proceedings necessary for the issuance, sale, and delivery of the bonds or any part or series of them.  The bond resolution shall fix the principal amount, denomination, date, maturities, place or places of payment, rights of redemption, if any, terms, form, conditions, and covenants of the bonds or each series of them.  The committee shall also determine and provide for the date and manner of sale of the bonds, and shall provide whether the notice of sale is to be published elsewhere in addition to the publication required by
AS 37.15.650
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-670">
            <num>37.15.670</num>
            <heading>Enforcement by holder.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.670.   Enforcement by holder.
The holder of any bonds or the trustee for the holders of the bonds or any series of them, may, by appropriate proceedings in the courts of record of the state, compel the transfer, setting aside, and payment of money and the enforcement of all of the terms, conditions, and covenants as required and provided in
AS 37.15.610
  37.15.760 and in the bond resolution.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-680">
            <num>37.15.680</num>
            <heading>Amounts required for payments.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.680.   Amounts required for payments.
The committee shall, before December 31 of each year, commencing with the year in which the bonds are issued, certify to the commissioner of revenue and the commissioner of transportation and public facilities the amounts required in the next ensuing calendar year by a bond resolution to be paid out of the revenue fund into the bond redemption fund and to be paid into and maintained in any reserve fund or account or any other fund or account created by a bond resolution.  The committee shall also certify to the commissioners the last date upon which payments may be made.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-690">
            <num>37.15.690</num>
            <heading>Bond negotiability.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.690.   Bond negotiability.
The bonds and the coupons attached to them are fully negotiable instruments under the laws of the state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-700">
            <num>37.15.700</num>
            <heading>Refunding.</heading>
            <subsection eId="37-15-700__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The bonds or any part of them may be refunded at or before their maturity by the issuance of refunding revenue bonds of the state if in the opinion of the committee refunding is advantageous to and in the best interest of the state and its inhabitants.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-700__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The issuance of refunding bonds need not be authorized by an act of the legislature, and the committee shall adopt the resolution and prepare all other documents and proceedings necessary for the issuance, exchange or sale, and delivery of the bonds.  All provisions of
AS 37.15.610
 37.15.760 applicable to revenue bonds are applicable to the refunding bonds and to the issuance, sale, or exchange of the bonds, except as otherwise provided in this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-700__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Refunding bonds may be issued in a principal amount sufficient to provide money for the payment of all bonds to be refunded by them, and, in addition, for the payment of all expenses incident to the calling, retiring, or paying of the outstanding bonds, and the issuance of the refunding bonds. These expenses include the difference in amount between the par value of the refunding bonds and any amount less than par for which the refunding bonds are sold, any amount necessary to be made available for the payment of interest on the refunding bonds from the date of sale of them to the date of payment of the bonds to be refunded or to the date upon which the bonds to be refunded will be paid under the call of the bonds or agreement with the holders of them, and the premium, if any, necessary to be paid in order to call or retire the outstanding bonds and the interest accruing on the outstanding bonds to the date of the call or retirement.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-710">
            <num>37.15.710</num>
            <heading>Bonds as legal investments.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.710.   Bonds as legal investments.
Toll facilities bonds are legal investments for all banks, trust companies, savings banks, savings and loan associations, and other persons carrying on a banking business, all insurance companies and other persons carrying on an insurance business, and all executors, administrators, trustees, and other fiduciaries.  The bonds may be accepted as security for deposits of all money of the state and its political subdivisions.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-720">
            <num>37.15.720</num>
            <heading>State toll facilities.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.720.   State toll facilities.
The state is authorized to acquire, construct, equip, and maintain toll bridges, tunnels, highways, roads, crossings, and causeways found to be necessary by the commissioner of transportation and public facilities.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-730">
            <num>37.15.730</num>
            <heading>Review of toll facility projects.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.730.   Review of toll facility projects.
A toll facility may be financed under
AS 37.15.610
 37.15.760 if the following conditions are met for that toll facility:
(1) the department submits to the governor and the legislature a feasibility study that finds that the toll facility is financially feasible and able to produce revenue adequate to repay the bonds with which it is financed;
(2) if financing in addition to revenue bonds is required to finance the toll facility, the department submits to the governor and legislature a finance plan that includes an estimate of the total cost of the toll facility and a description of the sources of money that will be used to finance the total cost of the toll facility; and
(3) the office of management and budget reviews the feasibility study and the finance plan, if required, and reports its findings and recommendations to the governor and legislature not later than 90 days after the study and plan are received by the office.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-740">
            <num>37.15.740</num>
            <heading>Toll facility charges.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.740.   Toll facility charges.
The commissioner of transportation and public facilities shall fix and collect the fees, charges, tolls, and rentals derived by the state from the ownership, lease, use, and operation of the facilities authorized by
AS 37.15.720
and 37.15.730 and improvements of the facilities as will provide revenue sufficient to comply with all of the covenants of the bond resolution.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-750">
            <num>37.15.750</num>
            <heading>Statutory construction.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.750.   Statutory construction.
AS 37.15.610
 37.15.760 shall be liberally construed in order to carry out the purposes for which the provisions were enacted, and all existing laws in conflict with
AS 37.15.610
  37.15.760 are superseded as necessary to accomplish the purposes of
AS 37.15.610
 37.15.760.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-760">
            <num>37.15.760</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.760.   Definitions.
In
AS 37.15.610
  37.15.760, unless the context requires otherwise,
(1) bond redemption fund means the toll facilities revenue bond redemption fund created by
AS 37.15.640
, including any accounts that are created in that fund after October 4, 1984;
(2) bond resolution means the resolution authorizing the issuance of bonds, adopted by the committee under
AS 37.15.660
;
(3) bonds means the toll facilities revenue bonds authorized by
AS 37.15.610
  37.15.760;
(4) committee means the state bond committee created by
AS 37.15.110
, or any other committee, body, department, or officer of the state that or who succeeds to the rights, powers, duties, and obligations of the state bond committee by act of the legislature;
(5) construction fund means the toll facilities construction fund created by
AS 37.15.620
;
(6) revenue fund means the toll facilities revenue fund created by
AS 37.15.630
;
(7) toll facilities means highways, roads, bridges, tunnels, crossings, and causeways upon which tolls, charges, rentals, or other user fees are placed by the commissioner of transportation and public facilities.
Article 7. Sport Fishing Facility Revenue Bonds.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-800">
            <num>37.15.800</num>
            <heading>Tax-exempt bonds and tax credits.</heading>
            <subsection eId="37-15-800__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>As authorized under 26 U.S.C. 146(e), the state bond committee shall allocate the private activity bond volume limit for the state. Each year at least 25 percent of the limit shall be allocated to municipalities. If the committee determines that a portion of the limit allocated to municipalities will not be used by a municipality during that year, the committee may reallocate that portion.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-800__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The committee may make a carry-forward election under 26 U.S.C. 146(f) with respect to all or a portion of the private activity bond volume limit, including allocations that lapse under (c) or (d) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-800__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An amount allocated under (a) of this section lapses on December 30 of the year in which the allocation was made unless</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-800__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the entity that received the allocation uses it before that date; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-800__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the amount allocated is the subject of a carry-forward election under 26 U.S.C. 146(f).</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-800__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The committee may adopt regulations relating to the lapsing of amounts under (c) of this section. Regulations adopted under this subsection may establish times when allocated amounts will lapse in addition to the time provided in (c) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-800__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The committee shall allocate tax credit limits and tax-exempt bond limits for the state in accordance with requirements imposed by federal law in connection with the tax credits and tax-exempt bonds. This subsection does not apply to low-income housing tax credits, qualified veterans' mortgage bonds under applicable provisions of 26 U.S.C. (Internal Revenue Code), or private activity bonds.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-800__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-800__subsec_f__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>private activity bond means a bond described in 26 U.S.C. 141;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="37-15-800__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>private activity bond volume limit means the maximum amount of private activity bonds that may be issued under 26 U.S.C. 146 during a calendar year in the state by all issuers, including the state, municipalities in the state, and public corporations that are agencies of either the state or a municipality in the state.
Article 8. Pension Obligation Bonds.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-900">
            <num>37.15.900</num>
            <heading>Bond authorization.</heading>
            <subsection eId="37-15-900__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of financing prepayment of all or a portion of a governmental employer's share of unfunded accrued actuarial liability of retirement systems, including the costs of issuance and administration, the issuance and sale of bonds of the state by the committee is authorized as provided in this section and
AS 37.15.903
  37.15.955, but only  after submitting a proposal to the Legislative Budget and Audit Committee under (e) of this section and if the state bond rating is the equivalent of AA- or better. The net proceeds of the sale of the bonds remaining after payment of costs of issuance and administration shall be transferred to the commissioner of administration for the account of the governmental employer whose share of unfunded accrued actuarial liability is to be prepaid for application to that liability. Accrued interest paid on the bonds shall be paid into the pension obligation bond redemption fund.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-900__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The total unpaid principal amount of bonds, including refunding bonds, but excluding refunded bonds, is limited as provided in
AS 37.15.903
. The bonds do not constitute a general obligation of the state. Authorization by the voters of the state or the legislature is not required.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-900__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The committee may enter into agreements with other state agencies as necessary or convenient to implement this section and
AS 37.15.903
  37.15.955.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-900__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The committee may contract for the services of underwriters, paying agents, trustees, bond printers, rating agencies, bond insurance, credit enhancement providers, accountants, financial advisors, and bond counsel, and for other services as are necessary to accomplish the bond issuance and sale.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-900__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before the issuance and sale of bonds under this section, the committee shall submit a proposal to the Legislative Budget and Audit Committee for review, and 45 days shall elapse before bonds are issued and sold, unless the Legislative Budget and Audit Committee earlier recommends that the committee proceed with the issuance. Should the Legislative Budget and Audit Committee recommend within the 45-day period that the committee not proceed with the issuance and sale of bonds, the committee shall again review the proposal, and, if the committee decides to issue and sell the bonds, the committee shall provide the Legislative Budget and Audit Committee with a statement of the committee's reasons for doing so before issuance under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-903">
            <num>37.15.903</num>
            <heading>Pension obligation bond limit.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.903.   Pension obligation bond limit.
The total unpaid principal amount of bonds, including refunding bonds, but excluding refunded bonds, issued by all state entities added together, for the purposes of financing prepayment of all or a portion of a governmental employer's share of unfunded accrued liability of retirement systems, may not exceed $1,500,000,000 or a funding ratio of actuarial assets to accrued liability greater than 85 percent, whichever is less.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-905">
            <num>37.15.905</num>
            <heading>Bond redemption fund.</heading>
            <subsection eId="37-15-905__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>There is established a special fund of the state, known as the pension obligation bond redemption fund, which is a trust fund for paying and securing the payment of the principal of and interest and redemption premium, if any, on the bonds, and which shall be at all times completely segregated and set apart from all other funds of the state. The bond redemption fund shall be drawn on only for the purpose of paying the principal of and interest and redemption premium, if any, on the bonds, together with related trustee fees, if any.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-905__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Money in the bond redemption fund may be invested in the same manner and on the same conditions as permitted for investing of money belonging to the state or held in the treasury under
AS 37.10.070
; however, the committee may agree with the bondholders to further limit these investments. Earnings on investments must be retained in the bond redemption fund.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-905__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Separate accounts may be created in the bond redemption fund for the purposes of paying and securing the bonds. The accounts may be combined for purposes of investment and for financial support to achieve the purposes of
AS 37.15.910
(c).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-910">
            <num>37.15.910</num>
            <heading>Bond terms.</heading>
            <subsection eId="37-15-910__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The bonds may be issued and sold at public or negotiated sale in the manner, in the amounts or series, and at the time or times that the committee determines. The bonds, or each series of them, shall be sold at the price and on the terms, conditions, and covenants set by the committee after considering market conditions. Interest rates may be fixed or variable.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-910__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The bonds mature at the time or times fixed by the committee. The bonds may be subject to redemption before their fixed maturities, as determined by the committee, with or without a premium or premiums. The bonds may be in denominations determined by the committee; may be issued in fully or partially registered form; must be payable as to principal and interest at the place or places determined by the committee; must be signed on behalf of the state in the manner provided by the committee; and must be issued under and subject to the terms, conditions, covenants, and protective features safeguarding payment of the bonds as found necessary by the committee.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-910__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the committee finds it reasonably necessary, the committee may select a trustee or trustees for the holders of the bonds, or any series of them, for the safeguarding and disbursement of any of the money in the bond redemption fund or for duties with respect to the enforcement, authentication, delivery, payment, and registration of the bonds as the committee may determine. The committee shall fix the rights, duties, powers, and obligations of the trustee or trustees.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-910__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In its determination of all matters and questions relating to the issuance and sale of the bonds and the fixing of their maturities, terms, conditions, and covenants as provided in (a) of this section, the decisions of the committee shall be those that are reasonably necessary for the best interests of the state and its inhabitants and that will accomplish the most advantageous sale of the bonds. Decisions of the committee, as expressed in a bond resolution, are final and are conclusively considered to comply with the requirements of
AS 37.15.900
 37.15.955.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-915">
            <num>37.15.915</num>
            <heading>Bond resolution.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.915.   Bond resolution.
The committee shall authorize the issuance of bonds by adopting a resolution and shall prepare all other documents and proceedings necessary for the issuance, sale, and delivery of the bonds or any part or series of them. The bond resolution must fix the principal amount, denominations, date, maturities, manner of sale, place or places of payment, rights of redemption, if any, terms, form, conditions, and covenants of the bonds or each series of them.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-920">
            <num>37.15.920</num>
            <heading>Enforcement by bond owner.</heading>
            <subsection eId="37-15-920__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The owner or owners of not less than 10 percent of the aggregate principal amount of any series or issue of bonds or the trustee for the owners of the bonds or any series of them may, by appropriate proceedings in state court, require and compel the transfer, setting aside, and payment of money and the enforcement of all of the terms, conditions, and covenants as required and provided in
AS 37.15.900
 37.15.955, as appropriate, and the bond resolution.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-920__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A proceeding under (a) of this section may be commenced and conducted only in the Superior Court for the State of Alaska, First Judicial District at Juneau.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-925">
            <num>37.15.925</num>
            <heading>Amounts required for payments.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.925.   Amounts required for payments.
The committee shall, before June 30 of each year or from time to time within the year, as appropriate, commencing with the year in which the bonds are issued, certify to the commissioner of revenue and the commissioner of administration the amounts required in the current fiscal year and the next ensuing fiscal year by the bond resolution or resolutions to be paid from the general fund into the bond redemption fund and to be paid into and maintained in any reserve fund or account or other fund or account created by the bond resolution or resolutions, and shall also certify to the commissioners the last date or dates on which payments may be made.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-930">
            <num>37.15.930</num>
            <heading>Purposes and sufficiency of revenue.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.930.   Purposes and sufficiency of revenue.
The proceeds of bonds may be used for the purposes described in
AS 37.15.900
(a), as appropriate. Bonds may not be issued unless the committee first finds that the actuarially assumed rate of return on the funds managed by the Alaska Retirement Management Board is projected to exceed the true interest cost to be paid on the bonds by at least 1.5 percent annually.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-935">
            <num>37.15.935</num>
            <heading>Refunding.</heading>
            <subsection eId="37-15-935__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The committee may refund the bonds or any part of them at or before their maturities or redemption dates by the issuance of refunding bonds of the state if the state bond rating is the equivalent of AA- or better and if, in the opinion of the committee, refunding is advantageous to and in the best interest of the state and its inhabitants.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-935__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The issuance of refunding bonds need not be authorized by the voters of the state or by an act of the legislature. The committee shall adopt the resolution or resolutions and prepare all other documents and proceedings necessary for the issuance, exchange or sale, and delivery of the refunding bonds. All provisions of
AS 37.15.900
 37.15.955 are applicable to the refunding bonds and to the issuance, sale, or exchange of them, except as otherwise provided in this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-935__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Refunding bonds may be issued in a principal amount sufficient to provide money for the advance or current refunding of all bonds to be refunded and interest on the refunded bonds and, in addition, for the payment of all costs of issuance and administration of the refunding bonds. These expenses also include the difference in amount between the par value of the refunding bonds and any amount less than par for which the refunding bonds are sold; the premium, if any, necessary to be paid to call or retire the outstanding bonds and the interest accruing on them to the date of the call or retirement; and other of these costs. The committee is authorized to incur expenses to carry out this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="37-15-935__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The committee may contract with a refunding trustee to hold the proceeds of refunding bonds in trust until the proceeds, together with earnings on the proceeds, are applied to pay the principal of, premium, if any, and interest on the bonds to be refunded. Until the refunding bond proceeds are applied, the proceeds may be invested in direct obligations of, or obligations guaranteed by, the United States or an agency or corporation of the United States whose obligations constitute direct obligations of, or obligations guaranteed by, the United States.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-940">
            <num>37.15.940</num>
            <heading>Bonds as legal investments.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.940.   Bonds as legal investments.
The bonds are legal investments for all banks, trust companies, savings banks, savings and loan associations, and other persons carrying on a banking business, all insurance companies and other persons carrying on an insurance business, and all executors, administrators, trustees, and other fiduciaries. The bonds may be accepted as security for deposits of all money of the state and its political subdivisions.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-945">
            <num>37.15.945</num>
            <heading>Statutory construction.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.945.   Statutory construction.
AS 37.15.900
 37.15.955 shall be liberally construed to carry out the purposes for which they were enacted.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-950">
            <num>37.15.950</num>
            <heading>Regulations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.950.   Regulations.
The committee may adopt regulations necessary to implement the provisions of
AS 37.15.900
 37.15.955.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_37-15-955">
            <num>37.15.955</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 37.15.955.   Definitions.
In
AS 37.15.900
 37.15.955,
(1) bond redemption fund means the pension obligation bond redemption fund established in
AS 37.15.905
;
(2) bond resolution means a resolution or resolutions adopted by the committee under
AS 37.15.915
authorizing the issuance of bonds;
(3) bonds means the pension obligation bonds authorized in
AS 37.15.900
 37.15.955;
(4) committee means the state bond committee created in
AS 37.15.110
or any other committee, body, department, or officer of the state that succeeds to the rights, powers, duties, and obligations of the state bond committee by law;
(5) costs of issuance and administration means all costs associated with issuance and administration of pension obligation bonds and refunding bonds, including costs of bond printing, official statements, financial advisors, travel costs, rating agencies, bond insurance, letters and lines of credit for credit enhancement, underwriters, legal services, paying agents, bond registrars, bond and escrow trustees, arbitrage rebate, and all other costs, including administrative costs, both direct and indirect.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>