<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-44/chapter-09"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-44/chapter-09"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="44.09"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-44/chapter-09/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-44/chapter-09/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-44/chapter-09/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-44/chapter-09/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_44">
        <num>44</num>
        <heading>State Government</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_44__chp_09">
          <num>09</num>
          <heading>State Seal, Flag, and Emblems</heading>
          <section eId="sec_44-09-010">
            <num>44.09.010</num>
            <heading>State seal.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.09.010.   State seal.
The official seal of the State of Alaska is comprised of two concentric circles between which appear the words The Seal of the State of Alaska and within the inner circle is the design of the seal corresponding to the representation in this section.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-09-015">
            <num>44.09.015</num>
            <heading>Use of seal without permission prohibited.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-09-015__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not use or make a die or impression of the state seal for any advertising or commercial purpose, unless written permission has first been obtained from the lieutenant governor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-09-015__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Violation of this section is a misdemeanor, and upon conviction is punishable by a fine of not more than $500, or by imprisonment for not more than six months, or by both.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-09-017">
            <num>44.09.017</num>
            <heading>Commemorative gold and silver medallions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-09-017__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Administration shall contract or otherwise arrange for the minting and sale of Alaska commemorative medallions minted only from .999 fine gold and silver in weights determined by the commissioner of administration. Gold and silver mined in Alaska shall be used in the production of the medallions. The state shall receive a royalty from the sale of the medallions. The amount of the royalty shall be determined by the commissioner of administration.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-09-017__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>One side of the commemorative medallions minted under this section shall contain the state seal. The design for the other side shall be determined in an annual contest conducted by the contractor under the supervision of the Department of Administration. Only designs using an Alaska theme and submitted by an Alaska resident may be considered in the contest. Payment for the winning design may not exceed $1,000.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-09-017__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 35 ch 126 SLA 1994.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-09-020">
            <num>44.09.020</num>
            <heading>State flag.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.09.020.   State flag.
The design of the official flag is eight gold stars in a field of blue, so selected for its simplicity, its originality, and its symbolism. The blue, one of the national colors, typifies the evening sky, the blue of the sea and of mountain lakes, and of wild flowers that grow in Alaskan soil, the gold being significant of the wealth that lies hidden in Alaska's hills and streams.
The stars, seven of which form the constellation Ursa Major, the Great Bear, the most conspicuous constellation in the northern sky, contains the stars which form the Dipper, including the Pointers which point toward the eighth star in the flag, Polaris, the North Star, the ever constant star for the mariner, the explorer, hunter, trapper, prospector, woodsman, and the surveyor. For Alaska the northernmost star in the galaxy of stars represents Alaska, the forty-ninth star in the national emblem.
The flag of the Territory of Alaska is the official flag of the state. The standard proportions and size graphically delineated herein shall be used in the manufacture of the official flag of Alaska. The stars shall be the color of natural yellow gold and the field of blue shall be of the same shade of blue used in the official manufacture of the national emblem of the United States. The design, standard proportions, and size are as follows:</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-09-030">
            <num>44.09.030</num>
            <heading>Display of flags.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-09-030__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The official flag of the state shall be displayed with the flag of the United States only from sunrise to sunset, or between the hours designated by proper authority.  However, the flag may be displayed after sunset upon special occasions when it is desired to produce a patriotic effect.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-09-030__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The flag of the United States and the flag of the State of Alaska shall be displayed daily, weather permitting, in the following places:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-09-030__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>on or near the main administration building of every institution under the authority or control of the state government;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-09-030__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in or near every schoolhouse during school days.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-09-030__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 3 ch 5 SLA 2011.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-09-030__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When displayed horizontally in a public facility, the flag shall be positioned with the hoist on the left and the North Star in the upper right corner.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-09-030__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When displayed vertically in a public facility, the flag shall be positioned with the hoist at the top and the North Star in the lower right corner.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-09-032">
            <num>44.09.032</num>
            <heading>Folding and presenting the state flag.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-09-032__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When folding the state flag, the following procedure shall be followed, whenever possible:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-09-032__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>hold the flag waist-high with another person, so that the flag is parallel to the ground and the hoist is on the left;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-09-032__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>fold the flag lengthwise, with the open edge up;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-09-032__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>holding the edges securely, rotate the flag so that five stars are facing up;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-09-032__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>fold the flag lengthwise a second time, with the open edge up;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-09-032__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>holding the edges securely, rotate the flag so that two stars are facing up;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-09-032__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>fold the flag widthwise, with the North Star facing down and the hoist on the right;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-09-032__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>holding the edges securely, fold the flag widthwise a second time, with the North Star facing down and the hoist on the right;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-09-032__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>fold the flag widthwise a third time, with the North Star facing up.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-09-032__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When presenting the folded flag to another person, the folded flag should be turned so that the North Star is nearest the receiver.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-09-034">
            <num>44.09.034</num>
            <heading>Retirement of the state flag.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.09.034.   Retirement of the state flag.
An official flag of the state that is no longer a fitting emblem for display because it is worn, tattered, or otherwise damaged may be respectfully retired by fire in a ceremony or other dignified manner honoring the flag as a fitting emblem for the state. When practicable, retirement of the state flag should occur in a public ceremony under the direction of uniformed personnel representing a state or federal military service or a patriotic society. If a formal ceremony is not practicable, a private ceremony is acceptable.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-09-040">
            <num>44.09.040</num>
            <heading>State song.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.09.040.   State song.
The song Alaska's Flag, with music composed by Elinor Dusenbury and words by Marie Drake, is the official song of the state.  The words of the official song are as follows:
Alaska's Flag
Eight stars of gold on a field of blue 
Alaska's flag. May it mean to you
The blue of the sea, the evening sky,
The mountain lakes, and the flow'rs nearby;
The gold of the early sourdough's dreams,
The precious gold of the hills and streams;
The brilliant stars in the northern sky,
The Bear  the Dipper  and, shining high,
The great North Star with its steady light,
Over land and sea a beacon bright.
Alaska's flag  to Alaskans dear,
The simple flag of a last frontier.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-09-045">
            <num>44.09.045</num>
            <heading>State motto.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.09.045.   State motto.
The official motto of the State of Alaska is: North to the Future.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-09-050">
            <num>44.09.050</num>
            <heading>State flower.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.09.050.   State flower.
The wild native forget-me-not is the state flower and floral emblem.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-09-060">
            <num>44.09.060</num>
            <heading>State bird.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.09.060.   State bird.
The Alaska Willow Ptarmigan (Lagopus lagopus alascensis Swarth) is the official bird of the state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-09-070">
            <num>44.09.070</num>
            <heading>State tree.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.09.070.   State tree.
The Sitka spruce (picea sitchensis), which is recognized as the most valuable tree species in Alaska and which is found in both national forests of the state, is the official tree of the state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-09-075">
            <num>44.09.075</num>
            <heading>State marine mammal.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.09.075.   State marine mammal.
The bowhead whale is the state marine mammal.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-09-078">
            <num>44.09.078</num>
            <heading>State land mammal.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.09.078.   State land mammal.
The moose (Alces alces) is the state land mammal.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-09-080">
            <num>44.09.080</num>
            <heading>State fish.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.09.080.   State fish.
The king salmon (Oncorhynchus tshawytscha) is the official fish of the state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-09-085">
            <num>44.09.085</num>
            <heading>State sport.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.09.085.   State sport.
Dog mushing is the official sport of Alaska.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-09-090">
            <num>44.09.090</num>
            <heading>State medal for heroism.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-09-090__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The governor is authorized to award a state medal for heroism directly or posthumously to any citizen of the state in recognition of a valorous and heroic deed performed in the saving of a life or for injury or death or threat of injury or death incurred in the service of the state or the citizen's community or on behalf of the health, welfare, or safety of other persons.  The medal shall be awarded by the governor with an appropriate ceremony.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-09-090__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The governor shall make arrangements for the designing of the medal for heroism through a statewide design competition participated in by the school children of the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-09-095">
            <num>44.09.095</num>
            <heading>North Star Medal.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-09-095__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The governor is authorized to award the North Star Medal directly or posthumously to any peace officer, correctional officer, firefighter, first responder, or member of a volunteer search and rescue group who dies or is seriously injured in the line of duty and has displayed exceptional bravery or heroism while performing those duties.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-09-095__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The governor shall present recipients of the North Star Medal with a ribbon, medal, and citation during a ceremony that may not take place more than once a year. The North Star Medal will be awarded to the recipient or, in the event the recipient is no longer living, to the recipient's next of kin.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-09-095__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nominations for the North Star Medal must be submitted to the commissioner of public safety by the highest ranking supervisor in the department or organization of the nominee. After reviewing the nominations, the commissioner of public safety shall submit the name or names of persons recommended for the North Star Medal to the governor for approval.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-09-097">
            <num>44.09.097</num>
            <heading>Honor and Remember Flag.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-09-097__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Honor and Remember Flag is designated as an official symbol of the state for the purpose of recognizing and honoring members of the armed forces of the United States who have died in the line of duty and their families.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-09-097__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The design of the Honor and Remember Flag is a red field signifying the blood spilled by brave men and women who sacrificed their lives for freedom, a blue star symbolizing active service in military conflict, a white border representing the purity of sacrifice, a gold star signifying the ultimate sacrifice of a warrior in active service who is not returning home and reflecting the value of a life given, a folded flag element signifying the final tribute to a fallen member of the armed forces and highlighting a family's sacrifice, and a flame signifying the eternal spirit of the departed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-09-097__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Honor and Remember Flag may be displayed at the locations listed in (d) of this section on any day, including</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-09-097__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the third Saturday in May, known as Armed Forces Day;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-09-097__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the last Monday in May, known as Memorial Day;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-09-097__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Friday immediately preceding Memorial Day, known as Alaska Veterans' Poppy Day;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-09-097__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the 14th of June, known as Flag Day;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-09-097__subsec_c__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the fourth of July, known as Independence Day;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-09-097__subsec_c__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the third Friday in September, known as National POW/MIA Recognition Day;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-09-097__subsec_c__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the last Sunday in September, known as Gold Star Mother's Day; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-09-097__subsec_c__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the 11th of November, known as Veterans Day.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-09-097__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Honor and Remember Flag may be displayed at the following locations on the days listed under (c) of this section:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-09-097__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the state capitol;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-09-097__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a court facility; in this paragraph, court facility has the meaning given in
AS 22.05.025</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-09-097__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the main municipal office location of each municipality;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-09-097__subsec_d__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>memorials to Alaska veterans constructed under
AS 44.35.030
; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-09-097__subsec_d__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Alaska veterans' cemeteries established and maintained under
AS 44.35.035
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-09-097__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An employee of the state or a municipality may not be required to report to work solely for the purpose of displaying the Honor and Remember Flag.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-09-097__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner of administration may adopt regulations to implement this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-09-099">
            <num>44.09.099</num>
            <heading>Honor and Sacrifice Flag.</heading>
            <subsection eId="44-09-099__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Honor and Sacrifice Flag is designated as an official symbol of the state for the purpose of recognizing and honoring the selfless service and individual sacrifice of firefighters and law enforcement officers who have died in the line of duty and their families.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-09-099__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The design of the Honor and Sacrifice Flag is a blue field symbolizing the national law enforcement community; a purple field signifying mourning the loss of a firefighter; a white field symbolizing the purity of heart within individuals who serve, protect, and are willing to face the challenges of each day regardless of risk; a black star representing the individuals who wear the distinctive badge, including sheriffs and members of the United States Marshal Service; a red Maltese cross recognizing the individuals who have fallen while serving in emergency response communities; a gold shield symbolizing the value of life given and recognizing all law enforcement officers and other public safety representatives who wear a shield, including emergency medical technicians, and who have made the ultimate sacrifice in the line of duty; a folded flag element signifying the final tribute to an individual fallen for the sake of others and highlighting a family's sacrifice; and a flame signifying an eternal reminder of the spirit that has departed this life yet burns on in the memory of all who knew and loved the fallen hero.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-09-099__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Honor and Sacrifice Flag may be displayed at the locations listed in (d) of this section on any day, including</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-09-099__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the ninth of January, known as National Law Enforcement Day;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-09-099__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the fourth of May, known as International Firefighters Day;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-09-099__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the 15th of May, known as Peace Officers Memorial Day;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-09-099__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the 14th of June, known as Flag Day;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-09-099__subsec_c__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the fourth of July, known as Independence Day; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-09-099__subsec_c__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the 11th of September, known as National Day of Service and Remembrance.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-09-099__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Honor and Sacrifice Flag may be displayed at the following locations on the days listed under (c) of this section:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="44-09-099__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the state capitol;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-09-099__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a court facility; in this paragraph, court facility has the meaning given in
AS 22.05.025</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-09-099__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>each office of the Department of Public Safety, each state trooper headquarters and station established under
AS 18.65.030
, and the Public Safety Training Academy for state troopers;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-09-099__subsec_d__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the main municipal office location of each municipality; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="44-09-099__subsec_d__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>memorials to state firefighters or law enforcement.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-09-099__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An employee of the state or a municipality may not be required to report to work solely for the purpose of displaying the Honor and Sacrifice Flag.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="44-09-099__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner of administration may adopt regulations to implement this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-09-100">
            <num>44.09.100</num>
            <heading>State gem.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.09.100.   State gem.
Jade is the official state gem.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-09-110">
            <num>44.09.110</num>
            <heading>State mineral.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.09.110.   State mineral.
Gold is the official state mineral.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-09-120">
            <num>44.09.120</num>
            <heading>State fossil.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.09.120.   State fossil.
The woolly mammoth (Mammuthus primigenius) is the official state fossil.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-09-130">
            <num>44.09.130</num>
            <heading>State insect.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.09.130.   State insect.
The four spot skimmer dragonfly is the official state insect.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-09-140">
            <num>44.09.140</num>
            <heading>State dog.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.09.140.   State dog.
The Alaskan Malamute is the official state dog.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_44-09-150">
            <num>44.09.150</num>
            <heading>State bolt-action rifle.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 44.09.150.   State bolt-action rifle.
The pre-1964 Winchester Model 70 bolt-action rifle in the following calibers is the official state bolt-action rifle: .22 Hornet, .220 Swift, .243 Winchester, .250-3000 Savage, .264 Winchester Magnum, .257 Roberts, .270 W.C.F., 7 mm, .300 Savage, .30-06, .300 H&amp;H Magnum, .300 Winchester Magnum, .308 Winchester, .358 Winchester, .35 Remington, .375 H&amp;H Magnum, .338 Winchester Magnum, .458 Winchester Magnum.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>