<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-2/chapter-25"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-2/chapter-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="2.25"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-2/chapter-25/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-2/chapter-25/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-2/chapter-25/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-2/chapter-25/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_2">
        <num>2</num>
        <heading>Aeronautics</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_2__chp_25">
          <num>25</num>
          <heading>Airport Zoning Act</heading>
          <section eId="sec_02-25-010">
            <num>02.25.010</num>
            <heading>Airport zoning regulations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 02.25.010.   Airport zoning regulations.
A person may not erect or permit to grow an airport hazard on land adjacent to the end of a runway of a public airport without a permit issued by the department. The area upon which these hazards are prohibited is the width of the runway, and extends from the airport boundary at the end of the runway, away from the runway in a direction parallel to its centerline for a distance equal to the length of the runway. An obstruction situated in an area not previously designated as an airport hazard area by the department is not a hazard if its height does not exceed five feet for each 200 feet distance from the boundary of the airport. The vertical measurement of the structure starts on the same plane as the surface of the runway.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-25-020">
            <num>02.25.020</num>
            <heading>Power to adopt regulations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 02.25.020.   Power to adopt regulations.
In addition to, or in place of, the airport hazard area described in
AS 02.25.010
, the department may adopt, administer, and enforce, under the police power and in the manner and upon the conditions prescribed in this chapter, airport zoning regulations for any airport within this state dividing the area surrounding the airport into zones. Within these zones, the department may specify the land uses permitted, and regulate and restrict the height to which structures and trees may be erected or allowed to grow, and require the abatement of lights, or electronic signals or emissions that may create a hazard to the operation of aircraft. In adopting or revising zoning regulations, the department shall consider, among other things, the character of the flying operations to be conducted at the airport, the nature of the terrain, the height of existing structures and trees above the level of the airport, the possibility of lowering or removing existing obstructions, and the views of the agency of the federal government charged with fostering civil aeronautics as to the aerial approaches necessary to safe flying operations at the airport.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-25-030">
            <num>02.25.030</num>
            <heading>Adoption of zoning regulations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 02.25.030.   Adoption of zoning regulations.
Airport zoning regulations may not be adopted or amended under this chapter except by action of the department after a public hearing at which parties in interest and citizens have an opportunity to be heard. At least 15 days' notice of the hearing shall be published in a newspaper of general circulation printed and published nearest the location of the airport concerned.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-25-040">
            <num>02.25.040</num>
            <heading>Publication of zoning plan.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 02.25.040.   Publication of zoning plan.
Upon the adoption of an airport zoning plan, the department shall prepare at least two copies of the plan, showing the airport and the airport hazard area, together with the designated height limits of possible hazards. One copy of the zoning plan shall be posted conspicuously at the airport concerned, and the other copy shall be filed in the office of the department.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-25-050">
            <num>02.25.050</num>
            <heading>Pre-existing use not affected.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 02.25.050.   Pre-existing use not affected.
All airport zoning regulations adopted under this chapter shall be reasonable, and the department may not require the removal, lowering, or other change or alteration of a structure or tree not conforming to the regulations when adopted or amended, or otherwise interfere with the continuance of any nonconforming use except under
AS 02.25.060
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-25-060">
            <num>02.25.060</num>
            <heading>Permits for removal of nonconforming structures or trees.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 02.25.060.   Permits for removal of nonconforming structures or trees.
Where advisable to facilitate the enforcement of zoning regulations adopted under this chapter, permits may be granted to establish or construct new structures and other uses and to replace existing structures and other uses or make substantial changes or substantial repairs. Before any nonconforming structure or tree may be replaced, substantially altered or repaired, rebuilt, allowed to grow higher, or replanted, a permit must be secured from the department authorizing the replacement, change or repair. A permit may not be granted allowing the structure or tree to be made higher or become a greater hazard to air navigation than it was when the applicable regulation was adopted. If the department determines that a nonconforming structure or tree is abandoned or more than 80 percent torn down, destroyed, deteriorated, or decayed, (1) a permit may not be granted allowing the structure or tree to exceed the applicable height limits or otherwise deviate from the zoning regulations; and (2) whether application is made for a permit under this section or not, the department may, by appropriate action, compel the owner of the nonconforming structure or tree, at the owner's own expense, to lower, remove, reconstruct, or equip the object to conform to the regulations. If the owner of the nonconforming structure or tree neglects or refuses to comply with the order within 10 days after notice, the department may proceed to have the object lowered, removed, reconstructed, or equipped, and the cost and expense is a lien upon the object and the land on which it is located. Unless the account is paid within 90 days from the service of notice on the agent or owner of the object or land, the sum bears interest at the rate of eight percent a year until paid, and shall be collected by foreclosure in the manner provided for the foreclosure of mortgages.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-25-070">
            <num>02.25.070</num>
            <heading>Variances.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 02.25.070.   Variances.
A person desiring to erect a structure, or increase the height of a structure, or permit the growth of a tree, or otherwise to use the person's property in violation of airport zoning regulations adopted under this chapter may apply to the department for a variance from the zoning regulations. Variances shall be allowed where a literal application or enforcement of the regulations would result in practical difficulty or unnecessary hardship and the relief granted would not be contrary to the public interest but would do substantial justice and would be in accordance with the spirit of the regulations and this chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-25-090">
            <num>02.25.090</num>
            <heading>Action by department.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 02.25.090.   Action by department.
The department may institute an action in the superior court to prevent, restrain, correct, or abate a violation of this chapter or of airport zoning regulations adopted under this chapter or of an order or ruling made in connection with their administration or enforcement, and the court shall give relief, by way of injunction or otherwise as may be proper, in order to fully effectuate the purposes of this chapter and of the regulations adopted and orders and rulings made under this chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-25-100">
            <num>02.25.100</num>
            <heading>Criminal liability for violation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 02.25.100.   Criminal liability for violation.
Each violation of this chapter or of a regulation, order, or ruling adopted or made under this chapter is a misdemeanor and is punishable by a fine of not more than $500 or by imprisonment for not more than 90 days or by both.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-25-110">
            <num>02.25.110</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 02.25.110.   Definitions.
In this chapter, unless the context otherwise requires,
(1) airport means an area of land or water designed for the landing and taking-off of aircraft and used or to be used as a point of arrival or departure by air;
(2) airport hazard means anything that may obstruct or interfere with the navigation or operation of aircraft on or in the vicinity of an airport, including man-made structures of all kinds, trees and other natural growths, lights or beacons, and electrical or electronic devices emitting signals capable of disrupting radio communication;
(3) airport hazard area means an area in the vicinity of an airport in which a hazard to the operation of aircraft might be situated, and that may be designated as such by the department;
(4) department means the Department of Transportation and Public Facilities;
(5) person means an individual, firm, copartnership, corporation, company, association, joint stock association, or body politic, and includes a trustee, receiver, assignee, or similar representative;
(6) structure means an object constructed or installed by man, including buildings, towers, smokestacks, and overhead transmission lines;
(7) tree means any object of natural growth.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-25-120">
            <num>02.25.120</num>
            <heading>Short title.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 02.25.120.   Short title.
This chapter may be cited as the Airport Zoning Act.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>