<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-20"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-20"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="14.20"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-20/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-20/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-20/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-20/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_14">
        <num>14</num>
        <heading>Education, Libraries, and Museums</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_14__chp_20">
          <num>20</num>
          <heading>Teachers and School Personnel</heading>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-010">
            <num>14.20.010</num>
            <heading>Teacher certificate required.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.20.010.   Teacher certificate required.
A person may not be employed as a teacher in the public schools of the state unless that person possesses a valid teacher certificate except that a person who has made application to the department for a teacher certificate or renewal of a teacher certificate that has not been acted on by the department may be employed as a teacher in the public schools of the state until the department has taken action on the application, but in no case may employment without a certificate last longer than three months. A person who has made application for a certificate under this section may teach for an additional 60 days beyond three months without a certificate if the department grants a written extension. An extension may be granted under this section for not more than 60 days to the person solely due to delay in the department's receipt of criminal justice information under
AS 12.62
or a national criminal history record check under
AS 12.62.400
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-015">
            <num>14.20.015</num>
            <heading>Recognition of certificates of out-of-state teachers.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-20-015__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall issue a preliminary teacher certificate to an out-of-state teacher who meets the requirements of this section. To be eligible for a preliminary teacher certificate, a person shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-015__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>have received at least a baccalaureate degree from an institution of higher education accredited by a recognized regional accrediting association or approved by the commissioner;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-015__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>hold a valid teacher certificate issued by another state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-015__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>have submitted fingerprints to the department to be used for a criminal history background check and been found by the department to be suitable for employment as a teacher under
AS 14.20.020</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-015__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>have paid the fee required by the department under
AS 14.20.020</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-015__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An out-of-state teacher who has been issued a preliminary teacher certificate under this section shall pass the competency examination designated by the board under
AS 14.20.020</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-015__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>within one year after the date the preliminary teacher certificate was issued. If the teacher does not pass the examination, the department shall immediately revoke the teacher's preliminary teacher certificate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-015__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The teacher certificate issued under this section must contain the same endorsements as those on the current valid regular teacher certificate issued by the other state. However, before teaching students in grades kindergarten through three, a teacher certificated under this section must complete coursework, training, or testing requirements, and demonstrate proficiency as determined by the department, in phonemic awareness, phonics, vocabulary development, reading fluency, oral language skills, and reading comprehension approved by the board in regulation. A teacher may apply coursework, training, or testing requirements completed under this subsection toward continuing education requirements established by the board in regulation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-015__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 8 ch 69 SLA 2022.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-015__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 8 ch 69 SLA 2022.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-015__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 8 ch 69 SLA 2022.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-015__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall by regulation adopt a process to expedite issuance of a certificate to the spouse of an active duty member of the armed forces of the United States.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-017">
            <num>14.20.017</num>
            <heading>Grace period for issuance of regular teacher certificates to previously certificated teachers.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-20-017__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall issue a teacher certificate as described in
AS 14.20.020
, subject to revocation, to a teacher who meets the requirements of this section. To be eligible for a revocable teacher certificate under this section, a person shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-017__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>have held a valid teacher certificate issued under
AS 14.20.020
that expired more than 12 months before the teacher applied for a certificate under this section;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-017__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>have paid the fee required by the department under
AS 14.20.020</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-017__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A revocable teacher certificate issued under this section is valid for one year, during which the teacher shall complete any requirements for the issuance of a regular teacher certificate under
AS 14.20.020
that the teacher has not already met. The department shall expedite the procedures required of teachers holding revocable teacher certificates who are seeking certification under
AS 14.20.020
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-017__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A teacher holding a revocable teacher certificate under this section who previously passed the competency examination designated by the board under
AS 14.20.020</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-017__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>is not required to retake the examination before being eligible for a regular certificate under
AS 14.20.020
. A teacher holding a revocable teacher certificate who did not previously take or pass the competency examination shall take and pass the examination within one year after the date the revocable teacher certificate was issued. If the teacher does not pass the examination, the department shall immediately revoke the revocable teacher certificate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-017__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A teacher holding a revocable teacher certificate under this section may not receive a teacher certificate issued under
AS 14.20.020
until the teacher submits fingerprints to the department to be used for a criminal history background check and the teacher has been found by the department to be suitable for employment as a teacher under
AS 14.20.020
(f).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-017__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The revocable teacher certificate issued under this section must contain the same endorsements as those on the teacher's expired teacher certificate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-017__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Employment on the basis of a revocable teacher certificate issued under this section shall be considered in determining whether a teacher qualifies for tenure under
AS 14.20.150
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-017__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A revocable teacher certificate and any endorsements issued under this section are valid for one year and may not be renewed under this section. The department may not issue a provisional certificate or a temporary certificate to a teacher who has held a teacher certificate issued under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-020">
            <num>14.20.020</num>
            <heading>Requirements for issuance of certificate; fingerprints.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-20-020__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (f) of this section, the department shall issue a teacher certificate to every person who meets the requirements in (b), (c), and (h) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-020__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person is not eligible for a teacher certificate unless that person has received at least a baccalaureate degree from an institution of higher education accredited by a recognized regional accrediting association or approved by the commissioner and, if applicable, has passed the examination or examinations required by (i) of this section. However, this subsection is not applicable to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-020__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>persons employed in the state public school system on September 1, 1962;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-020__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>persons issued an emergency certificate during a situation that, in the judgment of the commissioner, requires the temporary issuance of a certificate to a person not otherwise qualified.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-020__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board may establish by regulation additional requirements for the issuance of certificates. The board shall require teachers to submit fingerprints and the fees required by the Department of Public Safety under
AS 12.62.160
for criminal justice information and a national criminal history record check. The board shall submit the fingerprints and fees to the Department of Public Safety for a report of criminal justice information under
AS 12.62
and a national criminal history record check under
AS 12.62.400
. The department shall establish by regulation the fees to be charged for each certificate and for other charges assessed against teachers as part of certification. In establishing the fees to be charged, the department shall establish the fee levels so that the total amount of the fees collected relating to the certification of teachers approximately equals, when added to the other fees collected from teachers, the actual regulatory costs for certifying and disciplining teachers in the state. The department shall annually review each fee level to determine whether the regulatory costs are approximately equal to fee collections. If the review indicates that fee collections and regulatory costs are not approximately equal, the department shall calculate fee adjustments to the fees for certification of teachers and adopt regulations under this subsection to implement the adjustments. In January of each year, the department shall report on all fee levels and revisions for the previous year under this subsection to the office of management and budget. The department shall consider the board's recommendations concerning the fee levels and regulatory costs before revising fee schedules to comply with this subsection. In this subsection, regulatory costs means costs of the department that are attributable to regulation of the teaching profession, including the portion of the expenses of the board that are attributable to the regulation of the teaching profession and</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-020__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board may by regulation establish various classes of certificates.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-020__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 1 ch 36 SLA 2024].</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-020__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may not issue a teacher certificate to a person who has been convicted of a crime, or an attempt, solicitation, or conspiracy to commit a crime, involving a minor under
AS 11.41.410
 11.41.460 or a law or ordinance in another jurisdiction with elements similar to an offense described in this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-020__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 1 ch 36 SLA 2024].</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-020__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in
AS 14.20.015
, a person is not eligible for a teacher certificate unless the person has completed three semester hours in Alaska studies and three semester hours in multicultural education or cross-cultural communications. However, the commissioner may issue a provisional certificate, valid for no longer than two years, to an applicant who has not completed the semester hours required under this subsection at the time of application.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-020__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person is not eligible for an initial regular teacher certificate unless the person has taken and successfully completed a competency examination or examinations designated, at the time the person took the test, by the board. The board shall review nationally recognized examinations that are designed to test the competency of new teachers and shall designate those examinations that it finds adequately test the skills and abilities of new teachers. For each examination designated under this subsection, the board shall establish the minimum acceptable level of performance, including a passing score. The board shall reevaluate the passing score for a competency examination at least once every five years and shall review each examination designated by the board at least once every three years. The board shall prioritize the review of those examinations for which the minimum passing score deviates the most from the mean passing score adopted by other jurisdictions. When reevaluating a passing score for a competency examination, the board shall consider the historical effect of the established passing score, the potential effect of changing the passing score, and the passing score currently used for the examination by other jurisdictions. The board may allow a teacher who passed a comparable competency examination required by another jurisdiction to use a score from the other jurisdiction to satisfy the competency examination requirements under this subsection. The board shall adopt regulations to implement this subsection. A regulation that changes the passing score on a competency examination takes effect on the date that is one year after the date the board adopts the regulation, or a later date prescribed by the board. In this subsection, competency examination includes a basic competency examination with components in reading, writing, and mathematics and a subject area examination that is specific to the subject area in which the teacher will be teaching.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-020__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Whenever required by a provision of this chapter to submit fingerprints to use for a criminal background check for the purpose of determining a person's suitability for employment as a teacher, the department shall accept a name-based criminal history background check on a person from the agency performing the background check if the</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-020__subsec_j__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>person cannot submit legible fingerprint cards due to a permanent disability that precludes the person's ability to submit fingerprints; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-020__subsec_j__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>agency informs the department that its examination of at least two separate sets of fingerprint cards shows that the person's fingerprints are illegible due to a permanent skin condition.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-020__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in
AS 14.20.015
,  a person is not eligible for a teacher certificate unless the person has completed training regarding alcohol and drug related disabilities required under
AS 14.20.680
, training regarding sexual abuse and sexual assault awareness and prevention required under
AS 14.30.355
, training regarding dating violence and abuse awareness and prevention required under
AS 14.30.356
, and training related to suicide prevention required under
AS 14.30.362
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-020__subsec_l">
              <num>(l)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before teaching students in grades kindergarten through three, a teacher certificated under this section must complete coursework, training, or testing requirements in phonemic awareness, phonics, vocabulary development, reading fluency, oral language skills, and reading comprehension approved by the board in regulation. A teacher may apply coursework, training, or testing requirements completed under this subsection toward continuing education requirements established by the board in regulation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-022">
            <num>14.20.022</num>
            <heading>Subject-matter expert limited teacher certificate.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-20-022__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding
AS 14.20.020
, a person may be issued a subject-matter expert limited teacher certificate, valid only in the subject-matter in which the person has expertise, upon compliance with the requirements of this section. A subject-matter expert teacher may only be employed to teach subjects in which the person has satisfied the education or experience requirements set out in (b)(1) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-022__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To be eligible for a subject-matter expert limited teacher certificate, a person shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-022__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>hold at least a baccalaureate degree from an institution of higher education accredited by a recognized regional or national accrediting association or approved by the commissioner and
(A) have majored or minored in the subject that the person will be teaching; or
(B) have at least five years experience in the subject matter that the person will be teaching;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-022__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>have submitted fingerprints and the fees required by the Department of Public Safety under
AS 12.62.160
for criminal justice information and a national criminal history record check to the department; the department must have submitted the fingerprints and fees to the Department of Public Safety for a report of criminal justice information under
AS 12.62
and a national criminal history record check under
AS 12.62.400
and the person must have been found by the department to be suitable for employment as a teacher under
AS 14.20.020</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-022__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>be currently enrolled in an approved post-baccalaureate teacher education program at a regionally accredited institution meeting the requirements of
AS 14.20.020</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-022__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>that provides for completion of the regular teacher certificate education requirements within two years after receipt of a subject-matter expert limited teacher certificate under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-022__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before a school district or regional educational attendance area determines whether to hire a person as a subject-matter expert teacher under this section, the school district or regional educational attendance area shall administer a competency examination.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-022__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A subject-matter expert limited teacher certificate is valid for one school year and may be renewed for one additional school year upon a showing of substantial progress towards completion of the teacher education program required under (b)(3) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-022__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A school district or regional educational attendance area that employs a subject-matter expert teacher shall provide a mentor who is an experienced teacher for the subject-matter expert teacher for at least the first year of the subject-matter expert teacher's employment in the school district or regional educational attendance area.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-022__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person employed as a subject-matter expert teacher under this section is considered a certificated employee for purposes of
AS 14.25
(teachers' retirement system). Employment as a subject-matter expert teacher under this section counts as employment for purposes of acquiring tenure under
AS 14.20.150
; however, a person holding a subject-matter expert limited teacher certificate under this section is not entitled to tenure until the person receives a teacher certificate under
AS 14.20.020
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-022__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall adopt regulations necessary to implement this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-022__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, subject-matter expert teacher is a teacher qualified to teach under (b) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-023">
            <num>14.20.023</num>
            <heading>Limited language immersion teacher certificates.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-20-023__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding
AS 14.20.020
(b), the department may issue a limited language immersion teacher certificate, valid only in the area of expertise for which it is issued, to a person qualified under (b) of this section to teach any subject if the language of instruction is not English and the instruction is provided only to students who are enrolled in a language immersion program.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-023__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may apply for a limited language immersion teacher certificate under this section if the person is the subject of a request made under (c) of this section and demonstrates, as required by regulations adopted by the board, instructional skills and subject matter expertise sufficient to assure the public that the person is competent as a teacher. The board may require a person issued a limited language immersion teacher certificate under this section to undertake academic training as may be required by the board by regulation and make satisfactory progress in the academic training.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-023__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may issue a limited language immersion teacher certificate under this section if the school board of the district or regional educational attendance area in which an applicant for a limited language immersion teacher certificate will be teaching submits a request to the department for the limited language immersion teacher certificate to be issued to the applicant. A request for a limited language immersion teacher certificate under this section must specify the school district or regional educational attendance area, subject, and instructional language for which the certificate is valid.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-023__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board may adopt regulations necessary to implement this section. The regulations may not require an applicant for a limited language immersion teacher certificate under this section to achieve a minimum score on an examination unless the examination is given in the instructional language for which the certificate is valid.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-023__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A limited language immersion teacher certificate issued under this section is initially valid for one year. The department may, in accordance with regulations adopted by the board, extend or renew a limited language immersion teacher certificate issued to a person under this section if the school board of the district or regional educational attendance area in which the person is or will be teaching requests that the certificate be extended or renewed and certifies that the person has demonstrated skills in classroom instruction and student assessment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-025">
            <num>14.20.025</num>
            <heading>Limited teacher certificates.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.20.025.   Limited teacher certificates.
Notwithstanding
AS 14.20.020
(b), a person may be issued a limited certificate, valid only in the area of expertise for which it is issued, to teach Alaska Native language or culture, military science, or a vocational or technical course for which the board determines by regulation that baccalaureate degree training is not sufficiently available. A limited certificate may be issued under this section only if the school board of the district or regional educational attendance area in which the person will be teaching has requested its issuance. A person who applies for a limited certificate shall demonstrate, as required by regulations adopted by the board, instructional skills and subject matter expertise sufficient to ensure the public that the person is competent as a teacher. The board may require a person issued a limited certificate to undertake academic training as may be required by the board by regulation and make satisfactory progress in the academic training.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-027">
            <num>14.20.027</num>
            <heading>Reporting of and access to social security numbers.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.20.027.   Reporting of and access to social security numbers.
Notwithstanding
AS 14.20.010
 14.20.040, the department may not issue a teacher certificate under
AS 14.20.020
or a limited teacher certificate under
AS 14.20.025
unless the applicant has supplied the department with the applicant's social security number. Upon request, the department shall provide the social security number to the child support services agency created in
AS 25.27.010
, or the child support enforcement agency of another state, for child support purposes authorized under law.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-030">
            <num>14.20.030</num>
            <heading>Causes for revocation and suspension.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-20-030__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner or the Professional Teaching Practices Commission may revoke or suspend a certificate only for the following reasons:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-030__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>incompetency, which is defined as the inability or the unintentional or intentional failure to perform the teacher's customary teaching duties in a satisfactory manner;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-030__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>immorality, which is defined as the commission of an act which, under the laws of the state, constitutes a crime involving moral turpitude;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-030__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>substantial noncompliance with the school laws of the state or the regulations of the department; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-030__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>upon a determination by the Professional Teaching Practices Commission that there has been a violation of ethical or professional standards or contractual obligations.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-030__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner or the Professional Teaching Practices Commission shall revoke for life the certificate of a person who has been convicted of a crime, or an attempt, solicitation, or conspiracy to commit a crime, involving a minor under
AS 11.41.410
 11.41.460,
AS 11.61.125
, or 11.61.127, or a law or ordinance in another jurisdiction with elements similar to an offense described in this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-030__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner or the Professional Teaching Practices Commission shall request the chief administrative law judge (
AS 44.64.020
), to appoint an administrative law judge employed by the office of administrative hearings to preside at a hearing conducted under this section.
AS 44.64.060
and 44.64.070 do not apply to the hearing.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-035">
            <num>14.20.035</num>
            <heading>Evaluation of training and experience.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.20.035.   Evaluation of training and experience.
In evaluating an applicant for a position in a district or regional educational attendance area, a district or regional educational attendance area shall give preference to those applicants who demonstrate training or experience that establishes that the applicant is likely to be sensitive to the traditions and culture of the cultural backgrounds represented in the student population.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-040">
            <num>14.20.040</num>
            <heading>Applicability of the Administrative Procedure Act.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.20.040.   Applicability of the Administrative Procedure Act.
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act) applies to all proceedings under
AS 14.20.030
, and revocations and suspensions are final and reviewable in accordance with
AS 44.62.560
 44.62.570.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-095">
            <num>14.20.095</num>
            <heading>Right to comment and criticize not to be restricted.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.20.095.   Right to comment and criticize not to be restricted.
A bylaw or regulation of the commissioner, a school board, or local school administrator may not restrict or modify the right of a teacher to engage in comment and criticism outside school hours, regarding school personnel, members of the governing body of any school or school district, any other public official, or any school employee, to the same extent that any private individual may exercise the right.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-097">
            <num>14.20.097</num>
            <heading>Duty-free time.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.20.097.   Duty-free time.
Each governing body shall allow its teachers in school facilities with four or more teachers a daily duty-free mealtime of at least 30 minutes reasonably scheduled during the middle of the teacher's workday.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-100">
            <num>14.20.100</num>
            <heading>Unlawful to require statement of religious or political affiliation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.20.100.   Unlawful to require statement of religious or political affiliation.
A school board, or a member of a school board, may not require or compel a person applying for the position of teacher in the public schools of the state to state a religious or political affiliation.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-110">
            <num>14.20.110</num>
            <heading>Penalty for violation ofAS 14.20.100.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.20.110.   Penalty for violation of
AS 14.20.100
.
A person violating
AS 14.20.100
is punishable by a fine of not more than $100.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-120">
            <num>14.20.120</num>
            <heading>Statement of qualifications.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.20.120.   Statement of qualifications.
A statement of the qualifications of each teacher and superintendent employed by the state or a school district shall be filed with the commissioner.  The statement must contain the credits earned in college, normal school, or university, and the number of years of teaching experience both in the state and elsewhere in the form and manner prescribed by the commissioner.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-130">
            <num>14.20.130</num>
            <heading>Employment contracts.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.20.130.   Employment contracts.
An employer may, after January 1, issue contracts for the following school year to employees regularly qualified in accordance with the regulations of the department.  The contract for a superintendent may be for more than one school year but may not exceed three consecutive school years.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-136">
            <num>14.20.136</num>
            <heading>Reemployment of member of teachers' retirement system.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-20-136__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subject to (b)  (d) of this section, a school district may reemploy a member who is retired under a retirement plan established in
AS 14.25.009
 14.25.220, or a member who is retired under a retirement plan established in
AS 14.25.310
 14.25.590. In this subsection, school district has the meaning given in
AS 14.30.350
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-136__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A member who is retired under
AS 14.25.110</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-136__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>may not be reemployed under (a) of this section unless the member</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-136__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>certifies that the member and the school district did not arrange before the member retired from the school district for the member to be reemployed by the school district after the member retired; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-136__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has been retired for at least
(A) 60 days if the member is at least 62 years of age; or
(B) six months if the member is less than 62 years of age.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-136__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before reemploying a retired member under (a) of this section to fill a position, a school district shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-136__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>by resolution, adopt a policy that describes the circumstances of a shortage or anticipated shortage of applicants, other than retired members, who are qualified for particular positions and permits rehiring that complies with the requirements of this section; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-136__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>publicly advertise the position for 10 business days and actively recruit to fill the position by hiring a person other than a member who is retired.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-136__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A contract for reemployment under (a) of this section may not exceed 12 consecutive months.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-136__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A school district that reemploys a member under this section who is retired under the defined benefit retirement plan established in
AS 14.25.009
 14.25.220 is required to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-136__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide the administrator with
(A) a copy of the resolution and policy adopted under (c) of this section; and
(B) for every retired member who is rehired, a report identifying the member by name and describing the</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-136__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>circumstances of the shortage that necessitated the rehire; and
(ii) actions taken by the school district to comply with school district policy adopted under (c) of this section and the requirements of this section; and</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-136__subsec_i__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>make contributions under
AS 14.25.070
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-136__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The requirements of (c), (d), and (e)(1) of this section do not apply to the rehire of a member who is eligible for restoration of tenure rights under
AS 14.20.165
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-140">
            <num>14.20.140</num>
            <heading>Notification of lay off or nonretention.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-20-140__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a teacher who has acquired tenure rights is to be laid off under
AS 14.20.177
or is not to be retained for the following school year, the employer shall notify the teacher of the layoff or nonretention by writing, delivered before May 15, or by registered mail postmarked before May 15.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-140__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a teacher who has not acquired tenure rights is to be laid off under
AS 14.20.177
or is not to be retained for the following school year the employer shall notify the teacher of the layoff or nonretention by writing delivered on or before the last day of the school term or by registered mail postmarked on or before the last day of the school term.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-140__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding a teacher's right to continued employment under
AS 39.20.500
 39.20.550, a school district may notify a teacher of layoff or nonretention under this section for the following school year for a permissible reason.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-145">
            <num>14.20.145</num>
            <heading>Automatic reemployment.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.20.145.   Automatic reemployment.
If notification of nonretention or layoff is not given according to
AS 14.20.140
, a teacher is entitled to be reemployed in the same district for the following school year on the contract terms the teacher and the employer may agree upon, or, if no terms are agreed upon, the provisions of the previous contract are continued for the following school year, subject to
AS 14.20.158
. Except as provided in
AS 14.20.177
(e), the right to automatic reemployment under this section expires if the teacher does not accept reemployment within 30 days after the date on which the teacher receives a contract of reemployment. A teacher who is on family leave under
AS 39.20.500
 39.20.550 must comply with the 30-day deadline in this section to retain the teacher's reemployment rights under this section.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-147">
            <num>14.20.147</num>
            <heading>Transfer or absorption of attendance area and teachers.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-20-147__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When an attendance area is transferred from a currently operating district to, or absorbed into, a new or existing school district, the teachers for the attendance area also shall be transferred unless otherwise mutually agreed by the teacher or teachers and the chief school administrator of the new district if the district employs a chief school administrator. Accumulated or earned benefits, including seniority, salary level, tenure, leave, and retirement, accompany the teacher who is transferred.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-147__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 48 ch 15 SLA 2014.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-147__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>On the first day of service in the absorbing school district, a teacher transferred from a federal agency school shall be allowed the actual number of days of accumulated sick leave that the teacher has earned while teaching in the state. Consistent with the established district policy the absorbing district may allow credit for any other type of leave.  Credit for retirement shall be allowed in accordance with
AS 14.25.060
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-148">
            <num>14.20.148</num>
            <heading>Intradistrict teacher reassignments.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.20.148.   Intradistrict teacher reassignments.
When a teacher is involuntarily transferred or reassigned to a position for which the teacher is qualified, within the district, the teacher's moving expenses shall be paid unless the one-way driving distance is 20 miles or less from the teacher's present place of residence, or unless otherwise mutually agreed by the teacher and chief school administrator of the district if the district employs a chief school administrator.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-149">
            <num>14.20.149</num>
            <heading>Employee evaluation.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-20-149__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A school board shall adopt a certificated employee evaluation system for evaluation and improvement of the performance of the district's teachers and administrators. The evaluation system applies to all the district's certificated employees except the district's superintendent. A school board shall consider information from students, parents, community members, classroom teachers, affected collective bargaining units, and administrators in the design and periodic review of the district's certificated employee evaluation system. An evaluation of a certificated employee under this section must be based on observation of the employee in the employee's workplace.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-149__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The certificated employee evaluation system must</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-149__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establish district performance standards for the district's teachers and administrators that are based on professional performance standards adopted by the department by regulation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-149__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>require at least two observations for the evaluation of each nontenured teacher in the district each school year;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-149__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>require at least an annual evaluation of each tenured teacher in the district who met the district performance standards during the previous school year;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-149__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>permit the district to limit its evaluations of tenured teachers who have consistently exceeded the district performance standards to one evaluation every two school years;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-149__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>require the school district to perform an annual evaluation for each administrator;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-149__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>require the school district to prepare and implement a plan of improvement for a teacher or administrator whose performance did not meet the district performance standards, except if the teacher's or administrator's performance warrants immediate dismissal under
AS 14.20.170</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-149__subsec_b__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide an opportunity for students, parents, community members, teachers, and administrators to provide information on the performance of the teacher or administrator who is the subject of the evaluation to the evaluating administrator.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-149__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not conduct an evaluation under this section unless the person holds a type B certificate or is a site administrator under the supervision of a person with a type B certificate, is employed by the school district as an administrator, and has completed training in the use of the school district's teacher evaluation system.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-149__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A school district shall offer in-service training to the certificated employees who are subject to the evaluation system on a schedule adopted by the governing body of a school district. The training must address the procedures of the evaluation system, the standards that the district uses in evaluating the performance of teachers and administrators, and other information that the district considers helpful.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-149__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A school district shall provide a tenured teacher whose performance, after evaluation, did not meet the district performance standards with a plan of improvement. The evaluating administrator shall consult with the tenured teacher in setting clear, specific performance expectations to be included in the plan of improvement. The plan of improvement must address ways in which the tenured teacher's performance can be improved and shall last for not less than 90 workdays and not more than 180 workdays unless the minimum time is shortened by agreement between the evaluating administrator and the teacher. The plan of improvement shall be based on the professional performance standards outlined in the locally adopted school district evaluation procedure. The school district must observe the teacher at least twice during the course of the plan. If, at the conclusion of the plan of improvement, the tenured teacher's performance again does not meet the district performance standards, the district may nonretain the teacher under
AS 14.20.175
(b)(1).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-149__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A school district may place an administrator who has previously acquired tenure, whose performance, including performance as an evaluator under the district's certificated employee evaluation system, does not meet the district performance standards on a plan of improvement. The plan must address ways in which the administrator's performance can be improved and shall last for not less than 90 workdays and not more than 210 workdays unless the minimum time is shortened by agreement between the evaluating administrator and the administrator being evaluated. The school district must observe the administrator being evaluated at least twice during the course of the plan. If, at the conclusion of the plan of improvement, the administrator's performance again does not meet the district performance standards, the district may terminate its employment contract with the administrator. This subsection does not restrict the right of a school district to reassign an administrator to a teaching position consistent with the terms of an applicable collective bargaining agreement.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-149__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may request copies of each school district's certificated employee evaluation system and changes the district makes to the system.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-149__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Information provided to a school district under the school district's certificated employee evaluation system concerning the performance of an individual being evaluated under the system is not a public record and is not subject to disclosure under
AS 40.25.100
 40.25.295. However, the individual who is the subject of the evaluation is entitled to a copy of the information and may waive the confidentiality provisions of this subsection concerning the information.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-150">
            <num>14.20.150</num>
            <heading>Acquisition and reacquisition of tenure rights.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-20-150__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (c) or (d) of this section, a teacher acquires tenure rights in a district when the teacher</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-150__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>possesses a valid teaching certificate that authorizes the teacher to be employed as a certificated teacher or as an administrator under regulations adopted by the department;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-150__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has been employed as a teacher in the same district continuously for three full school years;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-150__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>receives, in the third year of any three-year period of continuous employment with the district, an evaluation under the district's evaluation system stating that the teacher's performance meets the district performance standards; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-150__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>on or before October 15 of the school year,
(A) accepts a contract for employment as a teacher in the district for a fourth consecutive school year; and
(B) performs a day of teaching services in the district during that school year.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-150__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, a full school year of employment means employment that begins on or before the first student count day required by the department in a school year or October 15, whichever occurs first, and continues through the remainder of the school year.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-150__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A superintendent may not acquire or maintain tenure in a district.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-150__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A teacher who has acquired tenure in a school district in the state and who loses tenure in the district because of a break in service may reacquire tenure in that school district under this subsection if the break in service was not the result of a dismissal under
AS 14.20.170
or nonretention under
AS 14.20.175
and did not last longer than one year. A break in service that begins on or after the last day of a school district's instructional days for a school year but before the first instructional day of the next school year will be considered to have lasted no longer than one year if the teacher is employed on the first instructional day of the school year that begins more than 12 but not more than 16 months after the beginning of the break in service. A previously tenured teacher reacquires tenure in the school district under this subsection when the teacher</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-150__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>possesses a valid teaching certificate that authorizes the teacher to be employed as a certificated teacher or as an administrator under regulations adopted by the department;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-150__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has been employed as a teacher in the district continuously for one full school year after a break in service that does not exceed the time limits set out in this subsection;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-150__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>receives, under the district's evaluation system, an acceptable evaluation from the district; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-150__subsec_d__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>on or before October 15 of the school year,
(A) accepts a contract for employment as a teacher in the district for a second consecutive school year; and
(B) performs a day of teaching services in the district during that school year.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-150__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (a) of this section, a teacher who has acquired tenure in a school district who moves to a new school district acquires tenure in the new school district on the first instructional day of the third year of employment in the new school district if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-150__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the teacher otherwise meets the qualifications for tenure set out in (a) of this section; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-150__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the break in service meets the requirements of (d) of this section.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-155">
            <num>14.20.155</num>
            <heading>Effect of tenure rights.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-20-155__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as otherwise provided in this chapter, a teacher who has acquired tenure rights has the right to employment within the district during continuous service.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-155__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A teacher who has acquired tenure rights may agree to a new contract at any time.  However, if the teacher fails to agree to a new contract, the provisions of the previous contract are continued subject to
AS 14.20.158
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-158">
            <num>14.20.158</num>
            <heading>Continued contract provisions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.20.158.   Continued contract provisions.
Continuation of the provisions of a teacher's contract under
AS 14.20.145
or 14.20.155 does not
(1) affect the alteration of the teacher's salary in accordance with the salary schedule prescribed by state law, or in accordance with a local salary schedule applicable to all teachers in the district and adopted by bylaws;
(2) limit the right of the employer to assign the teacher to any teaching, administrative, or counseling position for which the teacher is qualified; or
(3) limit the right of the employer to assign the teacher, as is reasonably necessary, to any school in the district.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-160">
            <num>14.20.160</num>
            <heading>Loss of tenure rights.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.20.160.   Loss of tenure rights.
Tenure rights are lost when the teacher's employment in the district is interrupted or terminated. However, a teacher on layoff status does not lose tenure rights during the period of layoff except as provided under
AS 14.20.177
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-165">
            <num>14.20.165</num>
            <heading>Restoration of tenure rights.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.20.165.   Restoration of tenure rights.
A teacher who held tenure rights and who was retired due to disability under
AS 14.25.130
, but whose disability (1) has been removed, and the removal of that disability is certified by a competent physician following a physical or mental examination, or (2) has been compensated for by rehabilitation or other appropriate restorative education or training, and that rehabilitation or restoration to health has been certified by the division of vocational rehabilitation of the Department of Labor and Workforce Development, shall be restored to full tenure rights in the district from which the teacher was retired, at such time as an opening for which the teacher is qualified becomes available.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-170">
            <num>14.20.170</num>
            <heading>Dismissal.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-20-170__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A teacher, including a teacher who has acquired tenure rights, may be dismissed at any time only for the following causes:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-170__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>incompetency, which is defined as the inability or the unintentional or intentional failure to perform the teacher's customary teaching duties in a satisfactory manner;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-170__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>immorality, which is defined as the commission of an act that, under the laws of the state, constitutes a crime involving moral turpitude; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-170__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>substantial noncompliance with the school laws of the state, the regulations or bylaws of the department, the bylaws of the district, or the written rules of the superintendent.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-170__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A teacher may be suspended temporarily with regular compensation during a period of investigation to determine whether or not cause exists for the issuance of a notification of dismissal according to
AS 14.20.180
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-170__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A teacher who is dismissed under this section is not entitled to a plan of improvement under
AS 14.20.149
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-175">
            <num>14.20.175</num>
            <heading>Nonretention.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-20-175__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A teacher who has not acquired tenure rights is subject to nonretention for the school year following the expiration of the teacher's contract for any cause that the employer determines to be adequate.  However, at the teacher's request, the teacher is entitled to a written statement of the cause for nonretention.  The boards of city and borough school districts and regional educational attendance areas shall provide by regulation or bylaw a procedure under which a nonretained teacher may request and receive an informal hearing by the board.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-175__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A teacher who has acquired tenure rights is subject to nonretention for the following school year only for the following causes:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-175__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the school district demonstrates that
(A) the district has fully complied with the requirements of
AS 14.20.149
with respect to the tenured teacher;
(B) the teacher's performance, after completion of the plan of improvement, failed to meet the performance objectives set out in the plan; and
(C) the evaluation of the teacher established that the teacher does not meet the district performance standards;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-175__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>immorality, which is defined as the commission of an act that, under the laws of the state, constitutes a crime involving moral turpitude; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-175__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>substantial noncompliance with the school laws of the state, the regulations or bylaws of the department, the bylaws of the district, or the written rules of the superintendent.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-177">
            <num>14.20.177</num>
            <heading>Reductions in force.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-20-177__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A school district may implement a layoff plan under this section if it is necessary for the district to reduce the number of tenured teachers because</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-177__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>school attendance in the district has decreased; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-177__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the basic need of the school district determined under
AS 14.17.410</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-177__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before a school district lays off any tenured teacher, the school board shall adopt a layoff plan. The plan must identify academic and other programs that the district intends to maintain in implementing the layoff plan. The plan must also include procedures for layoff and recall of tenured teachers consistent with this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-177__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in this subsection, a school district may place a tenured teacher on layoff status only after the district has given notice of nonretention to all nontenured teachers. However, a school district may retain a nontenured teacher and place on layoff status a tenured teacher if there is no tenured teacher in the district who is qualified to replace the nontenured teacher. The school district shall comply with the notice requirements set out in
AS 14.20.140
in placing a tenured or nontenured teacher on layoff status.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-177__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of this section, a tenured teacher is considered qualified for a position if the position is in</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-177__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>grades K  8 and the teacher has an elementary endorsement;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-177__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an established middle school and the teacher has
(A) an elementary endorsement;
(B) a middle school endorsement; or
(C) a secondary certificate with a subject area endorsement in the area of assignment in which the teacher filling the position will spend at least 40 percent of the teacher's time or the teacher has, within the five years immediately preceding the last date on which the teacher performed teaching services in the district before being laid off, received an evaluation stating that the teacher's performance in the subject or subjects meets the district performance standards; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-177__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>grades 9  12 and the teacher has an endorsement for each subject area in which the teacher filling the position will spend at least 40 percent of the teacher's time or the teacher has, within the five years immediately preceding the last date on which the teacher performed teaching services in the district before being laid off, received an evaluation stating that the teacher's performance in the subject or subjects meets the district performance standards.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-177__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For a period of three years after layoff, a teacher is on layoff status and is entitled to a hiring preference in the district where the teacher had been employed. The hiring preference applies only to vacant teaching positions for which the teacher is qualified. If a teacher is offered a teaching position under this subsection and the teacher declines the offer or fails to accept it within 30 days, the teacher is no longer considered to be on layoff status and is no longer entitled to a hiring preference under this section unless the teacher declines the offer because the teacher is contractually obligated to provide professional services to another private or public educational program.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-177__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding any provision of
AS 23.40
, the terms of a collective bargaining agreement entered into between a school district and a bargaining organization representing teachers on or after August 16, 1996, may not be in conflict with the provisions of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-177__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A teacher on layoff status is not entitled to be reemployed under
AS 14.20.145
and does not accrue leave. However, layoff status does not constitute a break in service for retaining tenure rights and accrued sick leave.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-177__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, school district or district means a city or borough school district or a regional educational attendance area.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-180">
            <num>14.20.180</num>
            <heading>Procedures upon notice of dismissal or nonretention.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-20-180__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before a teacher is dismissed, the employer shall give the teacher written notice of the proposed dismissal and a pretermination hearing. A pretermination hearing under this section must comport with the minimum requirements of due process, including an explanation of the employer's evidence and basis for the proposed dismissal and an opportunity for the teacher to respond. If, following a pretermination hearing, an employer determines that dismissal is appropriate, the employer shall provide written notice, including a statement of cause and a complete bill of particulars, of the decision. The dismissal is effective when the notice is delivered to the teacher.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-180__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An employer that has decided to nonretain a tenured teacher shall provide the teacher with written notice, including a statement of cause and a complete bill of particulars. The notice must comply with
AS 14.20.140
(a).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-180__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Within 15 days after receipt of a decision of dismissal under (a) of this section or nonretention under (b) of this section, a teacher may notify the employer in writing that the teacher is requesting a hearing before the school board under (d) of this section or that the teacher is invoking the grievance procedures under (e) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-180__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon receipt of a request for a hearing, the employer shall immediately schedule a hearing and notify the teacher in writing of the date, time, and place of the hearing. The teacher may elect to have either a public or a private hearing, and to have the hearing under oath or affirmation. The parties have a right to be represented by counsel and to cross-examine witnesses. The teacher has the right to subpoena a person who has made statements that are used as a basis for the employer's decision to dismiss or nonretain. A written transcript, tape, or similar recording of the proceedings shall be kept. A copy of the recording shall be furnished to the teacher, for cost, upon request of the teacher. A decision of the school board requires a majority vote of the membership, by roll call. The board's decision shall be in writing and must contain specific findings of fact and conclusions of law. A copy of the decision shall be furnished to the teacher within 10 days after the date of the decision. If the school board sustains the dismissal or nonretention, the teacher may appeal the decision to the superior court for judicial review based on the administrative record.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-180__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon receipt of a notice invoking the grievance procedures, the school board shall immediately schedule an informal hearing and notify the teacher in writing of the date, time, and place of the hearing. The hearing is for the purpose of reviewing the statement of cause and bill of particulars and not for the purpose of taking evidence. The teacher may choose whether the informal hearing is held in public or in private. A decision of the school board requires a majority vote of the membership, by roll call. The board's decision shall be in writing. The board shall promptly furnish a copy of the decision to the teacher. If the board sustains the dismissal or nonretention, the teacher may, within 15 days after receipt of the decision, give written notice to the school board and submit the matter to arbitration under the rules of the American Arbitration Association. The decision of the arbitrator is final and binding on the school board, the teacher, and the bargaining organization representing the teacher, if any. If the school board and the teacher agree, they may waive the informal hearing under this subsection and submit the matter directly to arbitration.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-210">
            <num>14.20.210</num>
            <heading>Authority of school board or department to adopt bylaws.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.20.210.   Authority of school board or department to adopt bylaws.
A school board or the department may adopt teacher tenure bylaws not in conflict with the regulations of the department or state law.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-215">
            <num>14.20.215</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.20.215.   Definitions.
In
AS 14.20.010
 14.20.215,
(1) continuous employment means employment that is without interruption except for temporary absences approved by the employer or its designee, or except for the interval between consecutive school terms if the teacher is employed only for the months of the school term;
(2) dismissal means termination by the employer of the contract services of the teacher during the time a teacher's contract is in force, and termination of the right to the balance of the compensation due the teacher under the contract;
(3) district performance standards means evaluation criteria for the district's teachers and administrators that are adopted by a school district under
AS 14.20.149
and that are based on the professional performance standards adopted by the department;
(4) employer means the school board or superintendent that appoints the teacher;
(5) nonretention means the election by an employer not to reemploy a teacher for the school year or school term immediately following the expiration of the teacher's current contract;
(6) school year includes school term if the teacher is employed only for the period of the school term;
(7) teacher means an individual who, for compensation, has primary responsibility to plan, instruct, and evaluate learning of elementary or secondary school students in the classroom or an equivalent setting and also includes individuals holding other positions as determined by the department by regulation.
Article 3. Salary Scales.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-220">
            <num>14.20.220</num>
            <heading>School experience for salary scales.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.20.220.   School experience for salary scales.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-220">
            <num>14.20.220</num>
            <heading>School experience for salary scales.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.20.220.   School experience for salary scales.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-225">
            <num>14.20.225</num>
            <heading>Teacher incentive payments and reimbursement of costs relating to national board certification.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-20-225__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In January of each year, a district or the department, as applicable, may pay an incentive payment of $5,000 to each teacher who is employed by the district or the department and who holds a current and valid national board certification.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-225__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A district or the department, as applicable, shall reimburse each teacher who is employed by the district or the department and who is pursuing an initial national board certification or renewal of a national board certification for the costs the teacher has paid to a nationally recognized board in pursuing or renewing the certification, including the costs of course materials, registration, and testing. The district or the department, as applicable, shall reimburse the teacher on an ongoing basis for the costs incurred by the teacher and not later than 60 days after the teacher makes a request for reimbursement.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-225__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall provide sufficient funding, subject to appropriation and in addition to the state aid received under
AS 14.17
, to a district to make national board certification incentive and reimbursement payments as provided in this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-225__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing in this section prohibits a district or the department from providing additional monetary incentives to a teacher.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-225__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-225__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>district has the meaning given in
AS 14.17.990
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-225__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>national board certification means individual achievement of national professional teaching standards as certified by a nationally recognized board.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-280">
            <num>14.20.280</num>
            <heading>Basis of leave.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.20.280.   Basis of leave.
A teacher who has rendered active service for seven or more years in a district is eligible for sabbatical leave. Sabbatical leave may be taken for educational purposes only, and for not more than one school year.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-290">
            <num>14.20.290</num>
            <heading>Application.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.20.290.   Application.
A teacher who wishes to take sabbatical leave shall apply to the governing body of the school district. The teacher shall submit information showing qualifications for sabbatical leave and a plan for education during the leave.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-300">
            <num>14.20.300</num>
            <heading>Selection of teachers.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-20-300__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The governing body of the school district has the responsibility for selection of the teachers to be granted sabbatical leave.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-300__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In selecting teachers for sabbatical leave, the governing body shall consider the benefit that the school district will derive from the proposed plan of the teacher for educational purposes, the field of study of the teacher, the contributions of the teacher to education in the state, and the seniority of the teacher.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-310">
            <num>14.20.310</num>
            <heading>Number of teachers on sabbatical leave; compensation.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-20-310__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The number of teachers eligible for sabbatical leave that may be allowed under
AS 14.20.280
 14.20.350 is as follows:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-310__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>not more than one-half of one percent of the total number of teachers from all borough and city school districts and regional educational attendance areas may be on state-supported sabbatical leave in any year;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-310__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>any number of teachers may be on sabbatical leave at school district or personal expense.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-310__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A teacher on state-supported sabbatical leave is entitled to one-half of base salary to be paid by the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-310__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A teacher on sabbatical leave at district expense is entitled to an amount of salary to be determined by the school board.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-320">
            <num>14.20.320</num>
            <heading>Responsibility of teacher.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.20.320.   Responsibility of teacher.
Upon the return of a teacher to the teaching position, the teacher shall make a report to the governing body concerning educational accomplishments.  A teacher who does not serve for at least a full year after returning shall refund to the school board money paid to the teacher under
AS 14.20.310
unless the failure to serve a full year after return is attributable to sickness, injury, or death.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-330">
            <num>14.20.330</num>
            <heading>Position, tenure, and retirement.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-20-330__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless it is otherwise agreed, a teacher returning from sabbatical leave shall return to the position occupied by that teacher when the sabbatical leave began.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-330__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A sabbatical leave is not an interruption of the continuous service necessary to attain or retain tenure under
AS 14.20.150
, 14.20.155, or 14.20.160. However, the time spent on sabbatical leave may not be counted in determining when a teacher has sufficient service to enable the teacher to acquire tenure rights.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-330__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A sabbatical leave is not a break in service for retirement purposes.  Payment into the retirement fund shall be made on the basis of full salary.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-340">
            <num>14.20.340</num>
            <heading>Military service and previous leaves of absence.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.20.340.   Military service and previous leaves of absence.
To determine eligibility for sabbatical leave, tours of military service and leaves of absence granted before July 1, 1963, are not considered years of active service.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-345">
            <num>14.20.345</num>
            <heading>Leave of absence without pay.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-20-345__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A teacher may be granted a leave of absence without pay for the purposes which may be approved by the governing body of the district if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-345__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the teacher's application is approved by the governing body of the district; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-345__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the teacher agrees to return to employment in a public school not later than the beginning of the school year following termination of the period for which the leave of absence was granted.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-345__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A leave of absence is not an interruption of the continuous service necessary to attain or retain retirement or tenure rights under
AS 14.20.150
, 14.20.155, or 14.20.160. However, the time spent on leave of absence may not be counted in determining when a teacher has sufficient service to enable the teacher to acquire retirement or tenure rights.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-345__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The leave of absence is not a break in service for retirement purposes.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-345__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The governing body of the district may agree to continue the teacher's retirement contributions if the teacher agrees to pay the percent required under
AS 14.25.050
of the salary the teacher would have received during the leave of absence and reimburse the district for the district's required retirement contribution. Each year of leave of absence then would count as a year of retirement service.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-345__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The governing body of the district may advance the teacher on the district salary schedule when the teacher returns to employment if the governing body determines that the teacher's leave of absence was educationally or professionally beneficial to the teacher or the district.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-345__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A teacher may make contributions to the retirement fund for each year or portion of a year of leave of absence taken.  The contribution shall include the required percent of the salary the teacher would have received had the leave of absence not been taken, plus the required employer and state contributions that would have been made.  Compound interest at the rate prescribed by regulation shall be added as computed from the beginning date of the leave of absence to the date the teacher pays the contribution.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-350">
            <num>14.20.350</num>
            <heading>Definition.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.20.350.   Definition.
In
AS 14.20.280
 14.20.350, teacher means a certificated member of the teaching, supervisory, or administrative corps in the public schools of the state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-370">
            <num>14.20.370</num>
            <heading>Teaching profession.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.20.370.   Teaching profession.
Teachers required by state law to be certificated, instructors in institutions of higher learning, school administrators, school program administrators, and school counselors are within the teaching profession.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-380">
            <num>14.20.380</num>
            <heading>Creation of a commission.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.20.380.   Creation of a commission.
There is a commission of professional educators known as the Professional Teaching Practices Commission.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-390">
            <num>14.20.390</num>
            <heading>Appointment and qualifications.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.20.390.   Appointment and qualifications.
The commission consists of nine members appointed by the governor and confirmed by a majority of the members of the legislature in joint session.  Each member, in addition to having been actively engaged in the teaching profession for at least five years immediately preceding appointment, shall be a citizen of the United States and a resident of the state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-400">
            <num>14.20.400</num>
            <heading>Composition of the commission.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.20.400.   Composition of the commission.
The commission consists of the following members:
(1) five classroom teachers;
(2) one principal;
(3) one superintendent;
(4) one representative of the office of the commissioner;
(5) one representative of an Alaska institution of higher learning.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-410">
            <num>14.20.410</num>
            <heading>Selection of members.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-20-410__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Members of the commission shall be selected as follows:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-410__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the five classroom teachers from lists of names submitted by recognized Alaska teachers' organizations, each list not to exceed 12 names; however, in lieu of one of the five, one classroom teacher may be selected from a list of not more than four names signed and submitted by not less than 25 teachers who have no affiliation with any organization qualified to submit nomination lists, with the limitation that no teacher may sign more than one list in any year;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-410__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the principal from a list of three names submitted by the Alaska Principals Association;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-410__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the superintendent from a list of three names submitted by the Superintendents Advisory Commission;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-410__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the representative of the office of the commissioner from a list of three names submitted by the commissioner;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-410__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the representative of an Alaska institution of higher learning from lists of names submitted by Alaska institutions of higher learning, each list not to exceed three names.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-410__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The lists shall be submitted to the commissioner who shall submit them as a group to the governor's office.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-410__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>At least 30 days before a position on the commission is due to become vacant, the chairman shall cause notice of the impending vacancy to be published and to be conveyed to each organized group eligible to submit a list of nominees.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-420">
            <num>14.20.420</num>
            <heading>Term of office.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-20-420__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The term of office for each member of the commission is three years and, except as provided in
AS 39.05.080</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-420__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Vacancies shall be filled by appointment by the governor and, except as provided in
AS 39.05.080</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-420__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An individual may not serve more than a total of two 3-year terms.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-420__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall select a chairman from among its members.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-430">
            <num>14.20.430</num>
            <heading>Dismissal.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.20.430.   Dismissal.
Any member may be removed by the governor for misconduct, malfeasance or nonfeasance in office, or incapacity.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-440">
            <num>14.20.440</num>
            <heading>Reimbursement.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.20.440.   Reimbursement.
Members of the commission shall receive per diem according to law and are to be granted administrative leave with full pay by their employer for time spent in the performance of official duties under
AS 14.20.370
 14.20.510.  If a member is required to spend more than 15 days in a fiscal year in the performance of official duties under
AS 14.20.370
 14.20.510, the state shall reimburse the employer for costs incurred after the 15th day.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-450">
            <num>14.20.450</num>
            <heading>Responsibilities of commission.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.20.450.   Responsibilities of commission.
The commission shall have the initial responsibility of developing, through the teaching profession, criteria of professional practices in areas including
(1) ethical and professional performance;
(2) preparation for and continuance in professional services; and
(3) contractual obligations.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-460">
            <num>14.20.460</num>
            <heading>Duties of commission.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.20.460.   Duties of commission.
The commission shall
(1) establish procedures, and adopt regulations to implement the purposes of
AS 14.20.370
 14.20.510;
(2) conduct investigations and hearings on alleged violations of ethical or professional teaching performance, contractual obligations, and professional teaching misconduct;
(3) review the regulations of the department as they relate to teacher certification and recommend necessary changes;
(4) review the decisions of the department regarding the issuance or denial of certificates and in its discretion recommend reversal of decisions.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-470">
            <num>14.20.470</num>
            <heading>Powers of commission.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-20-470__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission may</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-470__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>study proposals developed by regular committees of any existing professional organization whose members are within the teaching profession;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-470__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>subpoena witnesses, place them under oath, and maintain written records;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-470__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>warn or reprimand members of the teaching profession, if in the judgment of the commission such action is warranted;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-470__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>suspend or revoke the certificate of a member of the teaching profession for one of the reasons set out in
AS 14.20.030
except that in the case of an administrator, the commissioner must concur;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-470__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>make any recommendation to the board or to school boards that will promote an improvement in the teaching profession;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-470__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>request assistance through any of the investigative processes of any existing professional teaching organizations when analyzing charges of breach of ethical or professional teaching practices;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-20-470__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>appoint an executive secretary, delegate those ministerial functions to the executive secretary as the commission may decide and set the executive secretary's compensation with a starting salary not exceeding range 26, step B of the pay plan for state employees in
AS 39.27.011</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-470__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A decision issued by the commission with the approval of the commissioner under (a)(4) of this section is final.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-475">
            <num>14.20.475</num>
            <heading>Applicability of the Administrative Procedure Act.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.20.475.   Applicability of the Administrative Procedure Act.
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act) applies to regulations and proceedings under
AS 14.20.370
 14.20.510.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-480">
            <num>14.20.480</num>
            <heading>Effect of standards.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.20.480.   Effect of standards.
Members of the teaching profession are obligated to abide by the professional teaching standards adopted by the commission.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-500">
            <num>14.20.500</num>
            <heading>Support.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.20.500.   Support.
In addition to available state funds, the commission shall also be financed by members of the profession in accordance with regulations adopted by the department including, if necessary, an increase in the fees for certificates.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-510">
            <num>14.20.510</num>
            <heading>Short title.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.20.510.   Short title.
AS 14.20.370
 14.20.510 shall be known as the Professional Teaching Practices Act.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-620">
            <num>14.20.620</num>
            <heading>Entry into agreement.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.20.620.   Entry into agreement.
The interstate Agreement on Qualification of Educational Personnel is enacted into law and entered into in behalf of the State of Alaska with all other states and jurisdictions legally joining in it in a form substantially as contained in
AS 14.20.630
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-630">
            <num>14.20.630</num>
            <heading>Terms and provisions of agreement.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.20.630.   Terms and provisions of agreement.
The terms and provisions of the agreement referred to in
AS 14.20.620
are as follows:</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-640">
            <num>14.20.640</num>
            <heading>Designated state official to make contracts.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.20.640.   Designated state official to make contracts.
The designated state official to make contracts on behalf of the state under Article III of the agreement shall be the commissioner.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-650">
            <num>14.20.650</num>
            <heading>Filing and publishing of contracts.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.20.650.   Filing and publishing of contracts.
True copies of all contracts made on behalf of this state under the agreement shall be kept on file in the office of the commissioner and in the office of the lieutenant governor. The department shall publish all the contracts in convenient form.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-20-680">
            <num>14.20.680</num>
            <heading>Required alcohol and drug related disabilities training.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-20-680__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A school district or regional educational attendance area shall train each teacher, administrator, counselor, and specialist on the needs of individual students who have alcohol or drug related disabilities.  The training must utilize the best available educational technology and include an overview of medical and psychological characteristics associated with alcohol or drug related disabilities, family issues, and the specific educational needs of students with alcohol or drug related disabilities.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-20-680__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A school district or regional educational attendance area shall provide the training required under (a) of this section on a schedule adopted by the governing body of a school district or regional educational attendance area.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>