<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-13/chapter-65"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-13/chapter-65"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="13.65"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-13/chapter-65/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-13/chapter-65/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-13/chapter-65/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-13/chapter-65/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_13">
        <num>13</num>
        <heading>Decedents' Estates, Guardianships, Transfers, Trusts, and Health Care Decisions</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_13__chp_65">
          <num>65</num>
          <heading>Uniform Prudent Management of Institutional Funds</heading>
          <section eId="sec_13-65-010">
            <num>13.65.010</num>
            <heading>Standard of conduct in managing and investing institutional funds.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-65-010__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subject to the intent of a donor expressed in a gift instrument, an institution, in managing and investing an institutional fund, shall consider the charitable purposes of the institution and the purposes of the institutional fund.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-65-010__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to complying with the duty of loyalty imposed by law other than this chapter, each person responsible for managing and investing an institutional fund shall manage and invest the fund in good faith and with the care an ordinarily prudent person in a like position would exercise under similar circumstances.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-65-010__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In managing and investing an institutional fund, an institution</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="13-65-010__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>may incur only costs that are appropriate and reasonable in relation to the assets, the purposes of the institution, and the skills available to the institution; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-65-010__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall make a reasonable effort to verify facts relevant to the management and investment of the fund.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-65-010__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An institution may pool two or more institutional funds for purposes of management and investment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-65-010__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as otherwise provided by a gift instrument, the following rules apply:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="13-65-010__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in managing and investing an institutional fund, the following factors, if relevant, must be considered:
(A) general economic conditions;
(B) the possible effect of inflation or deflation;
(C) the expected tax consequences, if any, of investment decisions or strategies;
(D) the role that each investment or course of action plays within the overall investment portfolio of the fund;
(E) the expected total return from income and the appreciation of investments;
(F) other resources of the institution;
(G) the needs of the institution and the fund to make distributions and to preserve capital; and
(H) an asset's special relationship or special value, if any, to the charitable purposes of the institution;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-65-010__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>management and investment decisions about an individual asset may not be made in isolation but rather in the context of the institutional fund's portfolio of investments as a whole and as a part of an overall investment strategy having risk and return objectives reasonably suited to the fund and to the institution;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-65-010__subsec_e__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>except as otherwise provided by law other than this chapter, an institution may invest in any kind of property or type of investment consistent with the standards of this section;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-65-010__subsec_e__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an institution shall diversify the investments of an institutional fund unless the institution reasonably determines that, because of special circumstances, the purposes of the fund are better served without diversification;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-65-010__subsec_e__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>within a reasonable time after receiving property, an institution shall make and implement decisions concerning the retention or disposition of the property or to rebalance a portfolio in order to bring the institutional fund into compliance with the purposes, terms, distribution requirements, and other circumstances of the institution and the requirements of this chapter;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-65-010__subsec_e__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a person who has special skills or expertise, or is selected in reliance on the person's representation that the person has special skills or expertise, has a duty to use those special skills or that expertise in managing and investing institutional funds.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-65-020">
            <num>13.65.020</num>
            <heading>Appropriation for expenditure or accumulation of endowment fund; rules of construction.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-65-020__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subject to the intent of a donor expressed in a gift instrument, an institution may appropriate for expenditure or accumulate so much of an endowment fund as the institution determines is prudent for the uses, benefits, purposes, and duration for which the endowment fund is established. Unless stated otherwise in a gift instrument, the assets in an endowment fund are donor-restricted assets until appropriated for expenditure by the institution. In making a determination to appropriate or accumulate, the institution shall act in good faith, with the care that an ordinarily prudent person in a like position would exercise under similar circumstances, and shall consider, if relevant, the following factors:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="13-65-020__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the duration and preservation of the endowment fund;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-65-020__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the purposes of the institution and the endowment fund;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-65-020__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>general economic conditions;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-65-020__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the possible effect of inflation or deflation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-65-020__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the expected total return from income and the appreciation of investments;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-65-020__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>other resources of the institution; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-65-020__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the investment policy of the institution.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-65-020__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To limit the authority to appropriate for expenditure or accumulate under (a) of this section, a gift instrument must specifically state the limitation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-65-020__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Terms in a gift instrument designating a gift as an endowment, a direction or authorization in the gift instrument to use only income, interest, dividends, or rents, issues, or profits, or to preserve the principal intact, or words of similar meaning</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="13-65-020__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>create an endowment fund of permanent duration unless other language in the gift instrument limits the duration or purpose of the fund; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-65-020__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>do not otherwise limit the authority to appropriate for expenditure or accumulate under (a) of this section.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-65-030">
            <num>13.65.030</num>
            <heading>Delegation of management and investment functions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-65-030__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subject to a specific limitation set out in a gift instrument or in law other than this chapter, an institution may delegate to an external agent the management and investment of an institutional fund to the extent that an institution could prudently delegate under the circumstances. An institution shall act in good faith, with the care that an ordinarily prudent person in a like position would exercise under similar circumstances, in</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="13-65-030__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>selecting an agent;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-65-030__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establishing the scope and terms of the delegation, consistent with the purposes of the institution and the institutional fund; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-65-030__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>periodically reviewing the agent's actions in order to monitor the agent's performance and compliance with the scope and terms of the delegation.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-65-030__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In performing a delegated function, an agent owes a duty to the institution to exercise reasonable care to comply with the scope and terms of the delegation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-65-030__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An institution that complies with (a) of this section is not liable for the decisions or actions of an agent to whom the function was delegated.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-65-030__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>By accepting delegation of a management or investment function from an institution that is subject to the laws of this state, an agent submits to the jurisdiction of the courts of this state in all proceedings arising from or related to the delegation or the performance of the delegated function.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-65-030__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An institution may delegate management and investment functions to its committees, officers, or employees as authorized by law other than this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-65-040">
            <num>13.65.040</num>
            <heading>Release or modification of restrictions on management, investment, or purpose.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-65-040__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>With the donor's consent in a record, an institution may release or modify, in whole or in part, a restriction contained in a gift instrument on the management, investment, or purpose of an institutional fund. A release or modification may not allow a fund to be used for a purpose other than a charitable purpose of the institution.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-65-040__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a restriction contained in a gift instrument on the management or investment of an institutional fund becomes impracticable or wasteful or impairs the management or investment of the fund, or if, because of circumstances not anticipated by the donor, a modification of a restriction will further the purposes of the fund, the court, on application of the institution, may modify the restriction. The institution shall notify the attorney general of the application. To the extent practicable, a modification shall be made in accordance with the donor's probable intention.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-65-040__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a particular charitable purpose or a restriction contained in a gift instrument on the use of an institutional fund becomes unlawful, impracticable, impossible to achieve, or wasteful, the court, on application of an institution, may modify the purpose of the fund or the restriction on the use of the fund in a manner consistent with the charitable purposes expressed in the gift instrument.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-65-040__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If an institution determines that a restriction contained in a gift instrument on the management, investment, or purpose of an institutional fund is unlawful, impracticable, impossible to achieve, or wasteful, the institution, 90 days or more after notification of the attorney general, may release or modify the restriction, in whole or part, if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="13-65-040__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the institutional fund subject to the restriction has a total value of less than $50,000;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-65-040__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>more than 20 years have elapsed since the fund was established; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-65-040__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the institution uses the property in a manner the institution reasonably determines to be consistent with the charitable purposes expressed in the gift instrument.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-65-050">
            <num>13.65.050</num>
            <heading>Reviewing compliance.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.65.050.   Reviewing compliance.
Compliance with this chapter is determined in light of the facts and circumstances existing at the time a decision is made or an action is taken.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-65-060">
            <num>13.65.060</num>
            <heading>Relation to Electronic Signatures in Global and National Commerce Act.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.65.060.   Relation to Electronic Signatures in Global and National Commerce Act.
This chapter modifies, limits, and supersedes 15 U.S.C. 7001  7031 (Electronic Signatures in Global and National Commerce Act), but does not modify, limit, or supersede 15 U.S.C. 7001(c) or authorize electronic delivery of a notice described in 15 U.S.C. 7003(b).</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-65-070">
            <num>13.65.070</num>
            <heading>Application.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.65.070.   Application.
If another provision of law or of a governing instrument of an institution applies to an institutional fund but conflicts with this chapter, the other provision governs.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-65-080">
            <num>13.65.080</num>
            <heading>Uniformity of application and construction.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.65.080.   Uniformity of application and construction.
In applying and construing this chapter, consideration shall be given to the need to promote uniformity of the law with respect to its subject matter among states that enact it.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-65-090">
            <num>13.65.090</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.65.090.   Definitions.
In this chapter,
(1) charitable purpose means the relief of poverty, the advancement of education or religion, the promotion of health, the promotion of a governmental purpose, or another purpose the achievement of which is beneficial to the community;
(2) endowment fund means an institutional fund, or part of an institutional fund, not wholly expendable by the institution on a current basis under the terms of a gift instrument; the term does not include assets of an institution designated by an institution as an endowment fund for its own use;
(3) gift instrument means a record, including an institutional solicitation, under which property is granted to, transferred to, or held by an institutional fund;
(4) institution means
(A) a person, other than an individual, organized and operated exclusively for charitable purposes;
(B) a government or governmental subdivision, agency, or instrumentality, to the extent that it holds funds exclusively for a charitable purpose; or
(C) a trust that had both charitable and noncharitable interests, after all noncharitable interests have terminated;
(5) institutional fund means a fund held by an institution exclusively for charitable purposes; the term does not include
(A) program-related assets;
(B) a fund held for an institution by a trustee who is not an institution; or
(C) a fund in which a beneficiary who is not an institution has an interest, other than an interest that could arise on a violation or failure of the purposes of the fund;
(6) person means an individual, corporation, business trust, estate, trust, partnership, limited liability company, association, joint venture, public corporation, government or governmental subdivision, agency, or instrumentality, or another legal or commercial entity;
(7) program-related asset means an asset held by an institution primarily to accomplish a charitable purpose of the institution and not primarily for appreciation or the production of income;
(8) record means information that is inscribed on a tangible medium or that is stored in an electronic or other medium and is retrievable in perceivable form.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-65-095">
            <num>13.65.095</num>
            <heading>Short title.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.65.095.   Short title.
This chapter may be cited as the Uniform Prudent Management of Institutional Funds Act.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>