<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-6/chapter-45"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-6/chapter-45"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="6.45"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-6/chapter-45/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-6/chapter-45/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-6/chapter-45/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-6/chapter-45/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_6">
        <num>6</num>
        <heading>Banks and Financial Institutions</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_6__chp_45">
          <num>45</num>
          <heading>Alaska Credit Union Act</heading>
          <section eId="sec_06-45-010">
            <num>06.45.010</num>
            <heading>Responsibility of commissioner.</heading>
            <subsection eId="06-45-010__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall administer this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="06-45-010__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner may by regulation define the powers of credit unions formed under this chapter and adopt regulations to carry out the purposes of credit unions consistent with this chapter and
AS 06.01.020
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="06-45-010__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner may delegate any authority, power, or function granted by this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="06-45-010__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The records of credit unions shall be kept and reports shall be made in accordance with regulations adopted by the commissioner.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="06-45-010__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person appointed or elected by a credit union to a position requiring the receipt, payment, or custody of money or personal property owned by a credit union or in its custody or control as collateral or otherwise shall give bond in a corporate surety company approved by the commissioner on a form approved by the commissioner and in an amount prescribed by the commissioner. The commissioner may approve the use of a form of schedule or blanket bond which covers all the officers and employees of a credit union whose duties include the receipt, payment, or custody of money or other personal property for or on behalf of the credit union.  The commissioner may approve the use of a form of excess coverage bond under which a credit union may obtain coverage in excess of the basic surety coverage.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_06-45-020">
            <num>06.45.020</num>
            <heading>Formation of credit union.</heading>
            <subsection eId="06-45-020__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Seven or more natural persons who desire to form a credit union shall subscribe before an officer competent to administer oaths, articles of incorporation in duplicate that must state</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-020__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name of the credit union;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-020__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the location of the credit union and the territory in which it will operate;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-020__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the names and addresses of the subscribers to the certificate and the number of shares each subscribed;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-020__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the par value of the shares, which must be a minimum of $5 each;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-020__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the proposed field of membership specified in detail;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-020__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the term of the existence of the credit union, which may be perpetual; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-020__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the fact that the articles of incorporation are adopted to enable the persons to avail themselves of the advantages of this chapter.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="06-45-020__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The articles of incorporation must also include provisions required by the commissioner for the management of the business of the credit union, for the conduct of its affairs, and relating to the powers of its directors, officers, or stockholders.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="06-45-020__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>At the time of presenting the articles of incorporation to the commissioner the incorporators shall also submit proposed bylaws to the commissioner for approval. Except to the extent the articles of incorporation provide the structure and designate the offices, the bylaws shall provide the organizational structure of the credit union and specifically designate those offices that will be held by the executive or managing officers of the credit union. Copies of the original bylaws of the credit union and any amendments of the bylaws shall be filed with the commissioner.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="06-45-020__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner may prepare form articles of incorporation and form bylaws, consistent with this chapter, which may be used by credit union incorporators and shall be supplied to them on request.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_06-45-030">
            <num>06.45.030</num>
            <heading>Approval of articles of incorporation and issuance of certificate of authority.</heading>
            <subsection eId="06-45-030__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The articles of incorporation shall be presented to the commissioner for approval.  Before the certificate of authority is issued, the commissioner shall determine</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-030__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>whether the articles of incorporation and bylaws conform to the provisions of this chapter and to regulations of the commissioner;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-030__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the general character and fitness of the subscribers; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-030__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the economic advisability of establishing the proposed credit union.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="06-45-030__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A certificate of authority shall be delivered by the commissioner to the credit union if the required fee has been paid.  On issuance of the certificate of authority, the credit union is a body corporate and is subject to the limitations of this chapter, and is vested with all of the powers and charged with all of the liabilities conferred and imposed by this chapter upon credit unions organized under it.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_06-45-040">
            <num>06.45.040</num>
            <heading>Fees.</heading>
            <subsection eId="06-45-040__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall assess a credit union a fee for expenses under
AS 06.01.010
in processing an application</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-040__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for approval of articles of incorporation and bylaws and the issuance of a certificate of authority for a credit union;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-040__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for the approval of a branch of a credit union;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-040__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for a merger or conversion of a credit union; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-040__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for an examination under
AS 06.45.050
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="06-45-040__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Failure of a credit union to pay a fee required by (a)(2), (3), or (4) of this section within 30 days of receipt of billing from the commissioner is grounds for the revocation of the certificate of authority of the credit union.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_06-45-050">
            <num>06.45.050</num>
            <heading>Reports and examinations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 06.45.050.   Reports and examinations.
A credit union organized under this chapter is under the supervision of the commissioner and shall make an annual financial report to the commissioner and shall make other financial reports required by regulations adopted by the commissioner.  A credit union is subject to examination by the commissioner.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_06-45-060">
            <num>06.45.060</num>
            <heading>Powers of a credit union; remedy for interest violations.</heading>
            <subsection eId="06-45-060__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A credit union has succession in its corporate name during its existence and may</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-060__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>enter into a contract;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-060__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>sue and be sued;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-060__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>adopt, use, and alter a common seal;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-060__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>purchase, hold, and dispose of property;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-060__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>make loans, the maturities of which may not exceed 20 years except as provided in this chapter, and extend lines of credit to its members, to other credit unions, and to credit union organizations and participate with other credit unions, credit union organizations, or financial organizations in making loans to credit union members in accordance with the following:
(A) loans to members shall be made in conformity with regulations adopted by the commissioner, except that</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="06-45-060__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>a residential real estate loan that is made to finance the acquisition of a one- to four-family dwelling for the principal residence of a credit union member that is secured by a first lien on the dwelling may have a maturity not exceeding 30 years;
(ii) a loan to finance the purchase of a manufactured home that is secured by a first lien on the manufactured home, to be used as the residence of a credit union member, or for the repair, alteration, or improvement of a residential dwelling that is the residence of a credit union member must have a maturity not to exceed 20 years unless the loan is insured or guaranteed under (iii) of this subparagraph;
(iii) a loan secured by the insurance or guarantee of the federal government, of a state government, or an agency of either may be made for the maturity and under the terms and conditions specified in the law under which the insurance or guarantee is provided;
(iv) a loan or aggregate of loans to a director or member of the supervisory or credit committee of the credit union making the loan that exceeds $20,000 plus pledged shares shall be approved by the board of directors;</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="06-45-060__subsec_v">
              <num>(v)</num>
              <content>
                <p>loans to other members for which directors or members of the supervisory or credit committee act as guarantor or endorser shall be approved by the board of directors when the loans standing alone or when added to an outstanding loan or loans of the guarantor or endorser exceed $20,000;
(vi) the rate of interest may not exceed the greater of 15 percent a year or the rate specified in
AS 45.45.010
(b);
(vii) the taking, receiving, reserving, or charging of a rate of interest greater than is allowed by this paragraph, when knowingly done, is considered a forfeiture of the entire interest that the note, bill, or other evidence of debt carries with it, or that has been agreed to be paid on the note, bill, or other evidence of debt; if a greater rate of interest has been paid, the person by whom it has been paid or the person's legal representatives may recover back from the credit union taking or receiving it the entire amount of interest paid, but the action must be commenced within two years from the time the usurious collection was made;
(viii) a borrower may repay a loan before maturity in whole or in part on any business day without penalty;
(ix) loans shall be paid or amortized under regulations adopted by the commissioner that consider the needs or conditions of the borrowers, the amounts and duration of the loans, the interests of the members and the credit union, and other factors established in regulations adopted by the commissioner;</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="06-45-060__subsec_x">
              <num>(x)</num>
              <content>
                <p>the total dollar amount of real estate loans and manufactured home loans outstanding may not exceed 25 percent of the assets of the credit union without the written approval of the commissioner;
(xi) a credit union with assets of less than $3,000,000 may make real estate loans with maturities in excess of 15 years only with the approval of the commissioner;
(B) a self-replenishing line of credit to a borrower may be established to a stated maximum amount on terms and conditions that may be different from terms and conditions established for another borrower;
(C) loans to other credit unions require the approval of the board of directors of the loaning credit union;
(D) loans to credit union associations require the approval of the board of directors of the credit union and may not exceed one percent of the paid-in and unimpaired capital and surplus of the credit union;
(E) participation loans with other credit unions, credit union associations, or financial organizations shall be made in accordance with written policies of the board of directors of the credit union, except that a credit union that originates a loan for which participation arrangements are made in accordance with this section shall retain an interest not less than 10 percent of the face amount of the loan;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-060__subsec_x__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>receive from its members and from others payments on shares that may be issued at varying dividend rates, and payments on share certificates that may be issued at varying dividend rates and maturities, and establish share draft accounts, subject to terms, rates, and conditions as may be established by the board of directors of the credit union, within limitations prescribed by the commissioner;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-060__subsec_x__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>invest its funds
(A) in loans exclusively to members;
(B) in obligations of the United States or securities fully guaranteed as to principal and interest by the United States;
(C) in loans to other credit unions in the total amount not exceeding 25 percent of its paid-in and unimpaired capital and surplus in accordance with regulations adopted by the commissioner;
(D) in shares or accounts of savings and loan associations or mutual savings banks that are insured by the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation;
(E) in obligations issued by banks for cooperatives, federal land banks, federal intermediate credit banks, federal home loan banks, the Federal Home Loan Bank Board, or a corporation designated in 31 U.S.C. 9101 as a wholly owned federal government corporation; in obligations, participations, or other instruments of or issued by or fully guaranteed as to principal and interest by the Federal National Mortgage Association or the Government National Mortgage Association; in mortgages, obligations, or other securities that are or have been sold by the Federal Home Loan Mortgage Corporation under 12 U.S.C. 1454 or 12 U.S.C. 1455 (Federal Home Loan Mortgage Corporation Act); or in obligations or other instruments or securities of the Student Loan Marketing Association;
(F) in participation certificates evidencing beneficial interests in obligations, or in the right to receive interest and principal collections from obligations, that have been subjected by one or more federal agencies to a trust or trusts for which an executive department, agency, or instrumentality of the United States or its head has been named to act as trustee;
(G) in shares or deposits of a central credit union in which such investments are authorized by the board of directors of the credit union making the investment;
(H) in shares, share certificates, or share deposits of federally insured credit unions;
(I) in the shares, stocks, or obligations of another organization providing services that a</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="06-45-060__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>a corporation licensed under
AS 10.13
; or
(ii) a corporation attempting to become licensed under
AS 10.13
if the corporation intends to use the proceeds to fulfill the tasks necessary to become licensed under
AS 10.13
;
(L) in bankers' acceptances issued by a financial institution whose accounts are insured by an agency of the federal government;
(M) in stock of a federal home loan bank; the investment must be limited to the minimum amount of stock required for membership in the federal home loan bank, plus any additional stock purchase required to obtain an advance of funds from a federal home loan bank; and
(N) in obligations of, or issued by, a state or political subdivision of the state, except that a credit union may not invest more than 10 percent of its unimpaired capital and surplus in the obligations of any one issuer, exclusive of general obligations of the issuer; in this subparagraph, political subdivision of the state includes an agency, corporation, or instrumentality of a state or political subdivision;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-060__subsec_i__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>make deposits in national banks and in state banks, trust companies, and mutual savings banks operating in accordance with the laws of the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-060__subsec_i__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>borrow in accordance with regulations adopted by the commissioner from any source, in an aggregate amount not exceeding 50 percent of its paid-in and unimpaired capital and surplus, except that a credit union may discount with or sell to a federal intermediate credit bank an eligible obligation up to the amount of its paid-in and unimpaired capital;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-060__subsec_i__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>levy late charges, in accordance with the bylaws, for failure of members to meet promptly their obligations to the credit union;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-060__subsec_i__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>levy and enforce a lien upon the shares and dividends of a member to the extent of a loan made to, and any dues or charges payable by, the member;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-060__subsec_i__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in accordance with regulations adopted by the commissioner, sell to members negotiable checks, travelers checks, and money orders, and cash checks and money orders for members, for a fee which does not exceed the direct and indirect costs incident to providing the service;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-060__subsec_i__subsec_13">
                <num>(13)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in accordance with regulations adopted by the commissioner, purchase, sell, pledge, discount, or otherwise receive or dispose of, in whole or in part, eligible obligations of its members and purchase from a liquidating credit union notes made by individual members of the liquidating credit union at prices agreed upon by the board of directors of the liquidating credit union and the board of directors of the purchasing credit union; a purchase may not be made under authority of this paragraph if, upon the making of the purchase, the aggregate of the unpaid balances of notes purchased under authority of this paragraph exceeds five percent of the unimpaired capital and surplus of the credit union;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-060__subsec_i__subsec_14">
                <num>(14)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>sell all or a part of its assets to another credit union, purchase all or part of the assets of another credit union, and assume the liabilities of the selling credit union and those of its members subject to regulations of the commissioner;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-060__subsec_i__subsec_15">
                <num>(15)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>issue solicited or unsolicited credit cards or other similar credit granting devices to a member for obtaining money, goods, services or anything else of value; notwithstanding (5)(A)(vi) of this subsection and
AS 45.45.010
, when credit is extended under this section, the credit union may impose a service charge at a monthly rate as agreed upon by contract between the credit union and the member receiving the credit granting device, but the credit union may not hold the member liable for charges made on a credit card or other credit granting device before its acceptance by the member; before an unsolicited card is considered accepted by the member, the member shall execute and furnish to the credit union a written statement of acceptance; in addition, a credit union may charge fees for credit cards or other similar credit granting devices; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-060__subsec_i__subsec_16">
                <num>(16)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>exercise incidental powers as are necessary or required to enable it to carry on effectively the business for which it is incorporated.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="06-45-060__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, manufactured home has the meaning given in
AS 45.29.102
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_06-45-070">
            <num>06.45.070</num>
            <heading>Membership.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 06.45.070.   Membership.
Credit union membership consists of the incorporators and other persons and incorporated and unincorporated organizations, to the extent permitted by regulations adopted by the commissioner, elected to membership. Each member shall subscribe to at least one share of the stock of the credit union and pay the initial installment on the stock and a uniform entrance fee if required by the board of directors of the credit union.  Credit union membership is limited to groups having a common bond of occupation or association, or to groups within a well-defined neighborhood, community, or rural district. Shares may be issued in joint tenancy with right of survivorship with a person designated by the credit union member.  A joint tenant may not be permitted to vote, obtain loans, or hold office, unless the joint tenant is within the field of membership and is qualified for membership.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_06-45-080">
            <num>06.45.080</num>
            <heading>Meetings of members.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 06.45.080.   Meetings of members.
The fiscal year of a credit union ends December 31. The annual meeting of a credit union shall be held within three months after the end of the fiscal year at a place its bylaws prescribe.  Special meetings may be held under the bylaws.  A member may not vote by proxy, but a member other than a natural person may vote through an agent designated for the purpose.  A member may not have more than one vote.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_06-45-090">
            <num>06.45.090</num>
            <heading>Management of credit union.</heading>
            <subsection eId="06-45-090__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The business affairs of a credit union are managed by (1) a board of not less than five directors; (2) a credit committee of not less than three members; and (3) a supervisory committee of not less than three members or more than five members. The members of the board of directors shall be elected at the annual members meeting by and from the members. The supervisory committee shall be appointed by the board of directors, and a vacancy in the supervisory committee shall be filled by the board of directors. One of the members of the supervisory committee may be a member of the board of directors, other than the treasurer. The credit committee consists of an uneven number of three or more members appointed by the board of directors for the terms established by the bylaws. Members of the board of directors and of the credit and supervisory committees hold office for terms as the bylaws may provide.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="06-45-090__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A record of the names and addresses of the members of the board, the committees, and the officers of the credit union shall be filed with the commissioner within 10 days after election or appointment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_06-45-100">
            <num>06.45.100</num>
            <heading>Compensation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 06.45.100.   Compensation.
A member of the board of directors or of the credit or supervisory committees may not be compensated for service on the board of directors or credit or supervisory committees. Reasonable health, accident, and similar insurance protection is not compensation under this section and may be provided under regulations adopted by the commissioner.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_06-45-110">
            <num>06.45.110</num>
            <heading>Executive officers.</heading>
            <subsection eId="06-45-110__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>At its first meeting after the annual meeting of the members, the board of directors shall elect from its membership the executive officers of the credit union.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="06-45-110__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An executive officer, other than the treasurer, may not be compensated as an officer.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="06-45-110__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The offices of secretary and treasurer may be held by the same person.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="06-45-110__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The duties of the officers are determined by the bylaws.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="06-45-110__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The treasurer shall give bond with good and sufficient surety, in an amount and character to be determined by the board of directors in compliance with regulations adopted by the commissioner.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="06-45-110__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board of directors shall appoint a president to act as chief executive officer of the credit union and to be actively in charge of the operations of the credit union.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_06-45-120">
            <num>06.45.120</num>
            <heading>Board of directors.</heading>
            <subsection eId="06-45-120__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board of directors shall meet at least once a month and shall have the general direction and control of the business affairs of the credit union.  Minutes of all meetings shall be kept.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="06-45-120__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board of directors shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-120__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>act upon applications for membership;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-120__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>require an officer or employee having custody of or handling funds to give bond with good and sufficient surety in an amount and character to be determined by the board of directors in compliance with regulations adopted by the commissioner and authorize the payment of the premium by the credit union;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-120__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>fill vacancies in the board of directors until successors elected at the next annual meeting have qualified;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-120__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>have charge of investments other than loans to members; the board of directors may designate a committee of not less than two to act as an investment committee that has charge of making investments under rules and procedures established by the board of directors;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-120__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>determine the maximum number of shares and share certificates and the classes of shares and share certificates that may be held;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-120__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>subject to the limitations of this chapter, determine the interest rates on loans, the security, and the maximum amount that may be loaned or provided in lines of credit;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-120__subsec_b__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>subject to regulations adopted by the commissioner, authorize an interest refund to members of record at the close of business on the last day of any dividend period in proportion to the interest paid by the members during the dividend period; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-120__subsec_b__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide for compensation of officers and employees.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="06-45-120__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board of directors may appoint an executive committee of not less than three directors to exercise authority delegated to it under the conditions and limitations prescribed by the board of directors.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_06-45-130">
            <num>06.45.130</num>
            <heading>Applications for membership.</heading>
            <subsection eId="06-45-130__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board of directors shall establish procedures for the review and approval of applications for membership in the credit union.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="06-45-130__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each month the board of directors shall review a list of applications for membership acted on during the preceding month.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="06-45-130__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If an application for membership is denied, the reasons for the denial shall be furnished to the applicant on request.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="06-45-130__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board of directors may appoint a membership officer from the members of the credit union or the executive committee of the board of directors to review applications for membership. A treasurer, assistant treasurer, or loan officer may not review applications for membership.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_06-45-140">
            <num>06.45.140</num>
            <heading>Powers and duties of credit committee.</heading>
            <subsection eId="06-45-140__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The credit committee shall hold meetings to consider applications for loans and lines of credit as the business of the credit union may require but not less frequently than once a month. Reasonable notice of the meetings shall be given to members of the credit committee.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="06-45-140__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except for the loans or lines of credit required to be approved by the board of directors under
AS 06.45.060
(a)(5), a majority of the entire credit committee may approve an application.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="06-45-140__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The credit committee may delegate to a loan officer the power to approve loans and lines of credit. A loan officer shall furnish to the credit committee a record of each approved or unapproved application within seven days of the filing of the application.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="06-45-140__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An application not approved by a loan officer shall be acted on by the credit committee.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="06-45-140__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An individual may not disburse funds of a credit union for a loan, line of credit, or application that the individual approved in the capacity of loan officer.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="06-45-140__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Applications for loans and lines of credit shall be made on forms prepared by the credit committee.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_06-45-150">
            <num>06.45.150</num>
            <heading>Loan restriction.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 06.45.150.   Loan restriction.
A loan may not be made to a member if, on the making of the loan, the member would be indebted to the credit union on loans from the credit union in an amount exceeding 10 percent of the unimpaired capital and surplus of the credit union.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_06-45-160">
            <num>06.45.160</num>
            <heading>Security.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 06.45.160.   Security.
For the purposes of loans made under this chapter, an assignment of shares or the endorsement of a note constitutes security, and, subject to regulations adopted by the commissioner, insurance obtained under Title 1 of the National Housing Act is adequate security.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_06-45-170">
            <num>06.45.170</num>
            <heading>Powers and duties of supervisory committee; suspension of committee members.</heading>
            <subsection eId="06-45-170__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The supervisory committee shall conduct an annual audit of the accounts of the credit union and submit a report of the audit to the board of directors and a summary of the audit to the members at the next annual members meeting of the credit union. The supervisory committee may conduct supplementary audits as it considers necessary or as ordered by the commissioner, and submit reports of the supplementary audits to the board of directors.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="06-45-170__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The supervisory committee shall verify the passbooks and accounts of the members with the records of the treasurer from time to time, but not less frequently than once every two years. In this subsection, passbook includes a book, statement of account, or other record approved by the commissioner for use by credit unions.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="06-45-170__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The supervisory committee may by a unanimous vote suspend an officer of the credit union or a member of the credit committee or the board of directors until the next meeting of the members, which shall be held not less than seven or more than 14 days after the suspension under this subsection.  A suspension shall be acted upon by the members.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="06-45-170__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The supervisory committee may call by a majority vote a special meeting of the members to consider a violation of this chapter, the articles of incorporation or bylaws, or a practice of the credit union considered unsafe or unauthorized by the supervisory committee.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="06-45-170__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board of directors may by a majority vote suspend a member of the supervisory committee until the next meeting of the members, which shall be held not less than seven or more than 14 days after the suspension.  A suspension shall be acted upon by the members.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_06-45-180">
            <num>06.45.180</num>
            <heading>Reserves.</heading>
            <subsection eId="06-45-180__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>At the end of each accounting period the gross income of the credit union shall be determined. From this amount, there shall be set aside as a regular reserve against losses on loans and against other losses specified in regulations adopted by the commissioner under this chapter sums in accordance with the following schedule:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-180__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a credit union in operation for more than four years and having assets of $500,000 or more shall set aside
(A) 10 percent of gross income until the regular reserve equals four percent of the total of outstanding loans and risk assets; then
(B) five percent of gross income until the regular reserve equals six percent of the total of outstanding loans and risk assets;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-180__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a credit union in operation less than four years or having assets of less than $500,000 shall set aside
(A) 10 percent of gross income until the regular reserve equals seven and one-half percent of the total of outstanding loans and risk assets; then
(B) five percent of gross income until the regular reserve equals 10 percent of the total of outstanding loans and risk assets;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-180__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>when the regular reserve falls below the stated percent of the total of outstanding loans and risk assets, it shall be replenished by regular contributions in amounts as may be needed to maintain the stated reserve goals.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="06-45-180__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner may decrease the reserve requirement in (a) of this section when the decrease is necessary or desirable. The commissioner may also require special reserves to protect the interests of members either by general regulation or for an individual credit union.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_06-45-190">
            <num>06.45.190</num>
            <heading>Dividends.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 06.45.190.   Dividends.
At intervals as the board of directors may authorize and after provision for required reserves, the board of directors may declare, under regulations adopted by the commissioner, a dividend to be paid at different rates on different types of shares and at different rates and maturity dates in the case of share certificates.  Dividend credit may be accrued on various types of shares and share certificates as authorized by the board of directors.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_06-45-200">
            <num>06.45.200</num>
            <heading>Expulsion and withdrawal of members.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 06.45.200.   Expulsion and withdrawal of members.
A member may be expelled by a two-thirds vote of the members of a credit union present at a special meeting called for the purpose, but only after the member has been given an opportunity to be heard. Withdrawal or expulsion of a member does not discharge the liability of the member to the credit union.  The amount to be paid a withdrawing or expelled member by a credit union shall be determined and paid in the manner specified in the bylaws.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_06-45-210">
            <num>06.45.210</num>
            <heading>Minors or trusts.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 06.45.210.   Minors or trusts.
Shares of a credit union may be issued in the name of a minor or in trust, subject to conditions prescribed by the bylaws. When shares are issued in trust, the name of the beneficiary shall be disclosed to the credit union.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_06-45-220">
            <num>06.45.220</num>
            <heading>Suspension, conditional operation, and liquidation.</heading>
            <subsection eId="06-45-220__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner, upon a finding that the credit union is bankrupt, insolvent, or is operating in an unsafe or unsound manner or that the credit union has violated the provisions of its articles of incorporation or bylaws, this chapter, or regulations adopted by the commissioner, may exercise the powers granted under
AS 06.01.030
and temporarily suspend the operations of the credit union.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="06-45-220__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner, under the regulations adopted by the commissioner, may permit operations to continue under conditions and procedures established by the commissioner, or direct the credit union to cease operations and appoint a liquidating agent to liquidate the credit union.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_06-45-230">
            <num>06.45.230</num>
            <heading>Exemption from taxation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 06.45.230.   Exemption from taxation.
A credit union organized under this chapter, its property, franchises, capital, reserves, surpluses, and other funds, and its income are exempt from taxation by the state or a political subdivision of the state, except that real property and tangible personal property owned by a credit union is subject to taxation to the same extent that similar property is taxed.  This section does not prevent holdings in a credit union organized under this chapter from being included in the valuation of the personal property of the owners or holders under taxes imposed by the state or a political subdivision of the state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_06-45-240">
            <num>06.45.240</num>
            <heading>Conversions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="06-45-240__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A federal credit union may convert into a credit union organized under this chapter by complying with applicable federal law and by qualifying under this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="06-45-240__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A credit union organized under this chapter may convert into a federal credit union by complying with this chapter and by qualifying under federal law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_06-45-250">
            <num>06.45.250</num>
            <heading>Insurance of member accounts.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 06.45.250.   Insurance of member accounts.
A credit union organized under this chapter shall, under regulations adopted by the commissioner, participate in insurance of member accounts under programs offered by the National Credit Union Administration Board or a program of comparable insurance approved by the commissioner.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_06-45-260">
            <num>06.45.260</num>
            <heading>Liquidity facility participation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 06.45.260.   Liquidity facility participation.
A credit union organized under this chapter may, under regulations adopted by the commissioner, participate in the programs offered by the National Credit Union Central Liquidity Facility.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_06-45-270">
            <num>06.45.270</num>
            <heading>Conflict of interest.</heading>
            <subsection eId="06-45-270__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A member of the board of directors or a member of the credit committee or supervisory committee or an employee of a credit union may not participate in the deliberation or the determination of a question affecting the person's own pecuniary interest or the pecuniary interest of a corporation, partnership, or association in which the person is interested.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="06-45-270__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who violates (a) of this section may not thereafter serve as an officer, agent, or employee of a credit union.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_06-45-280">
            <num>06.45.280</num>
            <heading>Merger.</heading>
            <subsection eId="06-45-280__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A credit union may merge with another credit union under a plan agreed upon by a majority of the board of directors of each credit union and approved by a majority of the members of each credit union present at meetings called to approve the plan.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="06-45-280__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner may by regulation establish further procedures governing mergers.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_06-45-290">
            <num>06.45.290</num>
            <heading>Branch offices.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 06.45.290.   Branch offices.
A credit union may establish a branch office under regulations of the commissioner.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_06-45-295">
            <num>06.45.295</num>
            <heading>Automated teller machines.</heading>
            <subsection eId="06-45-295__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A state credit union may establish, maintain, and operate an automated teller machine on the premises of the main office or a branch office of the state credit union.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="06-45-295__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A state credit union may establish, maintain, and operate an automated teller machine at a location other than credit union premises by notifying the department 30 days before the date of establishment. An automated teller machine operated off credit union premises shall be made available on a nondiscriminatory basis for use by depositors of other depository institutions authorized to do business in the state, upon the agreement of the other depository institutions to pay a fair and equitable amount for the use of the machine.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="06-45-295__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The notice required by (b) of this section must include</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-295__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the location and general description of the surrounding area, including a description of the business establishment, if any, in which the machine will be located;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-295__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the manner of operation and the kinds of transactions that the machine will perform;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-295__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the names of the other depository institutions that will share the machine's services; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="06-45-295__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>other information required by the department.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="06-45-295__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A state credit union may invest in a corporation organized to operate machines that perform automated teller services for two or more depository institutions.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="06-45-295__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not establish or operate an automated teller machine that accepts deposits unless those deposits are insured by the National Credit Union Share Insurance Fund or another agency of the United States that insures deposits.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_06-45-300">
            <num>06.45.300</num>
            <heading>Unauthorized conduct of credit union business.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 06.45.300.   Unauthorized conduct of credit union business.
It is a class A misdemeanor for a natural person to conduct business under a name or title that contains the words credit union or a derivation of them or to represent to be conducting business as a credit union.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_06-45-310">
            <num>06.45.310</num>
            <heading>Transfer of credit union's property to preferred creditor is void.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 06.45.310.   Transfer of credit union's property to preferred creditor is void.
The transfer of property, money, or assets by a credit union after it becomes insolvent, to prefer one creditor over another, or to prevent the equal distribution of its property and assets among its creditors is void.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_06-45-340">
            <num>06.45.340</num>
            <heading>Limitations on credit unions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 06.45.340.   Limitations on credit unions.
A credit union may not acquire control directly or indirectly of another financial institution or invest in shares, stocks, or obligations of an insurance company, trade association, liquidity facility, or any other similar organization, corporation, or association except as expressly provided by this chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_06-45-400">
            <num>06.45.400</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 06.45.400.   Definitions.
In this chapter,
(1) commissioner means the commissioner of commerce, community, and economic development;
(2) credit union means a cooperative association organized in accordance with the provisions of this chapter for the purpose of promoting thrift among its members and creating a source of credit for provident or productive purposes;
(3) credit union association means an organization established primarily to serve the needs of its member credit unions under regulations adopted by the commissioner.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>