<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-16"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-16"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="14.16"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-16/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-16/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-16/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-16/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_14">
        <num>14</num>
        <heading>Education, Libraries, and Museums</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_14__chp_16">
          <num>16</num>
          <heading>Special Schools</heading>
          <section eId="sec_14-16-010">
            <num>14.16.010</num>
            <heading>Establishment of state boarding schools.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.16.010.   Establishment of state boarding schools.
The department may establish and operate boarding schools, to be managed in accordance with this chapter. A state boarding school must offer a secondary education curriculum to students enrolled in it, and must provide domiciliary services for students needing such services, if approved by the board.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-16-020">
            <num>14.16.020</num>
            <heading>Operation of state boarding schools.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.16.020.   Operation of state boarding schools.
In the management of state boarding schools, the board shall
(1) adopt a philosophy of education for state boarding schools;
(2) approve the employment of personnel necessary to operate state boarding schools;
(3) establish the salaries and benefits to be paid teachers, excluding administrators;
(4) designate the employees authorized to direct disbursements from the money appropriated for the operation of state boarding schools and for the construction of facilities;
(5) provide custodial services and routine maintenance of physical facilities;
(6) establish procedures for the development and implementation of curriculum and the selection and use of textbooks and instructional materials; the procedures must require a review of textbooks and instructional materials at least once every 10 years;
(7) prescribe health evaluation and placement screening programs for newly admitted students;
(8) establish procedures for staff evaluation; and
(9) establish procedures for providing the training under
AS 14.18.060
,
AS 14.20.149
, 14.20.680,
AS 14.30.355
, 14.30.356, 14.30.362,
AS 14.33.100
,
AS 18.66.310
, and
AS 47.17.022
; the procedures established under this paragraph must include a training schedule that ensures that not less than 50 percent of the total certificated staff employed by the district receive all of the training not less than every two years and that all of the certificated staff employed by the district receive all of the training not less than every four years.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-16-030">
            <num>14.16.030</num>
            <heading>Admission to school.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-16-030__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A state boarding school may admit students who are qualified in accordance with applicable admission standards. Preference for enrollment must be given to students currently enrolled at a boarding school and to students whose educational, emotional, or family requirements warrant attendance in a domiciliary environment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-16-030__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board shall prescribe admission standards and procedures by regulation. Admission standards may not discriminate in favor of or against any resident based on race, sex, creed, national origin, or the location or type of residence within the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-16-040">
            <num>14.16.040</num>
            <heading>Status of state boarding school.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.16.040.   Status of state boarding school.
A state boarding school is a public school of the state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-16-050">
            <num>14.16.050</num>
            <heading>Applicability of education laws.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-16-050__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The following provisions apply with respect to the operation and management of a state boarding school as if it were a school district:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-16-050__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>requirements relating to school district operations:
(A)
AS 14.03.030
 14.03.050 (defining the school term, day in session, and school holidays);
(B)
AS 14.03.083
 14.03.140 (miscellaneous provisions applicable to school district operations);
(C) [Repealed, § 3 ch 36 SLA 2024).
(D)
AS 14.12.150
(authorizing school districts to establish and participate in the services of a regional resource center);
(E)
AS 14.14.050
(imposing the requirement of an annual audit);
(F)
AS 14.14.110
(authorizing cooperation with other school districts);
(G)
AS 14.14.140</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-16-050__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>(establishing a prohibition on employment of a relative of the chief school administrator);
(H)
AS 14.18
(prohibiting discrimination based on sex in public education);</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-16-050__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>requirements relating to the public school funding program and the receipt and expenditure of that funding:
(A)
AS 14.17.500
(relating to student count estimates);
(B)
AS 14.17.505
(relating to school operating fund balances);
(C)
AS 14.17.500
 14.17.910 (setting out the procedure for payment of public school funding and imposing general requirements and limits on money paid);</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-16-050__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>requirements relating to teacher employment and retirement:
(A)
AS 14.14.105
and 14.14.107 (relating to sick leave);
(B)
AS 14.20.095
 14.20.215 (relating to the employment and tenure of teachers);
(C)
AS 14.20.280
 14.20.350 (relating to sabbatical leave provisions for teachers);
(D)
AS 23.40.070
 23.40.260 (authorizing collective bargaining by certificated employees), except with regard to teachers who are administrators and except that the board may delegate some or all of its responsibilities under those statutes;
(E)
AS 14.25
(provisions regarding the teachers' retirement system);</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-16-050__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>requirements relating to students and educational programs:
(A)
AS 14.30.180
 14.30.350 (relating to educational services for children with disabilities);
(B)
AS 14.30.360
 14.30.370 (establishing health education program standards);
(C)
AS 14.30.400
 14.30.410 (relating to bilingual and bicultural education).</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-16-050__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person employed as a teacher at Mt. Edgecumbe High School on May 28, 1988, acquires tenure rights in accordance with
AS 14.20.150
and 14.20.155 as though the person had been employed by a school district.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-16-060">
            <num>14.16.060</num>
            <heading>Status of employees.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.16.060.   Status of employees.
The employees of a state boarding school are state employees.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-16-070">
            <num>14.16.070</num>
            <heading>Applicability of Public Employment Relations Act.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.16.070.   Applicability of Public Employment Relations Act.
AS 23.40.070
 23.40.260 (Public Employment Relations Act) apply to the employees of a state boarding school.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-16-080">
            <num>14.16.080</num>
            <heading>Financial provisions applicable to state boarding school.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-16-080__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>AS 14.17.440
applies to the calculation of public school funding payable for operation of a state boarding school.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-16-080__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In the transmittals required by
AS 37.07.060
 37.07.062, the governor shall request amounts for the expenses of construction, rehabilitation, and improvement of the facilities of a state boarding school.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-16-080__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless specified otherwise in any appropriation bill,
AS 37.25.010
does not apply to an appropriation made for the purposes of (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-16-080__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>AS 37.25.020
applies to money appropriated for the purposes of (b) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-16-080__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of application for and receipt of federal aid to education, a state boarding school constitutes a local educational agency.
Article 2. School Districts Operating Residential Schools.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-16-100">
            <num>14.16.100</num>
            <heading>Application for residential school.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.16.100.   Application for residential school.
Before establishing a residential school, a school district shall apply to the department for approval to establish and operate a statewide or district-wide residential school. The department shall accept applications during an open application period conducted annually. A period of open application in itself does not indicate that the department will approve the establishment of a new residential school.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-16-200">
            <num>14.16.200</num>
            <heading>State funding for districts operating residential schools.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-16-200__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A district that operates a statewide or district-wide residential school for students in grades nine through 12 that has been approved by the department under regulations adopted by the board is eligible to receive a boarding stipend as reimbursement for the costs incurred by the district in operating that school. To be eligible for reimbursement for costs, a statewide or district-wide residential school operated by a district must provide a suitable student dormitory, food service, and daily access to a public school offering the appropriate grade level for a variable-length or 180-day school term as provided under
AS 14.03.030
for the full school year.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-16-200__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Costs that may be claimed by a district for reimbursement under (a) of this section are</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-16-200__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>one round trip on the least expensive means of transportation between the student's community of residence and the school during the school year if the district expends money for the trip; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-16-200__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a per-pupil monthly stipend to cover room and board expenses as determined by the department on a regional basis and not to exceed the following amounts:
(A) for the Southeast Region (Region I), $1,230;
(B) for the Southcentral Region (Region II), $1,200;
(C) for the Interior Region (Region III), $1,452;
(D) for the Southwest Region (Region IV), $1,509;
(E) for the Northern Remote Region (Region V), $1,776.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-16-200__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 4 ch 48 SLA 2013.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-16-200__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A district may cooperate with an Alaska Native organization, as defined in 20 U.S.C. 7546(2), or a nonprofit organization for the provision of room and board services to students enrolled in a statewide or district-wide residential school operated by a district under terms and conditions required for licensing in the state and as specified by the department in regulation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-16-200__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, district has the meaning given in
AS 14.17.990
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>