<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-19/chapter-30"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-19/chapter-30"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="19.30"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-19/chapter-30/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-19/chapter-30/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-19/chapter-30/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-19/chapter-30/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_19">
        <num>19</num>
        <heading>Highways and Ferries</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_19__chp_30">
          <num>30</num>
          <heading>Access Roads and Local Service Roads and Trails</heading>
          <section eId="sec_19-30-020">
            <num>19.30.020</num>
            <heading>Purpose.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.30.020.   Purpose.
The purpose of
AS 19.30.020
 19.30.051 is to facilitate the commercial development of mineral resources, except oil and gas, by authorizing funds to participate in construction of developmental access roads into areas where mining prospects of valid commercial promise are inaccessible to truck haulage. These access roads are to be constructed as rudimentary truck roads and to standards that can be readily improved for general public use.  It is the intent of the state to participate with mineral resource developers up to 50 percent for the cost of construction and maintenance of developmental access roads under
AS 19.30.020
 19.30.051.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-30-030">
            <num>19.30.030</num>
            <heading>Commissioner of natural resources to approve application.</heading>
            <subsection eId="19-30-030__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner of natural resources may approve applications for construction of developmental access roads under
AS 19.30.020
 19.30.051.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-30-030__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A request for construction assistance shall be submitted to the commissioner of natural resources by the resource developer, setting out the scope of the development and the resources to be developed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-30-030__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner of natural resources shall review the application and, if found feasible and participating funds are available, may enter into a contract in which the state will participate with the applicant in the cost of construction of the road, up to $50,000 or up to 50 percent of the cost, whichever is lower; however, the applicant shall pay for all right-of-way acquisition.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-30-030__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of (c) of this section, cost of construction includes, in addition to costs directly related to the project, the sum total of all costs of financing and carrying out the project.  These include, but are not limited to, the costs of all necessary studies, surveys, plans and specifications, architectural, engineering or other special services, acquisition of real property, site preparation and development, purchase, construction, reconstruction, and improvement of real property and the acquisition of machinery and equipment as may be necessary in connection with the project; an allocable portion of the administrative and operating expenses of the grantee; the cost of financing the project, including interest on bonds issued to finance the project; and the cost of other items, including any indemnity and surety bonds and premiums on insurance, legal fees, fees and expenses of trustees, depositaries, financial advisors, and paying agents for the bonds issued as the issuer considers necessary.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-30-040">
            <num>19.30.040</num>
            <heading>Construction and maintenance.</heading>
            <subsection eId="19-30-040__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon approval of an application and agreement as to state participation, the applicant resource developer shall submit to the commissioner of natural resources road plans and specifications for the standard of construction the applicant believes to be necessary to develop the mineral resource and protect the fish and game resources that may be affected by the road construction. Plans and specifications submitted by each applicant shall be forwarded by the commissioner of natural resources to the commissioner of transportation and public facilities and the commissioner of fish and game and, upon approval by them, the applicant may proceed with construction.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-30-040__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The applicant shall be allowed credit for the use of the applicant's workers and equipment or those of the applicant's contractor as the applicant's share of cost participation. The applicant must submit documentation satisfactory to the commissioner of transportation and public facilities to support the applicant's participation for this credit.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-30-040__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the total cost of the road is less than the original estimate, the state shall match only half of the actual cost.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-30-040__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the total cost of the road is greater than the original estimate, the applicant resource developer shall be responsible for all costs in excess of the agreed upon state participation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-30-040__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The road becomes the property of the state, and, so long as the road is used by the applicant resource developer, is open to public use, and the applicant shall bear one-half the cost of maintenance.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-30-045">
            <num>19.30.045</num>
            <heading>Canadian minerals.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.30.045.   Canadian minerals.
The state may elect, at the joint discretion of the commissioners of transportation and public facilities and natural resources, to authorize participation in a similar manner to that authorized in
AS 19.30.020
 19.30.040, in construction and maintenance of developmental access roads to the state border for the development of mineral resources that are in adjacent Canadian land if access roads are the most feasible way of developing those mineral resources, and if it is considered by the commissioners to be in the interest of the state to construct the roads; however, the state may participate up to $50,000, or up to one-third of the cost of construction and of the maintenance of these roads in the state, whichever is lower.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-30-051">
            <num>19.30.051</num>
            <heading>Regulations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.30.051.   Regulations.
The commissioner of natural resources and the commissioner of transportation and public facilities shall adopt regulations to implement the purposes of
AS 19.30.020
 19.30.051.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-30-060">
            <num>19.30.060</num>
            <heading>Purpose.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.30.060.   Purpose.
It is the purpose of
AS 19.30.060
 19.30.100 to provide access to state land that is programmed for surface disposal, and to provide access roads at the lowest possible cost.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-30-070">
            <num>19.30.070</num>
            <heading>Contracts for construction of roads.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.30.070.   Contracts for construction of roads.
The director of the division of lands may contract with private persons for the construction of roads to and on state land programmed for surface disposal that are not more than six miles from existing roads or highways.  Contracts under this section are governed by
AS 36.30
(State Procurement Code).</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-30-080">
            <num>19.30.080</num>
            <heading>Construction standards and maintenance.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.30.080.   Construction standards and maintenance.
An access road constructed under
AS 19.30.060
 19.30.100 shall be of low standard, not necessarily suitable for all weather use. The state is not under obligation to maintain an access road constructed under
AS 19.30.060
  19.30.100.  If an access road is constructed outside a municipality that has zoning ordinances, the right-of-way width for the road shall be determined by the division of lands and the Department of Transportation and Public Facilities.  If an access road is constructed within the boundaries of a municipality that has zoning ordinances, the right-of-way width shall conform to the subdivision control ordinances of the municipality. Contracts for the work on an access road are governed by
AS 36.30
(State Procurement Code).</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-30-090">
            <num>19.30.090</num>
            <heading>Payment of construction costs in land credit certificates.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.30.090.   Payment of construction costs in land credit certificates.
The cost of constructing access roads to state land shall be paid in freely transferable land credit certificates which may be applied toward the purchase or lease of any state land under the jurisdiction of the division of lands, except tide, submerged, and shoreland and land belonging to the state which have been obtained by escheat, purchase, or any means other than by general land grant.  A land credit certificate is valid for a period of 20 years after issue.  After the expiration of 20 years from date of issue the holder may not start an action against the state or any person based upon the certificate.  The method of disposing of land and resources and restrictions upon their disposal established by law or regulation are in no way affected by the use of land credit certificates.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-30-100">
            <num>19.30.100</num>
            <heading>Commissioner of natural resources may adopt regulations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.30.100.   Commissioner of natural resources may adopt regulations.
The commissioner of natural resources may adopt regulations necessary to carry out the purposes of
AS 19.30.060
 19.30.100.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-30-111">
            <num>19.30.111</num>
            <heading>Purpose.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.30.111.   Purpose.
It is the purpose of
AS 19.30.111
 19.30.251 to provide for the acquisition and construction of local service roads and trails that are not included in the approved federal-aid primary highway systems eligible for federal-state matching funds.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-30-121">
            <num>19.30.121</num>
            <heading>Regulations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.30.121.   Regulations.
The commissioner may adopt regulations necessary to carry out
AS 19.30.111
 19.30.241.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-30-127">
            <num>19.30.127</num>
            <heading>Allocation districts.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.30.127.   Allocation districts.
The state is divided into five allocation districts as follows:
(1) The boundary of allocation district one begins in Kamishak  Bay at 59° 15´ N, 154° 00´W; and travels north along longitude line 154° 00´W to latitude 63° 00´N; thence east along latitude line 63° 00´N to a point common with the boundaries of allocations districts two and five; southerly of the Denali Highway at Corkscrew Creek (Milepost 59.1); thence southerly to Prince William Sound at Fairmount Point 60° 53´45" N, 147° 27´W and inclusive of Kodiak, Afognak, Barren, Trinity, and Chirikof Islands.
(2) The boundary of allocation district two begins at and includes the point at which the Alaska Highway intersects the Alaska-Yukon border; travels northwesterly to the west abutment of the Little Tok River Bridge on Tok Cutoff Highway (Milepost 91.2); thence west to the northerly abutment of the McCallum Creek Bridge on the Richardson Highway (Milestone 202.4); thence west to a point directly north of the Denali Highway at Corkscrew Creek (Milepost 59.1); thence southwesterly to the Glenn Highway at Summit (Milepost 118) and continuing along that line to latitude 63° 00´N; thence west along latitude 63° 00´N; to longitude 154° 00´W; thence north along longitude 154° 00´W to the Arctic Ocean.
(3) The boundary of allocation district three begins in the Gulf of Alaska on longitude line 141° 00´W; thence north along longitude 141° 00´W to Boundary Point 187; thence southeasterly along the Canadian-United States border bounding Southeastern Alaska in its entirety.
(4) The boundary of allocation district four begins in the Arctic Ocean at Smith Bay 70° 54´N, 154° 19´W; on longitude line 154° 00´W; travels south along longitude 154° 00´W to latitude 59° 15´N in Kamishak Bay; thence east along latitude 59° 15´N to longitude 152° 15´W; thence southwesterly through Shelikof Strait and bounds of the entire Aleutian Chain.
(5) The boundary of allocation district five begins at the Gulf of Alaska on longitude line 141° 00´W and travels northerly along that line to the point (but not including the point) at which Alaska Highway intersects the Alaska-Yukon border; thence northwesterly to the west abutment of the Little Tok River Bridge on the Tok Cutoff Highway (Milepost 91.2); thence west to the northerly abutment of McCallum Creek Bridge on the Richardson Highway (Milepost 202.40; thence west to the point directly north of Denali Highway at Corkscrew Creek (Milepost 59.1); thence southwesterly to the Glenn Highway at Summit (Milepost 118); thence southerly to Prince William Sound at Fairmount Point 60° 53´45"N, 147° 27´W.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-30-131">
            <num>19.30.131</num>
            <heading>Allocation of funds.</heading>
            <subsection eId="19-30-131__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>During each fiscal year the commissioner shall allocate sums appropriated or otherwise designated for expenditure upon local service roads for that fiscal year among the five allocation districts in the following manner: one-half in the ratio that the area of each allocation district bears to the total area of the state and one-half in the ratio that the population of each allocation district bears to the total population of the state as shown by the latest available federal or state census or other census approved by the Department of Commerce, Community, and Economic Development.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-30-131__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall also further allocate the sums in each allocation district to the boroughs and unified municipalities within each allocation district in the following manner: one-half in the ratio that the area of each organized borough or unified municipality (excluding salt water areas) within that district bears to the total area of the allocation district and one-half in the ratio that the population of each organized borough area or each unified municipality within that district bears to the total population of the allocation district as shown by the latest available federal or state census or other census approved by the Department of Commerce, Community, and Economic Development.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-30-131__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall also further allocate portions of the sum allocated to any organized borough and to any home rule city within the organized borough in the following manner:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="19-30-131__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>one-half in the ratio that the area of each home rule city bears to the total area of the organized borough excluding salt water areas; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="19-30-131__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>one-half in the ratio that the population of each home rule city bears to the total population of the organized borough as shown by the latest available federal or state census or other census approved by the Department of Commerce, Community, and Economic Development.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-30-131__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The sums not allocated within each district to a local government under (b) and (c) of this section shall be allocated to the unorganized borough and administered by the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-30-141">
            <num>19.30.141</num>
            <heading>Acquisition and construction programs.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.30.141.   Acquisition and construction programs.
Before October 1 of each fiscal year each local government eligible for allocation of funds under
AS 19.30.131
shall submit to the commissioner for approval a five-year plan for the acquisition and construction of local service roads and trails. Before December 1 of each fiscal year the commissioner shall submit to the governor a five-year plan for the acquisition and construction of local service roads and trails, including the approved local government programs.  An organized borough shall include in its five-year plan local service road acquisition and construction programs for all cities other than home rule cities within the boundaries of the borough.  The commissioner shall include in the five-year plan local service road and trail acquisition and construction within the unorganized borough.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-30-151">
            <num>19.30.151</num>
            <heading>Local government participation.</heading>
            <subsection eId="19-30-151__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon application by a local government, local service roads and trails constructed under the provisions of
AS 19.30.111
 19.30.241 and located within the jurisdictional boundaries of a local government may be transferred to that local government upon approval by the department and after a vote of the people in the area.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-30-151__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner shall, upon request of a local government, transfer funds allocated under
AS 19.30.131
to any local government that has assumed local road powers for project cost amounts and contract award amounts submitted to the commissioner.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-30-151__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>AS 19.30.111
 19.30.241 do not prohibit a local government from participating financially in the acquisition and construction of a local service road or trail.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-30-161">
            <num>19.30.161</num>
            <heading>Design standards, rights-of-way, and widths.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.30.161.   Design standards, rights-of-way, and widths.
Design standards, rights-of-way, and widths for each local service road and trail project must have the prior approval of the commissioner, unless the project is under the supervision of a local government that has assumed local road powers. Where approval is required the commissioner must make a decision within 90 days after the Department of Transportation and Public Facilities' receipt of the local government's request.  If the project is under the supervision of a local government that has assumed road powers and the project is not located on a federal-aid secondary route, design standards, rights-of-way, and widths shall be established by the local government.  If a project under the supervision of a local government that has assumed road powers is located on a federal-aid secondary route, design standards, rights-of-way, and widths must have the prior approval of the commissioner.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-30-171">
            <num>19.30.171</num>
            <heading>Acquisition and conveyance of rights-of-way.</heading>
            <subsection eId="19-30-171__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The local government shall acquire all rights-of-way required for local service road and trail construction.  However, if the local government is unable to acquire the necessary right-of-way, the commissioner may acquire it in accordance with
AS 19.05.080
 19.05.120.  The commissioner may convey to the local government, by appropriate instrument executed in the name of the state, any land or interest in land which has been acquired by the state for the construction of local service roads or trails.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-30-171__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The costs incurred by the commissioner in acquiring this land or interest in land includes all costs and any fees incidental to acquisition.  All costs incurred in connection with the acquisition of the land or interest in land for local governments that have assumed local road powers shall be charged to the project allocation for which the land or interest in land is acquired.  Right-of-way acquisition costs incurred by the commissioner for local governments without local road powers under
AS 19.30.151</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-30-171__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>shall be charged to the project allocation for the local government for which the land or interest in land is acquired.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-30-171__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When rights-of-way for local service roads are acquired over land or interest in land owned by the state, the commissioner may make arrangements with the department having jurisdiction over the land as may be necessary to give the local government adequate rights-of-way, and any department having jurisdiction is directed to transfer the jurisdiction of the land to the commissioner.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-30-181">
            <num>19.30.181</num>
            <heading>Project agreements.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.30.181.   Project agreements.
A local government that has assumed local road powers may enter into a formal project agreement with the commissioner for the acquisition and construction of a specific project.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-30-191">
            <num>19.30.191</num>
            <heading>Letting of contracts.</heading>
            <subsection eId="19-30-191__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 15 ch 158 SLA 1980.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-30-191__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Contracts entered into by a local government that has assumed local road powers for the construction of each project shall be awarded only on the basis of the lowest responsible bid submitted by a bidder meeting established criteria of responsibility.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-30-191__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>All contracts by a local government that has not assumed local road powers must have the prior concurrence of the commissioner.  The commissioner may delegate the power to approve contracts to a local government that has assumed local road powers for the acquisition and construction of local service roads and trails.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-30-191__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (b) and (c) of this section and in
AS 44.33.300
, construction of each project shall be administered by the department in accordance with guidelines established by the commissioner by regulation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-30-201">
            <num>19.30.201</num>
            <heading>Construction.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.30.201.   Construction.
Except as provided under
AS 19.30.161
, the construction of a local service road or trail undertaken by the department or under its direct supervision under the provisions of
AS 19.30.111
 19.30.241 shall be performed according to approved design standards and is subject to the inspection and approval of the commissioner.  All construction work done and labor performed by or under the direct supervision of the department shall be in accordance with applicable state law.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-30-211">
            <num>19.30.211</num>
            <heading>Maintenance.</heading>
            <subsection eId="19-30-211__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall maintain, or cause to be maintained, any project constructed by the department under the provisions of
AS 19.30.111
 19.30.241, except that upon mutual agreement of the commissioner and the local government the responsibility for maintenance may be transferred to the local government if it is authorized to assume road maintenance powers.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-30-211__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall continue maintenance on all projects maintained by the department on January 1, 1980.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-30-211__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A local government may contract with the department for maintenance of a project.  The maximum annual maintenance cost to the local government may not exceed twice the amount of state aid to municipalities for roads.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-30-221">
            <num>19.30.221</num>
            <heading>Availability of allocated sums.</heading>
            <subsection eId="19-30-221__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>On and after the date that the commissioner has certified the sums allocated to each local government, the sums shall be available for expenditure under the provisions of this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-30-221__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>These allocated sums shall be available for expenditure for a period of five years after the close of the fiscal year for which the sums are authorized and any amounts so obligated remaining unexpended at the end of that period shall lapse and shall be available for other local service road or trail construction within that allocation district in accordance with
AS 19.30.111
 19.30.241.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-30-221__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This section applies to sums transferred under
AS 19.30.151
(b).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-30-221__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The payment of royalties required to obtain materials to construct local service road and trail projects is a valid expenditure under this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-30-241">
            <num>19.30.241</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.30.241.   Definitions.
In
AS 19.30.111
  19.30.241,
(1) construction means the building of a new road, street, or trail or the improvement of existing roads, streets or trails, and includes the necessary preliminary engineering, construction engineering and utility relocation;
(2) home rule city means a city as defined in
AS 29.04.010
;
(3) local government means an organized borough of any class, a unified municipality, or a city of any class;
(4) local service road means a public road that is used by an average of fewer than 750 vehicles each day and that is not designated as a route on the approved primary, urban, or interstate federal-aid highway system;
(5) project means an undertaking to construct a particular portion of a local service road or trail, or, if the context so implies, the particular portion of a local service road or trail so constructed;
(6) secondary road means a road that is not included in the approved federal-aid primary highway system and is being maintained by the state or local government;
(7) trail means a footpath or way on land or water that is open to public use as a matter of right whether or not a thoroughfare, particularly for dog sleds and mechanized snow vehicles.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-30-251">
            <num>19.30.251</num>
            <heading>Local government powers.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.30.251.   Local government powers.
Road construction and maintenance authority is granted to local governments, as defined in
AS 19.30.241
, which do not otherwise have that authority; however, the authority granted is limited to participation in the construction and maintenance of local service roads under
AS 19.30.111
 19.30.241.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-30-260">
            <num>19.30.260</num>
            <heading>Purpose.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.30.260.   Purpose.
The purpose of
AS 19.30.260
 19.30.320 is to facilitate funding for the upgrading, reconstruction, rehabilitation, or paving of existing subdivision roads within a road maintenance service area established under
AS 29.35.450
or under a home rule charter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-30-270">
            <num>19.30.270</num>
            <heading>Allocation of money.</heading>
            <subsection eId="19-30-270__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>During each fiscal year each municipality shall receive money from the department that has been appropriated or otherwise designated for expenditure for road improvements within the municipality, based on the total road mileage in each road maintenance service area in the municipality.  The amounts that are available shall be distributed pro rata among eligible municipalities.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-30-270__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Money allocated to a municipality under this section shall be disbursed by the municipality for road maintenance service areas based on a first come, first served priority of road maintenance service area applications, subject to a 50 percent match by each road maintenance service area.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-30-270__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Money allocated under this section shall be available for expenditure in the road maintenance service area for which the funds are authorized for a period of five years after the end of the fiscal year for which the funds are authorized.  Money allocated for a road maintenance service area that is unexpended and unobligated at the end of the five-year period shall be used for other road maintenance service areas in the same municipality in accordance with
AS 19.30.260
 19.30.320.  If there are no other road maintenance service areas in the municipality for which the money can be used, the municipality shall remit the unexpended and unobligated money to the department and it shall lapse into the general fund.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-30-270__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Fifty percent of the cost of construction in a road maintenance service area shall be paid by the road maintenance service area through road improvement district assessments, grants, or other appropriate financing means.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-30-280">
            <num>19.30.280</num>
            <heading>Eligibility.</heading>
            <subsection eId="19-30-280__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After establishing a road maintenance service area under
AS 29.35.450
, or under a home rule charter, a municipality may apply to the department for a grant as money is available for road improvements, subject to regulations adopted by the department to carry out the provisions of
AS 19.30.260
 19.30.320.  The department shall require a municipality to submit a five-year plan for the upgrading, reconstructing, rehabilitating, or paving of maintenance service area roads for approval before October 1 of each fiscal year.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-30-280__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality shall establish design standards for construction in a road maintenance service area.  An application for a grant for improving an existing road under this section which is constructed after July 1, 1984, may not be granted by the department until the existing road meets the minimum design standards of the municipality.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-30-290">
            <num>19.30.290</num>
            <heading>Administration.</heading>
            <subsection eId="19-30-290__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A contract entered into by a municipality for road construction within a road maintenance service area for which funds allocated to the municipality under
AS 19.30.260
 19.30.320 are used shall be awarded only on the basis of the lowest responsible bid by a bidder meeting established criteria of responsibility.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-30-290__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Construction under
AS 19.30.260
  19.30.320 shall be administered by the municipality in which the road maintenance service area is located.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-30-300">
            <num>19.30.300</num>
            <heading>Maintenance.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.30.300.   Maintenance.
The road maintenance service area shall be responsible for maintaining roads constructed under
AS 19.30.260
 19.30.320.  The road maintenance service area may contract with a municipality for maintenance of the roads.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-30-310">
            <num>19.30.310</num>
            <heading>Report.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.30.310.   Report.
No later than August 1 of each year, a municipality that has received money under
AS 19.30.270
shall submit a report to the department showing the use of the money by the municipality during the preceding fiscal year.  No later than December 1 of each year, the department shall prepare and submit to the governor a report showing the use of the money allocated under
AS 19.30.270
during the preceding fiscal year.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-30-320">
            <num>19.30.320</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.30.320.   Definitions.
In
AS 19.30.260
  19.30.320,
(1) construction or road improvement has the meaning given in
AS 19.59.001
and includes utility and drainage costs but excludes financial costs, right-of-way costs, and new road construction;
(2) municipality means a municipality that has road construction or maintenance powers;
(3) subdivision has the meaning given in
AS 40.15.900
.
Article 5. Rights-of-way Acquired under Former 43 U.S.C. 932.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-30-400">
            <num>19.30.400</num>
            <heading>Identification and acceptance of rights-of-way.</heading>
            <subsection eId="19-30-400__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The state claims, occupies, and possesses each right-of-way granted under former 43 U.S.C. 932 that was accepted either by the state or the territory of Alaska or by public users. A right-of-way acquired under former 43 U.S.C. 932 is available for use by the public under regulations adopted by the Department of Natural Resources unless the right-of-way has been transferred by the Department of Natural Resources to the Department of Transportation and Public Facilities, in which case the right-of-way is available for use by the public under regulations adopted by the Department of Transportation and Public Facilities.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-30-400__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Department of Natural Resources shall conduct the necessary research to identify rights-of-way that have been accepted by public users under former 43 U.S.C. 932 and that have not been previously identified, and shall annually report to the legislature by the first day of each regular session of the legislature on rights-of-way that have been identified and that are not listed in this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-30-400__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The rights-of-way listed in (d) of this section have been accepted by public users and have been identified to provide effective notice to the public of these rights-of-way. The failure to include or identify a right-of-way under (d) of this section does not relinquish any right, title, or interest the public has in a right-of-way.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-30-400__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The following rights-of-way are identified by the name of the right-of-way and the identification number the right-of-way has been assigned by the Department of Natural Resources in the Historic Trails Database, known as the RST number, which contains a complete description of the right-of-way:
RIGHT-OF-WAY NAME RST NUMBER
Cobb Lakes Trail 0001
Taylor  Humboldt0002
Hajducovich  Macomb Plateau Trail0003
Jualin Mine Road0004
Marvel Creek Cat Trail0005
Taylor Creek  Serpentine Hot Springs0006
Eureka  Rampart0007
Harrison Creek  Portage Creek0008
Coldfoot  Chandalar Lake Trail0009
Chicken  Franklin0010
Eagle  Alder Creek Trail0011
Nabesna  Chisana0012
Poorman  Ophir Route 10013
Unuk River Road0014
Long  Birch Creek Road0015
Aurora Trail (Dahl-Deering)0016
Knik Glacier Trail0017
Bettles  Wild Lake River Trail0018
Poorman  Ophir Route 20019
Wrong Way Lane (Harding Lake Trail)0020
Akiak  Crooked Creek0021
Akiakchak/Akiak  Phillips Bro-Russian Mis0022
Aniak  Tuluksak0024
Beaver  Caro0027
Bennett's Cutoff0028
Bethel  Quinhagak0030
Bethel  Kasigluk0031
Bethel  Tuluksak0032
Bluff  White Mountain0034
Boulder Creek Trail0036
Tramway Bar0038
Candle  Kiwalik0042
Rex Creek Trail0043
Chena Hot Sprgs  East Fork (Van Curlers)0046
Chickaloon  King River Road0047
Chistochina  Slate Creek0048
Chulitna Trail0052
Telaquana Trail0057
Dahl Creek Tractor Trail #10058
Crooked Creek  Aniak0059
Davidson's Landing  Taylor0060
Stephan Lake  Murder Lake0061
Dime Landing  Haycock Trail0062
Dishkaket  Kaltag0063
Donnelly  Washburn0064
Dunbar  Brooks Terminal0066
Eagle  Circle Mail Trail0067
Egegik  Kanatak0068
Elliot  Kotsina0069
Ester  Dunbar0070
Flat  Georgetown0076
Flat  Holy Cross  Anvik0077
Fortymile  Franklin0078
Murder Lake North to Ridgeline0080
Meiers Lodge  Dickey Lake0082
Batzulnetas  Suslota Pass Trail0083
Golovin  Council0084
Christian  Arctic Village0085
Goodnews Bay  Togiak0086
South Spit Goodnews Bay  Platinum Creek0087
Nakeen  Igiugig </p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-30-410">
            <num>19.30.410</num>
            <heading>Vacation of rights-of-way.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 19.30.410.   Vacation of rights-of-way.
Notwithstanding another provision of law, the Department of Natural Resources, the Department of Transportation and Public Facilities, or another agency of the state may not vacate a right-of-way acquired by the state under former 43 U.S.C. 932 unless
(1) a reasonably comparable, established alternate right-of-way or means of access exists that is sufficient to satisfy all present and reasonably foreseeable uses;
(2) the right-of-way is within a municipality, the municipal assembly or council has requested the vacation, a reasonable alternative means of access is available, and the vacation is in the best interests of the state; or
(3) the vacation is approved by the legislature.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_19-30-420">
            <num>19.30.420</num>
            <heading>Immunity from liability for damages; risk of use of right-of-way acquired under former 43 U.S.C. 932.</heading>
            <subsection eId="19-30-420__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding
AS 09.50.250
and
AS 09.65.070
, the state and its political subdivisions are not liable for damages, injury, or death arising from
AS 19.30.400
 19.30.420 and the recording of any rights-of-way identified in
AS 19.30.400
or acquired under former 43 U.S.C. 932.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="19-30-420__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A right-of-way identified under
AS 19.30.400
or acquired under former 43 U.S.C. 932 that is not designated as part of the state highway system under
AS 19.10.020
is traveled and used at the risk of the user. As to those rights-of-way and notwithstanding
AS 09.50.250
and
AS 09.65.070
, the state and a political subdivision of the state are not liable for damages, injury, or death</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="19-30-420__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>arising from the use of the right-of-way;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="19-30-420__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>arising from the failure to inspect, mark, or maintain the right-of-way;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="19-30-420__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>occurring in the right-of-way; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="19-30-420__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>associated with the right-of-way.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>