<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-5/chapter-35"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-5/chapter-35"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="5.35"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-5/chapter-35/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-5/chapter-35/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-5/chapter-35/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-5/chapter-35/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_5">
        <num>5</num>
        <heading>Amusements and Sports</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_5__chp_35">
          <num>35</num>
          <heading>Sports Facilities Grants</heading>
          <section eId="sec_05-35-010">
            <num>05.35.010</num>
            <heading>Grant of funds for sports facilities.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 05.35.010.   Grant of funds for sports facilities.
Subject to direct appropriation or through the proceeds of a bonding issue, the state shall make matching grants to municipalities of an amount equal to $50 per capita, based on the population of the municipality, to pay not more than one-half of the cost of construction of a facility to be used principally for sports.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_05-35-020">
            <num>05.35.020</num>
            <heading>Application and disbursement.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 05.35.020.   Application and disbursement.
Application for a grant under
AS 05.35.010
 05.35.070 shall be made before June 30, 1974.  Funds shall be disbursed upon demonstration that a proposed facility is of the type contemplated by
AS 05.35.010
 05.35.070 and that the applicant will pay its share of the cost of construction.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_05-35-030">
            <num>05.35.030</num>
            <heading>Maintenance and employment of facility.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 05.35.030.   Maintenance and employment of facility.
A municipality shall maintain a facility and employ it, or cause it to be employed, for the uses intended by
AS 05.35.010
 05.35.070 by direct operation, by operation through a contract manager, or by lease.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_05-35-040">
            <num>05.35.040</num>
            <heading>Power of municipality.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 05.35.040.   Power of municipality.
A municipality may own, maintain, and employ a facility constructed under
AS 05.35.010
 05.35.070.  The exercise of this power on an areawide basis is at the option of the borough and is not subject to the restrictions on acquiring additional areawide powers in
AS 29.35.300
 29.35.330.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_05-35-050">
            <num>05.35.050</num>
            <heading>Limitation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 05.35.050.   Limitation.
No more than one grant under
AS 05.35.010
 05.35.070 may be made within an organized borough.  If an organized borough refuses or fails to undertake a project within one year of July 1, 1972, a first class city within that organized borough may undertake a sports facility project.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_05-35-060">
            <num>05.35.060</num>
            <heading>Administration.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 05.35.060.   Administration.
The commissioner shall administer the grant program and in so doing liberally interpret
AS 05.35.010
 05.35.070.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_05-35-070">
            <num>05.35.070</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 05.35.070.   Definitions.
In
AS 05.35.010
 05.35.070,
(1) commissioner means the commissioner of commerce, community, and economic development;
(2) cost of construction includes, in addition to costs directly related to the project, the sum total of all costs of financing and carrying out of the project; these include, but are not limited to, the costs of all necessary studies, surveys, plans and specifications, architectural, engineering or other special services, acquisition of real property, site preparation and development, purchase, construction, reconstruction and improvement of real property, and the acquisition of machinery and equipment as may be necessary in connection with the project; an allocable portion of the administrative and operating expenses of the grantee; the cost of financing the project, including interest on bonds issued to finance the project; and the cost of other items, including any indemnity and surety bonds and premiums on insurance, legal fees, fees and expenses of trustees, depositaries, financial advisors, and paying agents for the bonds issued as the issuer considers necessary; it does not include the cost of promotion, travel, or feasibility studies;
(3) facility means a covered stadium or arena or any combination of them, or any other similar structure or structures, including related improvements such as parking areas, locker rooms, concession stands, restaurants, offices, press boxes, rest rooms, and storage areas, and including fixed or portable equipment, used in the operation of the facility;
(4) municipality means an organized borough of any class or a first class city outside an organized borough;
(5) population means the population of a municipality established by the final official 1970 U.S. Census or other reliable population data;
(6) used principally for sports means that the major use of a facility shall be for sporting events such as baseball games, rodeos, football games, soccer games, track and field meets, ice hockey matches, basketball games, and boxing and wrestling matches, viewed by spectators in substantial numbers, and that the use of a facility may be for organized participant sports and nonsports activities for which similar facilities are commonly used.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>