<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-16/chapter-43"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-16/chapter-43"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="16.43"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-16/chapter-43/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-16/chapter-43/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-16/chapter-43/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-16/chapter-43/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_16">
        <num>16</num>
        <heading>Fish and Game</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_16__chp_43">
          <num>43</num>
          <heading>Regulation of Entry into Alaska Commercial Fisheries</heading>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-010">
            <num>16.43.010</num>
            <heading>Purpose and findings of fact.</heading>
            <subsection eId="16-43-010__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>It is the purpose of this chapter to promote the conservation and the sustained yield management of Alaska's fishery resource and the economic health and stability of commercial fishing in Alaska by regulating and controlling entry of participants into the commercial fisheries in the public interest and without unjust discrimination.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-010__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The legislature finds that commercial fishing for fishery resources has reached levels of participation, on both a statewide and an area basis, that have impaired or threaten to impair the economic welfare of the fisheries of the state, the overall efficiency of the harvest, and the sustained yield management of the fishery resource.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-020">
            <num>16.43.020</num>
            <heading>Alaska Commercial Fisheries Entry Commission.</heading>
            <subsection eId="16-43-020__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>There is established the Alaska Commercial Fisheries Entry Commission as a regulatory and quasi-judicial agency of the state. The commission consists of two members appointed by the governor and confirmed by the legislature in joint session.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-020__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The governor shall designate one member of the commission as chair of the commission. The designated member serves as chair for a term of two years and may be designated chair for successive two-year terms. When there is a vacancy in the executive director position, the member serving as chair is responsible for and has authority over the internal administrative and personnel practices and procedures of the commission.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-030">
            <num>16.43.030</num>
            <heading>Term of office; vacancy and removal.</heading>
            <subsection eId="16-43-030__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The members of the commission shall be appointed for terms of four years.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-030__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A vacancy on the commission shall be filled by appointment by the governor and the appointment shall be confirmed by the legislature in joint session. Except as provided in
AS 39.05.080</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-030__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If there is a vacancy on the commission, a single commissioner may exercise all the powers and perform all the duties of the commission.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-030__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The governor may remove a commissioner from office for cause, including but not limited to incompetence, neglect of duty, or misconduct in office.  A commissioner being removed for cause shall be given a copy of the charges and afforded an opportunity to publicly present a defense in person or by counsel upon not less than 10 days' notice.  If a commissioner is removed for cause, the governor shall file with the lieutenant governor a complete statement of all charges made against the commissioner and the governor's findings based on the charges, together with a complete record of the proceedings.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-040">
            <num>16.43.040</num>
            <heading>Quorum.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 16.43.040.   Quorum.
Unless there is a vacancy on the commission, two members of the commission constitute a quorum for the transaction of business, for the performance of a duty, or for the exercise of a power of the commission.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-050">
            <num>16.43.050</num>
            <heading>Qualifications.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 16.43.050.   Qualifications.
The commission shall consist of two members with a broad range of professional experience, neither of whom has a vested economic interest in an interim-use permit, entry permit, commercial fishing vessel or gear, or in any fishery resource processing or marketing business.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-060">
            <num>16.43.060</num>
            <heading>Compensation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 16.43.060.   Compensation.
Members of the commission are in the exempt service and are entitled to a monthly salary equal to a step in Range 25 of the salary schedule in
AS 39.27.011
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-070">
            <num>16.43.070</num>
            <heading>Legal counsel.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 16.43.070.   Legal counsel.
The attorney general is the legal counsel for the commission. The attorney general shall advise the commission in legal matters arising in the discharge of its duties and represent the commission in suits to which it is a party.  However, the commission may retain additional legal counsel as appropriate.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-080">
            <num>16.43.080</num>
            <heading>Employment of personnel.</heading>
            <subsection eId="16-43-080__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission may employ those persons necessary to carry out the purposes of this chapter. Employees of the commission are in the exempt service under
AS 39.25.110
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-080__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to its staff of regular employees, the commission may contract for and engage the services of consultants, experts, and hearing officers as necessary.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-100">
            <num>16.43.100</num>
            <heading>Duties and general powers.</heading>
            <subsection eId="16-43-100__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To accomplish the purposes set out in
AS 16.43.010
, the commission shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-100__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>regulate entry into the commercial fisheries for all fishery resources in the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-100__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establish priorities for the application of the provisions of this chapter to the various commercial fisheries of the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-100__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establish administrative areas suitable for regulating and controlling entry into the commercial fisheries;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-100__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establish, for all types of gear, the maximum number of entry permits for each administrative area;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-100__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>designate, when necessary to accomplish the purposes of this chapter, particular species for which separate interim-use permits or entry permits will be issued;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-100__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establish qualifications for the issuance of entry permits;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-100__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>issue entry permits to qualified applicants;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-100__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>issue interim-use permits as provided in
AS 16.43.210
, 16.43.220, and 16.43.225;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-100__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establish, for all types of gear, the optimum number of entry permits for each administrative area;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-100__subsec_a__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>administer the buy-back program provided for in
AS 16.43.310
and 16.43.320 to reduce the number of outstanding entry permits to the optimum number of entry permits;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-100__subsec_a__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide for the transfer and reissuance of entry permits to qualified transferees;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-100__subsec_a__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide for the transfer and reissuance of entry permits for alternative types of legal gear, in a manner consistent with the purposes of this chapter;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-100__subsec_a__subsec_13">
                <num>(13)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establish and administer the collection of the annual fees provided for in
AS 16.43.160
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-100__subsec_a__subsec_14">
                <num>(14)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>administer the issuance of commercial fishing vessel licenses under
AS 16.05.490
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-100__subsec_a__subsec_15">
                <num>(15)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>issue educational entry permits to applicants who qualify under the provisions of
AS 16.43.340
 16.43.390;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-100__subsec_a__subsec_16">
                <num>(16)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establish reasonable user fees for services;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-100__subsec_a__subsec_17">
                <num>(17)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>issue landing permits under
AS 16.05.675
and regulations adopted under that section;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-100__subsec_a__subsec_18">
                <num>(18)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establish and collect annual fees for the issuance of landing permits that reasonably reflect the costs incurred in the administration and enforcement of provisions of law related to landing permits;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-100__subsec_a__subsec_19">
                <num>(19)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establish a moratorium on entry into commercial fisheries as provided in
AS 16.43.225
; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-100__subsec_a__subsec_20">
                <num>(20)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>when requested by a regional development organization formed under former
AS 44.33.895
, provide to the organization, without charge, public information contained in the commission's data with respect to relevant fisheries, including limited fisheries, fishery participants, and limited entry permit holders' harvests and earnings.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-100__subsec_a__subsec_21">
                <num>(21)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>[Repealed, § 20 ch 2 SLA 2014.]</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-100__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission may do all things necessary to the exercise of its powers under this chapter, whether or not specifically designated in this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-110">
            <num>16.43.110</num>
            <heading>Regulations and hearing procedures.</heading>
            <subsection eId="16-43-110__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission may adopt regulations, consistent with law, necessary or proper in the exercise of its powers or for the performance of its duties under this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-110__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall adopt regulations, consistent with due process of law, that govern practice and procedure and the conduct of all investigations, hearings, and proceedings that it holds.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-110__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Alaska Rules of Evidence apply to investigations, hearings, and proceedings before the commission, except when the commission determines that their application is not required in order to assure fair treatment of all parties and that the evidence is relevant and of the sort on which responsible persons are accustomed to rely in the conduct of serious matters.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-110__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission, a commissioner, or an employee authorized by the commission may administer oaths, certify to all official acts, and issue subpoenas and other process to compel the attendance of witnesses and the production of testimony, records, papers, accounts, and documents in an inquiry, investigation, hearing, or proceeding before the commission in any part of the state.  The commission may petition a court to enforce its subpoenas or other process.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-110__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall adopt regulations to provide for the correction of administrative error.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-110__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In case of a tie vote between commissioners in an adjudicatory proceeding, the decision of the hearing officer is the final administrative decision of the commission subject to review by a superior court under
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-120">
            <num>16.43.120</num>
            <heading>Application of Administrative Procedure Act.</heading>
            <subsection eId="16-43-120__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The administrative adjudication procedures of
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act) do not apply to adjudicatory proceedings of the commission except that final administrative determinations by the commission are subject to judicial review as provided in
AS 44.62.560
 44.62.570.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-120__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>AS 44.62.010
 44.62.319 and 44.62.640 apply to regulations adopted by the commission.
Article 2. Entry Permit System.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-140">
            <num>16.43.140</num>
            <heading>Permit required.</heading>
            <subsection eId="16-43-140__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not operate gear in the commercial taking of fishery resources without a valid entry permit or a valid interim-use permit issued by the commission.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-140__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A permit is not required of a crewmember or other person assisting in the operation of a unit of gear engaged in the commercial taking of fishery resources as long as the holder of the entry permit or the interim-use permit for that particular unit of gear is at all times present and actively engaged in the operation of the gear.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-140__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may hold more than one interim-use or entry permit issued or transferred under this chapter only for the following purposes:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-140__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>fishing more than one type of gear;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-140__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>fishing in more than one administrative area;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-140__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>harvesting particular species for which separate interim-use or entry permits are issued;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-140__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if authorized by regulations of the commission, fishing an entire unit of gear in a fishery in which the commission has issued entry permits for less than a unit of gear under
AS 16.43.270</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-140__subsec_c__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>consolidation of the fishing fleet for a salmon fishery; however, a person may hold not more than two entry permits for a salmon fishery under this paragraph, but the person who holds two entry permits for a salmon fishery may not engage in fishing under the second entry permit.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-150">
            <num>16.43.150</num>
            <heading>Terms and conditions of entry permit; annual renewal.</heading>
            <subsection eId="16-43-150__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as may be otherwise provided under
AS 16.43.270
(d), an entry permit authorizes the permittee to operate a unit of gear within a specified fishery.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-150__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The holder of an entry permit shall have the permit in possession at all times when engaged in the operation of gear for which it was issued.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-150__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each entry permit is issued for a term of one year and is renewable annually.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-150__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Failure to renew an entry permit for a period of two years from the year of last renewal results in a forfeiture of the entry permit to the commission, except as waived by the commission for good cause.  An entry permit may not be renewed until the fees for each preceding year during which the entry permit was not renewed are paid. However, failure to renew an entry permit in a year in which there is an administrative closure for the entire season for a specific fishery is good cause not to renew the entry permit.  The commission shall waive the payment of fees for that year.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-150__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An entry permit constitutes a use privilege that may be modified or revoked by the legislature without compensation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-150__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except for permits that are not transferable under
AS 16.43.170
(e), an entry permit survives the death of the holder.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-150__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in
AS 16.10.333
 16.10.338,
AS 44.81.215
, 44.81.225, and 44.81.231  44.81.250, an entry permit may not be</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-150__subsec_g__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>pledged, mortgaged, leased, or encumbered in any way;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-150__subsec_g__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>transferred with any retained right of repossession or foreclosure, or on any condition requiring a subsequent transfer; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-150__subsec_g__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>attached, distrained, or sold on execution of judgment or under any other process or order of any court, except as provided in
AS 16.43.170</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-150__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and (h).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-150__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless an entry permit holder has expressed a contrary intent in a will that is probated, the commission shall, upon the death of the permit holder, transfer the permanent permit by right of survivorship directly to the surviving spouse or, if no spouse survives, to a natural person designated by the permit holder on a form provided by the commission. If no spouse survives and if the person designated on the form, if any, does not survive, the permit passes as part of the permit holder's estate. A designation under this subsection must be acknowledged before a person authorized to administer an oath under
AS 09.63.010
or must be witnessed by two persons who are qualified under
AS 13.12.505
to witness the will of the permit holder. Except as provided in
AS 16.10.333
 16.10.337,
AS 44.81.215
, and 44.81.231  44.81.250, the permit is exempt from the claims of creditors of the estate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-150__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The holder of a transferable or nontransferable entry permit or of an interim-use permit may voluntarily relinquish the permit to the commission.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-160">
            <num>16.43.160</num>
            <heading>Fees.</heading>
            <subsection eId="16-43-160__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as specifically provided in this section, the commission shall establish annual fees for the issuance and annual renewal of entry permits or interim-use permits.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-160__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission may charge interest at a rate not to exceed the legal rate of interest established in
AS 45.45.010
on fees more than 60 days overdue.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-160__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The annual base fee for issuance or renewal of an entry permit or an interim-use permit may not be less than $30 or more than $3,000. The annual base fee must reasonably reflect the different rates of economic return for different fisheries. In addition to the annual base fee established by the commission under this subsection, a nonresident shall pay an annual nonresident surcharge for the issuance or renewal of one or more entry permits or interim-use permits. The commission shall establish the annual nonresident surcharge by regulation at an amount that is as close as is practicable to the maximum allowed by law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-160__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The holder of a permit whose household income, assets, and financial resources fall within the eligibility standards for the food stamp program under 7 U.S.C. 2011  2025, as amended, is subject to an annual base fee for the issuance or renewal of an entry permit or an interim-use permit that is equal to 50 percent of the annual base fee that the permit holder would otherwise pay under (c) of this section. In addition to the reduced annual base fee under this subsection, a nonresident who qualifies for a reduced fee under this subsection shall pay the annual nonresident surcharge established under (c) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-170">
            <num>16.43.170</num>
            <heading>Transfer of entry permits.</heading>
            <subsection eId="16-43-170__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in
AS 16.10.333
 16.10.338 and in
AS 44.81.231
 44.81.250, entry permits and interim-use permits are transferable only through the commission as provided in this section and
AS 16.43.180
and under regulations adopted by the commission. An involuntary transfer of an entry permit in a manner inconsistent with the statutes of this state and the regulations of the commission is void.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-170__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (e) of this section, the holder of an entry permit may transfer the permit to another person or to the commission upon 60 days notice of intent to transfer under regulations adopted by the commission. No sooner than 60 days nor later than 12 months from the date of notice to the commission, the holder of an entry permit may transfer the permit. If the proposed transferee, other than the commission, can demonstrate the present ability to participate actively in the fishery and the transfer does not violate any provision of this chapter or regulations adopted under this chapter, and if a certificate for the permit under
AS 16.10.333
(b)(1)  (2), 16.10.338, or
AS 44.81.231</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-170__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>is not in effect, the commission shall approve the transfer and reissue the entry permit to the transferee provided that neither party is prohibited by law from participating in the transfer.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-170__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 10 ch 135 SLA 2002.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-170__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 9 ch 73 SLA 1977.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-170__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The holder of an entry permit who qualified for that entry permit in a priority classification designated under
AS 16.43.250</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-170__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>may not transfer that permit.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-170__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The permanent transfer of an entry permit is void if proceedings in which commercial fishing privileges and licenses may be suspended under
AS 16.05.710
are pending against the permit holder at the time of transfer unless the transfer of the entry permit is allowed by order of the court in which the proceedings are pending.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-170__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may request the commission to transfer an entry permit due to an execution on a permit holder's interest in that permit if the execution is to enforce a lien recorded with the commission under
AS 25.27.230
(c). The request shall be made in the form and manner provided in this chapter and regulations adopted under this chapter. The commission may deny a request for transfer of an entry permit due to an execution of a holder's interest in that permit if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-170__subsec_g__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the execution does not comply with legal requirements or otherwise is not valid;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-170__subsec_g__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the transfer violates this chapter or regulations adopted under this chapter;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-170__subsec_g__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the proposed transferee or other party to the transfer is prohibited by law from participating in the transaction;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-170__subsec_g__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a certificate for the permit under
AS 16.10.333</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-170__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>is in effect at the time of the proposed transfer;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-170__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the proposed transferee of the entry permit, other than the commission, cannot demonstrate the present ability to actively participate in the fishery; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-170__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the holder of the entry permit as shown by the records of the commission demonstrates, under regulations adopted by the commission, that the entry permit is a necessary means of support for the holder and those dependent upon the holder.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-170__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (g) of this section, the commission may not approve a request for transfer of an entry permit after an execution sale unless the parties to the transfer offer the commission a right to purchase the permit at the same price and on the same terms as those of that execution sale. If the commission exercises its right to purchase the permit, the permit then shall be transferred to the commission.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-180">
            <num>16.43.180</num>
            <heading>Emergency transfers.</heading>
            <subsection eId="16-43-180__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall adopt regulations providing for the temporary emergency transfer of entry permits and interim-use permits when illness, disability, death, required military or government service, or other unavoidable hardship prevents the permit holder from participating in the fishery. To alleviate hardship pending a final determination of the permit holder's eligibility for an entry permit, the commission shall adopt regulations providing for the temporary emergency transfer of an interim-use permit issued under
AS 16.43.210</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-180__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or 16.43.225.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-180__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall adopt regulations providing for the temporary transfer of an entry permit upon the death of the permittee pending final disposition of the permit as a part of the permittee's estate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-200">
            <num>16.43.200</num>
            <heading>Administrative areas.</heading>
            <subsection eId="16-43-200__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall establish administrative areas suitable for regulating and controlling entry into the commercial fisheries.  The commission shall make the administrative areas reasonably compatible with the geographic areas for which specific commercial fishing regulations are adopted by the Board of Fisheries.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-200__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission may modify or change the boundaries of administrative areas when necessary and consistent with the purposes of this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-210">
            <num>16.43.210</num>
            <heading>Interim-use permit; qualifications.</heading>
            <subsection eId="16-43-210__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For each fishery that is not subject to a maximum number of entry permits under
AS 16.43.240
and not subject to a moratorium under
AS 16.43.225
, the commission shall issue interim-use permits under regulations adopted by the commission to all applicants who can establish their present ability to participate actively in the fishery for which they are making application.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-210__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before the issuance of the maximum number of entry permits for a given fishery, the commission may issue an interim-use permit to an applicant who may later become eligible for an entry permit under
AS 16.43.270
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-210__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To the extent that the commissioner of fish and game authorizes it under
AS 16.05.050
(a)(9), the commission may grant an interim-use permit to a person to engage in the commercial taking from a fishery on an experimental basis.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-210__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The sustained yield management and economic health of the following fisheries is severely impaired as a result, among other factors, of too many units of gear participating in the commercial harvest:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-210__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Bristol Bay registration area    drift gillnet fishery;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-210__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Cook Inlet registration area    drift gillnet fishery;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-210__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Prince William Sound registration area    drift gillnet fishery.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-210__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 69 ch 6 SLA 1984.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-220">
            <num>16.43.220</num>
            <heading>Terms and conditions of interim-use permits.</heading>
            <subsection eId="16-43-220__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall adopt regulations specifying the dates and places of application, the procedures to be followed in renewal of the interim-use permit including the time, place of its renewal, and for any other purpose incident to the administration of interim-use permits for that fishery.  An interim-use permit shall expire upon the final determination of the holder's eligibility for an entry permit.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-220__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 9 ch 73 SLA 1977.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-220__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The holder of an interim-use permit shall have the permit in possession at all times when engaged in the operation of the gear for which it was issued.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-225">
            <num>16.43.225</num>
            <heading>Moratorium on new entrants into certain fisheries.</heading>
            <subsection eId="16-43-225__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subject to (b) of this section, the commission may establish a moratorium on new entrants into a fishery</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-225__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>that has experienced recent increases in fishing effort that are beyond a low, sporadic level of effort;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-225__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>that has achieved a level of harvest that may be approaching or exceeding the maximum sustainable level for the fishery; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-225__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for which there is insufficient biological and resource management information necessary to promote the conservation and sustained yield management of the fishery.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-225__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission may establish a moratorium on new entrants into a fishery described in (a) of this section if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-225__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the commissioner of fish and game, subject to
AS 16.05.251</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-225__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the commission finds that
(A) the fishery has reached a level of participation that may threaten the conservation and the sustained yield management of the fishery resource and the economic health and stability of commercial fishing; and
(B) the commission has insufficient information to conclude that the establishment of a maximum number of entry permits under
AS 16.43.240
would further the purposes of this chapter.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-225__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission may establish a moratorium under this section for a continuous period of up to four years. A fishery that has been subject to a moratorium under this section may not be subjected to a subsequent moratorium under this section unless five years have elapsed since the previous moratorium expired.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-225__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>While a moratorium is in effect, the commission shall conduct investigations to determine whether a maximum number of entry permits should be established under
AS 16.43.240
by</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-225__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>conducting research into conditions in the fishery;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-225__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>consulting with the Department of Fish and Game and the Board of Fisheries; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-225__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>consulting with participants in the fishery.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-225__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall establish by regulation the qualifications for applicants for an interim-use permit for a fishery subject to a moratorium under this section. The qualifications must include the minimum requirements for past or present participation and harvest in the fishery. The commission may not issue an interim-use permit for a fishery subject to a moratorium under this section unless the applicant can satisfy the qualifications established under this subsection and establish the present ability and intent to participate actively in the fishery.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-227">
            <num>16.43.227</num>
            <heading>Southeast Alaska Dungeness crab fishery.</heading>
            <subsection eId="16-43-227__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission may establish a moratorium on new entrants into the southeast Alaska Dungeness crab fishery for a continuous period of up to four years without complying with
AS 16.43.225</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-227__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p> (c). While the moratorium is in effect, the commission shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-227__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>conduct the investigation required under
AS 16.43.225</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-227__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>establish by regulation the qualifications for an interim-use permit for the fishery, including minimum requirements for past or present participation and harvest in the fishery; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-227__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>issue interim-use permits for the fishery to applicants who satisfy the qualifications established under (2) of this subsection and who establish the present ability and intent to participate actively in the fishery.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-227__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding
AS 16.43.225
, for the purposes of this chapter</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-227__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an interim-use permit issued under this section shall be treated as an interim-use permit issued under
AS 16.43.225
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-227__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a moratorium established under this section shall be treated as a moratorium established under
AS 16.43.225
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-228">
            <num>16.43.228</num>
            <heading>Southeast Alaska dive fisheries.</heading>
            <subsection eId="16-43-228__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 4 ch 125 SLA 1996.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-228__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 4 ch 125 SLA 1996.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-228__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 4 ch 125 SLA 1996.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-228__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 4 ch 125 SLA 1996.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-228__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 22 ch 9 SLA 2014.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-228__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding
AS 16.43.225
, for the purposes of this chapter,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-228__subsec_f__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an interim-use permit issued under this section shall be treated as an interim-use permit issued under
AS 16.43.225
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-228__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a moratorium established under this section shall be treated as a moratorium established under
AS 16.43.225
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-228__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission may not consider participation in a fishery, subject to a moratorium on entry under this section, that occurs during the period of the moratorium in determining eligibility for an entry permit that may be issued for the fishery after termination of the moratorium.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-230">
            <num>16.43.230</num>
            <heading>Designation of distressed fisheries.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 16.43.230.   Designation of distressed fisheries.
Pending the determination of maximum numbers of entry permits under
AS 16.43.240
and before the initial issue of entry permits under
AS 16.43.270
, the commission shall designate as distressed fisheries those for which it estimates that the optimum number of entry permits will be less than the highest number of units of gear fished in that fishery during any one of the four years immediately preceding January 1, 1973.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-240">
            <num>16.43.240</num>
            <heading>Determination of the maximum number of entry permits for initial issue.</heading>
            <subsection eId="16-43-240__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in
AS 16.43.270
(a), the maximum number of entry permits for a distressed fishery designated under
AS 16.43.230
shall be the highest number of units of gear fished in that fishery during any one of the four years immediately preceding January 1, 1973.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-240__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the commission finds that a fishery, not designated as a distressed fishery under
AS 16.43.230
or not subject to a moratorium under
AS 16.43.225
, has reached levels of participation that require the limitation of entry under
AS 16.43.140
 16.43.330 in order to achieve the purposes of this chapter, the commission shall establish the maximum number of entry permits for that fishery.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-240__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the commission finds that a fishery subject to a moratorium under
AS 16.43.225
has reached levels of participation that require the limitation of entry under
AS 16.43.140
 16.43.330 in order to achieve the purposes of this chapter, the commission shall establish the maximum number of entry permits for that fishery.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-250">
            <num>16.43.250</num>
            <heading>Standards for initial issue of entry permits.</heading>
            <subsection eId="16-43-250__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Following the establishment of the maximum number of units of gear for a particular fishery under
AS 16.43.240
, the commission shall adopt regulations establishing qualifications for ranking applicants for entry permits according to the degree of hardship that they would suffer by exclusion from the fishery. The regulations shall define priority classifications of similarly situated applicants based upon a reasonable balance of the following hardship standards:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-250__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>degree of economic dependence upon the fishery, including, when reasonable for the fishery, the percentage of income derived from the fishery, reliance on alternative occupations, availability of alternative occupations, investment in vessels and gear;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-250__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>extent of past participation in the fishery, including, when reasonable for the fishery, the number of years of participation in the fishery, and the consistency of participation during each year.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-250__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall designate in the regulations those priority classifications of applicants who would suffer significant economic hardship by exclusion from the fishery.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-250__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall designate in the regulations those priority classifications of applicants who would suffer only minor economic hardship by exclusion from the fishery.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-250__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If an individual eligible to apply under
AS 16.43.260</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-250__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>has applied during application periods established under
AS 16.43.260</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-250__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>for two or more entry permits under
AS 16.43.260</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-250__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or (e) for the same specific fishery resource and the same specific type of gear in different administrative areas, but has failed to qualify for an entry permit for that type of fishery resource and gear, the individual's cumulative qualifications may be credited to the fishery for which the individual is most qualified. The commission shall issue an entry permit to the individual for the fishery if the individual's cumulative qualifications result in placing the individual in a category designated in (b) of this section. The qualifications credited to a fishery under this subsection may not be considered for the purpose of ranking the applicant under (a)-(c) of this section for any other fishery.  The commission may not revoke any permit previously issued notwithstanding the issuance of permits in excess of the maximum number established under
AS 16.43.230
 16.43.240 as a result of this subsection.  In this subsection, fishery includes all salmon fisheries of the state for which a maximum number of entry permits has been established by the commission under
AS 16.43.240
(b).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-250__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the cumulative qualifications of an individual under (d) of this section include points granted by the commission under (a) of this section for more than one fishery and the number of points required to place an applicant in the priority classification under (b) of this section is not the same for each of the fisheries, the commission shall obtain a quotient for the individual by dividing the number of points the individual has been granted for each fishery by the number of points needed to place an applicant in a priority classification under (b) of this section for that fishery.  If the sum of the quotients obtained under this subsection equals or exceeds 1.00, the individual is entitled to a permit under (d) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-260">
            <num>16.43.260</num>
            <heading>Application for initial issue of entry permits.</heading>
            <subsection eId="16-43-260__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall accept applications for entry permits only from applicants who have harvested fishery resources commercially while participating in the fishery as holders of gear licenses issued under former
AS 16.05.536
 16.05.670 or interim-use permits under
AS 16.43.210</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-260__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or 16.43.225 before the qualification date established in (d), (e), or (f) of this section. The commission may specify by regulation the calendar years of participation that will be considered for eligibility purposes.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-260__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall establish the opening and closing dates, places and form of application for entry permits for each fishery.  The commission may require the submission of specific verified evidence establishing the applicant's qualifications under the regulations adopted under
AS 16.43.250
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-260__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When an applicant is unable to establish qualifications for an entry permit by submitting the specific verified evidence required in the application by the commission, the applicant may request and obtain an administrative adjudication of the application according to the procedures established in
AS 16.43.110
(b).  At the hearing the applicant may present alternative evidence of qualifications for an entry permit.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-260__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (e) or (f) of this section, an applicant shall be assigned to a priority classification based solely upon the applicant's qualifications as of January 1, 1973.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-260__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (f) of this section, when the commission establishes the maximum number of entry permits for a particular fishery under
AS 16.43.240
after January 1, 1975, an applicant shall be assigned to a priority classification based solely upon the applicant's qualifications as of January 1 of the year during which the commission establishes the maximum number of entry permits for the fishery for which application is made.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-260__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the commission establishes the maximum number of entry permits under
AS 16.43.240
for a fishery that is subject to a moratorium under
AS 16.43.225
, an applicant for an entry permit for the fishery shall be assigned to a priority classification based solely upon the applicant's qualifications as of the effective date of the statute or regulation establishing the moratorium.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-270">
            <num>16.43.270</num>
            <heading>Initial issuance of entry permits.</heading>
            <subsection eId="16-43-270__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall issue entry permits, for each fishery, first to all qualified applicants in the priority classifications designated under
AS 16.43.250</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-270__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and then to qualified applicants in order of descending priority classification, until the number of entry permits issued equals the maximum number of entry permits established under
AS 16.43.230
and 16.43.240 for each fishery, except that a person within a priority classification specified under
AS 16.43.250</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-270__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>may not be denied an entry permit.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-270__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If, within the lowest priority classification of qualified applicants to which some entry permits may be issued, there are more applicants than there are entry permits to be issued, then the allocation of entry permits within that priority classification shall be by lottery.  However, the commission shall issue entry permits to all qualified applicants in that priority classification if the total number of permits issued for the fishery does not exceed the maximum number of entry permits established under
AS 16.43.240
for that fishery by more than five percent or 10 permits, whichever is greater.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-270__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If, at the time entry permits are issued, some applicants are still appealing the findings of an administrative adjudication under
AS 16.43.260
, a sufficient number of permits shall be reserved out of the permits to be issued to protect the rights of those applicants, assuming all the appeals will be resolved in favor of the applicants.  In the event that all appeals are not resolved in favor of the applicants, the remaining entry permits shall be allocated to the next most qualified applicants as provided in (a) and (b) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-270__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission may restrict the fishing capacity employed under an entry permit if, before the initial issuance of entry permits for a fishery, the commission determines that the fishing capacity in the fishery must be limited to achieve the purposes of this chapter, establishes criteria for determining the fishing capacity that is allowed under an entry permit, and establishes how fishing capacity will be measured. The maximum fishing capacity allowed under an entry permit must be based upon past participation in the fishery by the initial recipient of the entry permit during a period, specified by the commission, preceding the qualification date established under
AS 16.43.260
. The commission may define fishing capacity in terms of quantity of fishing gear, a proportion of the maximum amount of gear that can be utilized in the fishery under regulations of the Board of Fisheries, fishing vessel size or other characteristics, or other factors determined by the commission to affect the amount of fishing effort in the fishery. The recipient or transferee of an entry permit issued subject to this subsection may not exceed the fishing capacity allowed under the entry permit.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-290">
            <num>16.43.290</num>
            <heading>Optimum number of entry permits.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 16.43.290.   Optimum number of entry permits.
Following the issuance of entry permits under
AS 16.43.270
, the commission shall establish the optimum number of entry permits for each fishery based upon a reasonable balance of the following general standards:
(1) the number of entry permits sufficient to maintain an economically healthy fishery that will result in a reasonable average rate of economic return to the fishermen participating in that fishery, considering time fished and necessary investments in vessels and gear;
(2) the number of entry permits necessary to harvest the allowable commercial take of the fishery resource during all years in an orderly, efficient manner, and consistent with sound fishery management techniques;
(3) the number of entry permits sufficient to avoid serious economic hardship to those currently engaged in the fishery, considering other economic opportunities reasonably available to them.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-300">
            <num>16.43.300</num>
            <heading>Revisions of optimum number of entry permits.</heading>
            <subsection eId="16-43-300__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission may increase or decrease the optimum number of entry permits for a fishery when one or more of the following conditions makes a change desirable considering the purposes of this chapter:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-300__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an established long-term change in the biological condition of the fishery has occurred that substantially alters the optimum number of entry permits permissible applying the standards set out in
AS 16.43.290
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-300__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an established long-term change in market conditions has occurred, directly affecting the fishery, that substantially alters the optimum number of entry permits permissible under the standards set out in
AS 16.43.290
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-300__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the commission decreases the optimum number of entry permits for a fishery, the number of entry permits may be reduced only under the voluntary buy-back provisions set out in
AS 16.43.310
and 16.43.320.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-310">
            <num>16.43.310</num>
            <heading>Establishment of buy-back funds and permit buy-back assessments.</heading>
            <subsection eId="16-43-310__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the optimum number of entry permits is less than the number of entry permits outstanding in a fishery, the commission may establish a buy-back program, a buy-back plan, and a buy-back fund for that fishery.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-310__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission may establish by regulation a permit buy-back assessment for each fishery for which the commission has established a buy-back fund under (a) of this section. The amount of the assessment may not exceed seven percent of the value, as defined in
AS 43.75.290
, of fish that a permit holder in the fishery subject to the assessment removes from the state or transfers to a buyer in the state. The Department of Revenue shall collect an assessment established under this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-310__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall expend money appropriated to a buy-back fund for the purpose of reducing the number of entry permits in the fishery to the optimum number, at a rate to be established by the commission. The legislature may appropriate interest accrued on the money in a buy-back fund to that fund. Except as provided in
AS 16.43.320
, money appropriated to a buy-back fund does not lapse.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-320">
            <num>16.43.320</num>
            <heading>Administration of the buy-back program.</heading>
            <subsection eId="16-43-320__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>when the commission determines that the amount of revenue collected through the assessment is sufficient to purchase the number of entry permits necessary to achieve the optimum number of entry permits in the fishery and to offset the reasonable costs of the buy-back program for the fishery, including repayment of any debt the commission was authorized to incur to capitalize the buy-back fund for the fishery. The unexpended balance of appropriations made to a buy-back fund for a fishery shall lapse back into the fund from which the money was appropriated at the end of the fiscal year in which the buy-back program is terminated.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-330">
            <num>16.43.330</num>
            <heading>Issuance of new entry permits; appropriations related to fleet reduction.</heading>
            <subsection eId="16-43-330__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the number of outstanding entry permits for a fishery is less than the optimum number established under
AS 16.43.290
, the commission shall issue new entry permits to applicants who are presently able to engage actively in the fishery until the optimum number is reached.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-330__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall determine equitable methods of issuance, as appropriate, under (a) of this section that assure the receipt of fair market value for the permits issued.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-330__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a salmon fishery association qualified under
AS 16.40.250
takes part in a fleet reduction program by expending money or incurring debt to contract with permit holders to relinquish the holders' entry permits under
AS 16.43.150
(i), and if this section requires additional permits to be issued for the same fishery in which the fleet reduction program was implemented, the legislature may appropriate any resulting revenue to the association for reimbursement of money expended or to retire any outstanding debt incurred for fleet reduction purposes. An appropriation under this subsection must be made within 30 years after the date the money was expended or debt incurred.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-340">
            <num>16.43.340</num>
            <heading>Educational entry permits.</heading>
            <subsection eId="16-43-340__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to entry permits and interim-use permits, the commission may issue educational entry permits to public, private, or denominational educational institutions accredited by the Department of Education and Early Development or accredited institutions, career, or vocational programs approved by the Alaska Commission on Postsecondary Education, or full-time nonprofit residential child care facilities licensed by the Department of Health, division of social services, if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-340__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the program is offered to students at the junior high school level or above;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-340__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the issuance of an educational entry permit is reasonably necessary to the instruction of students under courses offered by the applicant for the educational entry permit;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-340__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the program is offered by an institution that is located in the state and has been in operation for at least two years; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-340__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the institution offering the program is not a correspondence institution.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-340__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An educational entry permit may only be used in a program conducted by the recipient of the permit for the purpose of training students in the methods of commercial fishing.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-340__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission may issue educational entry permits notwithstanding the establishment of maximum or optimum numbers under
AS 16.43.240
and 16.43.290.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-351">
            <num>16.43.351</num>
            <heading>Term and conditions of educational entry permit.</heading>
            <subsection eId="16-43-351__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Educational entry permits may be applied for on an annual basis and shall be issued for a term of one year. The permits are nontransferable.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-351__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A recipient may be issued an educational entry permit valid for designated fisheries in the administrative area the commission determines to be appropriate, considering the nature of the educational program and the location of the educational or vocational institution.  The recipient of an educational entry permit may not be issued an educational entry permit in more than one administrative area except as issued by the commission in its discretion upon good cause shown.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-351__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An educational entry permit issued under
AS 16.43.340
may be used by any agent or employee authorized by the recipient of the educational entry permit.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-351__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Annual fees for educational entry permits shall be as specified by commission regulation under the authority of
AS 16.43.160
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-361">
            <num>16.43.361</num>
            <heading>Disposition of fish.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 16.43.361.   Disposition of fish.
Fish caught under the authority of an educational entry permit are the property of the recipient of the permit.  The recipient may sell the fish and use the proceeds to pay for the costs of the training program. Revenues generated from the sale of fish harvested under an educational entry permit shall be paid to the general fund to the extent the revenues exceed costs of the training program.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-371">
            <num>16.43.371</num>
            <heading>Accounting of harvest.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 16.43.371.   Accounting of harvest.
The recipient of an educational entry permit shall report to the commission costs and earnings, amount of harvest, and other information the commission requires to monitor training programs of recipients of educational entry permits.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-381">
            <num>16.43.381</num>
            <heading>Adoption of regulations.</heading>
            <subsection eId="16-43-381__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Use privileges granted under
AS 16.43.340
 16.43.390 are subject to the regulations of the Board of Fisheries, which may adopt regulations exclusively applicable to the use of educational entry permits.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-381__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall adopt regulations relating to the issuance of educational entry permits, establishing eligibility criteria for recipients of the permits, and such other matters as are reasonably necessary to implement
AS 16.43.340
 16.43.390.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-390">
            <num>16.43.390</num>
            <heading>Definition of recipient.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 16.43.390.   Definition of recipient.
In
AS 16.43.340
 16.43.390, recipient means the entity to which an educational entry permit is issued.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-400">
            <num>16.43.400</num>
            <heading>Special harvest area entry permits.</heading>
            <subsection eId="16-43-400__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to entry permits, interim-use permits, and educational permits, the commission may issue special harvest area entry permits to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-400__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>holders of private, nonprofit hatchery permits issued by the Department of Fish and Game under
AS 16.10.400
 16.10.475 for salmon; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-400__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>nonprofit organizations holding a permit under
AS 16.12
for a shellfish enhancement project.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-400__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission may issue special harvest area entry permits notwithstanding the establishment of maximum or optimum numbers under
AS 16.43.240
and 16.43.290.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-410">
            <num>16.43.410</num>
            <heading>Term and conditions of special harvest area entry permits.</heading>
            <subsection eId="16-43-410__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Special harvest area entry permits may be applied for on an annual basis and shall be issued for a term of one year.  A permit is nontransferable.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-410__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A special harvest area entry permit may only be issued for the applicable area designated by the Department of Fish and Game as a special harvest area.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-410__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The annual fee for a special harvest area entry permit shall be specified by commission regulation under the authority of
AS 16.43.160
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-420">
            <num>16.43.420</num>
            <heading>Disposition of fish.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 16.43.420.   Disposition of fish.
Fish caught under the authority of a special harvest area entry permit are the property of the permit holder.  The permit holder may sell the fish if the proceeds are used in the manner described in
AS 16.10.450
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-430">
            <num>16.43.430</num>
            <heading>Authorized gear.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 16.43.430.   Authorized gear.
For the purposes of harvesting salmon or shellfish, a special harvest area entry permit holder may employ any fishing gear designated as legal gear in the applicable special harvest area by the Board of Fisheries.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-440">
            <num>16.43.440</num>
            <heading>Adoption of regulations.</heading>
            <subsection eId="16-43-440__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Use privileges granted under
AS 16.43.400
 16.43.440 are subject to the regulations of the Board of Fisheries.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-440__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission, after consultation with the Department of Fish and Game, shall adopt regulations that are reasonably necessary to implement
AS 16.43.400
 16.43.440.
Article 7. Vessel Permit System for Bering Sea Hair Crab Fishery.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-451">
            <num>16.43.451</num>
            <heading>Bering Sea hair crab fishery vessel permit system.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 16.43.451.   Bering Sea hair crab fishery vessel permit system.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-451">
            <num>16.43.451</num>
            <heading>Bering Sea hair crab fishery vessel permit system.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 16.43.451.   Bering Sea hair crab fishery vessel permit system.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-461">
            <num>16.43.461</num>
            <heading>Initial issuance of vessel permits.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 16.43.461.   Initial issuance of vessel permits.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-461">
            <num>16.43.461</num>
            <heading>Initial issuance of vessel permits.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 16.43.461.   Initial issuance of vessel permits.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-471">
            <num>16.43.471</num>
            <heading>Optimum number range of vessel permits.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 16.43.471.   Optimum number range of vessel permits.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-471">
            <num>16.43.471</num>
            <heading>Optimum number range of vessel permits.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 16.43.471.   Optimum number range of vessel permits.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-481">
            <num>16.43.481</num>
            <heading>Transfer and expiration of vessel entry permits.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 16.43.481.   Transfer and expiration of vessel entry permits.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-481">
            <num>16.43.481</num>
            <heading>Transfer and expiration of vessel entry permits.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 16.43.481.   Transfer and expiration of vessel entry permits.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-491">
            <num>16.43.491</num>
            <heading>Substitution of vessels.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 16.43.491.   Substitution of vessels.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-491">
            <num>16.43.491</num>
            <heading>Substitution of vessels.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 16.43.491.   Substitution of vessels.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-501">
            <num>16.43.501</num>
            <heading>Renewal of vessel permits.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 16.43.501.   Renewal of vessel permits.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-501">
            <num>16.43.501</num>
            <heading>Renewal of vessel permits.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 16.43.501.   Renewal of vessel permits.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-511">
            <num>16.43.511</num>
            <heading>Vessel permit fees.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 16.43.511.   Vessel permit fees.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-511">
            <num>16.43.511</num>
            <heading>Vessel permit fees.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 16.43.511.   Vessel permit fees.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-521">
            <num>16.43.521</num>
            <heading>General Bering Sea hair crab vessel permit provisions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 16.43.521.   General Bering Sea hair crab vessel permit provisions.
Article 8. Point System for Commercial Fishing Violations in Salmon Fisheries.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-521">
            <num>16.43.521</num>
            <heading>General Bering Sea hair crab vessel permit provisions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 16.43.521.   General Bering Sea hair crab vessel permit provisions.
Article 8. Point System for Commercial Fishing Violations in Salmon Fisheries.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-850">
            <num>16.43.850</num>
            <heading>Point system.</heading>
            <subsection eId="16-43-850__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For the purpose of identifying frequent violators of commercial fishing laws in salmon fisheries, the commission shall adopt regulations establishing a uniform system for the suspension of commercial salmon fishing privileges by assigning demerit points for convictions for violations of commercial fishing laws in salmon fisheries that are reported to the commission under
AS 16.43.880
. The commission shall assess demerit points against a permit holder for each violation of commercial fishing laws in a salmon fishery in accordance with (b) and (c) of this section. The commission shall assess points against a permit holder for the salmon fishery in which the violation of commercial fishing laws occurred.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-850__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall assess demerit points against a permit holder for a conviction of a violation of commercial fishing laws in a salmon fishery under
AS 16.05.722
,  16.05.723,  16.05.831;
AS 16.10.055
,  16.10.070   16.10.090,  16.10.100,  16.10.110,  16.10.120,  16.10.200   16.10.220, and  16.10.760   16.10.790 for the following violations in accordance with this schedule:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-850__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>fishing in closed waters  ..... 6 points;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-850__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>fishing during closed season or period  ..... 6 points;.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-850__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>fishing with more than the legal amount of gear  ..... 4 points;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-850__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>fishing with gear not allowed in fishery  ..... 6 points;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-850__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>fishing before expiration of transfer period  ..... 6 points;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-850__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>interfering with commercial fishing gear  ..... 4 points;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-850__subsec_b__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>fishing with more than the legal amount of gear on vessel  ..... 4 points;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-850__subsec_b__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>improper operation of fishing gear  ..... 4 points;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-850__subsec_b__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>permit holder not present when required  ..... 4 points;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-850__subsec_b__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>fishing with underlength or overlength vessel  ..... 6 points;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-850__subsec_b__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>wanton waste of fishery resources  ..... 4 points.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-850__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (b) of this section, if a permit holder's first conviction of a violation of commercial fishing laws in a salmon fishery in a 36-month period is a conviction under
AS 16.05.722
, the number of demerit points assessed against the permit holder for the violation must be one-half of the points assessed for the violation under (b) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-850__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall suspend a permit holder's commercial salmon fishing privileges for a salmon fishery for a period of</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-850__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>one year if the permit holder accumulates 12 or more points during any consecutive 36-month period as a result of convictions for violations of commercial fishing laws in the salmon fishery;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-850__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>two years if the permit holder accumulates 16 or more points during any consecutive 36-month period as a result of convictions for violations of commercial fishing laws in the salmon fishery;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-850__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>three years if the permit holder accumulates 18 or more points during any consecutive 36-month period as a result of convictions for violations of commercial fishing laws in the salmon fishery.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-855">
            <num>16.43.855</num>
            <heading>Assessment of points.</heading>
            <subsection eId="16-43-855__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notice of each assessment of points shall be given to the permit holder. Notice shall also be given to the permit holder before the expiration of a suspension of commercial salmon fishing privileges under
AS 16.43.850</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-855__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>that subsequent violations of commercial fishing laws in the salmon fishery may result in further suspensions of the permit. The notice may be given by first class mail.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-855__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The time periods provided for in
AS 16.43.850
for the accumulation of points shall be based on the date of conviction, either on a plea of guilty, nolo contendere, or a forfeiture of bail or collateral, or as a result of a trial, for violation of a commercial salmon fishing law.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-855__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The assessment of points against a permit holder by the commission under
AS 16.43.850
 16.43.895 is in addition to, and not in substitution for, other provisions of this title and is not a substitute for any penalty imposed by a court.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-855__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If points are assessed against a permit holder who holds a commercial fishing permit for a salmon fishery under an emergency transfer approved by the commission under
AS 16.43.180
, the same number of points shall also be assessed against the transferor of the permit. Points assessed against the transferor of the permit under this subsection shall be included in calculations made under
AS 16.43.850
(d).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-860">
            <num>16.43.860</num>
            <heading>Suspension.</heading>
            <subsection eId="16-43-860__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A permit holder whose commercial salmon fishing privileges for a salmon fishery are suspended under
AS 16.43.850
 16.43.895 may not obtain an entry permit or interim-use permit for that salmon fishery during the period of the suspension of the privileges. During the period for which the permit holder's privilege to obtain an entry permit or interim-use permit for a salmon fishery is suspended under this section, the commission may not issue a permit card to the permit holder for that fishery.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-860__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A permit holder whose privilege of obtaining a commercial fishing permit for a salmon fishery is suspended under
AS 16.43.850
 16.43.895 may not</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-860__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>engage in the salmon fishery under a crewmember license; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-860__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>lease or rent the permit holder's interest in a boat to another person if the boat would be used in the salmon fishery for which the permit holder's fishing privileges are suspended.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-860__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If, during the period for which a permit holder's commercial fishing privileges for a salmon fishery are suspended, the commission establishes a limited entry system for the salmon fishery, the permit holder shall be eligible to obtain an entry permit for that fishery to the extent that the permit holder qualifies for the entry permit under regulations adopted by the commission. If the permit holder qualifies for an entry permit for the fishery, the commission shall withhold issuance of the entry permit until the period of the suspension imposed under
AS 16.43.850
 16.43.895 has expired.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-860__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission may not transfer a commercial fishing permit for a salmon fishery under an emergency transfer under
AS 16.43.180
if, at the time of the application for the emergency transfer, the permit holder's commercial salmon fishing privileges for the salmon fishery have been suspended.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-870">
            <num>16.43.870</num>
            <heading>Notice and appeal.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 16.43.870.   Notice and appeal.
The commission shall provide notice of determinations of the commission under
AS 16.43.850
 16.43.895. Respondents may request a hearing under regulations adopted by the commission under
AS 16.43.110
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-880">
            <num>16.43.880</num>
            <heading>Required notice to commission.</heading>
            <subsection eId="16-43-880__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A court that convicts a person of a violation of commercial fishing laws under this title or under a regulation adopted under this title in a salmon fishery shall forward a record of the conviction to the commission on a weekly basis.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-880__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A conviction on a plea of nolo contendere accepted by the court or a forfeiture of bail or collateral deposited to secure a defendant's appearance in court that has not been vacated, or as a result of trial, is a conviction for purposes of
AS 16.43.850
 16.43.895.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-895">
            <num>16.43.895</num>
            <heading>Definitions forAS 16.43.850 16.43.895.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 16.43.895.   Definitions for
AS 16.43.850
 16.43.895.
In
AS 16.43.850
 16.43.895,
(1) commercial fishing law means a statute or regulation that regulates the conduct of a person engaged in commercial fishing activities by establishing requirements relating to fishing licenses and permits; catch records and reports; size, nature, quantity, or use of fishing vessels, sites, and gear; time, place, or manner of taking fishery resources; possession, transportation, sale, barter, or waste of fishery resources; or other aspects of commercial fishing;
(2) commercial fishing permit means an entry permit or an interim-use permit issued under this chapter;
(3) commercial salmon fishing privileges means the privilege of participating in an activity for which a commercial fishing permit to take salmon is required and the privilege of obtaining a commercial fishing permit to take salmon;
(4) permit holder includes the holder of a commercial fishing permit as the result of an emergency transfer, an applicant for a commercial fishing permit if the applicant's commercial fishing permit was suspended under
AS 16.43.850
 16.43.895, and a person whose privilege of obtaining a commercial fishing permit for a fishery is suspended under
AS 16.43.850
 16.43.895.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-940">
            <num>16.43.940</num>
            <heading>Exempted activities.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 16.43.940.   Exempted activities.
This chapter does not apply to activities authorized by a permit issued under
AS 16.40.100
or 16.40.120.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-945">
            <num>16.43.945</num>
            <heading>Commercial fishing privileges exempt from claims of creditors.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 16.43.945.   Commercial fishing privileges exempt from claims of creditors.
Except as provided in
AS 16.10.333
 16.10.338,
AS 16.43.170
(g),
AS 44.81.215
, and 44.81.231  44.81.250, commercial fishing privileges granted under this chapter, including entry permits, are exempt from claims of creditors, including claims under
AS 09.38.065
and
AS 45.29.408
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-950">
            <num>16.43.950</num>
            <heading>Applications of regulations of Board of Fisheries.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 16.43.950.   Applications of regulations of Board of Fisheries.
Nothing in this chapter limits the powers of the Board of Fisheries, including the power to determine legal types of gear and the power to establish size limitations or other uniform restrictions applying to a certain type of gear. Holders of interim-use permits or entry permits issued under this chapter are subject to all regulations adopted by the Board of Fisheries.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-955">
            <num>16.43.955</num>
            <heading>Hearings in proximity to Board of Fisheries meetings.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 16.43.955.   Hearings in proximity to Board of Fisheries meetings.
When practicable, a commission hearing that deals with the subject of limiting entry to a fishery shall be held on the same dates on which, and in the same building or in a building adjacent to the building in which, a Board of Fisheries meeting is being held.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-960">
            <num>16.43.960</num>
            <heading>Commission revocation or suspension of permits.</heading>
            <subsection eId="16-43-960__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission may revoke, suspend, or transfer all entry or interim-use permits held by a person who knowingly provides or assists in providing false information, or fails to correct false information provided to the commission for the purpose of obtaining a benefit for self or another, including the issuance, renewal, duplication, or transfer of an entry or interim-use permit, or vessel license. The commission may suspend that person's eligibility to hold an entry or interim-use permit for a period not to exceed three years, and may impose an administrative fine of not more than $5,000 on the person. The commission may also impose an administrative fine of not more than $5,000 on an entity whose officers, employees, representatives, or agents knowingly provide or assist in providing false information, or fail to correct false information provided, to the commission for the purpose of obtaining a benefit.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-960__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall serve the respondent personally or by certified or registered mail with a notice to show cause why the proposed action should not take place.  The notice to show cause must</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-960__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>be supported by an affidavit, which may be made on information or belief, setting out the facts that are the basis of the proposed actions;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-960__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide for a least 30 days' notice of the place, date, and time of the hearing where the respondent may present evidence in opposition to the proposed action; unless waived in writing by the respondent, the hearing shall be held within the judicial district in which the respondent resides if the respondent resides in the state; the hearing place shall be at the discretion of the commission for those respondents residing outside the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-960__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>specify the statutes or regulations violated;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-960__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>state with particularity the action proposed to be taken;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-960__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>indicate to the respondent that the respondent's ability to permanently transfer the permits that are the subject of the show cause proceedings has been suspended as of the date of the notice and will continue to be suspended until the exhaustion of all administrative and judicial remedies; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-960__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide other information the commission considers proper.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-960__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A permit subject to show cause proceedings under this section may not be transferred after the date of the notice in (b) of this section pending exhaustion of all administrative and judicial remedies arising from action taken under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-960__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except when there is a vacancy as provided in
AS 16.43.030
(c), the show cause hearing shall be conducted before a quorum of commissioners and shall be presided over by a hearing officer appointed by the commission who shall rule on the presentation of evidence and other procedural matters. Hearings shall be conducted in accordance with regulations adopted under
AS 16.43.110
(b).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-960__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The failure of a respondent properly served under (b) of this section to appear at the hearing is not grounds for setting aside any commission action taken.  However, the commission may in its discretion order a continuance or second hearing.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-960__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 8 ch 22 SLA 1985.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-960__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The provisions of this section apply to conduct occurring after January 1, 1973, but do not affect a permit held by a person who is a bona fide purchaser.  Failure to correct false information is a continuing offense.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-960__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Judicial review of commission determinations under this section is in accordance with
AS 44.62.560
 44.62.570; however, if a hearing de novo is granted under
AS 44.62.570
(d), the hearing may, in the discretion of the court, be had with a jury sitting if application for the jury hearing is filed with the court no later than 10 days after service of the notice of appeal.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-960__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An entry permit revoked by the commission under this section that is pledged as security for a loan under
AS 16.10.333
or
AS 44.81.231
shall be reassigned or sold as provided in
AS 16.10.337
or
AS 44.81.250
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-960__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall immediately cancel a limited entry permit card issued to a debtor under a loan made under
AS 16.10.300
 16.10.370 when the commission receives a certificate of loan termination containing a copy of the</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-960__subsec_j__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>notice required by
AS 16.10.335</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-960__subsec_j__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>notice that, if the debtor has filed bankruptcy, the automatic stay issued is no longer in effect and the debtor has not reaffirmed the debt.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-970">
            <num>16.43.970</num>
            <heading>Penalties.</heading>
            <subsection eId="16-43-970__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who violates a provision of this chapter or a regulation adopted under this chapter  is, upon conviction, guilty of a class B misdemeanor and is punishable by a fine of not more than $5,000 for a first conviction, and a fine of not more than $10,000 for a second or third conviction. Upon a first or second conviction under this subsection, the court may in its discretion also order the commission to suspend the commercial fishing privileges of the person for a period of not more than three years and to revoke one or more or all commercial fishing permits held by the person. Upon a third or subsequent conviction under this subsection, the person is also subject to a loss of commercial fishing privileges as provided under (i) of this section. This subsection does not apply to violations of
AS 16.43.140
(a).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-970__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who knowingly makes a false statement to the commission for the purpose of obtaining a benefit, including the issuance, renewal, duplication, or transfer of an entry or interim-use permit or vessel license or a person who assists another by knowingly making a false statement to the commission for the purpose of obtaining a benefit for another, is guilty of the crime of unsworn falsification in the second degree as set out in
AS 11.56.210
. Upon conviction, the person is also subject to suspension of commercial fishing privileges and revocation of commercial fishing permits under (i) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-970__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 12 ch 47 SLA 1981.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-970__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a permit holder is charged by the state with violating a provision of this chapter or a regulation adopted under this chapter, the holder may not transfer any interim-use or entry permit under
AS 16.43.170
until after the final adjudication or dismissal of the charges.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-970__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding any other provision of this section, an interim-use or entry permit may not be transferred while under suspension, without the consent of the commission.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-970__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A commercial fishing entry permit revoked under this section that is pledged as security for a loan under
AS 16.10.333
, or 16.10.338, or
AS 44.81.231
shall be reassigned as provided in
AS 16.10.337
or
AS 44.81.250
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-970__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who violates the provisions of
AS 16.43.140</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-970__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>is</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-970__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>upon a first conviction, guilty of a class B misdemeanor and may be sentenced to a definite term of imprisonment of not more than 90 days, or forfeiture of the person's fishing vessel, or both, and shall be sentenced to a fine of not less than $5,000 nor more than $10,000 and loss of commercial fishing privileges under (i) of this section;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-970__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>upon a second conviction, guilty of a class A misdemeanor and may be sentenced to a definite term of imprisonment of not more than one year, and shall be sentenced to a fine of not less than $10,000 nor more than $20,000, forfeiture of the person's fishing vessel, and loss of commercial fishing privileges under (i) of this section;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-970__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>upon a third or subsequent conviction, guilty of a class A misdemeanor and may be sentenced to a definite term of imprisonment of not more than one year, and shall be sentenced to a fine of not less than $20,000 nor more than $50,000, forfeiture of the person's fishing vessel, and loss of commercial fishing privileges under (i) of this section.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-970__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person convicted of violating the provisions of
AS 16.43.140</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-970__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>forfeits the value of the fishery resources found on board the person's vessel at the time of the violation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-970__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon the conviction of a person for an offense described under (a), (b), or (g) of this section, the court shall immediately notify the commission of the conviction. The notice provided by the court shall be accompanied by an order suspending commercial fishing privileges and revoking commercial fishing permits under (a) of this section, as appropriate. The commission shall, upon receipt of</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-970__subsec_i__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an order from the court under (a) of this section, suspend the commercial fishing privileges of a person for the period set by the court and revoke commercial fishing permits held by the person as directed by the court;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-970__subsec_i__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a notice from the court that a person has been convicted of a third or subsequent violation of (a) of this section, suspend all commercial fishing privileges of the person for a period of three years from the date of conviction and revoke all commercial fishing permits held by the person;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-970__subsec_i__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a notice from the court that a person has been convicted of a violation described under (b) of this section, suspend all commercial fishing privileges of the person for a period of three years from the date of conviction and revoke all commercial fishing permits held by the person;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-970__subsec_i__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a notice from the court that a person has been convicted of a violation described under (g)(1) of this section, suspend all commercial fishing privileges of the person for a period of one year from the date of conviction;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-970__subsec_i__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a notice from the court that a person has been convicted of a violation described under (g)(2) of this section, suspend all commercial fishing privileges of the person for a period of two years from the date of conviction;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-970__subsec_i__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a notice from the court that a person has been convicted of a violation described under (g)(3) of this section, suspend all commercial fishing privileges of the person for a period of five years from the date of conviction.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-970__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-970__subsec_j__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>commercial fishing permit means an entry permit or an interim-use permit issued under this chapter;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-970__subsec_j__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>commercial fishing privileges means the privilege of participating in an activity for which a commercial fishing permit is required and the privilege of obtaining a commercial fishing permit.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-975">
            <num>16.43.975</num>
            <heading>Public disclosure of certain documents prohibited.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 16.43.975.   Public disclosure of certain documents prohibited.
Documents submitted to the commission containing information relating to an individual's personal finances and information supplied by individuals for research purposes, produced in response to requests by the commission, are not subject to public disclosure.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-980">
            <num>16.43.980</num>
            <heading>Report and recommendations.</heading>
            <subsection eId="16-43-980__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall prepare an annual report and notify the legislature that it is available. The report must include but not be limited to the following:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-980__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a progress report on the reduction of entry permits to optimum levels;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="16-43-980__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>recommendations for additional legislation relating to the regulation of entry of participants and vessels into Alaska commercial fisheries.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="16-43-980__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 37 ch 14 SLA 1987.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_16-43-990">
            <num>16.43.990</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 16.43.990.   Definitions.
In this chapter,
(1) commission means the Alaska Commercial Fisheries Entry Commission;
(2) economically healthy fishery means a fishery that yields a sufficient rate of economic return to the fishermen participating in it to provide for, among other things, the following:
(A) maintenance of vessels and gear in satisfactory and safe operating condition; and
(B) ability and opportunity to improve vessels, gear and fishing techniques, including, when permissible, experimentation with new vessels, new gear, and new techniques;
(3) entity means a corporation, company, partnership, firm, association, organization, joint venture, trust, society, or other legal entity other than a natural person;
(4) fishery means the commercial taking of a specific fishery resource in a specific administrative area with a specific type of gear; however, the commission may designate a fishery to include more than one specific administrative area, gear type, or fishery resource;
(5) gear means the specific apparatus used in the commercial harvest of a species, including but not limited to purse seines, drift gill nets, set gill nets, and troll gear;
(6) optimum number includes an optimum range of numbers;
(7) person means a natural person; person does not include a corporation, company, partnership, firm, association, organization, joint venture, trust, society, or other legal entity other than a natural person;
(8) present ability to actively participate means the person applying for a permit is physically able to harvest fish in the fishery and has reasonable access to commercial fishing gear of the type utilized in that fishery;
(9) priority classification means the allocation of potential permit applicants into reasonable groupings of similarly situated applicants and the priority ranking of those groupings according to the extent to which they satisfy the standards of preference;
(10) type of gear means a customary and identifiable classification of gear and shall include:
(A) those classifications for which separate regulations were adopted by the Board of Fisheries and for which separate gear licenses were required by former
AS 16.05.550
  16.05.630; and
(B) distinct subclassifications of gear such as power troll gear and hand troll gear;
(11) unit of gear means the maximum amount of a specific type of gear that can be fished by a person under regulations established by the Board of Fisheries defining the legal requirements for that type of gear.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>