<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-13/chapter-16"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-13/chapter-16"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="13.16"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-13/chapter-16/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-13/chapter-16/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-13/chapter-16/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-13/chapter-16/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_13">
        <num>13</num>
        <heading>Decedents' Estates, Guardianships, Transfers, Trusts, and Health Care Decisions</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_13__chp_16">
          <num>16</num>
          <heading>Probate of Wills and Administration</heading>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-005">
            <num>13.16.005</num>
            <heading>Devolution of estate at death; restrictions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.005.   Devolution of estate at death; restrictions.
The power of a person to leave property by will, and the rights of creditors, devisees, and heirs to the property are subject to the restrictions and limitations contained in
AS 13.06

AS 13.36
to facilitate the prompt settlement of estates. Upon the death of a person, that person's real and personal property devolves to the persons to whom it is devised by the last will or to those indicated as substitutes for them in cases involving lapse, renunciation, or other circumstances affecting the devolution of testate estates, or in the absence of testamentary disposition, to the heirs, or to those indicated as substitutes for them in cases involving renunciation or other circumstances affecting devolution of intestate estates, subject to homestead allowance, exempt property and family allowance, to rights of creditors, elective share of the surviving spouse, and to administration.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-010">
            <num>13.16.010</num>
            <heading>Necessity of order of probate for will.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.010.   Necessity of order of probate for will.
Except as provided in
AS 13.16.680
, to be effective to prove the transfer of property or to nominate an executor, a will must be declared to be valid by an order of informal probate by the registrar or by an adjudication of probate by the court.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-015">
            <num>13.16.015</num>
            <heading>Necessity of appointment for administration.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.015.   Necessity of appointment for administration.
Except as otherwise provided in
AS 13.21
, to acquire the powers and undertake the duties and liabilities of a personal representative of a decedent, a person must be appointed by order of the court or registrar, qualify, and be issued letters. Administration of an estate is commenced by the issuance of letters.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-020">
            <num>13.16.020</num>
            <heading>Claims against decedent; necessity of administration.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.020.   Claims against decedent; necessity of administration.
A proceeding to enforce a claim against the estate of a decedent or the decedent's successors may not be revived or commenced before the appointment of a personal representative.  After the appointment and until distribution, all proceedings and actions to enforce a claim against the estate are governed by the procedure prescribed by this chapter.  After distribution a creditor whose claim has not been barred may recover from the distributees as provided in
AS 13.16.635
or from a former personal representative individually liable as provided in
AS 13.16.640
.  This section has no application to a proceeding by a secured creditor of the decedent to enforce a right to the security except as to any deficiency judgment that might be sought in the proceeding.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-025">
            <num>13.16.025</num>
            <heading>Proceedings affecting devolution and administration; jurisdiction of subject matter.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.025.   Proceedings affecting devolution and administration; jurisdiction of subject matter.
Persons interested in decedents' estates may apply to the registrar for determination in the informal proceedings provided in this chapter, and may petition the court for orders in formal proceedings within the court's jurisdiction including those described in this chapter. The court has exclusive jurisdiction of formal proceedings to determine how decedents' estates subject to the laws of this state are to be administered, expended, and distributed. The court has concurrent jurisdiction of any other action or proceeding concerning a succession or to which an estate, through a personal representative, may be a party, including actions to determine title to property alleged to belong to the estate, and of any action or proceeding in which property distributed by a personal representative or its value is sought to be subjected to rights of creditors or successors of the decedent.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-030">
            <num>13.16.030</num>
            <heading>Proceedings within the exclusive jurisdiction of court; service; jurisdiction over persons.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.030.   Proceedings within the exclusive jurisdiction of court; service; jurisdiction over persons.
In proceedings within the exclusive jurisdiction of the court where notice is required by
AS 13.06

AS 13.36
or by rule, and in proceedings to construe probated wills or determine heirs which proceedings concern estates that have not been and cannot at the time of these proceedings be opened for administration, interested persons may be bound by the orders of the court in respect to property in or subject to the laws of this state by notice in conformity with
AS 13.06.110
.  An order is binding as to all who are given notice of the proceeding though fewer than all interested persons are notified.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-035">
            <num>13.16.035</num>
            <heading>Scope of proceedings; proceedings independent; exception.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.035.   Scope of proceedings; proceedings independent; exception.
Unless supervised administration as described in
AS 13.16.215
  13.16.235 is involved,
(1) each proceeding before the court or registrar is independent of any other proceeding involving the same estate;
(2) petitions for formal orders of the court may combine various requests for relief in a single proceeding if the orders sought may be finally granted without delay; except as required for proceedings that are particularly described by other sections of this chapter, no petition is defective because it fails to embrace all matters that might then be the subject of a final order;
(3) proceedings for probate of wills or adjudications of no will may be combined with proceedings for appointment of personal representatives; and
(4) a proceeding for appointment of a personal representative is concluded by an order making or declining the appointment.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-040">
            <num>13.16.040</num>
            <heading>Probate, testacy, and appointment proceedings; ultimate time limit.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-16-040__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An informal probate or appointment proceeding or formal testacy or appointment proceeding, other than a proceeding to probate a will previously probated at the testator's domicile and appointment proceedings relating to an estate in which there has been a prior appointment, may not be commenced more than three years after the decedent's death, except</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-040__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if a previous proceeding was dismissed because of doubt about the fact of the decedent's death, appropriate probate, appointment, or testacy proceedings may be maintained at any time after the dismissal upon a finding that the decedent's death occurred before the initiation of the previous proceeding and the applicant or petitioner has not delayed unduly in initiating the subsequent proceeding;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-040__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>appropriate probate, appointment, or testacy proceedings may be maintained in relation to the estate of an absent, disappeared, or missing person for whose estate a conservator has been appointed, at any time within three years after the conservator becomes able to establish the death of the protected person;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-040__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a proceeding to contest an informally probated will and to secure appointment of the person with legal priority for appointment in the event the contest is successful, may be commenced within the later of 12 months from the informal probate or three years from the decedent's death;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-040__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an informal appointment or a formal testacy or appointment proceeding may be commenced after the three years if proceedings concerning the succession or estate administration have not occurred within the three-year period after the decedent's death, but the personal representative may not possess estate assets as provided in
AS 13.16.380
beyond that necessary to confirm title to the assets in the successors to the estate and claims other than expenses of administration may not be presented against the estate; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-040__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a formal testacy proceeding may be commenced at any time after three years from the decedent's death for the purpose of establishing an instrument to direct or control the ownership of property passing or distributable after the decedent's death from a person other than the decedent when the property is to be appointed by the terms of the decedent's will or is to pass or be distributed as a part of the decedent's estate or its transfer is otherwise to be controlled by the terms of the decedent's will.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-040__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The limitations in (a) of this section do not apply to proceedings to construe probated wills or determine heirs of an intestate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-040__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In cases under (a)(1) or (2) of this section, the date on which a testacy or appointment proceeding is properly commenced is considered to be the date of the decedent's death for purposes of other limitations provisions of
AS 13.06

AS 13.36
that relate to the date of death.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-045">
            <num>13.16.045</num>
            <heading>Statutes of limitation on decedent's cause of action.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.045.   Statutes of limitation on decedent's cause of action.
No statute of limitation running on a cause of action belonging to a decedent that had not been barred as of the date of death shall apply to bar a cause of action surviving the decedent's death sooner than four months after death.  A cause of action that, but for this section, would have been barred less than four months after death, is barred after four months unless tolled.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-055">
            <num>13.16.055</num>
            <heading>Venue for first and subsequent estate proceedings; location of property.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-16-055__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Venue for the first informal or formal testacy or appointment proceedings after a decedent's death is</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-055__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in the judicial district where the decedent was domiciled at the time of death; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-055__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if the decedent was not domiciled in this state, in any judicial district where
(A) property of the decedent was located at the time of death; or
(B) a fiduciary who is subject to the laws of this state and who comes into the control of property owned by the decedent at the time of death resides or has its principal place of business.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-055__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Venue for all subsequent proceedings within the exclusive jurisdiction of the court is in the place where the initial proceeding occurred, unless the initial proceeding has been transferred as provided in
AS 13.06.070
or (c) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-055__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the first proceeding was informal, on application of an interested person and after notice to the proponent in the first proceeding, the court, upon finding that venue is elsewhere, may transfer the proceeding and the file to the other court.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-055__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For the purpose of aiding determinations concerning location of assets that may be relevant in cases involving nondomiciliaries, a debt, other than one evidenced by investment or commercial paper or other instrument in favor of a nondomiciliary, is located where the debtor resides or, if the debtor is a person other than an individual, at the place where it has its principal office.  Commercial paper, investment paper, and other instruments are located where the instrument is.  An interest in property held in trust is located where the trustee may be sued.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-060">
            <num>13.16.060</num>
            <heading>Appointment or testacy proceedings; conflicting claim of domicile in another state.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.060.   Appointment or testacy proceedings; conflicting claim of domicile in another state.
If conflicting claims as to the domicile of a decedent are made in a formal testacy or appointment proceeding commenced in this state, and in a testacy or appointment proceeding after notice pending at the same time in another state, the court of this state must stay, dismiss, or permit suitable amendment in, the proceeding here unless it is determined that the local proceeding was commenced before the proceeding elsewhere.  The determination of domicile in the proceeding first commenced must be accepted as determinative in the proceeding of this state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-065">
            <num>13.16.065</num>
            <heading>Priority among persons seeking appointment as personal representative.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-16-065__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Whether the proceedings are formal or informal, persons who are not disqualified have priority for appointment in the following order:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-065__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the person with priority as determined by a probated will, including a person nominated by a power conferred in a will;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-065__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the surviving spouse of the decedent who is a devisee of the decedent;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-065__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>other devisees of the decedent;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-065__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the surviving spouse of the decedent;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-065__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>other heirs of the decedent;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-065__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>45 days after the death of the decedent, any creditor.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-065__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An objection to an appointment can be made only in formal proceedings.  In case of objection the priorities stated in (a) of this section apply except that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-065__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if the estate appears to be more than adequate to meet exemptions and costs of administration but inadequate to discharge anticipated unsecured claims, the court, on petition of creditors, may appoint any qualified person;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-065__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in case of objection to appointment of a person other than one whose priority is determined by will by an heir or devisee appearing to have a substantial interest in the estate, the court may appoint a person who is acceptable to heirs and devisees whose interests in the estate appear to be worth in total more than half of the probable distributable value, or, in default of this accord, any suitable person.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-065__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person entitled to letters under (a)(2)  (5) of this section, and a person aged 18 and over who would be entitled to letters but for the person's age, may nominate a qualified person to act as personal representative.  Any person aged 18 and over may renounce the right to nominate or to an appointment by appropriate writing filed with the court.  When two or more persons share a priority, those of them who do not renounce must concur in nominating another to act for them, or in applying for appointment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-065__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Conservators of the estates of protected persons, or if there is no conservator, any guardian except a guardian ad litem of a minor or incapacitated person, may exercise the same right to nominate, to object to another's appointment, or to participate in determining the preference of a majority in interest of the heirs and devisees that the protected person or ward would have if qualified for appointment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-065__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Appointment of one who does not have priority, including priority resulting from renunciation or nomination determined under this section, may be made only in formal proceedings. Before appointing one without priority, the court must determine that those having priority, although given notice of the proceedings, have failed to request appointment or to nominate another for appointment, and that administration is necessary.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-065__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>No person is qualified to serve as a personal representative who is</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-065__subsec_f__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>under the age of 19;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-065__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a person whom the court finds unsuitable in formal proceedings.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-065__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A personal representative appointed by a court of the decedent's domicile has priority over all other persons except where the decedent's will nominates different persons to be personal representative in this state and in the state of domicile.  The domiciliary personal representative may nominate another, who shall have the same priority as the domiciliary personal representative.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-065__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This section governs priority for appointment of a successor personal representative but does not apply to the selection of a special administrator.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-070">
            <num>13.16.070</num>
            <heading>Demand for notice of order or filing concerning decedent's estate.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.070.   Demand for notice of order or filing concerning decedent's estate.
Any person desiring notice of any order or filing pertaining to a decedent's estate in which the person has a financial or property interest, may file a demand for notice with the court at any time after the death of the decedent stating the name of the decedent, the nature of the demandant's interest in the estate, and the demandant's address or that of the demandant's attorney.  The clerk shall mail a copy of the demand to the personal representative if one has been appointed. After filing of a demand, no order or filing to which the demand relates shall be made or accepted without notice as prescribed in
AS 13.06.110
to the demandant or the demandant's attorney. The validity of an order that is issued or a filing that is accepted without compliance with this requirement is not affected by the error, but the petitioner receiving the order or the person making the filing may be liable for any damage caused by the absence of notice.  The requirement of notice arising from a demand under this provision may be waived in writing by the demandant and shall cease upon the termination of the demandant's interest in the estate.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-080">
            <num>13.16.080</num>
            <heading>Informal probate or appointment proceedings; application; contents.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-16-080__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Applications for informal probate or informal appointment shall be directed to the registrar, and verified by the applicant to be accurate and complete to the best of the applicant's knowledge and belief as to the following information:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-080__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>every application for informal probate of a will or for informal appointment of a personal representative other than a special or successor representative, must contain the following:
(A) a statement of the interest of the applicant;
(B) the name and age of the decedent, the date of death of the decedent, the judicial district and state of the decedent's domicile at the time of death, and the names and addresses of the spouse, children, heirs, and devisees and the ages of any who are minors so far as known or ascertainable with reasonable diligence by the applicant;
(C) if the decedent was not domiciled in the state at the time of death, a statement showing venue;
(D) a statement identifying and indicating the address of any personal representative of the decedent appointed in this state or elsewhere whose appointment has not been terminated;
(E) a statement indicating whether the applicant has received a demand for notice, or is aware of any demand for notice of any probate or appointment proceeding concerning the decedent that may have been filed in this state or elsewhere;
(F) a statement that the time limit for informal probate as provided in
AS 13.16.080
  13.16.130 has not expired either because three years or less have passed since the decedent's death, or, if more than three years from death have passed, that circumstances as described by
AS 13.16.040
authorizing tardy probate or appointment have occurred;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-080__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an application for informal probate of a will must state the following in addition to the statements required by (1) of this subsection:
(A) that the original of the decedent's last will is in the possession of the court, or accompanies the application, or that an authenticated copy of a will probated in another jurisdiction accompanies the application;
(B) that the applicant, to the best of the applicant's knowledge, believes the will to have been validly executed;
(C) that after the exercise of reasonable diligence, the applicant is unaware of any instrument revoking the will, and that the applicant believes that the instrument that is the subject of the application is the decedent's last will;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-080__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an application for informal appointment of a personal representative to administer an estate under a will must describe the will by date of execution and state the time and place of probate or the pending application or petition for probate; the application for appointment must adopt the statements in the application or petition for probate and state the name, address, and priority for appointment of the person whose appointment is sought;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-080__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an application for informal appointment of an administrator in intestacy must state in addition to the statements required by (1) of this subsection:
(A) that after the exercise of reasonable diligence the applicant is unaware of any unrevoked testamentary instrument relating to property having a situs in this state under
AS 13.06.060
, or a statement why any such instrument of which the applicant may be aware is not being probated;
(B) the priority of the person whose appointment is sought and the names of any other persons having a prior or equal right to the appointment under
AS 13.16.065
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-080__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an application for appointment of a personal representative to succeed a personal representative appointed under a different testacy status must refer to the order in the most recent testacy proceeding, state the name and address of the person whose appointment is sought and of the person whose appointment will be terminated if the application is granted, and describe the priority of the applicant;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-080__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an application for appointment of a personal representative to succeed a personal representative who has tendered a resignation as provided in
AS 13.16.290</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-080__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>By verifying an application for informal probate or informal appointment, the applicant submits personally to the jurisdiction of the court in any proceeding for relief from fraud relating to the application, or for perjury, that may be instituted against the applicant.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-085">
            <num>13.16.085</num>
            <heading>Informal probate; duty of registrar; effect of informal probate.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.085.   Informal probate; duty of registrar; effect of informal probate.
Upon receipt of an application requesting informal probate of a will, the registrar, upon making the findings required by
AS 13.16.090
, shall issue a written statement of informal probate if at least 120 hours have elapsed since the decedent's death.  Informal probate is conclusive as to all persons until superseded by an order in a formal testacy proceeding.  No defect in the application or procedure relating to it that leads to informal probate of a will renders the probate void.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-090">
            <num>13.16.090</num>
            <heading>Informal probate; proof and findings required.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-16-090__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In an informal proceeding for original probate of a will, the registrar shall determine whether</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-090__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the application is complete;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-090__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the applicant has made oath or affirmation that the statements contained in the application are true to the best of the applicant's knowledge and belief;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-090__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the applicant appears from the application to be an interested person as defined in
AS 13.06.050
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-090__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>on the basis of the statements in the application, venue is proper;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-090__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an original, duly executed and apparently unrevoked will is in the registrar's possession;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-090__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>any notice required by
AS 13.16.070
has been given and that the application is not within
AS 13.16.095
; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-090__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>it appears from the application that the time limit for original probate has not expired.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-090__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The application shall be denied if it indicates that a personal representative has been appointed in another judicial district of this state or, except as provided in (d) of this section, if it appears that this or another will of the decedent has been the subject of a previous probate order.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-090__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A will that appears to have the required signatures and that contains an attestation clause showing that requirements of execution under
AS 13.12.502
or 13.12.506 have been met shall be probated without further proof. In other cases, the registrar may assume execution if the will appears to have been properly executed, or the registrar may accept a sworn statement or affidavit of a person having knowledge of the circumstances of execution, whether or not the person was a witness to the will.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-090__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Informal probate of a will that has been previously probated elsewhere may be granted at any time upon written application by any interested person, together with deposit of an authenticated copy of the will and of the statement probating it from the office or court where it was first probated.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-090__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A will from a place that does not provide for probate of a will after death and that is not eligible for probate under (a) of this section, may be probated in this state upon receipt by the registrar of a duly authenticated copy of the will and a duly authenticated certificate of its legal custodian that the copy filed is a true copy and that the will has become operative under the law of the other place.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-095">
            <num>13.16.095</num>
            <heading>Informal probate; unavailable in certain cases.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.095.   Informal probate; unavailable in certain cases.
Applications for informal probate that relate to one or more of a known series of testamentary instruments, other than wills and codicils, the latest of which does not expressly revoke the earlier, shall be declined.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-100">
            <num>13.16.100</num>
            <heading>Informal probate; registrar not satisfied.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.100.   Informal probate; registrar not satisfied.
If the registrar is not satisfied that a will is entitled to be probated in informal proceedings because of failure to meet the requirements of
AS 13.16.090
and 13.16.095 or any other reason, the registrar may decline the application.  A declination of informal probate is not an adjudication and does not preclude formal probate proceedings.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-105">
            <num>13.16.105</num>
            <heading>Informal probate; notice requirements; information distribution.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-16-105__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The moving party must give notice as described by
AS 13.06.110
of the party's application for informal probate (1) to any person demanding it under
AS 13.16.070
, and (2) to any personal representative of the decedent whose appointment has not been terminated.  No other notice of informal probate is required.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-105__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If an informal probate is granted, within 30 days the applicant shall give written information of the probate to the heirs and devisees.  The information shall include the name and address of the applicant, the name and location of the court granting the informal probate, and the date of the probate.  The information shall be delivered or sent by ordinary mail to each of the heirs and devisees whose address is reasonably available to the applicant.  No duty to give information is incurred if a personal representative is appointed who is required to give the written information required by
AS 13.16.360
.  An applicant's failure to give information as required by this section is a breach of a duty to the heirs and devisees but does not affect the validity of the probate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-110">
            <num>13.16.110</num>
            <heading>Informal appointment proceedings; delay in order; duty of registrar; effect of appointment.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-16-110__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon receipt of an application for informal appointment of a personal representative other than a special administrator as provided in
AS 13.16.310
, if at least 120 hours have elapsed since the decedent's death, the registrar, after making the findings required by
AS 13.16.115
, shall appoint the applicant subject to qualification and acceptance; however, if the decedent was a nonresident, the registrar shall delay the order of appointment until 30 days have elapsed since death unless the personal representative appointed at the decedent's domicile is the applicant, or unless the decedent's will directs that the estate be subject to the laws of this state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-110__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The status of personal representative and the powers and duties pertaining to the office are fully established by informal appointment.  An appointment, and the office of personal representative created thereby, is subject to termination as provided in
AS 13.16.280
 13.16.300, but is not subject to retroactive vacation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-115">
            <num>13.16.115</num>
            <heading>Informal appointment proceedings; determinations required; denial of application.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-16-115__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In informal appointment proceedings, the registrar must determine whether</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-115__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the application for informal appointment of a personal representative is complete;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-115__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the applicant has made oath or affirmation that the statements contained in the application are true to the best of the applicant's knowledge and belief;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-115__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the applicant appears from the application to be an interested person as defined in
AS 13.06.050
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-115__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>on the basis of the statements in the application, venue is proper;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-115__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>any will to which the requested appointment relates has been formally or informally probated; but this requirement does not apply to the appointment of a special administrator;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-115__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>any notice required by
AS 13.16.070
has been given;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-115__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>from the statements in the application, the person whose appointment is sought has priority entitling the person to the appointment.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-115__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless
AS 13.16.300
controls, the application must be denied if it indicates that a personal representative who has not filed a written statement of resignation as provided in
AS 13.16.290</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-115__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>has been appointed in a judicial district of this state, that, unless the applicant is the domiciliary personal representative or the personal representative's nominee, the decedent was not domiciled in this state and that a personal representative whose appointment has not been terminated has been appointed by a court in the state of domicile, or that other requirements of this section have not been met.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-120">
            <num>13.16.120</num>
            <heading>Informal appointment proceedings; registrar not satisfied.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.120.   Informal appointment proceedings; registrar not satisfied.
If the registrar is not satisfied that a requested informal appointment of a personal representative should be made because of failure to meet the requirements of
AS 13.16.110
and 13.16.115, or for any other reason, the registrar may decline the application.  A declination of informal appointment is not an adjudication and does not preclude appointment in formal proceedings.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-125">
            <num>13.16.125</num>
            <heading>Informal appointment proceedings; notice requirements.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.125.   Informal appointment proceedings; notice requirements.
The moving party must give notice as described by
AS 13.06.110
of intention to seek an appointment informally (1) to any person demanding it under
AS 13.16.070
; and (2) to any person having a prior or equal right to appointment not waived in writing and filed with the court.  No other notice of an informal appointment proceeding is required.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-130">
            <num>13.16.130</num>
            <heading>Informal appointment unavailable in certain cases.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.130.   Informal appointment unavailable in certain cases.
If an application for informal appointment indicates the existence of a possible unrevoked testamentary instrument that may relate to property subject to the laws of this state, and that is not filed for probate in this court, the registrar shall decline the application.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-140">
            <num>13.16.140</num>
            <heading>Formal testacy proceedings; nature; when commenced.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-16-140__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A formal testacy proceeding is litigation to determine whether a decedent left a valid will.  A formal testacy proceeding may be commenced by an interested person filing a petition as described in
AS 13.16.145</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-140__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>in which the person requests that the court, after notice and hearing, enter an order probating a will, or a petition to set aside an informal probate of a will or to prevent informal probate of a will that is the subject of a pending application, or a petition in accordance with
AS 13.16.145</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-140__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>for an order that the decedent died intestate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-140__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A petition may seek formal probate of a will without regard to whether the same or a conflicting will has been informally probated.  A formal testacy proceeding may, but need not, involve a request for appointment of a personal representative.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-140__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>During the pendency of a formal testacy proceeding, the registrar shall not act upon any application for informal probate of any will of the decedent or any application for informal appointment of a personal representative of the decedent.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-140__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless a petition in a formal testacy proceeding also requests confirmation of the previous informal appointment, a previously appointed personal representative, after receipt of notice of the commencement of a formal probate proceeding, must refrain from exercising the power to make any further distribution of the estate during the pendency of the formal proceeding.  A petitioner who seeks the appointment of a different personal representative in a formal proceeding also may request an order restraining the acting personal representative from exercising any of the personal representative's powers of office and requesting the appointment of a special administrator. In the absence of a request, or if the request is denied, the commencement of a formal proceeding has no effect on the powers and duties of a previously appointed personal representative other than those relating to distribution.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-145">
            <num>13.16.145</num>
            <heading>Formal testacy or appointment proceedings; petition; contents.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-16-145__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Petitions for formal probate of a will, or for adjudication of intestacy with or without request for appointment of a personal representative, must be directed to the court, request a judicial order after notice and hearing, and contain further statements as indicated in this section.  A petition for formal probate of a will must</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-145__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>request an order as to the testacy of the decedent in relation to a particular instrument which may or may not have been informally probated and determining the heirs;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-145__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>contain the statements required for informal applications as stated in
AS 13.16.080</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-145__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>state whether the original of the last will of the decedent is in the possession of the court or accompanies the petition.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-145__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the original will is neither in the possession of the court nor accompanies the petition and no authenticated copy of a will probated in another jurisdiction accompanies the petition, the petition also must state the contents of the will, and indicate that it is lost, destroyed, or otherwise unavailable.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-145__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A petition for adjudication of intestacy and appointment of an administrator in intestacy must request a judicial finding and order that the decedent left no will and determining the heirs, contain the statements required by
AS 13.16.080
(a)(1) and (4) and indicate whether supervised administration is sought.  A petition may request an order determining intestacy and heirs without requesting the appointment of an administrator, in which case, the statements required by
AS 13.16.080
(a)(4)(B) may be omitted.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-150">
            <num>13.16.150</num>
            <heading>Formal testacy proceeding; notice of hearing on petition.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-16-150__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon commencement of a formal testacy proceeding, the court shall fix a time and place of hearing. Notice shall be given in the manner prescribed by
AS 13.06.110
by the petitioner to the persons enumerated in this subsection and to any additional person who has filed a demand for notice under
AS 13.16.070
.  Notice shall be given to the following persons: (1) the surviving spouse, children, and other heirs of the decedent; (2) the devisees and executors named in any will that is being, or has been probated or offered for informal or formal probate in the judicial district, or that is known by the petitioner to have been probated or offered for informal or formal probate elsewhere; and (3) any personal representative of the decedent whose appointment has not been terminated.  Notice may be given to other persons.  In addition, the petitioner shall give notice by publication to all unknown persons and to all known persons whose addresses are unknown who have any interest in the matters being litigated.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-150__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If it appears by the petition or otherwise that the fact of the death of the alleged decedent may be in doubt, or on the written demand of any interested person, a copy of the notice of the hearing on the petition shall be sent by registered mail to the alleged decedent at the last known address of the alleged decedent.  The court shall direct the petitioner to report the results of, or make and report back concerning, a reasonably diligent search for the alleged decedent in any manner that may seem advisable, including any or all of the following methods: (1) by inserting in one or more suitable periodicals a notice requesting information from any person having knowledge of the whereabouts of the alleged decedent; (2) by notifying law enforcement officials and public welfare agencies in appropriate locations of the disappearance of the alleged decedent; (3) by engaging the services of an investigator; the costs of any search so directed shall be paid by the petitioner if there is no administration or by the estate of the decedent in case there is administration.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-155">
            <num>13.16.155</num>
            <heading>Formal testacy proceedings; written objections to probate.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.155.   Formal testacy proceedings; written objections to probate.
Any party to a formal proceeding who opposes the probate of a will for any reason shall state in the pleadings the objections to probate of the will.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-160">
            <num>13.16.160</num>
            <heading>Formal testacy proceedings; uncontested cases; hearings and proof.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.160.   Formal testacy proceedings; uncontested cases; hearings and proof.
If a petition in a testacy proceeding is unopposed, the court may order probate or intestacy on the strength of the pleadings if satisfied that the conditions of
AS 13.16.180
have been met, or conduct a hearing in open court and require proof of the matters necessary to support the order sought. If evidence concerning execution of the will is necessary, the affidavit or testimony of one of any attesting witnesses to the instrument is sufficient.  If the affidavit or testimony of an attesting witness is not available, execution of the will may be proved by other evidence or affidavit.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-165">
            <num>13.16.165</num>
            <heading>Formal testacy proceedings; contested cases; testimony of attesting witnesses.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-16-165__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If evidence concerning execution of an attested will that is not self-proved is necessary in contested cases, the testimony of at least one of the attesting witnesses, if within the state, competent, and able to testify, is required.  Due execution of an attested or unattested will may be proved by other evidence.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-165__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the will is self-proved, compliance with signature requirements for execution is conclusively presumed and other requirements of execution are presumed subject to rebuttal without the testimony of any witness upon filing the will and the acknowledgment and affidavits annexed or attached to it, unless there is proof of fraud or forgery affecting the acknowledgment or affidavit.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-170">
            <num>13.16.170</num>
            <heading>Formal testacy proceedings; burdens in contested cases.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.170.   Formal testacy proceedings; burdens in contested cases.
In contested cases, petitioners who seek to establish intestacy have the burden of establishing prima facie proof of death, venue, and heirship.  Proponents of a will have the burden of establishing prima facie proof of due execution in all cases, and if they are also petitioners, prima facie proof of death and venue.  Contestants of a will have the burden of establishing lack of testamentary intent or capacity, undue influence, fraud, duress, mistake, or revocation.  Parties have the ultimate burden of persuasion as to matters with respect to which they have the initial burden of proof.  If a will is opposed by the petition for probate of a later will revoking the former, it shall be determined first whether the later will is entitled to probate, and if a will is opposed by a petition for a declaration of intestacy, it shall be determined first whether the will is entitled to probate.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-175">
            <num>13.16.175</num>
            <heading>Formal testacy proceedings; will construction; effect of final order in another jurisdiction.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.175.   Formal testacy proceedings; will construction; effect of final order in another jurisdiction.
Subject to
AS 13.06.068
, a final order of a court of another state determining testacy, the validity, or construction of a will made in a proceeding involving notice to and an opportunity for contest by all interested persons must be accepted as determinative by the courts of this state if it includes, or is based upon, a finding that the decedent was domiciled at death in the state where the order was made.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-180">
            <num>13.16.180</num>
            <heading>Formal testacy proceedings; order; foreign will.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.180.   Formal testacy proceedings; order; foreign will.
After the time required for any notice has expired, upon proof of notice, and after any hearing that may be necessary, if the court finds that the testator is dead, that venue is proper, and that the proceeding was commenced within the limitation prescribed by
AS 13.16.040
, it shall determine the decedent's domicile at death, any heirs, and the state of testacy of the decedent.  Any will found to be valid and unrevoked shall be formally probated.  Termination of any previous informal appointment of a personal representative that may be appropriate in view of the relief requested and findings is governed by
AS 13.16.300
. The petition shall be dismissed or appropriate amendment allowed if the court is not satisfied that the alleged decedent is dead.  A will from a place that does not provide for probate of a will after death, may be proved for probate in this state by a duly authenticated certificate of its legal custodian that the copy introduced is a true copy and that the will has become effective under the law of the other place.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-185">
            <num>13.16.185</num>
            <heading>Formal testacy proceedings; probate of more than one instrument.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.185.   Formal testacy proceedings; probate of more than one instrument.
If two or more instruments are offered for probate before a final order is entered in a formal testacy proceeding, more than one instrument may be probated if neither expressly revokes the other or contains provisions that work a total revocation by implication.  If more than one instrument is probated, the order shall indicate what provisions control in respect to the nomination of an executor, if any.  The order may, but need not, indicate how any provisions of a particular instrument are affected by the other instrument.  After a final order in a testacy proceeding has been entered, no petition for probate of any other instrument of the decedent may be entertained, except incident to a petition to vacate or modify a previous probate order and subject to the time limits of
AS 13.16.195
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-190">
            <num>13.16.190</num>
            <heading>Formal testacy proceedings; partial intestacy.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.190.   Formal testacy proceedings; partial intestacy.
If it becomes evident in the course of a formal testacy proceeding that, though one or more instruments are entitled to be probated, the decedent's estate is or may be partially intestate, the court shall enter an order to that effect.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-195">
            <num>13.16.195</num>
            <heading>Formal testacy proceedings; effect of order; vacation.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-16-195__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subject to appeal and subject to vacation as provided in this section and in
AS 13.16.200
, a formal testacy order under
AS 13.16.180
 13.16.190, including an order that the decedent did not leave a valid will and determining heirs, is final as to all persons with respect to all issues concerning the decedent's estate that the court considered or might have considered incident to its rendition relevant to the question of whether the decedent left a valid will, and to the determination of heirs, except that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-195__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the court shall entertain a petition for modification or vacation of its order and probate of another will of the decedent if it is shown that the proponents of the later-offered will were
(A) unaware of the later-offered will's existence at the time of the earlier proceeding; or
(B) unaware of the earlier proceeding and were not given notice of the proceeding, except by publication;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-195__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if intestacy of all or part of the estate has been ordered, the determination of heirs of the decedent may be reconsidered if it is shown that one or more persons were omitted from the determination and it is also shown that the persons were unaware of their relationship to the decedent, were unaware of the death, or were not given notice of any proceeding concerning the estate, except by publication;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-195__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a petition for vacation under either (1) or (2) of this subsection must be filed before the earliest of the following time limits:
(A) if a personal representative has been appointed for the estate, the time of entry of an order approving final distribution of the estate, or, if the estate is closed by statement, six months after the filing of the closing statement;
(B) whether or not a personal representative has been appointed for the estate of the decedent, the time prescribed by
AS 13.16.040
when it is no longer possible to initiate an original proceeding to probate a will of the decedent; or
(C) 12 months after the entry of the order sought to be vacated;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-195__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the order originally rendered in the testacy proceeding may be modified or vacated, if appropriate under the circumstances, by the order of probate of the later-offered will or the order redetermining heirs;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-195__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the finding of the fact of death is conclusive as to the alleged decedent only if notice of the hearing on the petition in the formal testacy proceeding was sent by registered or certified mail addressed to the alleged decedent at the last known address of the alleged decedent and the court finds that a search under
AS 13.16.150</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-195__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>was made.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-195__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the alleged decedent is not dead, even if notice was sent and search was made, the alleged decedent may recover estate assets in the hands of the personal representative.  In addition to any remedies available to the alleged decedent by reason of any fraud or intentional wrongdoing, the alleged decedent may recover any estate or its proceeds from distributees that is in their hands, or the value of distributions received by them, to the extent that any recovery from distributees is equitable in view of all of the circumstances.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-200">
            <num>13.16.200</num>
            <heading>Formal testacy proceedings; vacation of order for other cause.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.200.   Formal testacy proceedings; vacation of order for other cause.
For good cause shown, an order in a formal testacy proceeding may be modified or vacated within the time allowed for appeal.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-205">
            <num>13.16.205</num>
            <heading>Formal proceedings concerning appointment of personal representative.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-16-205__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A formal proceeding for adjudication regarding the priority or qualification of one who is an applicant for appointment as personal representative, or of one who previously has been appointed personal representative in informal proceedings, if an issue concerning the testacy of the decedent is or may be involved, is governed by
AS 13.16.145
, as well as by this section.  In other cases, the petition must contain or adopt the statements required by
AS 13.16.080
(a)(1) and describe the question relating to priority or qualification of the personal representative that is to be resolved.  If the proceeding precedes any appointment of a personal representative, it shall stay any pending informal appointment proceedings as well as any commenced thereafter.  If the proceeding is commenced after appointment, the previously appointed personal representative, after receipt of notice thereof, shall refrain from exercising any power of administration except as necessary to preserve the estate or unless the court orders otherwise.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-205__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After notice to interested persons, including all persons interested in the administration of the estate as successors under the applicable assumption concerning testacy, any previously appointed personal representative and any person having or claiming priority for appointment as personal representative, the court shall determine who is entitled to appointment under
AS 13.16.065
, make a proper appointment and, if appropriate, terminate any prior appointment found to have been improper as provided in cases of removal under
AS 13.16.295
.
Article 5. Supervised Administration.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-215">
            <num>13.16.215</num>
            <heading>Supervised administration; nature of proceeding.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.215.   Supervised administration; nature of proceeding.
Supervised administration is a single in rem proceeding to secure complete administration and settlement of a decedent's estate under the continuing authority of the court which extends until entry of an order approving distribution of the estate and discharging the personal representative or other order terminating the proceeding.  A supervised personal representative is responsible to the court, as well as to the interested parties, and is subject to directions concerning the estate made by the court on its own motion or on the motion of any interested party. Except as otherwise provided in
AS 13.16.215
 13.16.235, or as otherwise ordered by the court, a supervised personal representative has the same duties and powers as a personal representative who is not supervised.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-220">
            <num>13.16.220</num>
            <heading>Supervised administration; petition; order.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.220.   Supervised administration; petition; order.
A petition for supervised administration may be filed by any interested person or by a personal representative at any time or the prayer for supervised administration may be joined with a petition in a testacy or appointment proceeding.  If the testacy of the decedent and the priority and qualification of any personal representative have not been adjudicated previously, the petition for supervised administration must include the matters required of a petition in a formal testacy proceeding and the notice requirements and procedures applicable to a formal testacy proceeding apply.  If not previously adjudicated, the court shall adjudicate the testacy of the decedent and questions relating to the priority and qualifications of the personal representative in any case involving a request for supervised administration, even though the request for supervised administration may be denied. After notice to interested persons, the court shall order supervised administration of a decedent's estate as follows:
(1) if the decedent's will directs supervised administration, it shall be ordered unless the court finds that circumstances bearing on the need for supervised administration have changed since the execution of the will and that there is no necessity for supervised administration;
(2) if the decedent's will directs unsupervised administration, supervised administration shall be ordered only upon a finding that it is necessary for protection of persons interested in the estate; or
(3) in other cases if the court finds that supervised administration is necessary under the circumstances.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-225">
            <num>13.16.225</num>
            <heading>Supervised administration; effect on other proceedings.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-16-225__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The pendency of a proceeding for supervised administration of a decedent's estate stays action on any informal application then pending or thereafter filed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-225__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a will has been previously probated in informal proceedings, the effect of the filing of a petition for supervised administration is as provided for formal testacy proceedings by
AS 13.16.140
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-225__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After receiving notice of the filing of a petition for supervised administration, a personal representative who has been appointed previously may not exercise the power to distribute any estate.  The filing of the petition does not affect other powers and duties unless the court restricts the exercise of any of them pending full hearing on the petition.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-230">
            <num>13.16.230</num>
            <heading>Supervised administration; powers of personal representative.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.230.   Supervised administration; powers of personal representative.
Unless restricted by the court, a supervised personal representative has, without interim orders approving exercise of a power, all powers of personal representatives under
AS 13.06

AS 13.36
, but a supervised personal representative may not exercise the power to make any distribution of the estate without prior order of the court.  Any other restriction on the power of a personal representative that may be ordered by the court must be endorsed on the letters of appointment and, unless so endorsed, is ineffective as to persons dealing in good faith with the personal representative.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-235">
            <num>13.16.235</num>
            <heading>Supervised administration; interim orders; distribution and closing orders.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.235.   Supervised administration; interim orders; distribution and closing orders.
Unless otherwise ordered by the court, supervised administration is terminated by order in accordance with time restrictions, notices, and contents of orders prescribed for proceedings under
AS 13.16.620
.  Interim orders approving or directing partial distributions or granting other relief may be issued by the court at any time during the pendency of a supervised administration on the application of the personal representative or any interested person.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-245">
            <num>13.16.245</num>
            <heading>Qualification.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.245.   Qualification.
Before receiving letters, a personal representative shall qualify by filing with the appointing court any required bond and a statement of acceptance of the duties of the office.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-250">
            <num>13.16.250</num>
            <heading>Acceptance of appointment; consent to jurisdiction.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.250.   Acceptance of appointment; consent to jurisdiction.
By accepting appointment, a personal representative submits personally to the jurisdiction of the court in any proceeding relating to the estate that may be instituted by any interested person.  Notice of any proceeding shall be delivered to the personal representative, or mailed by ordinary first-class mail to the personal representative at the address as listed in the application or petition for appointment or as thereafter reported to the court and to the personal representative's address as then known to the petitioner.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-255">
            <num>13.16.255</num>
            <heading>Bond required; exceptions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.255.   Bond required; exceptions.
A personal representative shall execute and file a bond with the registrar unless
(1) the estate is testate and the will expressly waives surety bond as to the person qualifying as personal representative;
(2) the devisees or the heirs file written waiver of surety bond;
(3) the personal representative is a qualified corporate fiduciary; or
(4) the personal representative, pursuant to statute, has deposited cash or collateral with an agency of the state to secure performance of the personal representative's duties.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-260">
            <num>13.16.260</num>
            <heading>Bond amount; security; procedure; reduction.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.260.   Bond amount; security; procedure; reduction.
If bond is required and the provisions of the will or order do not specify the amount, unless stated in the application or petition, the person qualifying shall file a statement under oath with the registrar indicating the person's best estimate of the value of the personal estate of the decedent and of the income expected from the personal and real estate during the next year. The person qualifying shall execute and file a bond with the registrar, or give other suitable security, in an amount not less than the estimate. The registrar shall determine that the bond is duly executed by a corporate surety, or one or more individual sureties whose performance is secured by pledge of personal property, mortgage on real property, or other adequate security. The registrar may permit the amount of the bond to be reduced by the value of assets of the estate deposited with a domestic financial institution, as defined in
AS 13.33.201
, in a manner that prevents their unauthorized disposition. On petition of the personal representative or another interested person the court may excuse a requirement of bond, increase or reduce the amount of the bond, release sureties, or permit the substitution of another bond with the same or different sureties.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-265">
            <num>13.16.265</num>
            <heading>Demand for bond by interested person.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.265.   Demand for bond by interested person.
Any person apparently having an interest in the estate worth in excess of $1,000, or any creditor having a claim in excess of $1,000, may make a written demand that a personal representative give bond.  The demand must be filed with the registrar and a copy mailed to the personal representative, if appointment and qualification have occurred.  Thereupon, bond is required, but the requirement ceases if the person demanding bond ceases to be interested in the estate, or if bond is excused as provided in
AS 13.16.255
or 13.16.260. After receiving notice and until the filing of the bond or cessation of the requirement of bond, the personal representative shall refrain from exercising any powers of the personal representative's office except as necessary to preserve the estate.  Failure of the personal representative to meet a requirement of bond by giving suitable bond within 30 days after receipt of notice is cause for removal and appointment of a successor personal representative.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-270">
            <num>13.16.270</num>
            <heading>Terms and conditions of bonds.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-16-270__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The following requirements and provisions apply to any bond required by
AS 13.16.245
  13.16.330:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-270__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>bonds shall name the state as obligee for the benefit of persons interested in the estate and shall be conditioned upon the faithful discharge by the fiduciary of all duties according to law;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-270__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>unless otherwise provided by the terms of the approved bond, sureties are jointly and severally liable with the personal representative and with each other; the address of each surety shall be stated in the bond;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-270__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>by executing an approved bond of a personal representative, the surety consents to the jurisdiction of the probate court that issued letters to the primary obligor in any proceedings pertaining to the fiduciary duties of the personal representative and naming the surety as a party; notice of any proceeding shall be delivered to the surety or mailed by registered or certified mail to the surety at the address as listed with the court where the bond is filed and to the surety's address as then known to the petitioner;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-270__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>on petition of a successor personal representative, any other personal representative of the same decedent, or any interested person, a proceeding in the court may be initiated against a surety for breach of the obligation of the bond of the personal representative;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-270__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the bond of the personal representative is not void after the first recovery but may be proceeded against from time to time until the whole penalty is exhausted.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-270__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>No action or proceeding may be commenced against the surety on any matter as to which an action or proceeding against the primary obligor is barred by adjudication or limitation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-275">
            <num>13.16.275</num>
            <heading>Order restraining personal representative.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-16-275__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>On petition of any person who appears to have an interest in the estate, the court by temporary order may restrain a personal representative from performing specified acts of administration, disbursement, or distribution, or exercise of any powers or discharge of any duties of the personal representative's office, or make any other order to secure proper performance of the personal representative's duty, if it appears to the court that the personal representative otherwise may take some action that would jeopardize unreasonably the interest of the applicant or of some other interested person.  Persons with whom the personal representative may transact business may be made parties.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-275__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The matter shall be set for hearing within 10 days unless the parties otherwise agree.  Notice as the court directs shall be given to the personal representative and the personal representative's attorney of record, if any, and to any other parties named defendant in the petition.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-280">
            <num>13.16.280</num>
            <heading>Termination of appointment; general.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.280.   Termination of appointment; general.
Termination of appointment of a personal representative occurs as indicated in
AS 13.16.285
  13.16.300. Termination ends the right and power pertaining to the office of personal representative as conferred by
AS 13.06

AS 13.36
or any will, except that a personal representative, at any time before distribution or until restrained or enjoined by court order, may perform acts necessary to protect the estate and may deliver the assets to a successor representative. Termination does not discharge a personal representative from liability for transactions or omissions occurring before termination, or relieve the personal representative of the duty to preserve assets subject to the personal representative's control, to account therefor, and to deliver the assets.  Termination does not affect the jurisdiction of the court over the personal representative, but terminates the personal representative's authority to represent the estate in any pending or future proceeding.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-285">
            <num>13.16.285</num>
            <heading>Termination of appointment; death or disability.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.285.   Termination of appointment; death or disability.
The death of a personal representative or the appointment of a conservator for the estate of a personal representative, terminates the personal representative's appointment.  Until appointment and qualification of a successor or special representative to replace the deceased or protected representative, the representative of the estate of the deceased or protected personal representative, if any, has the duty to protect the estate possessed and being administered by the decedent or ward at the time the appointment terminates, has the power to perform acts necessary for protection, and shall account for and deliver the estate assets to a successor or special personal representative upon appointment and qualification.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-290">
            <num>13.16.290</num>
            <heading>Termination of appointment; voluntary.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-16-290__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An appointment of a personal representative terminates as provided in
AS 13.16.630
, one year after the filing of a closing statement.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-290__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An order closing an estate as provided in
AS 13.16.620
or 13.16.625 terminates an appointment of a personal representative.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-290__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A personal representative may resign the position by filing a written statement of resignation with the registrar after giving at least 15 days' written notice to the persons known to be interested in the estate.  If no one applies or petitions for appointment of a successor representative within the time indicated in the notice, the filed statement of resignation is ineffective as a termination of appointment and in any event is effective only upon the appointment and qualification of a successor representative and delivery of the assets to that successor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-295">
            <num>13.16.295</num>
            <heading>Termination of appointment by removal; cause; procedure.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-16-295__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person interested in the estate may petition for removal of a personal representative for cause at any time. Upon filing of the petition, the court shall fix a time and place for hearing.  Notice shall be given by the petitioner to the personal representative, and to other persons as the court may order.  Except as otherwise ordered as provided in
AS 13.16.275
, after receipt of notice of removal proceedings, the personal representative shall not act except to account, to correct maladministration or preserve the estate.  If removal is ordered, the court also shall direct by order the disposition of the assets remaining in the name of, or under the control of, the personal representative being removed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-295__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Cause for removal exists when removal would be in the best interests of the estate, or if it is shown that a personal representative or the person seeking appointment intentionally misrepresented material facts in the proceedings leading to appointment, or that the personal representative has disregarded an order of the court, has become incapable of discharging the duties of the office, or has mismanaged the estate or failed to perform any duty pertaining to the office.  Unless the decedent's will directs otherwise, a personal representative appointed at the decedent's domicile, incident to securing appointment either personally or for a nominee as ancillary personal representative, may obtain removal of another who was appointed personal representative in this state to administer local assets.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-300">
            <num>13.16.300</num>
            <heading>Termination of appointment; change of testacy status.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.300.   Termination of appointment; change of testacy status.
Except as otherwise ordered in formal proceedings, the probate of a will subsequent to the appointment of a personal representative in intestacy or under a will that is superseded by formal probate of another will, or the vacation of an informal probate of a will subsequent to the appointment of the personal representative under it, does not terminate the appointment of the personal representative although the personal representative's powers may be reduced as provided in
AS 13.16.140
. Termination occurs upon appointment in informal or formal appointment proceedings of a person entitled to appointment under the later assumption concerning testacy.  If no request for new appointment is made within 30 days after expiration of time for appeal from the order in formal testacy proceedings, or from the informal probate, changing the assumption concerning testacy, the previously appointed personal representative upon request may be appointed personal representative under the subsequently probated will, or as in intestacy as the case may be.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-305">
            <num>13.16.305</num>
            <heading>Successor personal representative.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.305.   Successor personal representative.
AS 13.16.080
  13.16.205 govern proceedings for appointment of a personal representative to succeed one whose appointment has been terminated.  After appointment and qualification, a successor personal representative may be substituted in all actions and proceedings to which the former personal representative was a party, and no notice, process, or claim that was given or served upon the former personal representative need be given to or served upon the successor in order to preserve any position or right the person giving the notice or filing the claim may thereby have obtained or preserved with reference to the former personal representative.  Except as otherwise ordered by the court, the successor personal representative has the powers and duties in respect to the continued administration that the former personal representative would have had if the appointment had not been terminated.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-310">
            <num>13.16.310</num>
            <heading>Special administrator; appointment.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.310.   Special administrator; appointment.
A special administrator may be appointed
(1) informally by the registrar on the application of any interested person when necessary to protect the estate of a decedent before the appointment of a general personal representative or if a prior appointment has been terminated as provided in
AS 13.16.285
;
(2) in a formal proceeding by order of the court on the petition of any interested person and finding, after notice and hearing, that appointment is necessary to preserve the estate or to secure its proper administration, including its administration in circumstances where a general personal representative cannot or should not act; if it appears to the court that an emergency exists, appointment may be ordered without notice.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-315">
            <num>13.16.315</num>
            <heading>Special administrator; who may be appointed.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-16-315__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a special administrator is to be appointed pending the probate of a will that is the subject of a pending application or petition for probate, the person named executor in the will shall be appointed if available and qualified.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-315__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In other cases, any proper person may be appointed special administrator.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-320">
            <num>13.16.320</num>
            <heading>Special administrator appointed informally; powers and duties.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.320.   Special administrator appointed informally; powers and duties.
A special administrator appointed by the registrar in informal proceedings pursuant to
AS 13.16.310
(1) has the duty to collect and manage the assets of the estate, to preserve them, to account for them, and to deliver them to the general personal representative upon qualification.  The special administrator has the power of a personal representative under
AS 13.06

AS 13.36
necessary to perform the special administrator's duties.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-325">
            <num>13.16.325</num>
            <heading>Special administrator appointed by court; power and duties.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.325.   Special administrator appointed by court; power and duties.
A special administrator appointed by order of the court in any formal proceeding has the power of a general personal representative except as limited in the appointment and duties as prescribed in the order.  The appointment may be for a specified time, to perform particular acts, or on other terms as the court may direct.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-330">
            <num>13.16.330</num>
            <heading>Termination of appointment; special administrator.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.330.   Termination of appointment; special administrator.
The appointment of a special administrator terminates in accordance with the provisions of the order of appointment or on the appointment of a general personal representative.  In other cases, the appointment of a special administrator is subject to termination as provided in
AS 13.16.280
 13.16.295.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-340">
            <num>13.16.340</num>
            <heading>Time of accrual of duties and powers.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.340.   Time of accrual of duties and powers.
The duties and powers of a personal representative commence upon appointment.  The powers of a personal representative relate back in time to give acts by the person appointed that are beneficial to the estate occurring prior to appointment the same effect as those occurring thereafter.  Prior to appointment, a person named executor in a will may carry out written instructions of the decedent relating to the decedent's body, funeral, and burial arrangements.  A personal representative may ratify and accept acts on behalf of the estate done by others where the acts would have been proper for a personal representative.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-345">
            <num>13.16.345</num>
            <heading>Priority among different letters.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.345.   Priority among different letters.
A person to whom general letters are issued first has exclusive authority under the letters until the appointment is terminated or modified.  If, through error, general letters are afterwards issued to another, the first appointed representative may recover any property of the estate in the hands of the representative subsequently appointed, but the acts of the latter done in good faith before notice of the first letters are not void for want of validity of appointment.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-350">
            <num>13.16.350</num>
            <heading>General duties; standard of care; relation and liability to persons interested in estate; standing to sue.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-16-350__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A personal representative is a fiduciary who shall observe the standards of care applicable to trustees under
AS 13.36.225
 13.36.290. A personal representative is under a duty to settle and distribute the estate of the decedent in accordance with the terms of any probated and effective will and
AS 13.06

AS 13.36
, and as expeditiously and efficiently as is consistent with the best interests of the estate. A personal representative shall use the authority conferred by
AS 13.06

AS 13.36
, the terms of the will, if any, and any order in proceedings to which the personal representative is party for the best interests of successors to the estate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-350__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A personal representative may not be surcharged for acts of administration or distribution if the conduct in question was authorized at the time.  Subject to other obligations of administration, an informally probated will is authority to administer and distribute the estate according to its terms. An order of appointment of a personal representative, whether issued in informal or formal proceedings, is authority to distribute apparently intestate assets to the heirs of the decedent if, at the time of distribution, the personal representative is not aware of a pending testacy proceeding, a proceeding to vacate an order entered in an earlier testacy proceeding, a formal proceeding questioning the appointment or fitness to continue, or a supervised administration proceeding. Nothing in this section affects the duty of the personal representative to administer and distribute the estate in accordance with the rights of claimants, the surviving spouse, any minor and dependent children and any pretermitted child of the decedent as described elsewhere in
AS 13.06

AS 13.36
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-350__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as to proceedings that do not survive the death of the decedent, a personal representative of a decedent domiciled in this state at death has the same standing to sue and be sued in the courts of this state and the courts of any other jurisdiction as the decedent had immediately before death.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-355">
            <num>13.16.355</num>
            <heading>Personal representative to proceed without court order; exception.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.355.   Personal representative to proceed without court order; exception.
A personal representative shall proceed expeditiously with the settlement and distribution of a decedent's estate and, except as otherwise specified or ordered in regard to a supervised personal representative, do so without adjudication, order, or direction of the court, but the personal representative may invoke the jurisdiction of the court, in proceedings authorized by
AS 13.06

AS 13.36
, to resolve questions concerning the estate or its administration.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-360">
            <num>13.16.360</num>
            <heading>Duty of personal representative; information to heirs and devisees.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.360.   Duty of personal representative; information to heirs and devisees.
Not later than 30 days after appointment, every personal representative, except any special administrator, shall give information of the appointment to the heirs and devisees, including, if there has been no formal testacy proceeding and if the personal representative was appointed on the assumption that the decedent died intestate, the devisees in any will mentioned in the application for appointment of a personal representative. The information shall be delivered or sent by ordinary mail to each of the heirs and devisees whose address is reasonably available to the personal representative. The duty does not extend to require information to persons who have been adjudicated in a prior formal testacy proceeding to have no interest in the estate.  The information must include the name and address of the personal representative, indicate that it is being sent to persons who have or may have some interest in the estate being administered, indicate whether bond has been filed, and describe the court where papers relating to the estate are on file.  The personal representative's failure to give this information is a breach of duty to the persons concerned but does not affect the validity of the appointment, the personal representative's powers or other duties.  A personal representative may inform other persons of the appointment by delivery or ordinary first-class mail.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-365">
            <num>13.16.365</num>
            <heading>Duty of personal representative; inventory and appraisal.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-16-365__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Within three months after appointment, a personal representative, who is not a special administrator or a successor to another representative who has previously discharged this duty, shall prepare and file or mail an inventory of property owned by the decedent at the time of death, listing it with reasonable detail, and indicating as to each listed item, its fair market value as of the date of the decedent's death, and the type and amount of any encumbrance that may exist with reference to any item.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-365__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The personal representative shall send a copy of the inventory to interested persons who request it.  The personal representative may also file the original of the inventory with the court.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-370">
            <num>13.16.370</num>
            <heading>Employment of appraisers.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.370.   Employment of appraisers.
The personal representative may employ a qualified and disinterested appraiser to assist in ascertaining the fair market value as of the date of the decedent's death of any asset the value of which may be subject to reasonable doubt. Different persons may be employed to appraise different kinds of assets included in the estate. The names and addresses of any appraiser shall be indicated on the inventory with the item or items appraised.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-375">
            <num>13.16.375</num>
            <heading>Duty of personal representative; supplementary inventory.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.375.   Duty of personal representative; supplementary inventory.
If any property not included in the original inventory comes to the knowledge of a personal representative or if the personal representative learns that the value or description indicated in the original inventory for any item is erroneous or misleading, the personal representative shall make a supplementary inventory or appraisal showing the market value as of the date of the decedent's death of the new item or the revised market value or descriptions, and the appraisers or other data relied upon, if any, and file it with the court if the original inventory was filed, or furnish copies of it or information on it to persons interested in the new information.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-380">
            <num>13.16.380</num>
            <heading>Duty of personal representative; possession of estate.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.380.   Duty of personal representative; possession of estate.
Except as otherwise provided by a decedent's will, every personal representative has a right to, and shall take possession or control of, the decedent's property, except that any real property or tangible personal property may be left with or surrendered to the person presumptively entitled to it unless or until, in the judgment of the personal representative, possession of the property by the personal representative will be necessary for purposes of administration.  The request by a personal representative for delivery of any property possessed by an heir or devisee is conclusive evidence, in any action against the heir or devisee for possession of it, that the possession of the property by the personal representative is necessary for purposes of administration.  The personal representative shall pay taxes on, and take all steps reasonably necessary for the management, protection, and preservation of, the estate in the personal representative's possession.  The personal representative may maintain an action to recover possession of property or to determine the title to it.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-381">
            <num>13.16.381</num>
            <heading>Disposition of unclaimed estate by personal representative.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.381.   Disposition of unclaimed estate by personal representative.
When there is no taker of an intestate estate, or if an heir, devisee, or claimant cannot be found and the missing person has no conservator, the personal representative shall handle the
(1) unclaimed personal property of the estate in accordance with
AS 34.45.280
 34.45.780; and
(2) unclaimed real property of the estate in accordance with
AS 38.95
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-385">
            <num>13.16.385</num>
            <heading>Power to avoid transfers.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.385.   Power to avoid transfers.
The property liable for the payment of unsecured debts of a decedent includes all property transferred by the decedent by any means that is in law void or voidable as against creditors, and subject to prior liens, the right to recover this property, so far as necessary for the payment of unsecured debts of the decedent, is exclusively in the personal representative.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-390">
            <num>13.16.390</num>
            <heading>Powers of personal representatives; in general.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.390.   Powers of personal representatives; in general.
Until termination of appointment, a personal representative has the same power over the title to property of the estate that an absolute owner would have, in trust however, for the benefit of the creditors and others interested in the estate. This power may be exercised without notice, hearing, or order of court.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-395">
            <num>13.16.395</num>
            <heading>Improper exercise of power; breach of fiduciary duty.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.395.   Improper exercise of power; breach of fiduciary duty.
If the exercise of power concerning the estate is improper, the personal representative is liable to interested persons for damage or loss resulting from breach of fiduciary duty to the same extent as a trustee of an express trust.  The rights of purchasers and others dealing with a personal representative shall be determined as provided in
AS 13.16.400
and 13.16.405.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-400">
            <num>13.16.400</num>
            <heading>Sale, encumbrance, or transaction involving conflict of interest voidable; exceptions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.400.   Sale, encumbrance, or transaction involving conflict of interest voidable; exceptions.
Any sale or encumbrance to the personal representative, the personal representative's spouse, agent, or attorney, or any corporation or trust in which the personal representative has a substantial beneficial interest, or any transaction that is affected by a substantial conflict of interest on the part of the personal representative, is voidable by any person interested in the estate except one who has consented after fair disclosure, unless
(1) the will or a contract entered into by the decedent expressly authorized the transaction; or
(2) the transaction is approved by the court after notice to interested persons.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-405">
            <num>13.16.405</num>
            <heading>Persons dealing with personal representative; protection.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.405.   Persons dealing with personal representative; protection.
A person who in good faith either assists a personal representative or deals with the personal representative for value is protected as if the personal representative properly exercised the personal representative's power.  The fact that a person knowingly deals with a personal representative does not alone require the person to inquire into the existence of a power or the propriety of its exercise.  Except for restrictions on powers of supervised personal representatives which are endorsed on letters as provided in
AS 13.16.230
, no provision in any will or order of court purporting to limit the power of a personal representative is effective except as to persons with actual knowledge of it.  A person is not bound to see to the proper application of estate assets paid or delivered to a personal representative.  The protection here expressed extends to instances in which some procedural irregularity or jurisdictional defect occurred in proceedings leading to the issuance of letters, including a case in which the alleged decedent is found to be alive.  The protection here expressed is not by substitution for that provided by comparable provisions of the laws relating to commercial transactions and laws simplifying transfers of securities by fiduciaries.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-410">
            <num>13.16.410</num>
            <heading>Transactions authorized for personal representatives; exceptions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.410.   Transactions authorized for personal representatives; exceptions.
Except as restricted or otherwise provided by the will or by an order in a formal proceeding and subject to the priorities stated in
AS 13.16.540
, a personal representative, acting reasonably for the benefit of the interested persons, may properly
(1) retain assets owned by the decedent pending distribution or liquidation, including those in which the representative is personally interested or that are otherwise improper for trust investment;
(2) receive assets from fiduciaries, or other sources;
(3) perform, compromise, or refuse performance of the decedent's contracts that continue as obligations of the estate, as the personal representative may determine under the circumstances; in performing enforceable contracts by the decedent to convey or lease land, the personal representative, among other possible courses of action, may:
(A) execute and deliver a deed of conveyance for cash payment of all sums remaining due or the purchaser's note for the sum remaining due secured by a mortgage or deed of trust on the land; or
(B) deliver a deed in escrow with directions that the proceeds, when paid in accordance with the escrow agreement, be paid to the successors of the decedent, as designated in the escrow agreement;
(4) satisfy written charitable pledges of the decedent irrespective of whether the pledges constituted binding obligations of the decedent or were properly presented as claims, if in the judgment of the personal representative the decedent would have wanted the pledges completed under the circumstances;
(5) if funds are not needed to meet debts and expenses currently payable and are not immediately distributable, deposit or invest liquid assets of the estate, including money received from the sale of other assets, in federally insured interest-bearing accounts, readily marketable secured loan arrangements, or other prudent investments which would be reasonable for use by trustees generally;
(6) acquire or dispose of an asset, including land in this or another state, for cash or on credit, at public or private sale; and manage, develop, improve, exchange, partition, change the character of, or abandon an estate asset;
(7) make ordinary or extraordinary repairs or alterations in buildings or other structures, demolish any improvements, raze existing or erect new party walls or buildings;
(8) subdivide, develop or dedicate land to public use; make or obtain the vacation of plats and adjust boundaries; or adjust differences in valuation on exchange or partition by giving or receiving considerations; or dedicate easements to public use without consideration;
(9) enter for any purpose into a lease as lessor or lessee, with or without option to purchase or renew, for a term within or extending beyond the period of administration;
(10) enter into a lease or arrangement for exploration and removal of minerals or other natural resources or enter into a pooling or unitization agreement;
(11) abandon property when, in the opinion of the personal representative, it is valueless, or is so encumbered, or is in condition that it is of no benefit to the estate;
(12) vote stocks or other securities in person or by general or limited proxy;
(13) pay calls, assessment, and other sums chargeable or accruing against or on account of securities, unless barred by the provisions relating to claims;
(14) hold a security in the name of a nominee or in other form without disclosure of the interest of the estate, but the personal representative is liable for any act of the nominee in connection with the security so held;
(15) insure the assets of the estate against damage, loss, and liability and insure the personal representative against liability as to third persons;
(16) borrow money with or without security to be repaid from the estate assets or otherwise; and advance money for the protection of the estate;
(17) effect a fair and reasonable compromise with any debtor or obligor, or extend, renew, or in any manner modify the terms of any obligation owing to the estate; if the personal representative holds a mortgage, pledge, or other lien upon property of another person, the personal representative may, in place of foreclosure, accept a conveyance or transfer of encumbered assets from the owner of it in satisfaction of the indebtedness secured by lien;
(18) pay taxes, assessments, compensation of the personal representative, and other expenses incident to the administration of the estate;
(19) sell or exercise stock subscription or conversion rights; consent, directly or through a committee or other agent, to the reorganization, consolidation, merger, dissolution, or liquidation of a corporation or other business enterprise;
(20) allocate items of income or expense to either estate income or principal, as permitted or provided by law;
(21) employ persons, including attorneys, auditors, investment advisors, or agents, even if they are associated with the personal representative, to advise or assist the personal representative in the performance of administrative duties; act without independent investigation upon their recommendations; and instead of acting personally, employ one or more agents to perform any act of administration, whether or not discretionary;
(22) prosecute or defend claims, or proceedings in any jurisdiction for the protection of the estate and of the personal representative in the performance of the personal representative's duties;
(23) sell, mortgage, or lease any real or personal property of the estate or any interest in it for cash, credit, or for part cash and part credit, and with or without security for unpaid balances;
(24) continue any unincorporated business or venture in which the decedent was engaged at the time of death
(A) in the same business form for a period of not more than four months from the date of appointment of a general personal representative if continuation is a reasonable means of preserving the value of the business including good will;
(B) in the same business form for any additional period of time that may be approved by order of the court in a formal proceeding to which the persons interested in the estate are parties; or
(C) throughout the period of administration if the business is incorporated by the personal representative and if none of the probable distributees of the business who are competent adults object to its incorporation and retention in the estate;
(25) incorporate any business or venture in which the decedent was engaged at the time of death;
(26) provide for exoneration of the personal representative from personal liability in any contract entered into on behalf of the estate;
(27) satisfy and settle claims and distribute the estate as provided in
AS 13.06
  13.36;
(28) consider discretionary distributions to a beneficiary as being made from capital gains realized during the year.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-415">
            <num>13.16.415</num>
            <heading>Powers and duties of successor personal representative.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.415.   Powers and duties of successor personal representative.
A successor personal representative has the same power and duty as the original personal representative to complete the administration and distribution of the estate, as expeditiously as possible, but the successor may not exercise any power expressly made personal to the executor named in the will.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-420">
            <num>13.16.420</num>
            <heading>Co-representatives; when joint action required.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.420.   Co-representatives; when joint action required.
If two or more persons are appointed co-representatives and unless the will provides otherwise, the concurrence of all is required on all acts connected with the administration and distribution of the estate. This restriction does not apply when any co-representative receives and gives a receipt for property due the estate, when the concurrence of all cannot readily be obtained in the time reasonably available for emergency action necessary to preserve the estate, or when a co-representative has been delegated to act for the others. Persons dealing with a co-representative, if actually unaware that another has been appointed to serve or if advised by the personal representative with whom they deal that the personal representative has authority to act alone for any of the reasons mentioned herein, are as fully protected as if the person with whom they dealt had been the sole personal representative.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-425">
            <num>13.16.425</num>
            <heading>Powers of surviving personal representative.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.425.   Powers of surviving personal representative.
Unless the terms of the will provide otherwise, every power exercisable by personal co-representatives may be exercised by the one or more remaining after the appointment of one or more is terminated, and if one of two or more nominated as co-executors is not appointed, those appointed may exercise all the powers incident to the office.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-430">
            <num>13.16.430</num>
            <heading>Compensation of personal representative.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.430.   Compensation of personal representative.
A personal representative is entitled to reasonable compensation for services.  If a will provides for compensation of the personal representative and there is no contract with the decedent regarding compensation, the personal representative may renounce the provision before qualifying and be entitled to reasonable compensation.  A personal representative also may renounce the right to all or any part of the compensation.  A written renunciation of fee may be filed with the court.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-435">
            <num>13.16.435</num>
            <heading>Expenses in estate litigation.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.435.   Expenses in estate litigation.
If any personal representative or person nominated as personal representative defends or prosecutes any proceeding in good faith, whether successful or not, that person is entitled to receive from the estate necessary expenses and disbursements including reasonable attorney fees incurred.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-440">
            <num>13.16.440</num>
            <heading>Review of employment of agents and other persons and compensation of personal representatives and other persons.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.440.   Review of employment of agents and other persons and compensation of personal representatives and other persons.
After notice to all interested persons or on petition of an interested person or on appropriate motion if administration is supervised, the propriety of employment of any person by a personal representative including any attorney, auditor, investment advisor, or other specialized agent or assistant, the reasonableness of the compensation of any person so employed, or the reasonableness of the compensation determined by the personal representative for the personal representative's services, may be reviewed by the court.  Any person who has received excessive compensation from an estate for services rendered may be ordered to make appropriate refunds.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-450">
            <num>13.16.450</num>
            <heading>Notice to creditors.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.450.   Notice to creditors.
Unless notice has already been given under this section, a personal representative upon appointment shall publish a notice once a week for three successive weeks in a newspaper of general circulation in the judicial district announcing the appointment and address and notifying creditors of the estate to present their claims within four months after the date of the first publication of the notice or be forever barred.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-455">
            <num>13.16.455</num>
            <heading>Statutes of limitations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.455.   Statutes of limitations.
Unless an estate is insolvent, the personal representative, with the consent of all successors whose interests would be affected, may waive any defense of limitations available to the estate.  If the defense is not waived, no claim that was barred by any statute of limitations at the time of the decedent's death shall be allowed or paid.  The running of any statute of limitations measured from some other event than death and advertisement for claims against a decedent is suspended during the four months following the decedent's death but resumes thereafter as to claims not barred pursuant to the sections that follow.  For purposes of any statute of limitations, the proper presentation of a claim under
AS 13.16.465
is equivalent to commencement of a proceeding on the claim.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-460">
            <num>13.16.460</num>
            <heading>Limitations on presentation of claims.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-16-460__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>All claims against a decedent's estate that arose before the death of the decedent, including claims of the state and any subdivision of it, whether due or to become due, absolute or contingent, liquidated or unliquidated, founded on contract, tort, or other legal basis, if not barred earlier by other statute of limitations, are barred against the estate, the personal representative, and the heirs and devisees of the decedent, unless presented as follows:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-460__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>within four months after the date of the first publication of notice to creditors if notice is given in compliance with
AS 13.16.450
; however, claims barred by the nonclaim statute at the decedent's domicile before the first publication for claims in this state are also barred in this state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-460__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>within three years after the decedent's death, if notice to creditors has not been published.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-460__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>All claims against a decedent's estate that arise at or after the death of the decedent, including claims of the state and any subdivision of it, whether due or to become due, absolute or contingent, liquidated or unliquidated, founded on contract, tort, or other legal basis, are barred against the estate, the personal representative, and the heirs and devisees of the decedent, unless presented as follows:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-460__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a claim based on a contract with the personal representative, within four months after performance by the personal representative is due;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-460__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>any other claim, within four months after it arises.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-460__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing in this section affects or prevents</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-460__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>any proceeding to enforce any mortgage, pledge, or lien upon property of the estate; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-460__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to the limits of the insurance protection only, any proceeding to establish liability of the decedent or the personal representative for which there is protection through liability insurance.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-465">
            <num>13.16.465</num>
            <heading>Manner of presentation of claims.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.465.   Manner of presentation of claims.
Claims against a decedent's estate may be presented as follows:
(1) the claimant may deliver or mail to the personal representative a written statement of the claim indicating its basis, the name and address of the claimant, and the amount claimed, or may file a written statement of the claim, in the form prescribed by rule, with the clerk of the court; the claim is considered presented on receipt of the written statement of claim by the personal representative or on the filing of the claim with the court, whichever occurs first; if a claim is not yet due, the date when it will become due shall be stated; if the claim is contingent or unliquidated, the nature of the uncertainty shall be stated; if the claim is secured, the security shall be described; failure to describe correctly the security, the nature of any uncertainty, and the due date of a claim not yet due does not invalidate the presentation made;
(2) the claimant may commence a proceeding against the personal representative in any court where the personal representative may be subjected to jurisdiction, to obtain payment of a claim against the estate, but the commencement of the proceeding must occur within the time limited for presenting the claim; no presentation of claim is required in regard to matters claimed in proceedings against the decedent that were pending at the time of death;
(3) if a claim is presented under (1) of this section, no proceeding on it may be commenced more than 60 days after the personal representative has mailed a notice of disallowance; but, in the case of a claim that is not presently due or that is contingent or unliquidated, the personal representative may consent to an extension of the 60-day period, or to avoid injustice the court, on petition, may order an extension of the 60-day period, but in no event shall the extension run beyond the applicable statute of limitations.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-470">
            <num>13.16.470</num>
            <heading>Priority of claim payment and preference.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-16-470__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the applicable assets of the estate are insufficient to pay all claims in full, the personal representative shall make payment in the following order:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-470__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>costs and expenses of administration;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-470__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>reasonable funeral expenses;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-470__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>debts and taxes with preference under federal law and past due child support payments, except payments required under
AS 25.27.120
 25.27.130;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-470__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>reasonable and necessary medical and hospital expenses of the last illness of the decedent, including compensation of persons attending the decedent;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-470__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>debts and taxes with preference under other laws of this state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-470__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>all other claims.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-470__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Preference may not be given in the payment of any claim over any other claim of the same class, and a claim due and payable is not entitled to a preference over claims not due.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-475">
            <num>13.16.475</num>
            <heading>Allowance of claims.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-16-475__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>As to claims presented in the manner described in
AS 13.16.465
within the time limit prescribed in
AS 13.16.460
, the personal representative may mail a notice to any claimant stating that the claim has been disallowed. If, after allowing or disallowing a claim, the personal representative changes a decision concerning the claim, the personal representative shall notify the claimant.  The personal representative may not change a disallowance of a claim after the time for the claimant to file a petition for allowance or to commence a proceeding on the claim has run and the claim has been barred.  Every claim that is disallowed in whole or in part by the personal representative is barred so far as not allowed unless the claimant files a petition for allowance in the court or commences a proceeding against the personal representative not later than 60 days after the mailing of the notice of disallowance or partial allowance if the notice warns the claimant of the impending bar.  Failure of the personal representative to mail to a claimant notice of action on a claim for 60 days after the time for original presentation of the claim has expired has the effect of a notice of allowance.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-475__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon the petition of the personal representative or of a claimant in a proceeding for the purpose, the court may allow in whole or in part any claim or claims presented to the personal representative or filed with the clerk of the court in due time and not barred by (a) of this section.  Notice in this proceeding shall be given to the claimant, the personal representative, and those other persons interested in the estate as the court may direct by order entered at the time the proceeding is commenced.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-475__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A judgment in a proceeding in another court against a personal representative to enforce a claim against a decedent's estate is an allowance of the claim.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-475__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless otherwise provided in any judgment in another court entered against the personal representative, allowed claims bear interest at the legal rate for the period commencing 60 days after the time for original presentation of the claim has expired unless based on a contract making a provision for interest, in which case they bear interest in accordance with that provision.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-480">
            <num>13.16.480</num>
            <heading>Payment of claims.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-16-480__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon the expiration of four months from the date of the first publication of the notice to creditors, the personal representative shall proceed to pay the claims allowed against the estate in the order of priority prescribed, after making provision for homestead, family and support allowances, for claims already presented that have not yet been allowed or whose allowance has been appealed, and for unbarred claims that may yet be presented, including costs and expenses of administration. By petition to the court in a proceeding for the purpose, or by appropriate motion if the administration is supervised, a claimant whose claim has been allowed but not paid as provided herein may secure an order directing the personal representative to pay the claim to the extent that funds of the estate are available for the payment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-480__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The personal representative at any time may pay any just claim that has not been barred, with or without formal presentation, but the personal representative is personally liable to any other claimant whose claim is allowed and who is injured by such payment if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-480__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the payment was made before the expiration of the time limit stated in (a) of this section and the personal representative failed to require the payee to give adequate security for the refund of any of the payment necessary to pay other claimants; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-480__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the payment was made, due to the negligence or wilful fault of the personal representative, in such a manner as to deprive the injured claimant of priority.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-485">
            <num>13.16.485</num>
            <heading>Individual liability of personal representative.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-16-485__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless otherwise provided in the contract, a personal representative is not individually liable on a contract properly entered into in a fiduciary capacity in the course of administration of the estate unless the personal representative fails to reveal the representative capacity and identify the estate in the contract.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-485__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A personal representative is individually liable for obligations arising from ownership or control of the estate or for torts committed in the course of administration of the estate only if personally at fault.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-485__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Claims based on contracts entered into by a personal representative in a fiduciary capacity, on obligations arising from ownership or control of the estate, or on torts committed in the course of estate administration may be asserted against the estate by proceeding against the personal representative in the personal representative's fiduciary capacity, whether or not the personal representative is individually liable therefor.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-485__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Issues of liability as between the estate and the personal representative individually may be determined in a proceeding for accounting, surcharge, or indemnification or other appropriate proceeding.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-490">
            <num>13.16.490</num>
            <heading>Secured claims.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.490.   Secured claims.
Payment of a secured claim is upon the basis of the amount allowed if the creditor surrenders the creditor's security; otherwise payment is upon the basis of one of the following:
(1) if the creditor exhausts the security before receiving payment, unless precluded by other law, upon the amount of the claim allowed less the fair value of the security; or
(2) if the creditor does not have the right to exhaust the security or has not done so, upon the amount of the claim allowed less the value of the security determined by converting it into money according to the terms of the agreement under which the security was delivered to the creditor, or by the creditor and personal representative by agreement, arbitration, compromise, or litigation.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-495">
            <num>13.16.495</num>
            <heading>Claims not due and contingent or unliquidated claims.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-16-495__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a claim that will become due at a future time or a contingent or unliquidated claim becomes due or certain before the distribution of the estate, and if the claim has been allowed or established by a proceeding, it is paid in the same manner as presently due and absolute claims of the same class.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-495__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In other cases the personal representative or, on petition of the personal representative or the claimant in a special proceeding for the purpose, the court may provide for payment as follows:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-495__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if the claimant consents, the claimant may be paid the present or agreed value of the claim, taking any uncertainty into account;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-495__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>arrangement for future payment, or possible payment, on the happening of the contingency or on liquidation may be made by creating a trust, giving a mortgage, obtaining a bond or security from a distributee, or otherwise.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-500">
            <num>13.16.500</num>
            <heading>Counterclaims.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.500.   Counterclaims.
In allowing a claim the personal representative may deduct any counterclaim that the estate has against the claimant.  In determining a claim against an estate a court shall reduce the amount allowed by the amount of any counterclaims and, if the counterclaims exceed the claim, render a judgment against the claimant in the amount of the excess.  A counterclaim, liquidated or unliquidated, may arise from a transaction other than that upon which the claim is based. A counterclaim may give rise to relief exceeding in amount or different in kind from that sought in the claim.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-505">
            <num>13.16.505</num>
            <heading>Execution and levies prohibited.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.505.   Execution and levies prohibited.
No execution may issue upon nor may any levy be made against any property of the estate under any judgment against a decedent or a personal representative, but this section shall not be construed to prevent the enforcement of mortgages, pledges, or liens upon real or personal property in an appropriate proceeding.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-510">
            <num>13.16.510</num>
            <heading>Compromise of claims.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.510.   Compromise of claims.
When a claim against the estate has been presented in any manner, the personal representative may, if it appears for the best interest of the estate, compromise the claim, whether due or not due, absolute or contingent, liquidated or unliquidated.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-515">
            <num>13.16.515</num>
            <heading>Encumbered assets.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.515.   Encumbered assets.
If any assets of the estate are encumbered by mortgage, pledge, lien, or other security interest, the personal representative may pay the encumbrance or any part of it, renew or extend any obligation secured by the encumbrance, or convey or transfer the assets to the creditor in satisfaction of a lien, in whole or in part, whether or not the holder of the encumbrance has presented a claim, if it appears to be for the best interest of the estate. Payment of an encumbrance does not increase the share of the distributee entitled to the encumbered assets unless the distributee is entitled to exoneration.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-520">
            <num>13.16.520</num>
            <heading>Administration in more than one state; duty of personal representative.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-16-520__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>All assets of estates being administered in this state are subject to all claims, allowances, and charges existing or established against the personal representative wherever appointed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-520__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the estate either in this state or as a whole is insufficient to cover all family exemptions and allowances determined by the law of the decedent's domicile, prior charges, and claims, after satisfaction of the exemptions, allowances, and charges, each claimant whose claim has been allowed either in the state or elsewhere in administrations of which the personal representative is aware, is entitled to receive payment of an equal proportion of each claim.  If a preference or security in regard to a claim is allowed in another jurisdiction but not in this state, the creditor so benefited is to receive dividends from local assets only upon the balance of the claim after deducting the amount of the benefit.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-520__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the family exemptions and allowances, prior charges, and claims of the entire estate exceed the total value of the portions of the estate being administered separately and this state is not the state of the decedent's last domicile, the claims allowed in this state shall be paid their proportion if local assets are adequate for the purpose, and the balance of local assets shall be transferred to the domiciliary personal representative.  If local assets are not sufficient to pay all claims allowed in this state the amount to which they are entitled, local assets shall be marshalled so that each claim allowed in this state is paid its proportion as far as possible, after taking into account all dividends on claims allowed in this state from assets in other jurisdictions.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-525">
            <num>13.16.525</num>
            <heading>Final distribution to domiciliary representative.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.525.   Final distribution to domiciliary representative.
The estate of a nonresident decedent being administered by a personal representative appointed in this state shall, if there is a personal representative of the decedent's domicile willing to receive it, be distributed to the domiciliary personal representative for the benefit of the successors of the decedent unless (1) by virtue of the decedent's will, if any, and applicable choice of law rules, the successors are identified under the local law of this state without reference to the local law of the decedent's domicile; (2) the personal representative of this state, after reasonable inquiry, is unaware of the existence or identity of a domiciliary personal representative; or (3) the court orders otherwise in a proceeding for a closing order under
AS 13.16.620
or incident to the closing of a supervised administration.  In other cases, distribution of the estate of a decedent shall be made in accordance with
AS 13.16.005
 13.16.400 and 13.16.535  13.16.695.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-530">
            <num>13.16.530</num>
            <heading>Application to trustees.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.530.   Application to trustees.
Notwithstanding
AS 13.16.450
 13.16.525, the trustee of a trust may, under
AS 13.36.368
(b)(3), take the action a personal representative may take under
AS 13.16.450
 13.16.525.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-535">
            <num>13.16.535</num>
            <heading>Successors' rights if no administration.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.535.   Successors' rights if no administration.
In the absence of administration, the heirs and devisees are entitled to the estate in accordance with the terms of a probated will or the laws of intestate succession.  Devisees may establish title by the probated will to devised property. Persons entitled to property by homestead allowance, exemption, or intestacy may establish title to it by proof of the decedent's ownership, death, and their relationship to the decedent.  Successors take subject to all charges incident to administration, including the claims of creditors and allowances of surviving spouse and dependent children, and subject to the rights of others resulting from abatement, retainer, advancement, and ademption.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-540">
            <num>13.16.540</num>
            <heading>Distribution; order in which assets appropriated; abatement.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-16-540__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (b) of this section and except as provided in connection with the share of the surviving spouse who elects to take an elective share, shares of distributees abate, without any preference or priority as between real and personal property, in the following order: (1) property not disposed of by the will; (2) residuary devises; (3) general devises; (4) specific devises.  For purposes of abatement, a general devise charged on any specific property or fund is a specific devise to the extent of the value of the property on which it is charged, and upon the failure or insufficiency of the property on which it is charged, a general devise to the extent of the failure or insufficiency.  Abatement within each classification is in proportion to the amounts of property each of the beneficiaries would have received if full distribution of the property had been made in accordance with the terms of the will.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-540__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the will expresses an order of abatement, or if the testamentary plan or the express or implied purpose of the devise would be defeated by the order of abatement stated in (a) of this section, the shares of the distributees abate as may be found necessary to give effect to the intention of the testator.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-540__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the subject of a preferred devise is sold or used incident to administration, abatement shall be achieved by appropriate adjustments in, or contribution from, other interests in the remaining assets.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-545">
            <num>13.16.545</num>
            <heading>Right of retainer.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.545.   Right of retainer.
The amount of a noncontingent indebtedness of a successor to the estate if due, or its present value if not due, shall be offset against the successor's interest; but the successor has the benefit of any defense that would be available to the successor in a direct proceeding for recovery of the debt.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-555">
            <num>13.16.555</num>
            <heading>Penalty clause for contest.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.555.   Penalty clause for contest.
A provision in a will purporting to penalize any interested person for contesting the will or instituting other proceedings relating to the estate is unenforceable if probable cause exists for instituting proceedings.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-560">
            <num>13.16.560</num>
            <heading>Distribution in kind; valuation; method.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-16-560__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless a contrary intention is indicated by the will, the distributable assets of a decedent's estate shall be distributed in kind to the extent possible through application of the following provisions:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-560__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a specific devisee is entitled to distribution of the thing devised, and a spouse or child who has selected particular assets of an estate as provided in
AS 13.12.402
 13.12.405 shall receive the items selected;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-560__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a homestead or family allowance or devise payable in money may be satisfied by value in kind if
(A) the person entitled to the payment has not demanded payment in cash;
(B) the property distributed in kind is valued at fair market value as of the date of its distribution; and
(C) no residuary devisee has requested that the asset in question remain a part of the residue of the estate;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-560__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>for the purpose of valuation under (2) of this subsection, securities regularly traded on recognized exchanges, if distributed in kind, are valued at the price for the last sale of like securities traded on the business day before distribution or, if there was no sale on that day, at the median between amounts bid and offered at the close of that day; assets consisting of sums owed the decedent or the estate by solvent debtors as to which there is no known dispute or defense are valued at the sum due with accrued interest or discounted to the date of distribution; for assets that do not have readily ascertainable values, a valuation as of a date not more than 30 days before the date of distribution, if otherwise reasonable, controls; for purposes of facilitating distribution, the personal representative may ascertain the value of the assets as of the time of the proposed distribution in any reasonable way, including the employment of qualified appraisers, even if the assets may have been previously appraised;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-560__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the residuary estate shall be distributed in any equitable manner, including distribution in kind, in cash, partially in kind, partially in cash, in divided interests, in undivided interests, pro rata among all the distributees, or by a method other than pro rata among all distributees; distribution under this paragraph may be made without regard to the income tax basis or other special tax attributes of the assets; a distribution under this paragraph may be made in whatever manner the personal representative finds to be the most practicable and in the best interests of the distributees.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-560__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After the probable charges against the estate are known, the personal representative may mail or deliver a proposal for distribution to all persons who have a right to object to the proposed distribution.  The right of any distributee to object to the proposed distribution on the basis of the kind or value of asset to be received by the distributee, if not waived earlier in writing, terminates if the distributee fails to object in writing received by the personal representative within 30 days after mailing or delivery of the proposal.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-565">
            <num>13.16.565</num>
            <heading>Distribution in kind; evidence.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.565.   Distribution in kind; evidence.
If distribution in kind is made, the personal representative shall execute an instrument or deed of distribution assigning, transferring, or releasing the assets to the distributee as evidence of the distributee's title to the property.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-570">
            <num>13.16.570</num>
            <heading>Distribution; right or title of distributee.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.570.   Distribution; right or title of distributee.
Proof that a distributee has received an instrument or deed of distribution of assets in kind, or payment in distribution, from a personal representative, is conclusive evidence that the distributee has succeeded to the interest of the estate in the distributed assets, as against all persons interested in the estate, except that the personal representative may recover the assets or their value if the distribution was improper.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-575">
            <num>13.16.575</num>
            <heading>Improper distribution; liability of distributee.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.575.   Improper distribution; liability of distributee.
Unless the distribution or payment no longer can be questioned because of adjudication, estoppel, or limitation, a distributee of property improperly distributed or paid, or a claimant who was improperly paid, is liable to return the property improperly received and its income since distribution if the distributee or claimant has the property.  If the distributee or claimant does not have the property, then the distributee or claimant is liable to return the value as of the date of disposition of the property improperly received and its income and gain.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-580">
            <num>13.16.580</num>
            <heading>Purchasers from distributees protected.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.580.   Purchasers from distributees protected.
If property distributed in kind or a security interest in it is acquired for value by a purchaser from or lender to a distributee who has received an instrument or deed of distribution from the personal representative, the purchaser or lender takes title free of rights of any interested person in the estate and incurs no personal liability to the estate, or to any interested person, whether or not the distribution was proper or supported by court order and whether or not the authority of the personal representative was terminated before execution of the instrument or deed. This section protects a purchaser from or lender to a distributee who, as personal representative, executed the deed of distribution, as well as a purchaser from or lender to any other distributee or transferee of a distributee. To be protected under this provision, a purchaser or lender need not inquire whether a personal representative acted properly in making the distribution in kind, even if the personal representative and the distributee are the same person, or whether the authority of the personal representative had terminated before the distribution. Any instrument described in this section that is recorded under
AS 40.17
or filed under former
AS 45.09
or under
AS 45.29
and that bears a notation of that recordation or filing is prima facie evidence that the transfer described in it was made for value.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-585">
            <num>13.16.585</num>
            <heading>Partition for purpose of distribution.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.585.   Partition for purpose of distribution.
When two or more heirs or devisees are entitled to distribution of undivided interests in any real or personal property of the estate, the personal representative or one or more of the heirs or devisees may petition the court before the formal or informal closing of the estate, to make partition.  After notice to the interested heirs or devisees, the court shall partition the property in the same manner as provided by the law for civil actions of partition.  The court may direct the personal representative to sell any property that cannot be partitioned without prejudice to the owners and that cannot conveniently be allotted to any one party.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-590">
            <num>13.16.590</num>
            <heading>Private agreements among successors to decedent binding on personal representative.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.590.   Private agreements among successors to decedent binding on personal representative.
Subject to the rights of creditors and taxing authorities, competent successors may agree among themselves to alter the interests, shares, or amounts to which they are entitled under the will of the decedent, or under the laws of intestacy, in any way that they provide in a written contract executed by all who are affected by its provisions.  The personal representative shall abide by the terms of the agreement subject to the obligation to administer the estate for the benefit of creditors, to pay all taxes and costs of administration, and to carry out the responsibilities of office for the benefit of any successors of the decedent who are not parties.  Personal representatives of decedents' estates are not required to see to the performance of trusts if the trustee thereof is another person who is willing to accept the trust. Accordingly, trustees of a testamentary trust are successors for the purposes of this section. Nothing in this section relieves trustees of any duties owed to beneficiaries of trusts.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-595">
            <num>13.16.595</num>
            <heading>Distributions to trustee.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-16-595__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before distributing to a trustee, the personal representative may require that the trust be registered if the state in which it is to be administered provides for registration and that the trustee inform the beneficiaries as provided in
AS 13.36.080
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-595__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the trust instrument does not excuse the trustee from giving bond, the personal representative may petition the appropriate court to require that the trustee post bond if the personal representative apprehends that distribution might jeopardize the interests of persons who are not able to protect themselves, and the personal representative may withhold distribution until the court has acted.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-595__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>No inference of negligence on the part of the personal representative shall be drawn from failure to exercise the authority conferred by (a) and (b) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-600">
            <num>13.16.600</num>
            <heading>Disposition of unclaimed assets.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-16-600__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If an heir, devisee, or claimant cannot be found, the personal representative shall distribute the share of personal property of the missing person to the person's conservator, or if the person has no conservator to the Department of Revenue to be deposited in the general fund as required by
AS 34.45.370
. Property distributable to the Department of Revenue under this subsection is subject to
AS 34.45.280
 34.45.780.  If notice to the heir, devisee, or claimant, substantially equivalent to that required by
AS 34.45.310
, has been given by the personal representative or other person,
AS 34.45.310
does not apply.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-600__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Real property distributable to a missing heir, devisee, or claimant shall be distributed first to the conservator of the heir, devisee, or claimant; if the heir, devisee, or claimant has no conservator, the real property passes to the state. Real property reported under this subsection is subject to
AS 38.95.200
 38.95.270.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-605">
            <num>13.16.605</num>
            <heading>Distribution to person under disability.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.605.   Distribution to person under disability.
A personal representative may discharge the obligation to distribute to any person under legal disability by distributing to the person's conservator, or any other person authorized by
AS 13.06

AS 13.36
or otherwise to give a valid receipt and discharge for the distribution.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-610">
            <num>13.16.610</num>
            <heading>Apportionment of estate taxes.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-16-610__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless the will provides otherwise, the tax shall be apportioned among all persons interested in the estate. The apportionment is to be made in the proportion that the value of the interest of each person interested in the estate bears to the total value of the interests of all persons interested in the estate.  The values used in determining the tax are to be used for that purpose.  If the decedent's will directs a method of apportionment of tax different from the method described in
AS 13.06

AS 13.36
, the method described in the will controls.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-610__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The court in which venue lies for the administration of the estate of a decedent, on petition for the purpose, may determine the apportionment of the tax.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-610__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the court finds that it is inequitable to apportion interest and penalties in the manner provided in (a) of this section, because of special circumstances, it may direct apportionment of them in the manner it finds equitable.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-610__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the court finds that the assessment of penalties and interest assessed in relation to the tax is due to delay caused by the negligence of the fiduciary, the court may charge the fiduciary with the amount of the assessed penalties and interest.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-610__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In any action to recover from any person interested in the estate the amount of the tax apportioned to the person in accordance with
AS 13.06

AS 13.36
, the determination of the court in respect thereto shall be prima facie correct.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-610__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The personal representative or other person in possession of the property of the decedent required to pay the tax may withhold from any property distributable to any person interested in the estate, upon its distribution, the amount of tax attributable to the distributee's interest. If the property in possession of the personal representative or other person required to pay the tax and distributable to any person interested in the estate is insufficient to satisfy the proportionate amount of the tax determined to be due from the person, the personal representative or other person required to pay the tax may recover the deficiency from the person interested in the estate.  If the property is not in the possession of the personal representative or the other person required to pay the tax, the personal representative or the other person required to pay the tax may recover from any person interested in the estate the amount of the tax apportioned to the person in accordance with this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-610__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If property held by the personal representative is distributed before final apportionment of the tax, the distributee shall provide a bond or other security for the apportionment liability in the form and amount prescribed by the personal representative.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-610__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In making an apportionment, allowances shall be made for any exemptions granted, for any classification made of persons interested in the estate, and for any deductions and credits allowed by the law imposing the tax.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-610__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Any exemption or deduction allowed by reason of the relationship of any person to the decedent or by reason of the purposes of the gift inures to the benefit of the person bearing the relationship or receiving the gift; but if an interest is subject to a prior present interest that is not allowable as a deduction, the tax apportionable against the present interest shall be paid from principal.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-610__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Any deduction for property previously taxed and any credit for gift taxes or death taxes of a foreign country paid by the decedent or the decedent's estate inures to the proportionate benefit of all persons liable to apportionment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-610__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Any credit for inheritance, succession, or estate taxes, or taxes in the nature thereof applicable to property or interests includable in the estate, inures to the benefit of the persons or interests chargeable with the payment thereof to the extent proportionately that the credit reduces the tax.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-610__subsec_l">
              <num>(l)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To the extent that property passing to or in trust for a surviving spouse or any charitable, public, or similar gift or devisee is not an allowable deduction for purposes of the tax solely by reason of an inheritance tax or other death tax imposed upon and deductible from the property, the property is not included in the computation provided for in (a) of this section, and to that extent no apportionment is made against the property. This subsection does not apply to any case if the result would be to deprive the estate of a deduction otherwise allowable under Section 2053(d) of the Internal Revenue Code of 1954, as amended, of the United States, relating to deduction for state death taxes on transfers for public, charitable, or religious uses.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-610__subsec_m">
              <num>(m)</num>
              <content>
                <p>No interest in income and no estate for years or for life or other temporary interest in any property or fund is subject to apportionment as between the temporary interest and the remainder.  The tax on the temporary interest and the tax, if any, on the remainder is chargeable against the corpus of the property or funds subject to the temporary interest and remainder.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-610__subsec_n">
              <num>(n)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Neither the personal representative nor other person required to pay the tax is under any duty to institute any action to recover from any person interested in the estate the amount of the tax apportioned to the person until the expiration of the three months next following final determination of the tax.  A personal representative or other person required to pay the tax who institutes the action within a reasonable time after the three-month period is not subject to any liability or surcharge because any portion of the tax apportioned to any person interested in the estate was collectable at a time following the death of the decedent but thereafter became uncollectable.  If the personal representative or other person required to pay the tax cannot collect from any person interested in the estate the amount of the tax apportioned to the person, the amount not recoverable shall be equitably apportioned among the other persons interested in the estate who are subject to apportionment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-610__subsec_o">
              <num>(o)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A personal representative acting in another state or a person required to pay the tax domiciled in another state may institute an action in the courts of this state and may recover a proportionate amount of the federal estate tax, of an estate tax payable to another state or of a death duty due by a decedent's estate to another state, from a person interested in the estate who is either domiciled in this state or who owns property in this state subject to attachment or execution.  For the purposes of the action the determination of apportionment by the court having jurisdiction of the administration of the decedent's estate in the other state is prima facie correct.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-610__subsec_p">
              <num>(p)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-610__subsec_p__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>estate means the gross estate of a decedent as determined for the purpose of federal estate tax and the estate tax payable to this state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-610__subsec_p__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>fiduciary means personal representative or trustee;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-610__subsec_p__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>person means any individual, partnership, association, joint stock company, corporation, government, political subdivision, governmental agency, or local governmental agency;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-610__subsec_p__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>person interested in the estate means any person entitled to receive, or who has received, from a decedent or by reason of the death of a decedent any property or interest in the property included in the decedent's estate; it includes a personal representative, conservator, and trustee;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-610__subsec_p__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>state means any state, territory, or possession of the United States, the District of Columbia, and the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-610__subsec_p__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>tax means the federal estate tax and the additional inheritance tax imposed by
AS 43.31
and interest and penalties imposed in addition to the tax.
Article 10. Closing Estates.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-620">
            <num>13.16.620</num>
            <heading>Formal proceedings terminating administration; testate or intestate; order of general protection.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-16-620__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A personal representative or any interested person may petition for an order of complete settlement of the estate. The personal representative may petition at any time, and any other interested person may petition after one year from the appointment of the original personal representative except that no petition under this section may be entertained until the time for presenting claims that arose before the death of the decedent has expired. The petition may request the court to determine testacy, if not previously determined, to consider the final account or compel or approve an accounting and distribution, to construe any will or determine heirs and adjudicate the final settlement and distribution of the estate.  After notice to all interested persons and hearing the court may enter an order or orders, on appropriate conditions, determining the persons entitled to distribution of the estate, and, as circumstances require, approving settlement and directing or approving distribution of the estate and discharging the personal representative from further claim or demand of any interested person.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-620__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If one or more heirs or devisees were omitted as parties in, or were not given notice of, a previous formal testacy proceeding, the court, on proper petition for an order of complete settlement of the estate under this section, and after notice to the omitted or unnotified persons and other interested parties determined to be interested on the assumption that the previous order concerning testacy is conclusive as to those given notice of the earlier proceeding, may determine testacy as it affects the omitted persons and confirm or alter the previous order of testacy as it affects all interested persons as appropriate in the light of the new proofs.  In the absence of objection by an omitted or unnotified person, evidence received in the original testacy proceeding constitutes prima facie proof of due execution of any will previously admitted to probate, or of the fact that the decedent left no valid will if the prior proceedings determined this fact.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-625">
            <num>13.16.625</num>
            <heading>Formal proceedings terminating testate administration; order construing will without adjudicating testacy.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.625.   Formal proceedings terminating testate administration; order construing will without adjudicating testacy.
A personal representative administering an estate under an informally probated will or any devisee under an informally probated will may petition for an order of settlement of the estate that will not adjudicate the testacy status of the decedent.  The personal representative may petition at any time, and a devisee may petition after one year, from the appointment of the original personal representative, except that no petition under this section may be entertained until the time for presenting claims that arose before the death of the decedent has expired. The petition may request the court to consider the final account or compel or approve an accounting and distribution, to construe the will and adjudicate final settlement and distribution of the estate. After notice to all devisees and the personal representative and hearing, the court may enter an order or orders, on appropriate conditions, determining the persons entitled to distribution of the estate under the will, and, as circumstances require, approving settlement and directing or approving distribution of the estate and discharging the personal representative from further claim or demand of any devisee who is a party to the proceeding and those the devisee represents.  If it appears that a part of the estate is intestate, the proceedings shall be dismissed or amendments made to meet the provisions of
AS 13.16.620
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-630">
            <num>13.16.630</num>
            <heading>Closing estates; by sworn statement of personal representative.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-16-630__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless prohibited by order of the court and except for estates being administered in supervised administration proceedings, a personal representative may close an estate by filing with the court no earlier than six months after the date of original appointment of a general personal representative for the estate, a verified statement stating that the personal representative, or a prior personal representative, has</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-630__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>published notice to creditors as provided by
AS 13.16.450
and that the first publication occurred more than six months before the date of the statement;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-630__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>fully administered the estate of the decedent by making payment, settlement, or other disposition of all claims that were presented, expenses of administration and estate, inheritance, and other death taxes, except as specified in the statement, and that the assets of the estate have been distributed to the persons entitled; if any claims remain undischarged, the statement must state whether the personal representative has distributed the estate subject to possible liability with the agreement of the distributees or it must state in detail other arrangements that have been made to accommodate outstanding liabilities; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-630__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>sent a copy of it to all distributees of the estate and to all creditors or other claimants of whom the personal representative is aware whose claims are neither paid nor barred and has furnished a full account in writing of the administration to the distributees whose interests are affected by it.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-630__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If no proceedings involving the personal representative are pending in the court one year after the closing statement is filed, the appointment of the personal representative terminates.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-635">
            <num>13.16.635</num>
            <heading>Liability of distributees to claimants.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.635.   Liability of distributees to claimants.
After assets of an estate have been distributed and subject to
AS 13.16.645
, an undischarged claim not barred may be prosecuted in a proceeding against one or more distributees. A distributee is not liable to claimants for amounts received as exempt property, homestead or family allowances, or for amounts in excess of the value of a distribution as of the time of distribution.  As between distributees, each shall bear the cost of satisfaction of unbarred claims as if the claim had been satisfied in the course of administration.  Any distributee who fails to notify other distributees of the demand made upon the distributee by the claimant in sufficient time to permit them to join in any proceeding in which the claim was asserted against the distributee loses the right of contribution against other distributees.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-640">
            <num>13.16.640</num>
            <heading>Limitations on proceedings against personal representative.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.640.   Limitations on proceedings against personal representative.
Unless previously barred by adjudication and except as provided in the closing statement, the rights of successors and of creditors whose claims have not otherwise been barred against the personal representative for breach of fiduciary duty are barred unless a proceeding to assert them is commenced within six months after the filing of the closing statement.  The rights thus barred do not include rights to recover from a personal representative for fraud, misrepresentation, or inadequate disclosure related to the settlement of the decedent's estate.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-645">
            <num>13.16.645</num>
            <heading>Limitations on actions and proceedings against distributees.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.645.   Limitations on actions and proceedings against distributees.
Unless previously adjudicated in a formal testacy proceeding or in a proceeding settling the accounts of a personal representative or otherwise barred, the claim of any claimant to recover from a distributee who is liable to pay the claim, and the right of any heir or devisee, or of a successor personal representative acting in their behalf, to recover property improperly distributed or the value of it from any distributee is forever barred at the later of (1) three years after the decedent's death; or (2) one year after the time of distribution of it.  This section does not bar an action to recover property or value received as the result of fraud.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-650">
            <num>13.16.650</num>
            <heading>Certificate discharging liens securing fiduciary performance.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.650.   Certificate discharging liens securing fiduciary performance.
After the appointment has terminated, the personal representative, the sureties of the personal representative, or any successor of either, upon the filing of a verified application showing, so far as is known by the applicant, that no action concerning the estate is pending in any court, is entitled to receive a certificate from the registrar that the personal representative appears to have fully administered the estate in question.  The certificate evidences discharge of any lien on any property given to secure the obligation of the personal representative in lieu of bond or any surety, but does not preclude action against the personal representative or the surety.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-655">
            <num>13.16.655</num>
            <heading>Subsequent administration.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.655.   Subsequent administration.
If other property of the estate is discovered after an estate has been settled and the personal representative discharged or after one year after a closing statement has been filed, the court upon petition of any interested person and upon notice as it directs may appoint the same or a successor personal representative to administer the subsequently discovered estate.  If a new appointment is made, unless the court orders otherwise, the provisions of
AS 13.06

AS 13.36
apply as appropriate; but no claim previously barred may be asserted in the subsequent administration.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-665">
            <num>13.16.665</num>
            <heading>Effect of approval of agreements.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.665.   Effect of approval of agreements.
A compromise of any controversy as to admission to probate of any instrument offered for formal probate as the will of a decedent, the construction, validity, or effect of any governing instrument, the rights or interests in the estate of the decedent, of any successor, or the administration of the estate, if approved in a formal proceeding in the court for that purpose, is binding on all the parties to the compromise including those unborn, unascertained or who could not be located. An approved compromise is binding even though it may affect a trust or an inalienable interest. A compromise does not impair the rights of creditors or of taxing authorities who are not parties to it.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-670">
            <num>13.16.670</num>
            <heading>Procedure for securing court approval of compromise.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.670.   Procedure for securing court approval of compromise.
The procedure for securing court approval of a compromise is as follows:
(1) the terms of the compromise shall be set out in an agreement in writing that shall be executed by all competent persons and parents acting for any minor child having beneficial interests or having claims that will or may be affected by the compromise; execution is not required by any person whose identity cannot be ascertained or whose whereabouts is unknown and cannot reasonably be ascertained;
(2) an interested person, including the personal representative, if any, or a trustee, then may submit the agreement to the court for its approval and for execution by the personal representative, the trustee of every affected testamentary trust, and other fiduciaries and representatives;
(3) after notice to all interested persons or their representatives, including the personal representative of any estate and all affected trustees of trusts, the court, if it finds that the contest or controversy is in good faith and that the effect of the agreement upon the interests of persons represented by fiduciaries or other representatives is just and reasonable, shall make an order approving the agreement and directing all fiduciaries under its supervision to execute the agreement; minor children represented only by their parents may be bound only if their parents join with other competent persons in execution of the compromise; upon the making of the order and the execution of the agreement, all further disposition of the estate is in accordance with the terms of the agreement.
Article 12. Collection of Personal Property by Affidavit and Summary Administration Procedure.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-680">
            <num>13.16.680</num>
            <heading>Collection of personal property by affidavit.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-16-680__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Thirty days after the death of a decedent, any person indebted to the decedent or having possession of tangible personal property or an instrument evidencing a debt, obligation, stock, or chose in action belonging to the decedent shall make payment of the indebtedness or deliver the tangible personal property or an instrument evidencing a debt, obligation, stock, or chose in action to a person claiming to be the successor of the decedent upon being presented an affidavit made by or on behalf of the successor stating that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-680__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the entire estate, wherever located, less liens and encumbrances, consists only of not more than
(A) vehicles subject to registration under
AS 28.10.011
with a total value that does not exceed $100,000; and
(B) personal property, other than vehicles described in (A) of this paragraph, that does not exceed $50,000;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-680__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>30 days have elapsed since the death of the decedent;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-680__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>no application or petition for the appointment of a personal representative is pending or has been granted in any jurisdiction; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-680__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the claiming successor is entitled to payment or delivery of the property.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-680__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A transfer agent of any security shall change the registered ownership on the books of a corporation from the decedent to the successor or successors upon the presentation of an affidavit as provided in (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-685">
            <num>13.16.685</num>
            <heading>Effect of affidavit.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.685.   Effect of affidavit.
The person paying, delivering, transferring, or issuing personal property or the evidence of it under affidavit is discharged and released to the same extent as if the person dealt with a personal representative of the decedent.  The person is not required to see to the application of the personal property or evidence of it or to inquire into the truth of any statement in the affidavit.  If any person to whom an affidavit is delivered refuses to pay, deliver, transfer, or issue any personal property or evidence of it, it may be recovered or its payment, delivery, transfer, or issuance compelled upon proof of their right in a proceeding brought for the purpose by or on behalf of the persons entitled to it.  Any person to whom payment, delivery, transfer, or issuance is made is answerable and accountable for it to any personal representative of the estate or to any other person having a superior right.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-690">
            <num>13.16.690</num>
            <heading>Small estates; summary administrative procedure.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.690.   Small estates; summary administrative procedure.
If it appears from the inventory and appraisal that the value of the entire estate, less liens and encumbrances, does not exceed homestead allowance, exempt property, family allowance, costs and expenses of administration, reasonable funeral expenses, and reasonable and necessary medical and hospital expenses of the last illness of the decedent, the personal representative, without giving notice to creditors, may immediately disburse and distribute the estate to the persons entitled to it and file a closing statement as provided in
AS 13.16.695
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-695">
            <num>13.16.695</num>
            <heading>Small estates; closing by sworn statement of personal representative.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-16-695__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless prohibited by order of the court and except for estates being administered by supervised personal representatives, a personal representative may close an estate administered under the summary procedures of
AS 13.16.690
by filing with the court, at any time after disbursement and distribution of the estate, a verified statement stating that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-695__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>to the best knowledge of the personal representative, the value of the entire estate, less liens and encumbrances, did not exceed homestead allowance, exempt property, family allowance, costs and expenses of administration, reasonable funeral expenses, and reasonable, necessary medical and hospital expenses of the last illness of the decedent;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-695__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the personal representative has fully administered the estate by disbursing and distributing it to the persons entitled to it; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="13-16-695__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the personal representative has sent a copy of the closing statement to all distributees of the estate and to all creditors or other claimants of whom the personal representative is aware whose claims are neither paid nor barred and has furnished a full account in writing of the administration to the distributees whose interests are affected.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-695__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If no action or proceeding involving the personal representative is pending in the court one year after the closing statement is filed, the appointment of the personal representative terminates.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-695__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A closing statement filed under this section has the same effect as one filed under
AS 13.16.630
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-695__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The superior court may authorize the disposal in a manner it prescribes of personal property which has not been disposed of under this section by the end of six months if no heirs or claimants have been located.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-700">
            <num>13.16.700</num>
            <heading>Settlement directed by court.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 13.16.700.   Settlement directed by court.
When a judge receives information that a person has died in the judge's judicial district leaving an estate with property limited to the property described under
AS 13.16.680
(a)(1) or less and no qualified person has appeared to take charge of the assets, the judge may immediately appoint a person, corporation, or attorney to settle the estate in the manner provided for in
AS 13.16.680
 13.16.695.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_13-16-705">
            <num>13.16.705</num>
            <heading>Inheritance of Native corporation stock.</heading>
            <subsection eId="13-16-705__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The settlement common stock or other inalienable stock in a corporation organized under the laws of Alaska under 43 U.S.C. 1601 et seq. (Alaska Native Claims Settlement Act) is not subject to probate nor shall its value be considered in determining the value of an estate or allowance under this title. Upon death of the holder, if the stock does not pass by the testamentary disposition clause on the stock certificate or by the form authorized under (b) of this section, properly executed, it passes by will or intestate succession. In such a case, the determination of the person entitled to the stock shall be made by the corporation that initially issued the stock or its designated agent. The determination shall be made on the basis of an affidavit, furnished to the corporation that initially issued the stock, or its agent, showing the right of the person entitled to the stock to receive it. The affidavit, accepted in good faith by the corporation or its agent, has the same effect as an affidavit under
AS 13.16.685
, and the person entitled to the stock, if the affidavit is not accepted, has the remedy set out in
AS 13.16.685
. In case of dispute as to the person entitled to receive the stock, a person claiming ownership may bring an independent action in the superior court.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-705__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless a separate form is provided that substantially satisfies the requirements of this subsection and that is distributed to the same extent as the certificate, each certificate representing the stock shall bear provisions, on its reverse side, containing blanks to be filled in by the owner, constituting a last will and testament for the purposes of this section and 43 U.S.C. 1606(h) insofar as the shares represented by that certificate are concerned. The clause may be signed by the owner, dated, and notarized. This testamentary disposition may be changed from time to time or revoked, and it governs unless there is a subsequently executed certificate, form, or formal will making specific disposition of the stock.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-705__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When ownership of stock passes by devise or inheritance or as a result of court action, the stock shall be partitioned, insofar as practicable, in whole shares among those entitled to them.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-705__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a deceased shareholder has failed to dispose of the stock by will and has no heirs under the applicable laws of intestacy, the shares escheat to the corporation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-705__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The situs of the stock is Alaska.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-705__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This section applies to stock as long as the stock remains inalienable.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="13-16-705__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Where appropriate, terms used in this section have the meanings given in
AS 13.06.050
. In this section, stock means the settlement common stock or other inalienable stock of a corporation organized under the laws of the state under 43 U.S.C. 1601 et seq. (Alaska Native Claims Settlement Act), and includes membership in a corporation organized under
AS 10.20
and inchoate rights to stock.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>