<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-11"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-11"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="8.11"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-11/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-11/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-11/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-11/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_8">
        <num>8</num>
        <heading>Business and Professions</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_8__chp_11">
          <num>11</num>
          <heading>Audiologists and Speech-language Pathologists</heading>
          <section eId="sec_08-11-010">
            <num>08.11.010</num>
            <heading>Qualifications for audiologist license.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-11-010__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>a Certificate of Clinical Competence in Audiology from the American Speech-Language-Hearing Association or the equivalent of the certificate; or
(ii) practiced audiology for two years as of January 1, 1986, or is in the process of completing the year of supervised clinical experience required for the Certificate of Clinical Competence of the American Speech-Language-Hearing Association; and</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-010__subsec_i__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has been fingerprinted and has provided the fees required by the Department of Public Safety under
AS 12.62.160
for criminal justice information and a national criminal history record check; the fingerprints and fees shall be forwarded to the Department of Public Safety to obtain a report of criminal justice information under
AS 12.62
and a national criminal history record check under
AS 12.62.400
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-11-015">
            <num>08.11.015</num>
            <heading>Qualifications for speech-language pathologist license.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.11.015.   Qualifications for speech-language pathologist license.
The department shall issue a license to practice speech-language pathology to an individual who
(1) is 18 years of age or older;
(2) applies on a form provided by the department;
(3) pays the fee required under
AS 08.11.050
;
(4) has not engaged in conduct that is a ground for imposing disciplinary sanctions under
AS 08.11.085
;
(5) furnishes evidence satisfactory to the department that the person holds a Certificate of Clinical Competence in speech-language pathology from the American Speech-Language-Hearing Association or the equivalent of the certificate; and
(6)  has been fingerprinted and has provided the fees required by the Department of Public Safety under
AS 12.62.160
for criminal justice information and a national criminal history record check; the fingerprints and fees shall be forwarded to the Department of Public Safety to obtain a report of criminal justice information under
AS 12.62
and a national criminal history record check under
AS 12.62.400
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-11-017">
            <num>08.11.017</num>
            <heading>Exemption from criminal justice information and criminal history record check.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.11.017.   Exemption from criminal justice information and criminal history record check.
An audiologist or speech-language pathologist holding a valid license under this chapter on July 1, 2024, is exempt from the requirements of
AS 08.11.010
(5) and 08.11.015(6), but is otherwise subject to this chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-11-020">
            <num>08.11.020</num>
            <heading>Temporary license to practice audiology as an audiologist.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-11-020__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>On receipt of the completed application the department shall issue a temporary license for the practice of audiology as an audiologist to an individual who is licensed to practice audiology in another state and has submitted to the department an application for a license under
AS 08.11.010
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-020__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may issue a temporary license to the following:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-020__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a nonresident for the practice of audiology as an audiologist in the state for 30 days or less in a calendar year, if the individual is licensed to practice audiology in another state, territory of the United States, foreign country, or province that has requirements for a license to practice audiology that are substantially equivalent to or higher than the requirements of
AS 08.11.010
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-020__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a nonresident for the practice of audiology as an audiologist in the state for 30 days or less in a calendar year, if the individual meets the qualifications and requirements for a license under
AS 08.11.010
, and resides in a state or territory of the United States or a foreign country or province that does not license individuals to practice audiology.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-020__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may impose by regulation additional limitations that it determines appropriate on a temporary license issued under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-11-025">
            <num>08.11.025</num>
            <heading>Temporary license to practice speech-language pathology as a speech-language pathologist.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-11-025__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may issue a temporary license for the practice of speech-language pathology as a speech-language pathologist to an individual who is licensed to practice speech-language pathology in another state and has submitted to the department an application for a license and appropriate fees under
AS 08.11.015
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-025__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Subject to (c) and (d) of this section, the department may issue a temporary license to the following:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-025__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a nonresident for the practice of speech-language pathology as a speech-language pathologist in the state for 60 days or less in a calendar year, if the individual is licensed to practice speech-language pathology in another state, territory of the United States, foreign country, or province that has requirements for a license to practice speech-language pathology that are substantially equivalent to or higher than the requirements of
AS 08.11.015
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-025__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a nonresident for the practice of speech-language pathology as a speech-language pathologist in the state for 60 days or less in a calendar year, if the individual meets the qualifications and requirements for a license under
AS 08.11.015
and resides in a state or territory of the United States or a foreign country or province that does not license individuals to practice speech-language pathology;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-025__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a person, whether a resident or not, who is in the process of completing a year of supervised clinical experience required for a certificate of clinical competence in speech-language pathology from the American Speech-Language Hearing Association.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-025__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall deny a temporary license to an applicant under (b) of this section if the board finds that the applicant has committed an act that is grounds for a disciplinary sanction under
AS 08.11.085
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-025__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may impose by regulation additional limitations that it determines appropriate on a temporary license issued under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-11-030">
            <num>08.11.030</num>
            <heading>Reinstatement of lapsed license or registration; renewal of suspended license or registration.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-11-030__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 49 ch 94 SLA 1987.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-030__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 49 ch 94 SLA 1987.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-030__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may reinstate a lapsed license or registration if the license or registration has lapsed for less than two years and if the individual submits to the department an application for renewal and pays a delinquency fee in addition to the renewal fee.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-030__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A suspended license or registration is subject to expiration and must be renewed as provided in
AS 08.01.100
, but the renewal does not entitle the individual while the license or registration remains suspended to practice audiology, speech-language pathology, or as a speech-language pathologist assistant, or to engage in other activity or conduct that violates the order or judgment that suspended the license.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-11-040">
            <num>08.11.040</num>
            <heading>Display of license.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-11-040__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An individual licensed to practice audiology as an audiologist or licensed to practice speech-language pathology as a speech-language pathologist in the state shall display the license in a prominent place at each place of business of the individual.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-040__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If an audiologist or speech-language pathologist has more than one place of business, the department shall, on request and payment of a fee, issue a duplicate license for each place of business of the individual.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-11-042">
            <num>08.11.042</num>
            <heading>Activities of speech-language pathologist assistant.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-11-042__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not practice as a speech-language pathologist assistant in the state without registration under this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-042__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (e) of this section, a person registered under this chapter and who is under the immediate supervision of a person licensed as a speech-language pathologist in the state may perform treatment of a person who is medically fragile, as determined by the licensed speech-language pathologist, or who otherwise demonstrates a need for assistance with feeding or swallowing.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-042__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (b) and (e) of this section, a person registered under this chapter and who is under the direct supervision of a person licensed as a speech-language pathologist in the state may perform screening and treatment techniques or activities and assist the speech-language pathologist during assessments, research, in-service training, and public relations activities.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-042__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (b), (c), and (e) of this section, a person registered under this chapter and who is under the indirect supervision of a person licensed as a speech-language pathologist in the state may</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-042__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>perform screening and treatment activities, excluding interpretation, if the supervising speech-language pathologist has previously given instruction on the performance of those screening and treatment activities, has observed the assistant in the performance of those activities, and has determined that the speech-language pathologist assistant is competent to perform those activities;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-042__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>conduct clerical tasks, including record keeping, documentation of a person's progress toward meeting established objectives as stated in the treatment plan or individualized education plan, scheduling, and equipment maintenance;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-042__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>implement a documented treatment plan, individualized education plan, or protocol developed by the supervising speech-language pathologist;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-042__subsec_d__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>sign treatment notes if the note is reviewed and cosigned by the supervising speech-language pathologist; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-042__subsec_d__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>discuss with the client and the client's family members or guardian behaviors observed by the speech-language pathologist assistant during treatment of the client when the behaviors are supported by documented objective data.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-042__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A registered speech-language pathologist assistant may not</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-042__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>administer diagnostic assessment tools, perform formal or informal evaluations, or interpret test or evaluation results;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-042__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>participate in family conferences, on an interdisciplinary team, at a staff meeting, or at an individualized education plan meeting in which diagnostic information is interpreted or in which plans for a client's treatment are developed or reviewed without the presence of a licensed speech-language pathologist;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-042__subsec_e__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>write, develop, or modify a client's treatment plan or individualized education plan;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-042__subsec_e__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>assist a client without following a documented treatment plan or individualized education plan that has been prepared by a licensed and adequately trained speech-language pathologist;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-042__subsec_e__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>sign a client record or billing record that does not contain the signature of a licensed speech-language pathologist;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-042__subsec_e__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>select a person for speech-language pathology services;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-042__subsec_e__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide counseling to a client or a client's family or guardian;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-042__subsec_e__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>disclose clinical or confidential information, either orally, in writing, or by electronic means, to anyone not designated in writing to receive the communication by a licensed speech-language pathologist; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-042__subsec_e__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>perform screening of feeding or swallowing functions.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-11-043">
            <num>08.11.043</num>
            <heading>Qualifications for speech-language pathologist assistant registration.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-11-043__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall register an individual as a speech-language pathologist assistant if the individual submits an application on a form approved by the department, pays the required fee, and</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-043__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>submits proof satisfactory to the department that the individual has successfully completed
(A) an associate of applied science degree in disabilities with a speech-language support emphasis either from the University of Alaska Anchorage in affiliation with Prince William Sound Community College or from another approved program; or
(B) a bachelor's degree in speech-language pathology from an accredited institution; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-043__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>submits proof satisfactory to the department that the individual has successfully completed 100 hours of field work supervised by a licensed speech-language pathologist.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-043__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding the requirements of (a) of this section, the department shall register an individual as a speech-language pathologist assistant if the individual provides proof satisfactory to the department that the individual has been employed in a position for at least one year preceding July 1, 2004, that includes the practice of speech-language pathologist assistant as set out in
AS 08.11.042
and if the individual</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-043__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>submits an application on a form approved by the department;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-043__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>pays the required fee;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-043__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>submits proof satisfactory to the department that the individual has passed a competency-based checklist examination adopted by the department; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-043__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>submits a written recommendation from a licensed speech-language pathologist in support of the application.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-043__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall maintain a registry of individuals registered under this section and shall notify an applicant in writing of a decision to approve or deny an application under this section. An approval is valid for two years, except as provided under
AS 08.11.083
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-043__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall renew a valid registration issued under this chapter if the speech-language pathologist assistant submits a timely application on a form approved by the department accompanied by a sworn statement that the applicant has available documentation of approved continuing education consisting of 15 clock hours for the preceding two years. The department shall approve continuing education if the education is provided at state or regional conferences, workshops, formal in-service training, independent study programs, or a combination of these, and pertains to communication disorders.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-11-045">
            <num>08.11.045</num>
            <heading>Supervision of speech-language pathologist assistant.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-11-045__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A speech-language pathologist qualified under (b) of this section shall design and implement a plan for supervision of a speech-language pathologist assistant that protects the client and that maintains the highest possible standard of care. The amount of supervision required in the plan must be documented and must take into account the experience and skills of the speech-language pathologist assistant, the client's needs, the service setting, the tasks assigned, and the laws governing the activities of the speech-language pathologist assistant. A plan for supervision must provide for direct supervision of the speech-language pathologist assistant for at least 50 percent of the speech-language pathologist assistant services during the first 90 days of employment of the speech-language pathologist assistant and, after the first 90 days of employment, for at least 20 percent of the speech-language pathologist assistant services.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-045__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A speech-language pathologist is qualified to supervise a speech-language pathologist assistant only if the speech-language pathologist is familiar with all applicable laws and</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-045__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is licensed under this chapter; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-045__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has a valid Type A or Type C teaching certificate issued under
AS 14.20
with an endorsement in speech-language pathology, speech and hearing sciences, or communication disorders.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-045__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A speech-language pathologist qualified under (b) of this section who agrees to supervise a speech-language pathologist assistant shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-045__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>monitor and evaluate the services provided and documentation completed by the speech-language pathologist assistant, including the competency level for the type of client and service site and compliance with all applicable laws;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-045__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>assist the speech-language pathologist assistant in the development of a professional development plan that includes at least 15 clock hours of approved continuing education under
AS 08.11.043</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-045__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>biennially; and</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-045__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>direct the handling of emergencies by the speech-language pathologist assistant.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-045__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A speech-language pathologist may not supervise more than two individuals or carry a higher caseload of clients while supervising a speech-language pathologist assistant than when the speech-language pathologist was not supervising a speech-language pathologist assistant.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-11-050">
            <num>08.11.050</num>
            <heading>Fees.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.11.050.   Fees.
The department shall set fees under
AS 08.01.065
for each of the following:
(1) application;
(2) credential review;
(3) audiologist license and speech-language pathologist license;
(4) temporary license;
(5) renewal of license;
(6) delinquency;
(7) reinstatement;
(8) duplicate license;
(9) speech-language pathologist assistant registration application and renewal;
(10)  compact privilege.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-11-070">
            <num>08.11.070</num>
            <heading>Dealing in hearing aids.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.11.070.   Dealing in hearing aids.
An audiologist may deal in hearing aids as a hearing aid dealer without being licensed as a hearing aid dealer under
AS 08.55
, but shall comply with
AS 08.55.050
, 08.55.070, 08.55.100, 08.55.110(a), 08.55.110(b)(3) and (c)  (h), and 08.55.130(7)  (13) when dealing in hearing aids.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-11-080">
            <num>08.11.080</num>
            <heading>Grounds for imposition of disciplinary sanctions on an audiologist.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-11-080__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After a hearing, the department may impose a disciplinary sanction on an audiologist when the department finds that the licensee</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-080__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>secured a license through deceit, fraud, or intentional misrepresentation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-080__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>engaged in deceit, fraud, or intentional misrepresentation in the course of practicing audiology;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-080__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>advertised professional services in a false or misleading manner;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-080__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has been convicted of a felony or other crime that affects the person's ability to continue to practice competently and safely;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-080__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>continued to practice audiology after becoming unfit due to
(A) professional incompetence;
(B) use of drugs or alcohol in a manner that affects the person's ability to practice audiology competently and safely;
(C) physical or mental disability;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-080__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>permitted another person to use the licensee's license;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-080__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>employed a person who does not have a valid current license to practice audiology to perform work as an audiologist covered by this chapter;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-080__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>failed to comply with a provision of this chapter or a regulation adopted under this chapter, or an order of the department.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-080__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may not impose disciplinary sanctions on an audiologist for the evaluation, diagnosis, or treatment of a person through audio, video, or data communications when physically separated from the person if the audiologist</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-080__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>or another licensed health care provider is available to provide follow-up care;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-080__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>requests that the person consent to sending a copy of all records of the encounter to a primary care provider if the audiologist is not the person's primary care provider and, if the person consents, the audiologist sends the records to the person's primary care provider; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-080__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>meets the requirements established by the department in regulation.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-080__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall adopt regulations restricting the evaluation, diagnosis, supervision, and treatment of a person as authorized under (b) of this section by establishing standards of care, including standards for training, confidentiality, supervision, practice, and related issues.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-11-083">
            <num>08.11.083</num>
            <heading>Grounds for imposition of disciplinary sanctions on a speech-language pathologist assistant.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-11-083__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After a hearing, the department may impose a disciplinary sanction on a registered speech-language pathologist assistant when the department finds that the registrant</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-083__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>secured a registration through deceit, fraud, or intentional misrepresentation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-083__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>fraudulently or deceptively used a registration;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-083__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>altered a registration;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-083__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>sold, bartered, or offered to sell or barter a registration;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-083__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>engaged in deceit, fraud, or intentional misrepresentation in the course of assisting in the practicing of speech-language pathology;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-083__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>advertised speech-language services in a manner that is false, misleading, or deceptive;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-083__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has been convicted of a felony or other crime that affects the person's ability to continue to practice competently and safely, including a crime involving drugs or alcohol;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-083__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>engaged in unprofessional conduct, in sexual misconduct, or in lewd or immoral behavior in connection with the delivery of professional services to clients;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-083__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>continued to practice speech-language pathology after becoming unfit due to
(A) professional incompetence or gross negligence;
(B) use of drugs or alcohol in a manner that affects the person's ability to practice speech-language pathology competently and safely;
(C) a physical or mental disability;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-083__subsec_a__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>permitted another person to use the registrant's registration;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-083__subsec_a__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has been disciplined by an official government body with jurisdiction over licensure, certification, or registration of a health care or teaching practice; a certified copy of the final disciplinary action constitutes conclusive evidence against the person;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-083__subsec_a__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>failed to maintain confidentiality except as otherwise required or permitted by law;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-083__subsec_a__subsec_13">
                <num>(13)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>failed to comply with a provision of this chapter or a regulation adopted under this chapter, or an order of the department.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-083__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may not impose disciplinary sanctions on a speech- language pathologist assistant for the evaluation, diagnosis, or treatment of a person through audio, video, or data communications when physically separated from the person if the speech-language pathologist assistant</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-083__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>or another licensed health care provider is available to provide follow-up care;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-083__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>requests that the person consent to sending a copy of all records of the encounter to a primary care provider if the speech-language pathologist assistant is not the person's primary care provider and, if the person consents, the speech-language pathologist assistant sends the records to the person's primary care provider; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-083__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>meets the requirements established by the board in regulation.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-083__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall adopt regulations restricting the evaluation, diagnosis, supervision, and treatment of a person as authorized under (b) of this section by establishing standards of care, including standards for training, confidentiality, supervision, practice, and related issues.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-11-085">
            <num>08.11.085</num>
            <heading>Grounds for imposition of disciplinary sanctions on a speech-language pathologist.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-11-085__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After a hearing, the department may impose a disciplinary sanction on a speech-language pathologist when the department finds that the licensee</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-085__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>secured a license or temporary license through deceit, fraud, or intentional misrepresentation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-085__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>fraudulently or deceptively used a license or temporary license;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-085__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>altered a license or temporary license;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-085__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>sold, bartered, or offered to sell or barter a license or temporary license;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-085__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>engaged in deceit, fraud, or intentional misrepresentation in the course of practicing speech-language pathology;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-085__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>advertised professional services in a false or misleading manner;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-085__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has been convicted of a felony or other crime that affects the person's ability to continue to practice competently and safely;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-085__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>engaged in unprofessional conduct, in sexual misconduct, or in lewd or immoral behavior in connection with the delivery of professional services to clients;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-085__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>continued to practice speech-language pathology after becoming unfit due to
(A) professional incompetence;
(B) use of drugs or alcohol in a manner that affects the person's ability to practice speech-language pathology competently and safely;
(C) a physical or mental disability;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-085__subsec_a__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>permitted another person to use the licensee's license or temporary license;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-085__subsec_a__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>employed a person who does not have a valid current license or temporary license to practice speech-language pathology to perform work as a speech-language pathologist covered by this chapter;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-085__subsec_a__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>failed to comply with a provision of this chapter or a regulation adopted under this chapter, or an order of the department.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-085__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may not impose disciplinary sanctions on a speech- language pathologist for the evaluation, diagnosis, or treatment of a person through audio, video, or data communications when physically separated from the person if the speech-language pathologist</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-085__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>or another licensed health care provider is available to provide follow-up care;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-085__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>requests that the person consent to sending a copy of all records of the encounter to a primary care provider if the speech-language pathologist is not the person's primary care provider and, if the person consents, the speech-language pathologist sends the records to the person's primary care provider; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-085__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>meets the requirements established by the board in regulation.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-085__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall adopt regulations restricting the evaluation, diagnosis, supervision, and treatment of a person as authorized under (b) of this section by establishing standards of care, including standards for training, confidentiality, supervision, practice, and related issues.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-11-090">
            <num>08.11.090</num>
            <heading>Disciplinary sanctions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-11-090__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When it finds that an audiologist has committed an act listed in
AS 08.11.080
, that a speech-language pathologist has committed an act listed in
AS 08.11.085
, or that a speech-language pathologist assistant has committed an act listed in
AS 08.11.083
, the department may impose the following sanctions singly or in combination:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-090__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>permanently revoke a license or registration to practice;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-090__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>suspend a license or registration for a determinate period of time;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-090__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>censure a licensee or registrant;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-090__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>issue a letter of reprimand;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-090__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>place a licensee or registrant on probationary status and require the licensee or registrant to
(A) report regularly to the department on matters involving the basis of probation;
(B) limit practice to those areas prescribed;
(C) continue professional education until a satisfactory degree of skill has been attained in those areas determined by the department to need improvement;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-090__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>impose limitations or conditions on the practice of a licensee or registrant.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-090__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may withdraw a limitation, condition, or probationary status if it finds that the deficiency that required the sanction has been remedied.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-090__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may summarily suspend a license before final hearing or during the appeals process if the department finds that the licensee poses a clear and immediate danger to the public welfare and safety if the licensee continues to practice. An individual whose license is suspended under this subsection is entitled to a hearing conducted by the office of administrative hearings (
AS 44.64.010
) not later than seven days after the effective date of the order. The individual may appeal the suspension after the hearing to the superior court.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-090__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may reinstate a license or registration that has been suspended or revoked if the department finds after a hearing that the individual is able to practice with reasonable skill and safety.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-090__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>One year after revocation of a license or registration issued under this chapter, the individual whose license or registration was revoked may reapply for the license or registration. The department may require an examination for reinstatement.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-090__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may place a registrant on probation, with the costs of probation to be borne by the registrant</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-090__subsec_f__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in lieu of revocation or suspension;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-090__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>upon the issuance of a registration to an individual who has been found guilty of unprofessional conduct but who otherwise qualifies for registration under this chapter; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-090__subsec_f__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>as a condition upon the reissuance or reinstatement of any registration that has been suspended or revoked by the department.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-090__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may require a registrant who has been placed on probation or who has been suspended to obtain additional professional training, including continuing education or clinical or field work.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-11-095">
            <num>08.11.095</num>
            <heading>Revocation of speech-language pathologist license.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.11.095.   Revocation of speech-language pathologist license.
After a hearing, the department shall revoke the speech-language pathologist license of a person who does not continue to be able to furnish the evidence required for licensure under
AS 08.11.015
(5).</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-11-100">
            <num>08.11.100</num>
            <heading>Prohibited acts.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-11-100__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless a person is licensed or granted a compact privilege as an audiologist under this chapter, the person may not</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-100__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>practice audiology;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-100__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>use a title indicating or representing that the person practices as an audiologist;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-100__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>advertise that the person practices audiology.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-100__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless a person is licensed or granted a compact privilege as a speech-language pathologist under this chapter, the person may not</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-100__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>practice speech-language pathology;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-100__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>use a title indicating or representing that the person practices as a speech-language pathologist;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-100__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>advertise that the person practices speech-language pathology.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-11-110">
            <num>08.11.110</num>
            <heading>Penalty.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.11.110.   Penalty.
A person who violates
AS 08.11.100
is guilty of a class B misdemeanor.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-11-120">
            <num>08.11.120</num>
            <heading>Audiology exemptions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-11-120__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This chapter does not apply to an individual who practices audiology consistent with the accepted standards and code of ethics of the individual's profession as part of the individual's duties as</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-120__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a physician licensed under
AS 08.64
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-120__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an employee of the federal government who is required to practice audiology during the employment, if
(A) the employer maintains appropriate supervision of the individual's practice of audiology;
(B) the individual practices audiology as part of the duties for which the individual is employed;
(C) the individual practices audiology in the facility where the individual is employed or under the supervision of the federal governmental unit where the individual is employed; and
(D) the individual does not render or offer to render audiology services to the public for compensation in addition to the salary the individual receives from the federal governmental unit;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-120__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a student, intern, or resident pursuing a course of study in audiology at an accredited college or a clinical training facility approved by the department, if the activities of the student, intern, or resident constitute part of a supervised course of study and the student, intern, or resident is designated as an audiology intern, audiology trainee, or other title approved by the department that clearly indicates that the person is training to be an audiologist.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-120__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding the provisions of this chapter,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-120__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a nurse licensed under
AS 08.68
may perform hearing sensitivity evaluations;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-120__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an individual licensed as a hearing aid dealer under
AS 08.55
may deal in hearing aids;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-120__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an individual holding a class A certificate issued by the Conference of Executives of American Schools of the Deaf may teach the hearing impaired;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-120__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an individual may engage in the testing of hearing as part of a hearing conservation program that complies with the regulations of the Occupational Safety and Health Administration of the federal government if the individual is certified to do the testing by a state or federal agency acceptable to the Occupational Safety and Health Administration;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-120__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an individual may perform hearing screening under
AS 47.20.310
if authorized to do so under a protocol adopted under
AS 47.20.310</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-120__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>by the Department of Health.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-120__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An individual who is not an audiologist, but who is exempt under this section, may not use a title or description stating or implying that the person is an audiologist.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-120__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An individual exempt under (a)(2) of this section may consult with and disseminate research findings and scientific information to accredited academic institutions or governmental agencies, and offer lectures to the public for a fee, monetary or otherwise, without being licensed under this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-120__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An individual who is not licensed under this chapter but who teaches the practice of audiology in an audiologist training program at a college or university may use the title audiologist but may not practice audiology.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-11-125">
            <num>08.11.125</num>
            <heading>Speech-language pathology exemptions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-11-125__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as otherwise specifically provided in this section, this chapter does not apply to an individual who practices speech-language pathology as part of the individual's duties as</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-125__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a physician licensed under
AS 08.64
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-125__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an employee of, or contractor with, a school district while practicing speech-language pathology for the school district;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-125__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a student, intern, or resident pursuing a course of study in speech-language pathology at an accredited college or a clinical training facility approved by the department if the activities of the student, intern, or resident constitute part of a supervised course of study and the student, intern, or resident is designated as a speech-language pathology intern, speech-language pathology trainee, or other title approved by the department that clearly indicates that the person is training to be a speech-language pathologist.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-125__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An individual who is not licensed as a speech-language pathologist but who is exempt under (a)(1) or (3) of this section may not use a title or description stating or implying that the person is a speech-language pathologist.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-125__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An individual who is not licensed under this chapter but who teaches the practice of speech-language pathology in a speech-language pathology training program at a college or university may use the title speech-language pathologist but may not practice speech-language pathology.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-11-130">
            <num>08.11.130</num>
            <heading>Administrative Procedure Act.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.11.130.   Administrative Procedure Act.
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act) applies to regulations and proceedings under this chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-11-200">
            <num>08.11.200</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.11.200.   Definitions.
In this chapter, unless the context indicates otherwise,
(1) audiologist means an individual who is licensed under
AS 08.11.010
to practice audiology in the state;
(2) dealing in hearing aids has the meaning given in
AS 08.55.200
;
(3) department means the Department of Commerce, Community, and Economic Development;
(4) direct supervision means supervision that is on-site or available by visual or real-time electronic means through which a supervising speech-language pathologist observes and guides a speech-language pathologist assistant while the assistant performs a clinical activity; direct supervision may include demonstration, coaching, and observation to the extent that the demonstration, coaching, or observation otherwise meets the requirements of this paragraph;
(5) hearing aid has the meaning given in
AS 08.55.200
;
(6) immediate supervision means supervision in the physical presence of the speech-language pathologist assistant during the provision of client services by the speech-language pathologist assistant;
(7) indirect supervision means supervision by telephonic or electronic means or by intermittent on-site visits while located either inside or outside of the facility in which the speech-language pathologist assistant is located; indirect supervision may include demonstrations, record review, evaluation of audiotaped or videotaped client services, or communication by telephone or electronic mail to the extent that these activities otherwise meet the requirements of this paragraph;
(8) practice of audiology means the application of principles, methods, and procedures of measurement, testing, appraisal, prediction, consultation, habilitation, rehabilitation, counseling, and instruction related to hearing and hearing impairment for the purpose of modifying communicative disorders involving speech, language, auditory function, including auditory training, speech reading and the recommendation, evaluation, fitting, and sale of hearing aids, including the fitting of ear molds;
(9) practice of speech-language pathology means the application of principles, methods, and procedures related to the development and disorders of human communication, including
(A) screening for, identifying, assessing, interpreting, diagnosing, rehabilitating, and preventing disorders of speech, such as disorders related to articulation, fluency, voice, and language;
(B) screening for, identifying, assessing, interpreting, diagnosing, and rehabilitating disorders of oral-pharyngeal function or dysphagia or related disorders;
(C) screening for, identifying, assessing, interpreting, diagnosing, and rehabilitating cognitive and communication disorders;
(D) assessing, selecting, and developing augmentative and alternative communication systems and providing training in their use;
(E) providing aural rehabilitation and related counseling services to hearing impaired individuals and their families;
(F) enhancing speech-language proficiency and communication effectiveness, such as accent reduction; and
(G) screening of hearing and other factors for the purpose of speech-language evaluation or the initial identification of individuals with other communication disorders, if judgments and descriptive statements about the results of the screening are limited to pass-fail determinations;
(10) screening means a procedure in which a client is identified by either pass or fail for purposes of necessitating further evaluation of speech, language, or hearing;
(11) speech-language pathologist means an individual who is licensed under
AS 08.11.015
to practice speech-language pathology in the state;
(12) supervision means the provision of direction and evaluation of the tasks assigned.
Article 2. Audiology and Speech-Language Interstate Compact.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-11-300">
            <num>08.11.300</num>
            <heading>Audiology and speech-language interstate compact enacted.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A license issued to an audiologist or speech-language pathologist by a home state to a resident in that state shall be recognized by each member state as authorizing an audiologist or speech-language pathologist to practice audiology or speech-language pathology, under a privilege to practice, in each member state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A state must implement or utilize procedures for considering the criminal history records of applicants for initial privilege to practice. These procedures shall include the submission of fingerprints or other biometric-based information by applicants for the purpose of obtaining an applicant's criminal history record information from the Federal Bureau of Investigation and the agency responsible for retaining that state's criminal records.</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A member state must fully implement a criminal background check requirement, within a time frame established by rule, by receiving the results of the Federal Bureau of Investigation record search on criminal background checks and use the results in making licensure decisions.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Communication between a member state, the Commission and among member states regarding the verification of eligibility for licensure through the Compact shall not include any information received from the Federal Bureau of Investigation relating to a federal criminal records check performed by a member state under Public Law 92-544.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon application for a privilege to practice, the licensing board in the issuing remote state shall ascertain, through the data system, whether the applicant has ever held, or is the holder of, a license issued by any other state, whether there are any encumbrances on any license or privilege to practice held by the applicant, whether any adverse action has been taken against any license or privilege to practice held by the applicant.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each member state shall require an applicant to obtain or retain a license in the home state and meet the home state's qualifications for licensure or renewal of licensure, as well as, all other applicable state laws.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For an audiologist:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Must meet one of the following educational requirements:
(A) On or before, Dec. 31, 2007, has graduated with a master's degree or doctorate in audiology, or equivalent degree regardless of degree name, from a program that is accredited by an accrediting agency recognized by the Council for Higher Education Accreditation, or its successor, or by the United States Department of Education and operated by a college or university accredited by a regional or national accrediting organization recognized by the board; or
(B) On or after, Jan. 1, 2008, has graduated with a Doctoral degree in audiology, or equivalent degree, regardless of degree name, from a program that is accredited by an accrediting agency recognized by the Council for Higher Education Accreditation, or its successor, or by the United States Department of Education and operated by a college or university accredited by a regional or national accrediting organization recognized by the board; or
(C) Has graduated from an audiology program that is housed in an institution of higher education outside of the United States</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>for which the program and institution have been approved by the authorized accrediting body in the applicable country; and
(ii) the degree program has been verified by an independent credentials review agency to be comparable to a state licensing board-approved program.</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_i__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Has completed a supervised clinical practicum experience from an accredited educational institution or its cooperating programs as required by the Commission;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_i__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Has successfully passed a national examination approved by the Commission;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_i__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Holds an active, unencumbered license;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_i__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Has not been convicted or found guilty, and has not entered into an agreed disposition, of a felony related to the practice of audiology, under applicable state or federal criminal law;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_i__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Has a valid United States Social Security or National Practitioner Identification number.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For a speech-language pathologist:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_f__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Must meet one of the following educational requirements:
(A) Has graduated with a master's degree from a speech- language pathology program that is accredited by an organization recognized by the United States Department of Education and operated by a college or university accredited by a regional or national accrediting organization recognized by the board; or
(B) Has graduated from a speech-language pathology program that is housed in an institution of higher education outside of the United States (a) for which the program and institution have been approved by the authorized accrediting body in the applicable country and (b) the degree program has been verified by an independent credentials review agency to be comparable to a state licensing board-approved program.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Has completed a supervised clinical practicum experience from an educational institution or its cooperating programs as required by the Commission;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_f__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Has completed a supervised postgraduate professional experience as required by the Commission;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_f__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Has successfully passed a national examination approved by the Commission;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_f__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Holds an active, unencumbered license;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_f__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Has not been convicted or found guilty, and has not entered into an agreed disposition, of a felony related to the practice of speech-language pathology, under applicable state or federal criminal law;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_f__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Has a valid United States Social Security or National Practitioner Identification number.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The privilege to practice is derived from the home state license.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An audiologist or speech-language pathologist practicing in a member state must comply with the state practice laws of the state in which the client is located at the time service is provided. The practice of audiology and speech-language pathology shall include all audiology and speech-language pathology practice as defined by the state practice laws of the member state in which the client is located. The practice of audiology and speech-language pathology in a member state under a privilege to practice shall subject an audiologist or speech-language pathologist to the jurisdiction of the licensing board, the courts and the laws of the member state in which the client is located at the time service is provided.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Individuals not residing in a member state shall continue to be able to apply for a member state's single-state license as provided under the laws of each member state. However, the single-state license granted to these individuals shall not be recognized as granting the privilege to practice audiology or speech-language pathology in any other member state. Nothing in this Compact shall affect the requirements established by a member state for the issuance of a single-state license.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Member states may charge a fee for granting a compact privilege.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Member states must comply with the bylaws and rules and regulations of the Commission.
SECTION 4. COMPACT PRIVILEGE</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To exercise the compact privilege under the terms and provisions of the Compact, the audiologist or speech-language pathologist shall:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Hold an active license in the home state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Have no encumbrance on any state license;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Be eligible for a compact privilege in any member state in accordance with Section 3;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Have not had any adverse action against any license or compact privilege within the previous 2 years from date of application;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Notify the Commission that the licensee is seeking the compact privilege within a remote state(s);</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Pay any applicable fees, including any state fee, for the compact privilege;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Report to the Commission adverse action taken by any non- member state within 30 days from the date the adverse action is taken.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For the purposes of the compact privilege, an audiologist or speech- language pathologist shall only hold one home state license at a time.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in Section 6, if an audiologist or speech-language pathologist changes primary state of residence by moving between two member states, the audiologist or speech-language pathologist must apply for licensure in the new home state, and the license issued by the prior home state shall be deactivated in accordance with applicable rules adopted by the Commission.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The audiologist or speech-language pathologist may apply for licensure in advance of a change in primary state of residence.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A license shall not be issued by the new home state until the audiologist or speech-language pathologist provides satisfactory evidence of a change in primary state of residence to the new home state and satisfies all applicable requirements to obtain a license from the new home state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If an audiologist or speech-language pathologist changes primary state of residence by moving from a member state to a non-member state, the license issued by the prior home state shall convert to a single-state license, valid only in the former home state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The compact privilege is valid until the expiration date of the home state license. The licensee must comply with the requirements of Section 4(a) to maintain the compact privilege in the remote state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A licensee providing audiology or speech-language pathology services in a remote state under the compact privilege shall function within the laws and regulations of the remote state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A licensee providing audiology or speech-language pathology services in a remote state is subject to that state's regulatory authority. A remote state may, in accordance with due process and that state's laws, remove a licensee's compact privilege in the remote state for a specific period of time, impose fines, and/or take any other necessary actions to protect the health and safety of its citizens.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a home state license is encumbered, the licensee shall lose the compact privilege in any remote state until the following occur:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_j__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The home state license is no longer encumbered; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_j__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Two years have elapsed from the date of the adverse action.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Once an encumbered license in the home state is restored to good standing, the licensee must meet the requirements of Section 4(a) to obtain a compact privilege in any remote state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_l">
              <num>(l)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Once the requirements of Section 4(j) have been met, the licensee must meet the requirements in Section 4(a) to obtain a compact privilege in a remote state.
SECTION 5. COMPACT PRIVILEGE TO PRACTICE TELEHEALTH
Member states shall recognize the right of an audiologist or speech-language pathologist, licensed by a home state in accordance with Section 3 and under rules promulgated by the Commission, to practice audiology or speech-language pathology in any member state via telehealth under a privilege to practice as provided in the Compact and rules promulgated by the Commission.
SECTION 6. ACTIVE DUTY MILITARY PERSONNEL OR THEIR SPOUSES
Active duty military personnel, or their spouse, shall designate a home state where the individual has a current license in good standing. The individual may retain the home state designation during the period the service member is on active duty. Subsequent to designating a home state, the individual shall only change their home state through application for licensure in the new state.
SECTION 7. ADVERSE ACTIONS</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to the other powers conferred by state law, a remote state shall have the authority, in accordance with existing state due process law, to:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Take adverse action against an audiologist's or speech-language pathologist's privilege to practice within that member state.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Issue subpoenas for both hearings and investigations that require the attendance and testimony of witnesses as well as the production of evidence. Subpoenas issued by a licensing board in a member state for the attendance and testimony of witnesses or the production of evidence from another member state shall be enforced in the latter state by any court of competent jurisdiction, according to the practice and procedure of that court applicable to subpoenas issued in proceedings pending before it. The issuing authority shall pay any witness fees, travel expenses, mileage and other fees required by the service statutes of the state in which the witnesses or evidence are located.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Only the home state shall have the power to take adverse action against an audiologist's or speech-language pathologist's license issued by the home state.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of taking adverse action, the home state shall give the same priority and effect to reported conduct received from a member state as it would if the conduct had occurred within the home state. In so doing, the home state shall apply its own state laws to determine appropriate action.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The home state shall complete any pending investigations of an audiologist or speech-language pathologist who changes primary state of residence during the course of the investigations. The home state shall also have the authority to take appropriate action(s) and shall promptly report the conclusions of the investigations to the administrator of the data system. The administrator of the coordinated licensure information system shall promptly notify the new home state of any adverse actions.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If otherwise permitted by state law, the member state may recover from the affected audiologist or speech-language pathologist the costs of investigations and disposition of cases resulting from any adverse action taken against that audiologist or speech-language pathologist.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The member state may take adverse action based on the factual findings of the remote state, provided that the member state follows the member state's own procedures for taking the adverse action.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Joint Investigations</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_f__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>In addition to the authority granted to a member state by its respective audiology or speech-language pathology practice act or other applicable state law, any member state may participate with other member states in joint investigations of licensees.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Member states shall share any investigative, litigation, or compliance materials in furtherance of any joint or individual investigation initiated under the Compact.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If adverse action is taken by the home state against an audiologist's or speech-language pathologist's license, the audiologist's or speech-language pathologist's privilege to practice in all other member states shall be deactivated until all encumbrances have been removed from the state license. All home state disciplinary orders that impose adverse action against an audiologist's or speech- language pathologist's license shall include a statement that the audiologist's or speech-language pathologist's privilege to practice is deactivated in all member states during the pendency of the order.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a member state takes adverse action, it shall promptly notify the administrator of the data system. The administrator of the data system shall promptly notify the home state of any adverse actions by remote states.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing in this Compact shall override a member state's decision that participation in an alternative program may be used in lieu of adverse action.
SECTION 8. ESTABLISHMENT OF THE AUDIOLOGY AND SPEECH-LANGUAGE PATHOLOGY COMPACT COMMISSION</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Compact member states hereby create and establish a joint public agency known as the Audiology and Speech-Language Pathology Compact Commission:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Commission is an instrumentality of the Compact states.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Venue is proper and judicial proceedings by or against the Commission shall be brought solely and exclusively in a court of competent jurisdiction where the principal office of the Commission is located. The Commission may waive venue and jurisdictional defenses to the extent it adopts or consents to participate in alternative dispute resolution proceedings.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Nothing in this Compact shall be construed to be a waiver of sovereign immunity.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Membership, Voting and Meetings</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Each member state shall have two (2) delegates selected by that member state's licensing board. The delegates shall be current members of the licensing board. One shall be an audiologist and one shall be a speech-language pathologist.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>An additional five (5) delegates, who are either a public member or board administrator from a state licensing board, shall be chosen by the Executive Committee from a pool of nominees provided by the Commission at Large.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Any delegate may be removed or suspended from office as provided by the law of the state from which the delegate is appointed.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The member state board shall fill any vacancy occurring on the Commission, within 90 days.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Each delegate shall be entitled to one (1) vote with regard to the promulgation of rules and creation of bylaws and shall otherwise have an opportunity to participate in the business and affairs of the Commission.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A delegate shall vote in person or by other means as provided in the bylaws. The bylaws may provide for delegates' participation in meetings by telephone or other means of communication.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_b__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Commission shall meet at least once during each calendar year. Additional meetings shall be held as set forth in the bylaws.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Commission shall have the following powers and duties:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Establish the fiscal year of the Commission;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Establish bylaws;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Establish a Code of Ethics;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Maintain its financial records in accordance with the bylaws;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_c__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Meet and take actions as are consistent with the provisions of this Compact and the bylaws;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_c__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Promulgate uniform rules to facilitate and coordinate implementation and administration of this Compact. The rules shall have the force and effect of law and shall be binding in all member states;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_c__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Bring and prosecute legal proceedings or actions in the name of the Commission, provided that the standing of any state audiology or speech-language pathology licensing board to sue or be sued under applicable law shall not be affected;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_c__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Purchase and maintain insurance and bonds;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_c__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Borrow, accept, or contract for services of personnel, including, but not limited to, employees of a member state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_c__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Hire employees, elect or appoint officers, fix compensation, define duties, grant individuals appropriate authority to carry out the purposes of the Compact, and to establish the Commission's personnel policies and programs relating to conflicts of interest, qualifications of personnel, and other related personnel matters;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_c__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Accept any and all appropriate donations and grants of money, equipment, supplies, materials and services, and to receive, utilize and dispose of the same; provided that at all times the Commission shall avoid any appearance of impropriety and/or conflict of interest;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_c__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Lease, purchase, accept appropriate gifts or donations of, or otherwise to own, hold, improve or use, any property, real, personal or mixed;
provided that at all times the Commission shall avoid any appearance of impropriety;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_c__subsec_13">
                <num>(13)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Sell, convey, mortgage, pledge, lease, exchange, abandon, or otherwise dispose of any property, real, personal, or mixed;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_c__subsec_14">
                <num>(14)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Establish a budget and make expenditures;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_c__subsec_15">
                <num>(15)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Borrow money;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_c__subsec_16">
                <num>(16)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Appoint committees, including standing committees composed of members, and other interested persons as may be designated in this Compact and the bylaws;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_c__subsec_17">
                <num>(17)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Provide and receive information from, and cooperate with, law enforcement agencies;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_c__subsec_18">
                <num>(18)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Establish and elect an Executive Committee; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_c__subsec_19">
                <num>(19)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Perform other functions as may be necessary or appropriate to achieve the purposes of this Compact consistent with the state regulation of audiology and speech-language pathology licensure and practice.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Executive Committee</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Executive Committee shall have the power to act on behalf of the Commission according to the terms of this Compact;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Executive Committee shall be composed of 10 members:
(A) Seven voting members who are elected by the Commission from the current membership of the Commission;
(B) Two ex-officios, consisting of one nonvoting member from a recognized national audiology professional association and one nonvoting member from a recognized national speech-language pathology association; and
(C) One ex-officio, nonvoting member from the recognized membership organization of the audiology and speech-language pathology licensing boards.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The ex-officio members shall be selected by their respective organizations.</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Commission may remove any member of the Executive Committee as provided in bylaws.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Executive Committee shall meet at least annually.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_e__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Executive Committee shall have the following duties and responsibilities:
(A) Recommend to the entire Commission changes to the rules or bylaws, changes to this Compact legislation, fees paid by Compact member states such as annual dues, and any commission Compact fee charged to licensees for the compact privilege;
(B) Ensure Compact administration services are appropriately provided, contractual or otherwise;
(C) Prepare and recommend the budget;
(D) Maintain financial records on behalf of the Commission;
(E) Monitor Compact compliance of member states and provide compliance reports to the Commission;
(F) Establish additional committees as necessary; and
(G) Other duties as provided in rules or bylaws.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_e__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Meetings of the Commission. All meetings shall be open to the public, and public notice of meetings shall be given in the same manner as required under the rulemaking provisions in Section 10.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_e__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Commission or the Executive Committee or other committees of the Commission may convene in a closed, non-public meeting if the Commission or Executive Committee or other committees of the Commission must discuss:
(A) Non-compliance of a member state with its obligations under the Compact;
(B) The employment, compensation, discipline or other matters, practices or procedures related to specific employees or other matters related to the Commission's internal personnel practices and procedures;
(C) Current, threatened, or reasonably anticipated litigation;
(D) Negotiation of contracts for the purchase, lease, or sale of goods, services, or real estate;
(E) Accusing any person of a crime or formally censuring any person;
(F) Disclosure of trade secrets or commercial or financial information that is privileged or confidential;
(G) Disclosure of information of a personal nature where disclosure would constitute a clearly unwarranted invasion of personal privacy;
(H) Disclosure of investigative records compiled for law enforcement purposes;
(I) Disclosure of information related to any investigative reports prepared by or on behalf of or for use of the Commission or other committee charged with responsibility of investigation or determination of compliance issues pursuant to the Compact; or
(J) Matters specifically exempted from disclosure by federal or member state statute.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_e__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>If a meeting, or portion of a meeting, is closed pursuant to this provision, the Commission's legal counsel or designee shall certify that the meeting may be closed and shall reference each relevant exempting provision.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_e__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Commission shall keep minutes that fully and clearly describe all matters discussed in a meeting and shall provide a full and accurate summary of actions taken, and the reasons therefore, including a description of the views expressed. All documents considered in connection with an action shall be identified in minutes. All minutes and documents of a closed meeting shall remain under seal, subject to release by a majority vote of the Commission or order of a court of competent jurisdiction.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_e__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Financing of the Commission
(A) The Commission shall pay, or provide for the payment of, the reasonable expenses of its establishment, organization, and ongoing activities.
(B) The Commission may accept any and all appropriate revenue sources, donations, and grants of money, equipment, supplies, materials, and services.
(C) The Commission may levy on and collect an annual assessment from each member state or impose fees on other parties to cover the cost of the operations and activities of the Commission and its staff, which must be in a total amount sufficient to cover its annual budget as approved each year for which revenue is not provided by other sources. The aggregate annual assessment amount shall be allocated based upon a formula to be determined by the Commission, which shall promulgate a rule binding upon all member states.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_e__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Commission shall not incur obligations of any kind prior to securing the funds adequate to meet the same; nor shall the Commission pledge the credit of any of the member states, except by and with the authority of the member state.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_e__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Commission shall keep accurate accounts of all receipts and disbursements. The receipts and disbursements of the Commission shall be subject to the audit and accounting procedures established under its bylaws. However, all receipts and disbursements of funds handled by the Commission shall be audited yearly by a certified or licensed public accountant, and the report of the audit shall be included in and become part of the annual report of the Commission.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Qualified Immunity, Defense, and Indemnification</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_f__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The members, officers, executive director, employees and representatives of the Commission shall be immune from suit and liability, either personally or in their official capacity, for any claim for damage to or loss of property or personal injury or other civil liability caused by or arising out of any actual or alleged act, error or omission that occurred, or that the person against whom the claim is made had a reasonable basis for believing occurred within the scope of Commission employment, duties or responsibilities; provided that nothing in this paragraph shall be construed to protect any person from suit and/or liability for any damage, loss, injury, or liability caused by the intentional or willful or wanton misconduct of that person.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Commission shall defend any member, officer, executive director, employee or representative of the Commission in any civil action seeking to impose liability arising out of any actual or alleged act, error, or omission that occurred within the scope of Commission employment, duties, or responsibilities, or that the person against whom the claim is made had a reasonable basis for believing occurred within the scope of Commission employment, duties, or responsibilities; provided that nothing herein shall be construed to prohibit that person from retaining his or her own counsel; and provided further, that the actual or alleged act, error, or omission did not result from that person's intentional or willful or wanton misconduct.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_f__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Commission shall indemnify and hold harmless any member, officer, executive director, employee, or representative of the Commission for the amount of any settlement or judgment obtained against that person arising out of any actual or alleged act, error or omission that occurred within the scope of Commission employment, duties, or responsibilities, or that person had a reasonable basis for believing occurred within the scope of Commission employment, duties, or responsibilities, provided that the actual or alleged act, error, or omission did not result from the intentional or willful or wanton misconduct of that person.
SECTION 9. DATA SYSTEM</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Commission shall provide for the development, maintenance, and utilization of a coordinated database and reporting system containing licensure, adverse action, and investigative information on all licensed individuals in member states.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding any other provision of state law to the contrary, a member state shall submit a uniform data set to the data system on all individuals to whom this Compact is applicable as required by the rules of the Commission, including:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Identifying information;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Licensure data;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Adverse actions against a license or compact privilege;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Non-confidential information related to alternative program participation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Any denial of application for licensure, and the reason(s) for denial; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Other information that may facilitate the administration of this Compact, as determined by the rules of the Commission.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Investigative information pertaining to a licensee in any member state shall only be available to other member states.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Commission shall promptly notify all member states of any adverse action taken against a licensee or an individual applying for a license. Adverse action information pertaining to a licensee in any member state shall be available to any other member state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Member states contributing information to the data system may designate information that may not be shared with the public without the express permission of the contributing state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Any information submitted to the data system that is subsequently required to be expunged by the laws of the member state contributing the information shall be removed from the data system.
SECTION 10. RULEMAKING</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Commission shall exercise its rulemaking powers pursuant to the criteria set forth in this Section and the rules adopted thereunder. Rules and amendments shall become binding as of the date specified in each rule or amendment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a majority of the legislatures of the member states rejects a rule, by enactment of a statute or resolution in the same manner used to adopt the Compact within 4 years of the date of adoption of the rule, the rule shall have no further force and effect in any member state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Rules or amendments to the rules shall be adopted at a regular or special meeting of the Commission.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Prior to promulgation and adoption of a final rule or rules by the Commission, and at least thirty days in advance of the meeting at which the rule shall be considered and voted upon, the Commission shall file a Notice of Proposed Rulemaking:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>On the website of the Commission or other publicly accessible platform; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>On the website of each member state audiology or speech-language pathology licensing board or other publicly accessible platform or the publication in which each state would otherwise publish proposed rules.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Notice of Proposed Rulemaking shall include:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The proposed time, date, and location of the meeting in which the rule shall be considered and voted upon;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The text of the proposed rule or amendment and the reason for the proposed rule;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_e__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A request for comments on the proposed rule from any interested person; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_e__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The manner in which interested persons may submit notice to the Commission of their intention to attend the public hearing and any written comments.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Prior to the adoption of a proposed rule, the Commission shall allow persons to submit written data, facts, opinions and arguments, which shall be made available to the public.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Commission shall grant an opportunity for a public hearing before it adopts a rule or amendment if a hearing is requested by:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_g__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>At least twenty-five (25) persons;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_g__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A state or federal governmental subdivision or agency; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_g__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>An association having at least twenty-five (25) members.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a hearing is held on the proposed rule or amendment, the Commission shall publish the place, time, and date of the scheduled public hearing. If the hearing is held via electronic means, the Commission shall publish the mechanism for access to the electronic hearing.</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_h__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>All persons wishing to be heard at the hearing shall notify the executive director of the Commission or other designated member in writing of their desire to appear and testify at the hearing not less than five (5) business days before the scheduled date of the hearing.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_h__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Hearings shall be conducted in a manner providing each person who wishes to comment a fair and reasonable opportunity to comment orally or in writing.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_h__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>All hearings shall be recorded. A copy of the recording shall be made available on request.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_h__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Nothing in this section shall be construed as requiring a separate hearing on each rule. Rules may be grouped for the convenience of the Commission at hearings required by this section.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Following the scheduled hearing date, or by the close of business on the scheduled hearing date if the hearing was not held, the Commission shall consider all written and oral comments received.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If no written notice of intent to attend the public hearing by interested parties is received, the Commission may proceed with promulgation of the proposed rule without a public hearing.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Commission shall, by majority vote of all members, take final action on the proposed rule and shall determine the effective date of the rule, if any, based on the rulemaking record and the full text of the rule.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_l">
              <num>(l)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon determination that an emergency exists, the Commission may consider and adopt an emergency rule without prior notice, opportunity for comment, or hearing, provided that the usual rulemaking procedures provided in the Compact and in this section shall be retroactively applied to the rule as soon as reasonably possible, in no event later than ninety (90) days after the effective date of the rule. For the purposes of this provision, an emergency rule is one that must be adopted immediately in order to:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_l__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Meet an imminent threat to public health, safety, or welfare;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_l__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Prevent a loss of Commission or member state funds; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_l__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Meet a deadline for the promulgation of an administrative rule that is established by federal law or rule.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_m">
              <num>(m)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Commission or an authorized committee of the Commission may direct revisions to a previously adopted rule or amendment for purposes of correcting typographical errors, errors in format, errors in consistency, or grammatical errors.
Public notice of any revisions shall be posted on the website of the Commission. The revision shall be subject to challenge by any person for a period of thirty (30) days after posting. The revision may be challenged only on grounds that the revision results in a material change to a rule. A challenge shall be made in writing and delivered to the chair of the Commission prior to the end of the notice period. If no challenge is made, the revision shall take effect without further action. If the revision is challenged, the revision may not take effect without the approval of the Commission.
SECTION 11. OVERSIGHT, DISPUTE RESOLUTION, AND ENFORCEMENT</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Dispute Resolution</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Upon request by a member state, the Commission shall attempt to resolve disputes related to the Compact that arise among member states and between member and non-member states.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Commission shall promulgate a rule providing for both mediation and binding dispute resolution for disputes as appropriate.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Enforcement</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Commission, in the reasonable exercise of its discretion, shall enforce the provisions and rules of this Compact.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>By majority vote, the Commission may initiate legal action in the United States District Court for the District of Columbia or the federal district where the Commission has its principal offices against a member state in default to enforce compliance with the provisions of the Compact and its promulgated rules and bylaws. The relief sought may include both injunctive relief and damages. In the event judicial enforcement is necessary, the prevailing member shall be awarded all costs of litigation, including reasonable attorney's fees.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The remedies herein shall not be the exclusive remedies of the Commission. The Commission may pursue any other remedies available under federal or state law.
SECTION 12. DATE OF IMPLEMENTATION OF THE INTERSTATE COMMISSION FOR AUDIOLOGY AND SPEECH-LANGUAGE PATHOLOGY PRACTICE AND ASSOCIATED RULES, WITHDRAWAL, AND AMENDMENT</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Compact shall come into effect on the date on which the Compact statute is enacted into law in the 10th member state. The provisions, which become effective at that time, shall be limited to the powers granted to the Commission relating to assembly and the promulgation of rules. Thereafter, the Commission shall meet and exercise rulemaking powers necessary to the implementation and administration of the Compact.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Any state that joins the Compact subsequent to the Commission's initial adoption of the rules shall be subject to the rules as they exist on the date on which the Compact becomes law in that state. Any rule that has been previously adopted by the Commission shall have the full force and effect of law on the day the Compact becomes law in that state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Any member state may withdraw from this Compact by enacting a statute repealing the same.</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A member state's withdrawal shall not take effect until six (6) months after enactment of the repealing statute.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-11-300__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Withdrawal shall not affect the continuing requirement of the withdrawing state's audiology or speech-language pathology licensing board to comply with the investigative and adverse action reporting requirements of this act prior to the effective date of withdrawal.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing contained in this Compact shall be construed to invalidate or prevent any audiology or speech-language pathology licensure agreement or other cooperative arrangement between a member state and a non-member state that does not conflict with the provisions of this Compact.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This Compact may be amended by the member states. No amendment to this Compact shall become effective and binding upon any member state until it is enacted into the laws of all member states.
SECTION 13. CONSTRUCTION AND SEVERABILITY
This Compact shall be liberally construed so as to effectuate the purposes thereof. The provisions of this Compact shall be severable and if any phrase, clause, sentence or provision of this Compact is declared to be contrary to the constitution of any member state or of the United States or the applicability thereof to any government, agency, person or circumstance is held invalid, the validity of the remainder of this Compact and the applicability thereof to any government, agency, person or circumstance shall not be affected thereby. If this Compact shall be held contrary to the constitution of any member state, the Compact shall remain in full force and effect as to the remaining member states and in full force and effect as to the member state affected as to all severable matters.
SECTION 14. BINDING EFFECT OF COMPACT AND OTHER LAWS</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing herein prevents the enforcement of any other law of a member state that is not inconsistent with the Compact.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>All laws in a member state in conflict with the Compact are superseded to the extent of the conflict.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>All lawful actions of the Commission, including all rules and bylaws promulgated by the Commission, are binding upon the member states.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>All agreements between the Commission and the member states are binding in accordance with their terms.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-11-300__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In the event any provision of the Compact exceeds the constitutional limits imposed on the legislature of any member state, the provision shall be ineffective to the extent of the conflict with the constitutional provision in question in that member state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>