<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-07"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-07"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="8.07"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-07/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-07/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-07/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-07/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_8">
        <num>8</num>
        <heading>Business and Professions</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_8__chp_07">
          <num>07</num>
          <heading>Athletic Trainers</heading>
          <section eId="sec_08-07-010">
            <num>08.07.010</num>
            <heading>License required.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-07-010__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An individual may not practice or offer to practice athletic training, or allow another person to offer athletic training by the individual, in the state without being licensed under this chapter, unless the individual is</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-07-010__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a student in an accredited athletic trainer program who is practicing athletic training under the supervision of an athletic trainer or a person licensed to practice medicine or osteopathy under
AS 08.64
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-07-010__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>licensed, certified, or registered as an athletic trainer in another state and is present in the state for not more than 90 days in a calendar year for a specific athletic event or series of athletic events with an individual or group not based in the state; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-07-010__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in the military service of the United States or as an employee of the federal government performing athletic training services within the scope of the individual's official duties.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-07-010__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This section does not prohibit a person licensed under another chapter of this title from performing functions defined as athletic training if those functions are within the scope of that person's license and the person does not use a title listed in (d) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-07-010__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing in this chapter requires licensing of a coach or fitness trainer who</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-07-010__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>does not use a title listed in (d) of this section; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-07-010__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is acting within the scope of the person's duties as a coach or fitness trainer.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-07-010__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unless licensed under this chapter or exempted under (a)(2) or (3) of this section, an individual may not use the titles athletic trainer, licensed athletic trainer, certified athletic trainer, athletic trainer certified, A.T., A.T.L., C.A.T., A.T.C., or any combination of those terms to indicate that the individual is a licensed athletic trainer.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-07-020">
            <num>08.07.020</num>
            <heading>Qualifications for license; fee; renewal.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-07-020__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall issue an athletic trainer license to an individual who</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-07-020__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>applies to the department on a form provided by the department;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-07-020__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>meets the requirements established in regulation by the department;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-07-020__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>pays the fees established by the department; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-07-020__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provides proof of certification by the Board of Certification, Inc., or another nationally recognized professional association approved by the department.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-07-020__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An athletic trainer license may be renewed upon proof of certification by the Board of Certification, Inc., or another nationally recognized professional association approved by the department and as provided in
AS 08.01.100
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-07-030">
            <num>08.07.030</num>
            <heading>Scope of practice of athletic trainers.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-07-030__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An athletic trainer may practice athletic training only under the direction of a person licensed to practice medicine or osteopathy under
AS 08.64
. In this subsection, direction means the physician authorizes a procedure by a verbal order if the physician is present or by written order, telecommunication, or athletic training treatment plans, protocols, or standing orders established by the physician if the physician is not present.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-07-030__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An athletic trainer shall immediately refer an athlete to an appropriate licensed health care professional if the athletic trainer determines that athletic training is contraindicated or the symptoms or conditions present require treatment outside the scope of practice of an athletic trainer.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-07-030__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The practice of an athletic trainer includes</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-07-030__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the treatment of an athlete for an athletic injury or illness prevention;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-07-030__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the clinical evaluation and assessment of an athlete for an athletic injury or illness sustained or exacerbated while participating in an athletic or sport-related exercise or activity;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-07-030__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the immediate care and treatment of an athlete for an athletic injury or illness sustained or exacerbated while participating in an athletic or sport-related exercise or activity; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-07-030__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the rehabilitation and reconditioning of an athlete from an athletic injury or illness sustained or exacerbated while participating in an athletic or sport-related exercise or activity.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-07-030__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, health care professional has the meaning given to health care provider in
AS 09.65.300
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-07-040">
            <num>08.07.040</num>
            <heading>Regulations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.07.040.   Regulations.
After consulting the professional standards issued by the Board of Certification, Inc., the board's successor, or another nationally recognized professional association approved by the department, the department shall adopt regulations to protect the public, ensure quality patient care, and regulate the licensing of athletic trainers that include
(1) minimum standards for licensure as an athletic trainer;
(2) minimum standards of care for practice as an athletic trainer; and
(3) continuing education requirements.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-07-090">
            <num>08.07.090</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.07.090.   Definitions.
In this chapter,
(1) athlete means an individual who participates in an athletic or sport-related exercise or activity, including interscholastic, intercollegiate, intramural, semiprofessional, and professional sports activities;
(2) athletic injury or illness means an injury or illness sustained or exacerbated through participation in an activity, exercise, recreation, sport, or game requiring physical strength, range of motion, flexibility, body awareness and control, speed, stamina, or agility of a type sustained in association with sports participation as part of an educational institution, professional sports club, amateur sports club, recreational sports club, or organization;
(3) athletic trainer means an individual who is licensed under
AS 08.07.020
to practice athletic training in this state;
(4) athletic training means injury and illness prevention and the evaluation, assessment, immediate care, treatment, rehabilitation, and reconditioning of an athletic injury or illness.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>