<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-4/chapter-21"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-4/chapter-21"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="4.21"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-4/chapter-21/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-4/chapter-21/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-4/chapter-21/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-4/chapter-21/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_4">
        <num>4</num>
        <heading>Alcoholic Beverages</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_4__chp_21">
          <num>21</num>
          <heading>General Provisions</heading>
          <section eId="sec_04-21-010">
            <num>04.21.010</num>
            <heading>Municipal regulation and taxation.</heading>
            <subsection eId="04-21-010__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may adopt ordinances governing the importation, barter, sale, and consumption of alcoholic beverages within the municipality and may ban possession of alcoholic beverages under
AS 04.11.491
(a)(5). An ordinance adopted under this section may not be inconsistent with this title or regulations adopted under this title. In a municipality that has adopted a local option under
AS 04.11.491
(a)(1), (2), or (3), an ordinance is not inconsistent with this title if it limits</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-010__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the monthly amounts of alcoholic beverages a person may import into the municipality;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-010__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the percent of alcohol by volume that an alcoholic beverage may contain; a limit imposed under this paragraph may not be less than 40 nor more than 76 percent alcohol by volume; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-010__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the type of alcoholic beverage container that may be possessed in the municipality.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="04-21-010__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After the adoption of a local option under
AS 04.11.491
(a), a municipality may adopt an ordinance making the sale, importation, or possession of alcoholic beverages a misdemeanor to the extent prohibited under the local option. The ordinance may not be inconsistent with this title or the regulations adopted under this title.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="04-21-010__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A municipality may not impose taxes on alcoholic beverages except a</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-010__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>property tax on alcoholic beverage inventories;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-010__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>sales tax on alcoholic beverage sales if sales taxes are imposed on other sales within the municipality;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-010__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>sales tax on alcoholic beverage sales that was in effect before July 1, 1985; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-010__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>sales and use tax on alcoholic beverages if the sale of alcoholic beverages within the municipality has been prohibited under
AS 04.11.491</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="04-21-010__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>At least 10 days before the date set for municipal action on an application for the issuance, renewal, relocation, or transfer of ownership of a proposed license, the municipality shall provide written notice of the proposed action and the time and place for a hearing to a community council that</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-010__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is established by municipal charter or ordinance to advise the municipal governing body; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-010__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has jurisdiction over the area affected by the proposed action.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_04-21-012">
            <num>04.21.012</num>
            <heading>Keg registration.</heading>
            <subsection eId="04-21-012__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not purchase a keg or similar container holding four or more gallons of an alcoholic beverage unless the person provides proof that the person is over 21 years of age and completes and signs a registration form. The purchaser of a keg or similar container holding four or more gallons of an alcoholic beverage may not remove or obliterate the temporary identifying tag on the keg or container.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="04-21-012__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A licensee or an agent or employee of a licensee who sells or offers for sale a keg or similar container holding four or more gallons of an alcoholic beverage shall require a purchaser to show acceptable proof of age under
AS 04.21.050</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="04-21-012__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and sign the sworn statement on a registration form. The licensee shall complete the registration form and affix a temporary tag with a unique identifier to the keg or container before releasing the container to the purchaser. The licensee shall retain a copy of the form for one year and make the form available for inspection.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="04-21-012__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board shall prescribe a registration form for use by licensees and purchasers. The board may approve for use a registration form adopted by a local governing body. A registration form must include</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-012__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name of the seller;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-012__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name of the purchaser;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-012__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a description of the proof of age provided by the buyer, including the identification number, if any;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-012__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the unique identifier on the temporary tag attached to the keg or container under (b) of this section.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="04-21-012__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A licensee or an agent or employee of a licensee who sells a keg or similar container holding four or more gallons of an alcoholic beverage without completing a registration form or affixing a temporary identification tag to the keg or container commits the crime of selling alcoholic beverages in an unregistered keg.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="04-21-012__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who is not licensed under this title or the employee or agent of a person who is not licensed under this title who possesses a keg or similar container holding four or more gallons of an alcoholic beverage without a temporary identification tag commits the crime of possessing alcoholic beverages in an unregistered keg.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="04-21-012__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Selling alcoholic beverages in an unregistered keg is a violation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="04-21-012__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Possessing alcoholic beverages in an unregistered keg is a violation and is punishable by a fine of $100.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_04-21-015">
            <num>04.21.015</num>
            <heading>Private manufacture of alcoholic beverages.</heading>
            <subsection eId="04-21-015__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (b) of this section, the provisions of this title do not apply to the private manufacture of alcoholic beverages.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="04-21-015__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This section does not apply to
AS 04.16.050
, 04.16.051, 04.16.080;
AS 04.21.010
, 04.21.020; alcoholic beverages manufactured in a quantity that exceeds the limit imposed on private manufacture under federal law; or an area that has adopted a local option law under
AS 04.11.491
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_04-21-020">
            <num>04.21.020</num>
            <heading>Civil liability of persons providing alcoholic beverages.</heading>
            <subsection eId="04-21-020__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided under (b) and (d) of this section, a person who provides alcoholic beverages to another person may not be held civilly liable for injuries resulting from the intoxication of that person unless the person who provides the alcoholic beverages holds a license authorized under
AS 04.09.020
 04.09.370 or is an agent or employee of a licensee and</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-020__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the alcoholic beverages are provided to a person under 21 years of age in violation of
AS 04.16.051
, unless the licensee, agent, or employee secures in good faith from the person a signed statement, liquor identification card, or driver's license meeting the requirements of
AS 04.21.050</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="04-21-020__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and (b), that indicates that the person is 21 years of age or older; or</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-020__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the alcoholic beverages are provided to a drunken person in violation of
AS 04.16.030
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="04-21-020__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who sells or barters an alcoholic beverage to another person in violation of
AS 04.09.060
,
AS 04.09.800
, or
AS 04.11.010
is strictly liable (1) to the recipient or another person for civil damages if, while under the influence of the alcoholic beverage, the person receiving the alcoholic beverage engages in conduct that results in civil damages and the recipient's being under the influence of the alcoholic beverage substantially contributes to the civil damages; and (2) for the cost to the state or a political subdivision of the state to criminally prosecute a person who receives an alcoholic beverage from a person who violates
AS 04.11.010
if the prosecution results from the violation of
AS 04.11.010
described in this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="04-21-020__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In an action under (b) or (d) of this section, it is not a defense that the person receiving the alcoholic beverage voluntarily consumed the alcoholic beverage or that the person receiving the alcoholic beverage was voluntarily under the influence of the alcoholic beverage.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="04-21-020__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who knowingly furnishes or delivers an alcoholic beverage to a person under 21 years of age in violation of
AS 04.16.051
is civilly liable to the recipient or another person for civil damages if, while under the influence of the alcoholic beverage, the person receiving the alcoholic beverage engages in conduct that results in civil damages and the recipient's being under the influence of the alcoholic beverage substantially contributes to the civil damages.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="04-21-020__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, civil damages includes damages for personal injury, death, or injury to property of a person, including the state or a political subdivision of the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_04-21-025">
            <num>04.21.025</num>
            <heading>Alcohol server education course.</heading>
            <subsection eId="04-21-025__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided under (e) and (f) of this section, as a condition of issuance or renewal of a license or conditional contractor's permit and selling alcoholic beverages under a license or conditional contractor's permit, the board shall require a licensee or permittee who sells or serves alcoholic beverages and a licensee's or permittee's agents and employees who sell or serve alcoholic beverages or check the identification of a patron to complete an alcohol server education course approved by the board.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="04-21-025__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The subjects that are included in an approved alcohol server education course shall be determined under regulations adopted by the board. In approving alcohol server education courses, the board shall consider the needs of both urban and rural licensees regarding access to an approved alcohol server education course and allow a licensee, permittee, agent, or employee to complete an alcohol server education course online or in person. A licensee, permittee, agent, or employee who sells or serves alcoholic beverages shall keep the card described in (c) of this section or other proof acceptable to the board of successful completion of an approved alcohol server education course on the licensed premises during working hours.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="04-21-025__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A licensee, permittee, agent, or employee shall complete the course required under (a) of this section and pass a written test, online or in person, demonstrating an understanding of the course subjects not more than 30 days after being licensed, permitted, or employed. The course provider shall issue a card to each individual who completes the course and passes the written test. A card issued under this subsection is valid for three years from the date of issue. A licensee, permittee, agent, or employee may renew a card issued under this section; to renew the card, the licensee, permittee, agent, or employee must pass a written test demonstrating an understanding of the course subjects. Notwithstanding the 30-day period for completing the course and passing the written test under this subsection, a person may not sell or serve alcoholic beverages or check the identification of a patron at a permitted event under
AS 04.09.600
 04.09.710 unless the person possesses a valid card issued before the event.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="04-21-025__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board shall review an approved alcohol server education course at least once every three years.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="04-21-025__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person licensed as a common carrier dispensary shall train agents and employees who sell or serve alcoholic beverages or who check the identification of a patron on provisions of state law regarding sale of alcoholic beverages, including
AS 04.16.015
, 04.16.020, 04.16.030, 04.16.051, 04.16.052, 04.16.120, 04.16.125,
AS 04.21.030
, and 04.21.050. The training must include the subjects of the effects of alcohol consumption, identifying a drunken person, determining valid identification, intervention to prevent unlawful alcohol consumption, and penalties for unlawful acts by agents and employees of licensees. A common carrier licensee shall, once every three years, provide the board with a description of its training program including the subjects taught, teaching method, and testing required.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="04-21-025__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This section does not apply to the following licenses:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-025__subsec_f__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>brewery manufacturer license under
AS 04.09.020
, unless the licensee holds a manufacturer sampling endorsement;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-025__subsec_f__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>winery manufacturer license under
AS 04.09.030
, unless the licensee holds a manufacturer sampling endorsement;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-025__subsec_f__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>distillery manufacturer license under
AS 04.09.040
, unless the licensee holds a manufacturer sampling endorsement;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-025__subsec_f__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>general wholesale license under
AS 04.09.100
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-025__subsec_f__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>limited wholesale brewed beverage and wine license under
AS 04.09.110
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-025__subsec_f__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>manufacturer direct shipment license under
AS 04.09.370
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="04-21-025__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who violates (a)  (c) or (e) of this section commits the offense of failure to comply with alcohol server education requirements.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="04-21-025__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Failure to comply with alcohol server education requirements is a violation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_04-21-030">
            <num>04.21.030</num>
            <heading>Responsibility of licensees, agents, and employees.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 04.21.030.   Responsibility of licensees, agents, and employees.
The licensee has a duty to exercise that degree of care that a reasonable person would observe to ensure that a business under the person's control is lawfully conducted.  This duty of the licensee includes, but is not limited
(1) to ensuring the compliance by agents or employees with this title and regulations adopted under this title, including acting with reasonable diligence to determine that agents or employees are advised of the provisions of this title and the regulations adopted under this title, either by securing the agent's or employee's written acknowledgement of posted instructions or otherwise; and
(2) to ensuring the compliance of the premises with public health, fire, and safety codes and ordinances of the state or municipality having jurisdiction.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_04-21-035">
            <num>04.21.035</num>
            <heading>Responsibility of partners of a limited liability partnership or foreign limited liability partnership.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 04.21.035.   Responsibility of partners of a limited liability partnership or foreign limited liability partnership.
Notwithstanding any other provision of
AS 32.06
, a partner of a limited liability partnership or a foreign limited liability partnership holding a license under this title is not relieved of the obligation or the liability otherwise imposed upon a holder of a liquor license under this title solely because the license is held by a limited liability partnership or a foreign limited liability partnership.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_04-21-040">
            <num>04.21.040</num>
            <heading>Sales on federal reservations.</heading>
            <subsection eId="04-21-040__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A wholesaler of alcoholic beverages may sell alcoholic beverages to a person who does not have a license under this title who has a fixed place of business on land in the state maintained by the United States government as a military or naval reservation, a national park, or other federal reservation.  A sale may be made under this section only if the purchaser is a ship's service store, officers club, officers mess, post exchange, or similar organization.  The wholesaler may deliver alcoholic beverages only to persons specified and at places designated in a written order issued by the federal organization for which the purchase is made.  A licensee making sales and deliveries under this section shall keep the original order attached to the copy of the invoice on file at the premises of the licensee.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="04-21-040__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Alcoholic beverages received on federal reservations under this section may not be removed for resale or public use outside the federal reservation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="04-21-040__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A wholesaler who sells alcoholic beverages on a federal reservation under this section shall pay the state excise tax imposed by
AS 43.60.010
on the alcoholic beverages sold and may subsequently claim credit for the excise taxes paid if the sale is made to an organization that is an instrumentality of the federal government.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_04-21-050">
            <num>04.21.050</num>
            <heading>Proof of age and of not being restricted from purchasing alcoholic beverages.</heading>
            <subsection eId="04-21-050__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a licensee or an agent or employee of the licensee questions or has reason to question whether a person entering licensed premises, or ordering, purchasing, attempting to purchase, or otherwise procuring or attempting to procure alcoholic beverages,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-050__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has attained the age of 21 years or is entering without consent in violation of
AS 04.16.049</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-050__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>is restricted from purchasing alcoholic beverages under
AS 04.16.160
, the licensee, agent, or employee may, but has no duty or obligation to, require the person to furnish proof acceptable under (b) of this section that the person is not restricted from purchasing alcoholic beverages or require the person to sign a statement that the person is not restricted from purchasing alcoholic beverages under
AS 04.16.160
; this statement shall be made on a form prepared by and furnished to the licensee by the board.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="04-21-050__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in
AS 04.16.160
, a valid driver's license or a valid identification card is acceptable as proof of age or that the person is not restricted from purchasing alcoholic beverages when used for identification in the purchase of alcoholic beverages and for securing entry to and remaining on premises where alcoholic beverages are sold if the license or identification card is made of or encased in plastic and contains a photograph of the licensee or card holder and a statement of age or date of birth. A licensee, agent, or employee may elect to not accept a passport, military identification card, or other identification as proof that the person is not restricted from purchasing alcoholic beverages and may require the person to furnish a valid driver's license or state identification card or otherwise furnish proof that the person is not a resident of this state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="04-21-050__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A licensee, or an agent or employee of the licensee, may not be charged for a violation of
AS 04.16.047
 04.16.052 if a signed statement as provided in (a) of this section is secured in good faith, or a valid driver's license or identification card is presented indicating that the owner and possessor of the presented driver's license or identification card is 21 or 16 years of age or over or is not restricted from purchasing alcoholic beverages, as appropriate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_04-21-055">
            <num>04.21.055</num>
            <heading>Refusal of service.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 04.21.055.   Refusal of service.
A licensee, an agent, or employee may refuse to sell, give, or serve alcoholic beverages to a person if the licensee, agent, or employee reasonably believes that the consumption of alcohol by that person may result in serious harm to that person or to others.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_04-21-060">
            <num>04.21.060</num>
            <heading>Warehousing of alcoholic beverages.</heading>
            <subsection eId="04-21-060__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A licensee may stock, warehouse, or otherwise store alcoholic beverages in a place elsewhere than premises indicated on the license if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-060__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the premises to be used for storage are inspected and approved by the board before their use;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-060__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the use of the premises for storage is authorized by local zoning ordinances; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-060__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the premises are accessible for inspection as provided in
AS 04.11.630
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="04-21-060__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A licensee who stores alcoholic beverages elsewhere than on the licensed premises and who fails to comply with (a)(1)  (3) of this section commits the offense of unauthorized warehousing.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="04-21-060__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Unauthorized warehousing is a violation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_04-21-065">
            <num>04.21.065</num>
            <heading>Posting of warning signs.</heading>
            <subsection eId="04-21-065__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A holder of one of the following types of licenses or permits shall post on the licensed or designated premises three separate warning signs as described in (b) of this section:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-065__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>brewery manufacturer license under
AS 04.09.020
with a manufacturer sampling endorsement under
AS 04.09.410
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-065__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>winery manufacturer license under
AS 04.09.030
with a manufacturer sampling endorsement under
AS 04.09.410
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-065__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>distillery manufacturer license under
AS 04.09.040
with a manufacturer sampling endorsement under
AS 04.09.410
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-065__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>beverage dispensary license under
AS 04.09.200
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-065__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>restaurant or eating place license under
AS 04.09.210
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-065__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>club license under
AS 04.09.220
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-065__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>package store license under
AS 04.09.230
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-065__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>pub license under
AS 04.09.240
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-065__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>theater license under
AS 04.09.250
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-065__subsec_a__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>common carrier dispensary license under
AS 04.09.260
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-065__subsec_a__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>sporting activity or event license under
AS 04.09.270
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-065__subsec_a__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>outdoor recreation lodge license under
AS 04.09.280
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-065__subsec_a__subsec_13">
                <num>(13)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>fair license under
AS 04.09.290
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-065__subsec_a__subsec_14">
                <num>(14)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>golf course license under
AS 04.09.300
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-065__subsec_a__subsec_15">
                <num>(15)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>destination resort license under
AS 04.09.310
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-065__subsec_a__subsec_16">
                <num>(16)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>brewery retail license under
AS 04.09.320
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-065__subsec_a__subsec_17">
                <num>(17)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>winery retail license under
AS 04.09.330
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-065__subsec_a__subsec_18">
                <num>(18)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>distillery retail license under
AS 04.09.340
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-065__subsec_a__subsec_19">
                <num>(19)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>beverage dispensary tourism license under
AS 04.09.350
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-065__subsec_a__subsec_20">
                <num>(20)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>seasonal restaurant or eating place tourism license under
AS 04.09.360
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-065__subsec_a__subsec_21">
                <num>(21)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>beverage dispensary caterer's permit under
AS 04.09.610
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-065__subsec_a__subsec_22">
                <num>(22)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>restaurant caterer's dining permit under
AS 04.09.620
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-065__subsec_a__subsec_23">
                <num>(23)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>club caterer's permit under
AS 04.09.630
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-065__subsec_a__subsec_24">
                <num>(24)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>art exhibit event permit under
AS 04.09.640
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-065__subsec_a__subsec_25">
                <num>(25)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>music festival permit under
AS 04.09.650
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-065__subsec_a__subsec_26">
                <num>(26)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>nonprofit organization event permit under
AS 04.09.660
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-065__subsec_a__subsec_27">
                <num>(27)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>package store tasting event permit under
AS 04.09.680
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-065__subsec_a__subsec_28">
                <num>(28)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>conditional contractor's permit under
AS 04.09.710
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-065__subsec_a__subsec_29">
                <num>(29)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>another license or permit issued by the board authorizing consumption of alcoholic beverages.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="04-21-065__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The warning signs required by (a) of this section must be at least 11 inches by 14 inches, and the lettering must be at least one-half inch high and in contrasting colors. The first sign must read, WARNING: Drinking alcoholic beverages such as beer, wine, wine coolers, and distilled spirits or smoking cigarettes during pregnancy can cause birth defects. The second sign must read, WARNING: A person who provides alcoholic beverages to a person under 21 years of age, if convicted under
AS 04.16.051
, could be imprisoned for up to five years and fined up to $50,000. The third sign must read, WARNING: An unaccompanied person under 21 years of age who enters these premises in violation of law may, under
AS 04.16.049
(e), be civilly liable for damages of $1,500. The license or permit holder shall display the first and second signs in a manner that would make them conspicuous to a person who will be purchasing or consuming alcoholic beverages or smoking cigarettes on the licensed or designated premises and shall conspicuously display the third sign at each door through which customers enter the licensed premises.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="04-21-065__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board shall furnish a sign required under this section to a person who requests it with the intention of displaying it.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="04-21-065__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A peace officer may issue a citation for a violation of this section. The provisions of
AS 12.25.175
 12.25.230 apply to the issuance of a citation under this subsection.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="04-21-065__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An employee of the board designated by the board to enforce this section may issue a citation for a violation of this section regardless of whether the violation was committed in the employee's presence. A citation issued under this subsection must be in the same form and shall be processed in the same manner as a citation issued by a peace officer under (d) of this section. An employee of the board may not arrest a person for a violation of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="04-21-065__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A holder of a license or permit who violates this section is guilty of a violation as defined in
AS 11.81.900</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="04-21-065__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and upon conviction is punishable by a fine of not less than $20 nor more than $300. Each day a violation continues after a citation for the violation has been issued constitutes a separate violation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="04-21-065__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The supreme court shall establish a schedule of bail amounts for violations of this section. The bail amount may not exceed the maximum fine that may be imposed for the violation under (f) of this section. The bail amount for a violation must appear on the citation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="04-21-065__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a person cited for a violation under this section does not contest the citation, the person may, on or before the 30th day after the date of the citation, mail or personally deliver to the clerk of the court in which the citation is filed</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-065__subsec_h__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the amount of bail indicated on the citation for the violation; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-065__subsec_h__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a copy of the citation indicating that the right to an appearance is waived, a plea of no contest is entered, and the bail is forfeited.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="04-21-065__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When bail has been forfeited under (h) of this section, a judgment of conviction shall be entered. Forfeiture of bail is a complete satisfaction for the violation. The clerk of the court accepting the bail shall provide the violator with a receipt stating that fact if requested.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="04-21-065__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person cited under this section is guilty of failure to obey a citation under
AS 12.25.230
if the person fails to pay the bail amount established under (g) of this section or to appear in court as required.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="04-21-065__subsec_k">
              <num>(k)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The board or any affected party may institute an action in the superior court to enjoin repeated violations of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="04-21-065__subsec_l">
              <num>(l)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding
AS 04.11.370
, the board is not required to suspend or revoke a license or permit for a violation of this section; however, the board may consider a violation of this section when determining under
AS 04.11.370
(a)(2) whether continuation of activities authorized under a license or permit would be in the best interests of the public.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_04-21-070">
            <num>04.21.070</num>
            <heading>Enforcement.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 04.21.070.   Enforcement.
Peace officers shall investigate and report to the board violations of this title.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_04-21-078">
            <num>04.21.078</num>
            <heading>Court records of persons under 21 years of age.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 04.21.078.   Court records of persons under 21 years of age.
The Alaska Court System may not publish on a publicly available website the court records of a violation of
AS 04.16.049
, 04.16.050, 04.16.060(g), or a similar ordinance of a municipality, if the violation was charged separately and was not joined with any other minor offense or criminal charge at the time of filing.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_04-21-080">
            <num>04.21.080</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="04-21-080__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this title,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-080__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a person acts with criminal negligence with respect to a result or to a circumstance described by a provision of law defining an offense when the person fails to perceive a substantial and unjustifiable risk that the result will occur or that the circumstance exists; the risk must be of such a nature and degree that the failure to perceive it constitutes a gross deviation from the standard of care that a reasonable person would observe in the situation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-080__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a person acts knowingly with respect to conduct or to a circumstance described by a provision of law defining an offense when the person is aware that the person's conduct is of that nature or that the circumstance exists; when knowledge of the existence of a particular fact is an element of an offense, that knowledge is established if a person is aware of a substantial probability of its existence, unless the person actually believes it does not exist; a person who is unaware of conduct or a circumstance of which the person would have been aware had the person not been intoxicated acts knowingly with respect to that conduct or circumstance;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-080__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a person acts recklessly with respect to a result or to a circumstance described by a provision of law defining an offense when the person is aware of and consciously disregards a substantial and unjustifiable risk that the result will occur or that the circumstance exists; the risk must be of such a nature and degree that disregard of it constitutes a gross deviation from the standard of conduct that a reasonable person would observe in the situation; a person who is unaware of a risk of which the person would have been aware had the person not been intoxicated acts recklessly with respect to that risk.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="04-21-080__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this title,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-080__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>alcoholic beverage means a spirituous, vinous, malt, or other fermented or distilled liquid, whatever the origin, that is intended for human consumption as a beverage and that contains one-half of one percent or more of alcohol by volume, whether produced commercially or privately; however, in an area that has adopted a local option under
AS 04.11.491
, alcoholic beverage means a spirituous, vinous, malt, or other fermented or distilled liquid, whatever the origin, that is intended for human consumption as a beverage by the person who possesses or attempts to possess it and that contains alcohol in any amount if the liquid is produced privately, or that contains one-half of one percent or more of alcohol by volume, if the liquid is produced commercially;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-080__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>board means the Alcoholic Beverage Control Board;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-080__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>bona fide restaurant means an establishment or a portion of an establishment where, during all times alcoholic beverages are served or consumed,
(A) the patron's principal activity is consumption of food; and
(B) a variety of types of food items appropriate for meals is prepared on site and available for sale as shown on a menu provided to patrons and filed with the board;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-080__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>[Repealed, § 164 ch 8 SLA 2022.]</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-080__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>brewed beverage means an alcoholic beverage made by fermenting cereal grains, including beer and malt beverages, sake, and kombucha;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-080__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>calendar year means the period beginning January 1 and ending December 31;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-080__subsec_b__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>cider means a type of wine made primarily from fermented apples, apple juice, or concentrate;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-080__subsec_b__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>community diversion panel means a youth court or other group serving as a sentencing option for a person convicted under this title;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-080__subsec_b__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>community work means and is limited to work on projects designed to reduce or eliminate environmental damage, protect the public health, or improve public land, forests, parks, roads, highways, facilities, or education; community work may not confer a private benefit on a person except as may be incidental to the public benefit;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-080__subsec_b__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>designated premises means any or all designated portions of a building or structure, rooms or enclosures in the building or structure, or real estate leased, used, controlled, or operated by a licensee or permittee for the purpose for which the license or permit is issued by the board at the location of the site for which the license or permit is issued;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-080__subsec_b__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>director means the director of the Alcoholic Beverage Control Board;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-080__subsec_b__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>distilled spirit means an alcoholic beverage that is first fermented and then distilled;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-080__subsec_b__subsec_13">
                <num>(13)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>distributing point means a location where alcoholic beverages are distributed from a warehouse;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-080__subsec_b__subsec_14">
                <num>(14)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>drunken person means a person whose physical or mental conduct is substantially impaired as a result of the introduction of an alcoholic beverage into the person's body and who exhibits those plain and easily observed or discovered outward manifestations of behavior commonly known to be produced by the overconsumption of alcoholic beverages;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-080__subsec_b__subsec_15">
                <num>(15)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>established village means an area that does not contain any part of an incorporated city or another established village and that is
(A) an unincorporated community that is in the unorganized borough and that has 25 or more permanent residents; or
(B) an unincorporated community that is in an organized borough, has 25 or more permanent residents, and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="04-21-080__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>is on a road system and is located more than 50 miles outside the boundary limits of a unified municipality, or
(ii) is not on a road system and is located more than 15 miles outside the boundary limits of a unified municipality;</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-080__subsec_i__subsec_16">
                <num>(16)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>foreign limited liability company has the meaning given in
AS 10.50.990
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-080__subsec_i__subsec_17">
                <num>(17)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>foreign limited liability partnership has the meaning given in
AS 32.06
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-080__subsec_i__subsec_18">
                <num>(18)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>golf course means a course that is open to the public, having at least nine holes, and covering at least 2,950 yards;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-080__subsec_i__subsec_19">
                <num>(19)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>half-keg means a keg designed to be a bulk container for, and containing not more than, 15 1/2 gallons of malt beverages;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-080__subsec_i__subsec_20">
                <num>(20)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>juvenile alcohol safety action program means
(A) a juvenile alcohol safety action program developed and implemented or approved by the Department of Health under
AS 47.37
;
(B) any other alcohol education or treatment program approved by the Department of Health under
AS 47.37
if a program described in (A) of this paragraph is not available in the community in which the person resides; or
(C) a program or counseling approved by the court if a program or treatment described in (A) of this paragraph is not available in the community where the person resides;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-080__subsec_i__subsec_21">
                <num>(21)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>kombucha means a brewed beverage made from fermented tea and containing at least one-half percent alcohol by volume;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-080__subsec_i__subsec_22">
                <num>(22)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>licensed premises means any or all designated portions of a building or structure, rooms or enclosures in the building or structure, or real estate leased, used, controlled, or operated by a licensee in the conduct of business for which the licensee is licensed by the board at the specific address for which the license or an endorsement to the license is issued;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-080__subsec_i__subsec_23">
                <num>(23)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>limited liability company means an organization under
AS 10.50
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-080__subsec_i__subsec_24">
                <num>(24)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>limited liability organization means a limited liability company, a foreign limited liability company, a limited liability partnership, or a foreign limited liability partnership;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-080__subsec_i__subsec_25">
                <num>(25)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>limited liability partnership has the meaning given in
AS 32.06
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-080__subsec_i__subsec_26">
                <num>(26)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>local governing body means, as appropriate, a city council, a borough assembly, or a traditional village council, but does not include a corporation established under the Alaska Native Claims Settlement Act;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-080__subsec_i__subsec_27">
                <num>(27)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>manufacture means the creation of alcoholic content by use of fermentation with natural or artificial sugar or yeast or distillation.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-080__subsec_i__subsec_28">
                <num>(28)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>mead means a type of wine made primarily from honey;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-080__subsec_i__subsec_29">
                <num>(29)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>sake means a type of brewed beverage made primarily from fermented rice;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="04-21-080__subsec_i__subsec_30">
                <num>(30)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>wine means an alcoholic beverage made from fermented grapes or other fruit or honey.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>