<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-15/chapter-35"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-15/chapter-35"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="15.35"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-15/chapter-35/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-15/chapter-35/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-15/chapter-35/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-15/chapter-35/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_15">
        <num>15</num>
        <heading>Elections</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_15__chp_35">
          <num>35</num>
          <heading>State Elections</heading>
          <section eId="sec_15-35-010">
            <num>15.35.010</num>
            <heading>Election of governor and lieutenant governor.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.35.010.   Election of governor and lieutenant governor.
A governor and lieutenant governor shall be elected at the general election in 1962 and every four years thereafter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-35-020">
            <num>15.35.020</num>
            <heading>Election of legislature.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.35.020.   Election of legislature.
One-half of the members of the state senate and all members of the state house of representatives shall be elected at each general election in accordance with the apportionment articles of the Constitution of the State of Alaska.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-35-030">
            <num>15.35.030</num>
            <heading>Approval or rejection of supreme court justice.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.35.030.   Approval or rejection of supreme court justice.
Each supreme court justice shall be subject to approval or rejection at the first general election held more than three years after the justice's appointment.  If approved, the justice shall thereafter be subject to approval or rejection in a like manner every tenth year.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-35-040">
            <num>15.35.040</num>
            <heading>Filing declaration by supreme court justice.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.35.040.   Filing declaration by supreme court justice.
Each justice seeking retention in office shall file with the director a declaration of candidacy for retention no later than August 1 before the general election at which approval or rejection is requisite.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-35-041">
            <num>15.35.041</num>
            <heading>Requirement of filing fee for supreme court candidate.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.35.041.   Requirement of filing fee for supreme court candidate.
At the time the declaration is filed, each candidate for retention shall pay a filing fee to the director. The filing fee for a candidate for retention on the supreme court is $100.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-35-050">
            <num>15.35.050</num>
            <heading>Placing name of supreme court justice on ballot.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.35.050.   Placing name of supreme court justice on ballot.
The director shall place the name of a supreme court justice who has properly filed a declaration of candidacy for retention on the ballot in each judicial district of the state for the general election at which approval is sought.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-35-053">
            <num>15.35.053</num>
            <heading>Approval or rejection of a judge of the court of appeals.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.35.053.   Approval or rejection of a judge of the court of appeals.
Each judge of the court of appeals shall be subject to approval or rejection at the first general election held more than three years after the judge's appointment.  If approved, the judge is thereafter subject to approval or rejection in a like manner every eighth year.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-35-055">
            <num>15.35.055</num>
            <heading>Filing declaration by judge of the court of appeals.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.35.055.   Filing declaration by judge of the court of appeals.
Each judge of the court of appeals seeking retention in office shall file with the director a declaration of candidacy for retention no later than August 1 before the general election at which approval or rejection is requisite.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-35-057">
            <num>15.35.057</num>
            <heading>Requirement of filing fee for court of appeals.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.35.057.   Requirement of filing fee for court of appeals.
At the time the declaration is filed, each candidate for retention shall pay a filing fee to the director. The filing fee for a candidate for retention on the court of appeals is $100.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-35-059">
            <num>15.35.059</num>
            <heading>Placing name of judge of the court of appeals on ballot.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.35.059.   Placing name of judge of the court of appeals on ballot.
The director shall place the name of a judge of the court of appeals who has properly filed a declaration of candidacy for retention on the ballot in each judicial district of the state for the general election at which approval is sought.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-35-060">
            <num>15.35.060</num>
            <heading>Approval or rejection of superior court judge.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.35.060.   Approval or rejection of superior court judge.
Each superior court judge shall be subject to approval or rejection at the first general election held more than three years after the judge's appointment.  If approved, the judge shall thereafter be subject to approval or rejection in a like manner every sixth year.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-35-070">
            <num>15.35.070</num>
            <heading>Filing declaration by superior court judge.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.35.070.   Filing declaration by superior court judge.
Each judge seeking retention in office shall file with the director a declaration of candidacy for retention no later than August 1 before the general election at which approval or rejection is requisite.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-35-071">
            <num>15.35.071</num>
            <heading>Requirement of filing fee for superior court candidate.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.35.071.   Requirement of filing fee for superior court candidate.
At the time the declaration is filed, each candidate for retention shall pay a filing fee to the director. The filing fee for a candidate for retention on the superior court is $30.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-35-080">
            <num>15.35.080</num>
            <heading>Determination of judicial district in which to seek approval.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.35.080.   Determination of judicial district in which to seek approval.
The judge shall seek approval in the judicial district to which the judge was originally appointed, except in case of assignments and transfers with the judge's consent, in which case the judge shall seek approval in the district where the judge has served the major portion of the judge's term.  The judge shall designate on the declaration of candidacy the judicial district to which the judge was appointed, except in case of assignments and transfers in which case the judge shall designate the district where the judge has served the major portion of the judge's term.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-35-090">
            <num>15.35.090</num>
            <heading>Placing name of superior court judge on ballot.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.35.090.   Placing name of superior court judge on ballot.
The director shall place the name of a superior court judge who has properly filed a declaration of candidacy for retention on the ballot in the judicial district designated in the declaration of candidacy for the general election at which approval is sought.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-35-100">
            <num>15.35.100</num>
            <heading>Approval or rejection of district judge.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-35-100__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each district judge shall be subject to approval or rejection at the first general election held more than two years after the judge's appointment under the provisions of
AS 22.15.170
. If approved, the judge shall thereafter be subject to approval or rejection in a like manner every fourth year.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-35-100__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The district judge shall seek approval in the judicial district in which the judge was originally appointed, or in the district where the judge has served the major portion of the judge's term.  The district judge shall designate on the declaration of candidacy the judicial district in which the judge was appointed, or the district where the judge has served the major portion of the judge's term.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-35-110">
            <num>15.35.110</num>
            <heading>Filing declaration by district judge.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.35.110.   Filing declaration by district judge.
Each district judge seeking retention in office shall file with the director a declaration of candidacy for retention no later than August 1 before the general election at which approval or rejection is requisite.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-35-120">
            <num>15.35.120</num>
            <heading>Requirement of filing fee for district court candidate.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.35.120.   Requirement of filing fee for district court candidate.
At the time the declaration is filed, each candidate for retention on the district court shall pay a filing fee of $30 to the director.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-35-130">
            <num>15.35.130</num>
            <heading>Placing name of district judge on ballot.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.35.130.   Placing name of district judge on ballot.
The director shall place the name of a district judge who has properly filed a declaration of candidacy for retention on the ballot in the judicial district designated in the declaration of candidacy for the general election at which approval is sought.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-35-135">
            <num>15.35.135</num>
            <heading>Withdrawal of candidacy; removal of name from general election ballot.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-35-135__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notice of withdrawal of candidacy for retention for a supreme court justice, judge of the court of appeals, superior court judge, or district court judge must be in writing over the signature of the candidate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-35-135__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The name of a candidate for retention for supreme court justice, judge of the court of appeals, superior court judge, or district court judge must appear on the general election ballot unless notice under (a) of this section of withdrawal of candidacy is received by the director at least 64 days before the date of the general election.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>