<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-17/chapter-21"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-17/chapter-21"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="17.21"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-17/chapter-21/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-17/chapter-21/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-17/chapter-21/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-17/chapter-21/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_17">
        <num>17</num>
        <heading>Food and Drugs</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_17__chp_21">
          <num>21</num>
          <heading>Illicit Synthetic Drugs</heading>
          <section eId="sec_17-21-010">
            <num>17.21.010</num>
            <heading>Illicit synthetic drugs.</heading>
            <subsection eId="17-21-010__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not possess, offer, display, market, advertise for sale, or sell an illicit synthetic drug.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="17-21-010__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A synthetic drug is illicit if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="17-21-010__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the label
(A) is false or misleading;
(B) does not specify the identity of the substances contained in the synthetic drug; or
(C) does not specify the name and place of business of the manufacturer, packer, or distributor; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="17-21-010__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the synthetic drug has one or more of the following characteristics:
(A) the packaging or labeling of the synthetic drug suggests that the user will achieve euphoria, a hallucination, mood enhancement, relaxation, stimulation, or another effect on the body;
(B) the name or packaging of the synthetic drug uses images or labels suggesting that it is a controlled substance or has the effect of a controlled substance;
(C) the synthetic drug resembles a controlled substance in appearance, in chemical structure, or composition;
(D) the synthetic drug is marketed or advertised for a particular use or purpose and the cost of the synthetic drug is disproportionately higher than other products marketed or advertised for the same or similar use or purpose;
(E) the synthetic drug contains a warning label stating or suggesting that the synthetic drug is in compliance with state laws regulating controlled substances;
(F) the synthetic drug is a product to which has been added a synthetic chemical or synthetic chemical compound that does not have a legitimate relationship to the advertised use of the product.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="17-21-010__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>It is an affirmative defense to an action for a violation of this section that a product is expressly exempted from or is expressly regulated under and is in compliance with state or federal law. In this subsection, affirmative defense has the meaning given in
AS 11.81.900
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_17-21-020">
            <num>17.21.020</num>
            <heading>Exemption.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 17.21.020.   Exemption.
AS 17.21.010
does not apply to a synthetic drug intended solely for investigational use by experts qualified by scientific training and experience to investigate the safety of drugs if the drug is plainly labeled for investigational use only, and the investigational use is authorized by state or federal law.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_17-21-030">
            <num>17.21.030</num>
            <heading>Enforcement and penalties.</heading>
            <subsection eId="17-21-030__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner of public safety is responsible for enforcing this chapter and may</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="17-21-030__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>delegate that authority as appropriate; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="17-21-030__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>cooperate with the Department of Health in carrying out the commissioner's enforcement activities.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="17-21-030__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This section does not limit the authority of a peace officer.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="17-21-030__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who violates
AS 17.21.010
is guilty of a violation, and, upon conviction, is punishable by a fine of not more than $500.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="17-21-030__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The provisions of this section are in addition to the remedies available under
AS 45.50.471
 45.50.561.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_17-21-090">
            <num>17.21.090</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="17-21-090__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>a crystalline or powder product in crystalline, loose powder, block, tablet, or capsule form; or
(ii) plant material in granular, loose leaf, powder, or liquid form or used as a food additive; and
(C) not a controlled substance.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>