<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-18/chapter-25"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-18/chapter-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="18.25"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-18/chapter-25/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-18/chapter-25/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-18/chapter-25/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-18/chapter-25/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_18">
        <num>18</num>
        <heading>Health, Safety, Housing, Human Rights, and Public Defender</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_18__chp_25">
          <num>25</num>
          <heading>Assistance to Hospitals and Health Facilities</heading>
          <section eId="sec_18-25-010">
            <num>18.25.010</num>
            <heading>Department to render aid.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.25.010.   Department to render aid.
The department may facilitate the purchase, construction, and repair of, and obtain necessary equipment for, nonprofit hospitals operated by municipalities, communities, and associations in the state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-25-020">
            <num>18.25.020</num>
            <heading>Determination of necessity.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.25.020.   Determination of necessity.
The department shall initiate appropriate action under
AS 18.25.010
 18.25.030 when it determines which projects are of most immediate necessity, and shall allot money to the municipalities, communities, and associations on a matching basis, or in accordance with their financial ability and urgency of the need.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-25-030">
            <num>18.25.030</num>
            <heading>Intent.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.25.030.   Intent.
It is the intent of
AS 18.25.010
 18.25.030 to provide financial aid to municipalities, communities, and associations for which an attempt at complete financing by themselves of a necessary project would entail great hardship. It is also intended that the department utilize the money authorized under
AS 18.25.010
 18.25.030 so far as can be arranged to assist the municipalities, communities, and associations in matching funds with the federal government under applicable federal law for hospital assistance.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-25-040">
            <num>18.25.040</num>
            <heading>Department to render aid.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.25.040.   Department to render aid.
The department may assist in cases of operational deficits of community operated nonprofit hospitals and clinics in the state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-25-050">
            <num>18.25.050</num>
            <heading>Determination of necessity.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.25.050.   Determination of necessity.
The department shall initiate appropriate action in accordance with the provisions of
AS 18.25.040
 18.25.060 as soon as the department determines which projects are of most immediate necessity.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-25-060">
            <num>18.25.060</num>
            <heading>Intent.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.25.060.   Intent.
It is the intent of
AS 18.25.040
 18.25.060 to provide financial aid, or funds to match available federal funds to aid localities or municipalities whose taxable values are limited in scope and for whom an attempt at community financing of a community operated nonprofit hospital or clinic would entail insurmountable hardship.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-25-070">
            <num>18.25.070</num>
            <heading>Department to render assistance.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.25.070.   Department to render assistance.
The department may assist in the purchase, construction, repair, and equipping of facilities to improve and protect community health, and may provide financial assistance for the operation of the facilities in case of operational deficits.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-25-080">
            <num>18.25.080</num>
            <heading>Intent and purpose.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.25.080.   Intent and purpose.
It is the intent of
AS 18.25.070
 18.25.110 to assist communities and areas in developing and improving health service facilities by the purchase, construction, renovation, or establishment of hospitals, health centers, or clinics, or quarters for personnel, and the purchase of furnishings, supplies, and equipment and making the other expenditures necessary to carry out the purpose of
AS 18.25.070
 18.25.110.  Assistance is to be given in areas that would otherwise be denied adequate facilities, because the taxable values are limited in scope and an attempt at total community financing of a project would cause hardship or prevent its realization.  It is also intended that the department utilize the money authorized under
AS 18.25.070
 18.25.110 so far as can be arranged to assist municipalities in matching funds with the federal government under federal law.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-25-090">
            <num>18.25.090</num>
            <heading>Use of purchases.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.25.090.   Use of purchases.
Purchases under
AS 18.25.070
 18.25.110 are to be used for the purpose for which appropriated and when the purpose is discontinued the items shall be returned to the department for use elsewhere.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-25-100">
            <num>18.25.100</num>
            <heading>Regulations authorized.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.25.100.   Regulations authorized.
The department shall adopt regulations for
(1) the establishment of criteria, minimum requirements, and standards for assistance to communities under
AS 18.25.070
 18.25.110;
(2) the establishment of the fiscal and accounting procedures and controls considered necessary for the payment of grants;
(3) the compilation of data and information from the communities concerned that will support the need for assistance under
AS 18.25.070
 18.25.110;
(4) the establishment of procedures by which communities may apply for assistance;
(5) accepting financial or other assistance from the federal government under federal law to carry out the purpose of
AS 18.25.070
 18.25.110 through matching funds or grants;
(6) cooperation and coordination with other state boards, departments, or agencies engaged in construction programs in areas applying for assistance under
AS 18.25.070
 18.25.110.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-25-110">
            <num>18.25.110</num>
            <heading>Report of grants made.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.25.110.   Report of grants made.
Within 10 days of the convening of each legislative session, the department shall have completed a report of grants made under
AS 18.25.070
 18.25.110 and notified the legislature that the report is available.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_18-25-120">
            <num>18.25.120</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 18.25.120.   Definitions.
In this chapter, department means the Department of Health.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>