<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-57"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-57"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="14.57"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-57/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-57/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-57/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-14/chapter-57/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_14">
        <num>14</num>
        <heading>Education, Libraries, and Museums</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_14__chp_57">
          <num>57</num>
          <heading>Museums and Natural and Cultural History Repositories</heading>
          <section eId="sec_14-57-010">
            <num>14.57.010</num>
            <heading>The state museum.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-57-010__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall manage and have complete charge of all of the property contained in the institution known as the state museum. The museum is designated as a repository of natural and cultural history collections and shall be operated and maintained as a designated repository in the state capital. Branch museums may be established and maintained in other localities in the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-57-010__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-57-010__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>acquire artifacts, natural history specimens, art objects, etc., that pertain to the human and natural history of Alaska by purchase and by gift;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-57-010__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>identify, catalog, preserve, and display these acquisitions;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-57-010__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>acquire and catalog Alaskan photographs and maintain a card catalog of this collection;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-57-010__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>accept endowments, grants, and gifts in accordance with
AS 37.07
(the Executive Budget Act);</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-57-010__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>collect and maintain books, periodicals, pamphlets, and other materials pertinent to museum administration, techniques, and collections;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-57-010__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>assist and advise in the development of local museums;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-57-010__subsec_b__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>collect and keep current information concerning museum activities throughout the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-57-010__subsec_b__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>coordinate the museum activities of the state with those of other agencies;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-57-010__subsec_b__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>keep the museum open at reasonable hours for the convenience of visitors;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-57-010__subsec_b__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>provide museum services and administer state and other grants-in-aid to museums in the state to supplement and improve their services, the grants to be paid from money appropriated for that purpose, or from other money available for that purpose.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-57-010__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may establish by regulation, and collect, reasonable user fees and other fees for services provided by the department under this chapter. The department may negotiate reduced fees or group discounts with, or offer reduced fees or group discounts to, persons who bring groups of people to visit the museum or a branch of the museum.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-57-012">
            <num>14.57.012</num>
            <heading>Designated natural and cultural history repositories.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-57-012__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may designate natural and cultural history repositories in addition to the state museum as provided under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-57-012__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An institution located in the state that seeks designation as a natural and cultural history repository may apply on a form and under procedures established by the department in regulation. The procedures must include submission of evidence acceptable to the department that the institution</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-57-012__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>adheres to currently established criteria of collection preservation and storage, including employment of long-term, professional, and systematic curatorial services;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-57-012__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>ensures public access commensurate with the nature of the objects of the collection in the repository;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-57-012__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has a statewide scope of collection;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-57-012__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>has a statewide scope of knowledge dissemination;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-57-012__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>maintains a museum certification issued by a nationally recognized entity;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-57-012__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>complies with 25 U.S.C. 3001  3013 (Native American Graves Protection and Repatriation Act); and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-57-012__subsec_b__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>meets other standards established in regulation by the department.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-57-012__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall maintain a list of designated repositories.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-57-012__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A repository may accept and expend funds from any available source, including federal and state grants and donations, for the purpose of acquiring, cataloging, curating, and preserving state natural and cultural history collections.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-57-012__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A designation of a repository confers no acquisition, management, or other rights to the department over the collections held by a designated repository.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-57-012__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, institution means a museum, a cultural center, or an affiliated research component of a museum or cultural center.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-57-020">
            <num>14.57.020</num>
            <heading>Museum Collections Advisory Committee.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-57-020__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>There is created in the department the State Museum Collections Advisory Committee consisting of five members appointed by the board to serve at the board's pleasure for staggered three-year terms.  The appointees shall be broadly representative of the public's interest in the preservation of the human, cultural, natural, archeological, and anthropological history of Alaska.  When possible, some of the committee members shall be known for, or possess, special expertise or a culturally relevant background in these aspects of the art and history of the state.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-57-020__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A member appointed to fill a vacancy serves for the unexpired term of the member succeeded.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-57-030">
            <num>14.57.030</num>
            <heading>Officers; meetings, rules of procedure, quorum.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-57-030__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The committee shall elect a chair from among its members.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-57-030__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The committee shall meet at least once every six months and at the call of its chair, on petition of a majority of its members, or at the call of the commissioner, or the director of the museum, at a mutually convenient time and place both for the members of the committee and for interested members of the public. A meeting of the committee may be held by teleconference.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-57-030__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The committee shall adopt rules of procedure to govern its meetings.  A majority of the members of the committee constitutes a quorum.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-57-040">
            <num>14.57.040</num>
            <heading>Compensation; per diem, travel expenses.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.57.040.   Compensation; per diem, travel expenses.
The members of the committee serve without compensation, but they are entitled to per diem and travel expenses as authorized by law for boards and commissions.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-57-050">
            <num>14.57.050</num>
            <heading>Collections management; acquisitions and dispositions.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-57-050__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>On recommendation of the committee, the department shall adopt regulations governing the museum's in-house acquisitions committee, and the management and disposition of artifacts, natural history specimens, art objects, collections or other items, materials, or properties that are owned by, in the custody of, or are proposed for acquisition by, the state museum. The regulations must be consistent with
AS 14.57.200
 14.57.290.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-57-050__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Artifacts, natural history specimens, art objects, collections, or other items, materials, or properties that relate to the history of Alaska and are appropriate for preservation in the state museum of a value of $5,000 or more may not be acquired by purchase, gift, or exchange, or otherwise nor may any item owned by, or in the custody of, the state museum be disposed of by sale, gift, exchange, or otherwise, without the written approval of the committee. In recommending the acquisition or disposal of an item under this subsection for the state museum, the committee shall evaluate the need for the item or collection proposed for acquisition or disposal with reference to the scope of collections of the state museums.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-57-050__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The committee may obtain an independent, professional appraisal of the value of each item to be acquired or disposed of by or for the state museum.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-57-060">
            <num>14.57.060</num>
            <heading>Advisory duties.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.57.060.   Advisory duties.
The committee shall act in an advisory capacity to the board as to the general acquisition and deaccession policies and programs of the state museum.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-57-070">
            <num>14.57.070</num>
            <heading>Conflict of interest.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-57-070__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A member of the committee may not act on a matter relating to the state museum in which the member's relationship with another person or with respect to the acquisition or disposition of an item owned by, in custody of, or proposed to be acquired by or for the state museum creates a conflict of interest.  A committee member may not</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-57-070__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>have a pecuniary or property interest in an item that is proposed to be acquired or disposed of by or for the state museum;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-57-070__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>have a pecuniary or property interest, directly or indirectly, in a contract to which the museum, or the state on behalf of the museum, is a party; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-57-070__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>receive compensation for services rendered to the state museum as a consultant, expert, appraiser, or otherwise, except as provided in
AS 14.57.040
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-57-070__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (a) of this section, a committee member may bequeath or donate an item to the state museum.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-57-080">
            <num>14.57.080</num>
            <heading>Definition.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.57.080.   Definition.
In
AS 14.57.020
 14.57.080, committee means the state Museum Collections Advisory Committee.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-57-100">
            <num>14.57.100</num>
            <heading>Acquisitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.57.100.   Acquisitions.
Subject to appropriation by the legislature under
AS 37.14.530
, the director may use the balance of the net income account of the Alaska heritage endowment fund to acquire culturally or historically significant artifacts, natural history specimens, art objects, collections, and other items, materials, or properties that represent and document Alaska's land, natural history, and people for
(1) the Alaska State Museum; and
(2) the Sheldon Jackson Museum.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-57-110">
            <num>14.57.110</num>
            <heading>Ownership of acquired items.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.57.110.   Ownership of acquired items.
Except when ownership of an item is transferred under
AS 14.57.120
, an item acquired under
AS 14.57.100
becomes the property of the state museum.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-57-120">
            <num>14.57.120</num>
            <heading>Criteria applicable to acquisitions from the fund.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.57.120.   Criteria applicable to acquisitions from the fund.
Subject to approval given by the Museum Collections Advisory Committee under
AS 14.57.050
(b), the director may
(1) establish by contract the terms and conditions of custody, protection, conservation, and exhibition of an item acquired by the state museum if the item is acquired and custody of it is assigned to another institution;
(2) transfer ownership of an item to an institution having custody of an item acquired from the net income account of the fund if the director is satisfied that the institution will provide necessary care and protection of the item; or
(3) assign long-term custody of an item to an institution having custody of an item acquired from the net income account of the fund if the director is satisfied that the institution to which custody of the item is transferred will provide necessary care and protection of the item in accordance with a contract entered into under (1) of this section.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-57-130">
            <num>14.57.130</num>
            <heading>Disposition of acquired items.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.57.130.   Disposition of acquired items.
Subject to approval of the Museum Collections Advisory Committee under
AS 14.57.050
(b), the director may establish a deaccession policy under which the director may exchange or otherwise convey title to an item acquired from the net income account of the fund in accordance with generally accepted principles governing the disposal of these items.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-57-199">
            <num>14.57.199</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.57.199.   Definitions.
In
AS 14.57.100
 14.57.199,
(1) director means the director of the division of the department that has responsibility for state libraries, archives, and museums;
(2) fund means the Alaska heritage endowment fund established in
AS 37.14.500
;
(3) net income account means the account established in
AS 37.14.510
.
Article 3. Property Held by Museums.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-57-200">
            <num>14.57.200</num>
            <heading>Acquisition of title to loaned property.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-57-200__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A museum may acquire the title to documented property loaned to the museum if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-57-200__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>at least seven years have passed after the expiration date of the loan without written or other contact between the lender and the museum; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-57-200__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the loan does not have an expiration date and at least seven years have passed without written or other contact between the lender and the museum since the loan was made.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-57-200__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To acquire title to property under this section, the museum shall first send a notice by certified mail to the lender's latest address if the museum has an address for the lender. The notice must include</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-57-200__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a statement that the loan is terminated;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-57-200__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a brief and general description of the property;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-57-200__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the date or approximate date, if known, when the owner loaned the property to the museum;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-57-200__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name, address, and telephone number of the museum representative to contact for more information or to make a claim;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-57-200__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the lender's name and latest address; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-57-200__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a statement that outlines the schedule and requirements for the museum to acquire title under this section.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-57-200__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a valid claim is not received by the museum within 30 days from the date the notice was mailed under (b) of this section or if the museum does not have an address for the lender, the museum shall publish a notice at least once a week for four consecutive weeks in a newspaper of general circulation in the judicial district where the museum is located and, if the museum has an address for the lender, in</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-57-200__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the judicial district in which the lender's latest address is located if the address is in this state; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-57-200__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the county, borough, or other geographical organizational entity of the jurisdiction in which the lender's latest address is located if the address is in a jurisdiction other than this state.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-57-200__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The notice published under (c) of this section must contain</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-57-200__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the information required for the notice in (b)(1)  (5) of this section;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-57-200__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the date of the last publication of the notice under (c) of this section; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-57-200__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a statement that the museum will acquire title to the loaned property if a valid claim to the property is not received by the museum within 45 days from the date of the last publication of the notice under (c) of this section.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-57-200__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The museum acquires the title to the property, subject to reclamation of the property under
AS 14.57.220
, as of the 46th day after the date of the last publication of the notice under (c) of this section, if the requirements of (a)  (d) of this section are satisfied and if a valid claim to the loaned property is not received by the museum within 45 days after the date of the last publication of the notice under (c) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-57-200__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, address means a description of the location of the lender, as shown on a museum's records, that is sufficient for delivery by mail.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-57-210">
            <num>14.57.210</num>
            <heading>Acquisition of title to undocumented property.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-57-210__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A museum may acquire title to undocumented property held by a museum for seven years or longer if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-57-210__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the seven-year holding period is verified by the written records of the museum;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-57-210__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>when this paragraph is applicable, the museum has notified by mail all corporations, except nonprofit corporations, created under 43 U.S.C. 1601 et seq. (Alaska Native Claims Settlement Act) that the undocumented property appears to be a Native artifact, that the corporations are requested to view, identify, and catalog the property within one year after the notification, and that the museum may take steps to acquire title to the property after the one-year notification period and the seven-year holding period have expired without a person filing a claim with the museum that the person is the owner of the property; in this paragraph, the periods may run concurrently; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-57-210__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>during the seven-year holding period, or the longer period if expanded by the application of (2) of this subsection, a person has not filed a claim with the museum that the person is the owner of the property.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-57-210__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To acquire title under (a) of this section, the museum shall publish a notice at least once a week for four consecutive weeks in a newspaper of general circulation in the judicial district where the museum is located. The notice must include</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="14-57-210__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a brief and general description of the property;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-57-210__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the date or approximate date, if known, of the acquisition of the property by the museum;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-57-210__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the name, address, and telephone number of the museum representative to contact for more information or to make a claim of ownership;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-57-210__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the date of the last publication of the notice under this subsection; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="14-57-210__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a statement that the museum will acquire title to the property if a valid claim of an owner to the property is not received by the museum within 45 days from the date of the last publication of the notice under this subsection.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-57-210__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The museum acquires the title to the undocumented property, subject to reclamation of the property under
AS 14.57.220
, as of the 46th day after the date of the last publication of the notice under (b) of this section if the requirements of (a) and (b) of this section are satisfied and if a valid claim of an owner to the property is not received by the museum within 45 days after the date of the last publication of the notice under (b) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-57-220">
            <num>14.57.220</num>
            <heading>Reclamation of property.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.57.220.   Reclamation of property.
In addition to any other right of reclamation the person may have under 25 U.S.C. 3001  3013 (Native American Graves Protection and Repatriation Act), after title to documented property or undocumented property is acquired by a museum under
AS 14.57.200
 14.57.290, the lender or owner of the property has two years to bring an action in court against the museum to claim the property. If an action is not brought by the end of this two-year period and if the museum has taken its action under
AS 14.57.200
 14.57.290 in good faith, a person does not have a claim to the property against the museum, the museum's employees, or the museum's agents.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-57-230">
            <num>14.57.230</num>
            <heading>Museum obligations regarding loaned property.</heading>
            <subsection eId="14-57-230__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A museum shall keep written records regarding loaned property for at least two years from the date of acquiring title to the property under
AS 14.57.200
or 14.57.210.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-57-230__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A museum shall keep written records on all property it acquires by loan. The records must contain the owner's name, address, and the telephone number, the duration of the loan, and the beginning date of the loan period.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-57-230__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A museum is responsible for notifying a lender of the museum's change of location or elimination.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="14-57-230__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>At the time the museum enters into the loan, the museum shall inform the lender of the requirements of
AS 14.57.200
 14.57.290.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-57-240">
            <num>14.57.240</num>
            <heading>Obligation of lenders.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.57.240.   Obligation of lenders.
A lender shall notify the museum of a change of address or a change in the ownership of the loaned property in order to ensure the retention of rights to the loaned property.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-57-250">
            <num>14.57.250</num>
            <heading>Relationship to other laws.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.57.250.   Relationship to other laws.
If
AS 14.57.200
 14.57.290 conflict with another provision of state law,
AS 14.57.200
 14.57.290 govern to the extent of the conflict.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_14-57-290">
            <num>14.57.290</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 14.57.290.   Definitions.
In
AS 14.57.200
 14.57.290, unless the context indicates otherwise,
(1) documented property means property in the possession of a museum for which the museum has a reasonable means of determining the owner;
(2) lender means a person whose name appears on the records of a museum as the person legally entitled to the property held by the museum;
(3) loan or loaned means a deposit with or deposited with a museum if title to the property is not transferred to the museum or if the agreement for the deposit does not include a provision that the museum acquires title at some time after the deposit is made or an option for the museum to acquire title at some time after the deposit is made;
(4) museum means an organized and permanent public institution, including a historical society, historical park, historical site, and historical monument, that is primarily educational, scientific, historical, artistic, or cultural in purpose and that owns, borrows, cares for, studies, archives, or exhibits property;
(5) property means tangible animate or inanimate objects under a museum's care that have intrinsic educational, scientific, historical, artistic, aesthetic, or cultural value;
(6) undocumented property means property in the possession of a museum for which the museum does not have a reasonable means of determining the owner.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>