<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-5/chapter-10"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-5/chapter-10"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="5.10"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-5/chapter-10/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-5/chapter-10/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-5/chapter-10/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-5/chapter-10/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_5">
        <num>5</num>
        <heading>Amusements and Sports</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_5__chp_10">
          <num>10</num>
          <heading>Boxing and Wrestling</heading>
          <section eId="sec_05-10-010">
            <num>05.10.010</num>
            <heading>Licenses for boxing and wrestling matches.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 05.10.010.   Licenses for boxing and wrestling matches.
The athletic commission may issue, and for cause revoke, a license to conduct boxing contests, sparring or wrestling matches, or exhibitions as provided in this chapter under terms and conditions and at times and places as the commission may determine. The holder of a license may conduct boxing contests, sparring and wrestling matches, and exhibitions under terms and conditions and at times and places as the commission may determine.  If the commission refuses to grant a license to an applicant, or cancels a license, the applicant, or the holder of the cancelled license may, upon application, have a hearing under the provisions of
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act).</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_05-10-020">
            <num>05.10.020</num>
            <heading>Power of commission.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 05.10.020.   Power of commission.
The commission shall direct, supervise, and control all boxing contests, or sparring and wrestling matches or exhibitions conducted inside the state, and a boxing contest, sparring or wrestling match or exhibition may not be held inside the state except in accordance with the provisions of this chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_05-10-030">
            <num>05.10.030</num>
            <heading>License for contest, match, or exhibition where admission fee is charged; exemption.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 05.10.030.   License for contest, match, or exhibition where admission fee is charged; exemption.
The commission may issue, and for cause revoke, a license to conduct, hold, or give boxing, sparring and wrestling contests, matches, and exhibitions where an admission fee is charged by a club, corporation, organization, association, or fraternal society.  However, boxing contests, sparring or wrestling matches or exhibitions conducted by an elementary school, high school, college, or university, whether public or private, or by the official student association thereof, whether on or off the school, college, or university grounds, where all the participating contestants are bona fide students enrolled in an elementary school, high school, college, or university, inside the state, are not subject to this chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_05-10-040">
            <num>05.10.040</num>
            <heading>Examination of participants in unlicensed contests.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 05.10.040.   Examination of participants in unlicensed contests.
Every contestant in a boxing contest, sparring or wrestling match not conducted under this chapter shall be examined within eight hours before the contest by a practicing physician.  The examining physician may disqualify any contestant the physician considers physically unfit to participate.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_05-10-050">
            <num>05.10.050</num>
            <heading>Regulations applicable to educational institutions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 05.10.050.   Regulations applicable to educational institutions.
The scholastic organizations exempted from the provisions of this chapter shall comply with the regulations of the commission applicable to boxing contests, sparring or wrestling matches, or exhibitions conducted by it.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_05-10-060">
            <num>05.10.060</num>
            <heading>License required.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 05.10.060.   License required.
Except as provided in this chapter, a boxing contest, sparring or wrestling match or exhibition may not be conducted inside the state except under a license issued in accordance with this chapter and the regulations of the commission.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_05-10-070">
            <num>05.10.070</num>
            <heading>Application for license.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 05.10.070.   Application for license.
A club, corporation, organization, association, or fraternal society affected by this chapter may apply to the commission for a license.  An application must be in writing and upon a form prescribed by the commission and must be verified in the manner the commission requires and accompanied by an annual license fee of $100.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_05-10-080">
            <num>05.10.080</num>
            <heading>Duration of license.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 05.10.080.   Duration of license.
The licenses provided for in
AS 05.10.070
and 05.10.120 shall be issued for a six-month or 12-month period and shall expire on June 30 and December 31 of each year.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_05-10-090">
            <num>05.10.090</num>
            <heading>Licensee bond.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 05.10.090.   Licensee bond.
A licensee shall file a good and sufficient bond in the sum of $1,000 with the commission in cities of fewer than 10,000 inhabitants and a good and sufficient bond in the sum of $2,500 in cities of more than 10,000 inhabitants.  The bond must be conditioned for the faithful performance by the licensee of the provisions of this chapter, the payment of the taxes as provided for in this chapter, and the obeying of all regulations of the commission.  The bond is subject to the approval of the attorney general.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_05-10-100">
            <num>05.10.100</num>
            <heading>Statement and report of contest.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 05.10.100.   Statement and report of contest.
A licensee shall, within three days before the holding of a boxing contest, sparring or wrestling match, or exhibition, file with the commission a statement setting forth the name of each contestant, the contestant's manager, and other information the commission requires.  One week after the completion of the contest, the licensee shall file with the Department of Revenue and the commission a written verified report, showing the number of tickets sold for the contest, the price charged for them and the gross proceeds from the sale, and other information the commission requires.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_05-10-110">
            <num>05.10.110</num>
            <heading>Inspectors.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 05.10.110.   Inspectors.
The commission may appoint official inspectors.  In the absence of a member of the commission, at least one inspector shall be present at any boxing contest, sparring or wrestling match, or exhibition held under this chapter. An inspector shall carry a card signed by the chairman of the commission evidencing the inspector's authority. The inspector shall see that all regulations of the commission and the provisions of this chapter are strictly complied with and shall be present at the accounting of the gross receipts of the contest.  An inspector may receive from the licensee the statement of receipts provided for in this chapter and shall immediately transmit the statement to the commission and to the Department of Revenue.  An inspector is entitled to a fee not exceeding $7.50 for each contest officially attended.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_05-10-120">
            <num>05.10.120</num>
            <heading>Annual licenses to participants; fees; exemptions; designation of referee.</heading>
            <subsection eId="05-10-120__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission may grant annual licenses upon application in compliance with the regulations adopted by the commission and the payment of the fees prescribed for managers, referees, examining physicians, boxers, wrestlers, seconds, and trainers.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="05-10-120__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The following is the schedule of annual fees:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="05-10-120__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>examining physicians, $10;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="05-10-120__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>managers, $50;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="05-10-120__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>referees, $10;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="05-10-120__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>seconds, $10;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="05-10-120__subsec_b__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>trainers, $10;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="05-10-120__subsec_b__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>boxers, $10;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="05-10-120__subsec_b__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>wrestlers, $10.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="05-10-120__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This section does not apply to contestants or participants in strictly amateur contests or fraternal organizations or veterans' organizations chartered by congress or a federal department or a bona fide athletic club holding and promoting athletic contests or smokers where all funds are used primarily for the benefit of their members.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="05-10-120__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The annual license may be revoked by the commission for cause under
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="05-10-120__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commission shall designate the referee for the contest from among licensed referees.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="05-10-120__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person may not participate or serve in any of the above capacities unless licensed as provided in this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_05-10-130">
            <num>05.10.130</num>
            <heading>Participation in purse or conducting sham contest.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 05.10.130.   Participation in purse or conducting sham contest.
A person or a member of any group of persons or corporation promoting wrestling or boxing exhibitions or contests who participates directly or indirectly in the purse or fee of a manager of a boxer or wrestler or a boxer or a wrestler, and a licensee who conducts or participates in any sham or fake boxing contest or sparring match or exhibition, forfeits the license granted under this chapter and the commission shall declare the license cancelled and void and the licensee may not thereafter receive another license.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_05-10-140">
            <num>05.10.140</num>
            <heading>Suspensions for violations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 05.10.140.   Suspensions for violations.
A contestant who participates in a sham or fake boxing contest or sparring match or exhibition or who violates a regulation of the commission shall be penalized as follows:
(1) for the first offense the contestant shall be restrained by order of the commission for a period of at least three months from participating in a contest held under the provisions of this chapter, with the suspension taking effect immediately after the occurrence of the offense;
(2) for a second offense the contestant shall be permanently suspended from participation in a contest held under the provisions of this chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_05-10-150">
            <num>05.10.150</num>
            <heading>Failure to make reports.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 05.10.150.   Failure to make reports.
Whenever a licensee fails to make a report of a contest within the time prescribed by this chapter or when the report is unsatisfactory to the commission or to the Department of Revenue, the secretary shall examine the books and records of the licensee.  The secretary may subpoena and examine under oath the licensee and any other person the secretary considers necessary to a determination of the total gross receipts from a contest and the amount of tax on the receipts.  If, upon the completion of the examination, it is determined that an additional tax is due, notice shall be served upon the licensee, and, upon failure to pay the additional tax within 20 days after service of the notice, the licensee forfeits the license and is permanently disqualified from receiving a new license.  In addition the licensee and the members thereof are jointly and severally liable to the state in the penal sum of $1,000.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_05-10-160">
            <num>05.10.160</num>
            <heading>Penalty for conducting contests or exhibitions without license.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 05.10.160.   Penalty for conducting contests or exhibitions without license.
A person, club, corporation, organization, association, or fraternal society conducting boxing, sparring, or wrestling contests or exhibitions without a license is guilty of a misdemeanor.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_05-10-170">
            <num>05.10.170</num>
            <heading>General penalty.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 05.10.170.   General penalty.
A person violating a provision of this chapter for which no penalty is provided in this chapter is guilty of a misdemeanor.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>