<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-2/chapter-35"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-2/chapter-35"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="2.35"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-2/chapter-35/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-2/chapter-35/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-2/chapter-35/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-2/chapter-35/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_2">
        <num>2</num>
        <heading>Aeronautics</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_2__chp_35">
          <num>35</num>
          <heading>Uniform Air Licensing Act</heading>
          <section eId="sec_02-35-090">
            <num>02.35.090</num>
            <heading>License and permit to be exhibited on request.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 02.35.090.   License and permit to be exhibited on request.
A certificate, permit, rating, or license required for an airman by the federal government shall be kept in the person's personal possession when the person is operating in the state and shall be presented for inspection upon the demand of a peace officer or another officer of the state or of a municipality, or a member, official, or employee of the department or an official, manager, or person in charge of an airport upon which the airman lands, or upon the reasonable request of any other person. A certificate, permit, or license required by the federal government for an aircraft shall be carried in the aircraft at all times while the aircraft is operating in the state. It shall be conspicuously posted in the aircraft where it may be readily seen by passengers or inspectors, and shall be presented for inspection upon the demand of a peace officer or another officer of the state or of a municipality, or a member, official, or employee of the department, or an official, manager, or person in charge of an airport upon which the aircraft lands, or upon the reasonable request of any person.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-35-110">
            <num>02.35.110</num>
            <heading>Emergency rations and equipment.</heading>
            <subsection eId="02-35-110__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An airman may not make a flight inside the state with an aircraft unless emergency equipment is carried as follows:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="02-35-110__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the following minimum equipment must be carried during the summer months:
(A) rations for each occupant sufficient to sustain life for one week;
(B) one axe or hatchet;
(C) one first aid kit;
(D) an assortment of tackle such as hooks, flies, lines, and sinkers;
(E) one knife;
(F) fire starter;
(G) one mosquito headnet for each occupant;
(H) two small signalling devices such as colored smoke bombs, railroad fuses, or Very pistol shells, in sealed metal containers;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="02-35-110__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in addition to the equipment required under (1) of this subsection, the following must be carried as minimum equipment from October 15 to April 1 of each year:
(A) one pair of snowshoes;
(B) one sleeping bag;
(C) one wool blanket or equivalent for each occupant over four.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="02-35-110__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding (a) of this section, operators of multi-engine aircraft licensed to carry more than 15 passengers need carry only the food, mosquito nets, and signalling equipment at all times other than the period from October 15 to April 1 of each year, when two sleeping bags, and one blanket for every two passengers shall also be carried.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="02-35-110__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>All of the above requirements as to emergency rations and equipment are considered to be minimum requirements which are to remain in full force and effect, except as further safety measures may be from time to time imposed by the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-35-120">
            <num>02.35.120</num>
            <heading>Penalties for lack of license or permit or violation of regulations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 02.35.120.   Penalties for lack of license or permit or violation of regulations.
A person who acts as an airman for a civil aircraft when flown or operated in this state without holding an existing airman's license or permit issued in accordance with federal law, who flies or causes to be flown in this state any civil aircraft without an existing license or permit for that aircraft issued in accordance with federal law, or who violates a provision of a regulation adopted under this chapter is punishable by a fine of not more than $500 or by imprisonment for not more than six months or by both.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-35-130">
            <num>02.35.130</num>
            <heading>Penalty for violation ofAS 02.35.090and 02.35.110.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 02.35.130.   Penalty for violation of
AS 02.35.090
and 02.35.110.
A person violating a provision of
AS 02.35.090
and 02.35.110 is guilty of a misdemeanor and upon conviction is punishable by a fine of not more than $500.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-35-150">
            <num>02.35.150</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 02.35.150.   Definitions.
In this chapter,
(1) commissioner means the commissioner of transportation and public facilities;
(2) department means the Department of Transportation and Public Facilities.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-35-160">
            <num>02.35.160</num>
            <heading>Short title.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 02.35.160.   Short title.
This chapter may be cited as the Uniform Air Licensing Act.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>