<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-2/chapter-15"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-2/chapter-15"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="2.15"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-2/chapter-15/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-2/chapter-15/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-2/chapter-15/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-2/chapter-15/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_2">
        <num>2</num>
        <heading>Aeronautics</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_2__chp_15">
          <num>15</num>
          <heading>Alaska Aeronautics Act of 1949</heading>
          <section eId="sec_02-15-010">
            <num>02.15.010</num>
            <heading>Purpose.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 02.15.010.   Purpose.
The purpose of this chapter is to encourage and develop aeronautics and the establishment and operation of a state system of airports through cooperation with municipalities, and otherwise, including cooperation with the federal government and acceptance and utilization of federal funds allotted for this purpose.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-15-020">
            <num>02.15.020</num>
            <heading>Powers of department.</heading>
            <subsection eId="02-15-020__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may perform acts, issue and amend orders, adopt reasonable general or special regulations and procedures, and establish minimum standards, consistent with the provisions of this chapter, as it considers necessary to carry out the provisions of this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="02-15-020__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may enter into contracts necessary or advisable to the execution of the powers granted it by this chapter. Where the planning, acquisition, construction, improvement, maintenance, or operation of an airport or air navigation facility is financed wholly or partially with federal money, the department, as agent of the state, or of a municipality, or person, may let contracts in the manner prescribed by the federal authorities acting under the laws and rules and regulations of the United States.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="02-15-020__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may accept federal money and money from other public or private sources to accomplish in whole or in part any of the purposes of this chapter. All federal money accepted under this chapter shall be accepted and expended by the department upon the terms and conditions prescribed by the United States.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-15-030">
            <num>02.15.030</num>
            <heading>Conformity to federal law.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 02.15.030.   Conformity to federal law.
The department may not adopt a regulation, order, or standard that is inconsistent or contrary to any act of the Congress of the United States or regulations promulgated or standards established. A regulation, order, or standard may not be adopted that duplicates any current rules or regulations issued by a federal agency, or that applies to aircraft, airports, or air navigation facilities owned or operated by the federal government.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-15-040">
            <num>02.15.040</num>
            <heading>Cooperation with federal agencies.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 02.15.040.   Cooperation with federal agencies.
The department shall cooperate with the Federal Emergency Management Agency, the armed forces of the United States government, and the Federal Aviation Administration for the purpose of coordinating aviation activities in carrying out the civil defense program.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-15-050">
            <num>02.15.050</num>
            <heading>Miscellaneous powers and duties of department.</heading>
            <subsection eId="02-15-050__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may confer with and hold joint hearings with agencies of the United States in connection with matters arising under this chapter or relating to the sound development of aeronautics.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="02-15-050__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may avail itself of the cooperation, services, records, and facilities of the agencies of the United States as fully as may be practicable in the administration and enforcement of this chapter. The department shall, upon request, furnish to the agencies of the United States its cooperation, services, records, and facilities, insofar as may be practicable.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="02-15-050__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department or a state or municipal police officer shall report to the appropriate agency of the United States all accidents in aeronautics in this state of which it or the police officer is informed, and shall, insofar as practicable, preserve, protect, and prevent the removal of the component parts of an aircraft involved in an accident being investigated until the federal agency institutes an investigation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="02-15-050__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 14 ch 56 SLA 2001.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="02-15-050__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may report to the appropriate federal agencies and agencies of states proceedings instituted charging violation of any sections of this chapter and penalties, of which it has knowledge, imposed upon an airman or the owner or operator of an aircraft for violation of the law of this state relating to aeronautics, or for violation of the regulations or orders of the department. The department may receive reports of penalties and other data from agencies of the federal government and states and, when necessary, enter into agreements with federal agencies and the agencies of states governing the delivery, receipt, exchange, and use of reports and data. The department may make the reports and data available to a court of this state and to a state or municipal officer authorized to enforce the aeronautics laws.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="02-15-050__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may draft and recommend suitable legislation to advance the interests of the state in aeronautics; represent the state in aeronautical matters before the federal agencies and other state agencies; and participate as party plaintiff or defendant on behalf of the state or as intervenor in a controversy that involves the interests of the state in aeronautics.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="02-15-050__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may acquire data on passenger enplanements from air carriers; however, the department may not obtain passenger manifests from air carriers except for matters concerning public safety.
Article 2. State Airports.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-15-060">
            <num>02.15.060</num>
            <heading>Establishment, operation, and maintenance.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 02.15.060.   Establishment, operation, and maintenance.
The department may plan, establish, construct, enlarge, improve, maintain, equip, operate, regulate, protect, and police airports and air navigation facilities within the state.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-15-070">
            <num>02.15.070</num>
            <heading>Acquisition and disposal of property.</heading>
            <subsection eId="02-15-070__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For the purposes specified in
AS 02.15.060
the department may, by purchase, gift, devise, lease, condemnation, or otherwise, acquire real or personal property, or any interest in the property including easements in airport hazards or land outside the boundaries of an airport or airport site, necessary to permit the removal, elimination, obstruction-marking, or obstruction-lighting of airport hazards, or to prevent the establishment of airport hazards. The department may acquire existing airports and air navigation facilities in the same manner except it may not acquire or take over an airport or air navigation facility owned or controlled by a municipality or person without the consent of the municipality or person.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="02-15-070__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may, by sale, lease, or otherwise, dispose of all, a portion of, or an interest in a property, airport, or air navigation facility described in (a) of this section. The proceeds of any disposition shall be used for the purposes set out in this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-15-080">
            <num>02.15.080</num>
            <heading>Joint operations.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 02.15.080.   Joint operations.
The department may exercise the powers granted by
AS 02.15.060
 02.15.100 jointly with a person, municipality, or agency of the state, or with the United States.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-15-090">
            <num>02.15.090</num>
            <heading>Operation and use privileges; fees and charges.</heading>
            <subsection eId="02-15-090__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In operating an airport or air navigation facility owned or controlled by the state, the department may enter into contracts, leases, and other arrangements covering periods not exceeding 55 years with a person, municipality, or the United States, granting the privilege of using or improving an airport or air navigation facility or a portion of it or space in it for commercial, governmental, or other public purposes, including private plane tie down, or conferring the privilege of supplying goods, commodities, services, or facilities at an airport or air navigation facility. The department may establish the terms and conditions and fix the charges, rentals, and fees for the privileges or services that are reasonable and uniform for the same class of privilege or service. Charges, rentals, or fees authorized by this subsection may be fixed for the international airports by order of the commissioner or by negotiated or competitively offered contract. Notwithstanding
AS 37.10.050
(a), the fixing of charges, rentals, or fees as permitted under this subsection is not subject to the adoption of regulation provisions of
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act). The terms, conditions, charges, rentals, and fees shall be established with due regard to the property and improvements used and the expense of operation to the state. A charge, rental, or fee imposed on a person who is not a lessee or concessionaire of the airport may not have the effect of charging a percentage of the gross revenue of the person as a condition of on-site access to customers who use the airport facility unless the charge, rental, or fee was in existence before January 1, 2006, and this exception is not affected if the department amends, increases, or decreases a charge, rental, or fee that was in effect before January 1, 2006. Use of state land and buildings by the Alaska Wing, Civil Air Patrol and its squadrons shall be permitted without rental charges. If the department permits space in state-owne</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="02-15-090__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may by contract or other arrangement, upon a consideration fixed by it, grant to a qualified municipality or person for a reasonable period of time the privilege of operating, as agent of the state or otherwise, an airport owned or controlled by the state. A municipality or person granted that privilege may not operate the airport other than as a public airport or enter into a contract, lease, or other arrangement in connection with the operation that the department may not have undertaken under (a) or (c)  (e) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="02-15-090__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding the right of the public to rightful, equal, and uniform use under (a) of this section, before the expiration of a land lease, including the termination of a lease in holdover status, entered into under this section, the lessee may apply for a new lease, or for an extended term under the existing lease, for the same land. The commissioner shall approve the application for a new land lease or an extended term under this section without offering the land to other persons for leasing if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="02-15-090__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the lessee is in compliance with the terms and conditions of the existing or holdover lease; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="02-15-090__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the continued use of the leasehold is consistent with written airport operation policies and is in the state's best interest.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="02-15-090__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A land lessee owns title to the permanent improvements that the lessee constructed or purchased during the term of the lease, unless the lease expressly provides that the state is the owner of the permanent improvements.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="02-15-090__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>At the expiration, termination, or cancellation of a land lease entered into under this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="02-15-090__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a lessee who owns the improvements under (d) of this section shall continue to own the permanent improvements that the lessee constructed or purchased on a leasehold if the lessee is granted under (c) of this section a new lease or an extended term for the same land;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="02-15-090__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a lessee may sell the permanent improvements owned by the lessee to a succeeding lessee of the same land;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="02-15-090__subsec_e__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>at the option of the lessee, the permanent improvements owned by the lessee may be sold by the state at public auction with the proceeds from the sale of the improvements going to the lessee, less administrative costs of the auction and obligations owed under the lease to the state; the successful bidder has the same right to enter into a new lease under (c) of this section without the department offering the land to other persons for leasing;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="02-15-090__subsec_e__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>after notice by the department, the permanent improvements owned by the lessee shall be removed at the lessee's sole expense if
(A) the permanent improvements do not comply with written airport operational policies or are not in the state's best interest;
(B) the permanent improvements are not sold under (2) or (3) of this subsection; or
(C) the department makes written findings that the permanent improvements are a hazard to the public health and safety;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="02-15-090__subsec_e__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>title to the permanent improvements vests in the department if the state purchases or otherwise contracts for the ownership of the permanent improvements, or if the lessee abandons the permanent improvements.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="02-15-090__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall require as a term of all aviation-related contracts, leases, and other arrangements for use or occupancy of an airport operated by the department, including the international airports, that the parties to the contract, lease, or other arrangement, including the department, shall be required to reimburse each other according to the principles of comparative fault for amounts paid others for personal injury and property damage. The apportionment of liability among the parties to an agreement under this subsection may not affect the rights of persons who are not parties to the agreement.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="02-15-090__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the department determines that it is in the best interests of the state to require that persons holding aviation-related leases, permits, or concession contracts for use or occupancy of an airport operated by the department, including international airports, provide insurance coverage, the department shall develop and adopt by regulation guidelines for the types and limits of insurance coverage required for aviation-related leases, permits, or concession contracts. The department may authorize a variation from the coverage required by the regulation if the department finds in writing that the variation is necessary considering the best interests of the state and the unique circumstances underlying a specific aviation-related lease, permit, or concession contract.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="02-15-090__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For the privilege of occupying or using a state-owned facility on an airport, which facility is or will be acquired, constructed, equipped, installed, or improved with the proceeds of indebtedness, the payment of which, with approval of the commissioner, is or will be secured solely by proceeds from customer facility charges, the department may require all persons under contract to occupy or use all or a portion of the planned facility, and shall require occupants or users of all or a portion of the facility, to collect from their customers a uniform customer facility charge and remit the proceeds to (1) the department if the state on behalf of the department incurred the indebtedness; or (2) a trustee or another third party bound to use the proceeds for the principal, interest, reserves, and any other applicable requirements of the indebtedness documentation if the state on behalf of the department did not incur the indebtedness. The commissioner shall set the customer facility charge at an amount projected to generate proceeds sufficient to satisfy all requirements established by the indebtedness documentation, including payment of principal and interest on the indebtedness, maintenance of any reserves, and satisfaction of any other requirement of the indebtedness documentation. The commissioner shall periodically adjust the amount of the customer facility charge to reflect changes in the amounts necessary to pay the principal of and interest on the indebtedness, to maintain any required reserves, and to satisfy all other requirements established by the indebtedness documentation and to reflect changes in the number of occupants, users, or customers of the facility. The proceeds of the customer facility charge are not revenue of the state securing any other indebtedness. The commissioner may impose charges authorized by this subsection for the international airports by order or by negotiated or competitively offered contract. The department shall provide for publi</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="02-15-090__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In addition to requiring collection of a customer facility charge to be applied as described in (h) of this section, the department may require occupants or users of, or persons under contract to occupy or use, all or a portion of a state-owned facility on an airport, which facility is or will be acquired, constructed, equipped, installed, or improved with the proceeds of indebtedness, the payment of which is secured solely by proceeds of a customer facility charge, to collect from their customers a uniform customer facility maintenance charge and to remit the proceeds to (1) the department if the state on behalf of the department incurred the indebtedness; or (2) a trustee or another third party if the state on behalf of the department did not incur the indebtedness. The commissioner shall set the customer facility maintenance charge at an amount projected to generate proceeds sufficient to pay some or all, as determined by the commissioner, of the costs, fees, and expenses required to operate and maintain the facility, including costs of insurance and maintenance of reserves for the facility. The commissioner shall periodically adjust the amount of the customer facility maintenance charge to reflect changes in costs, fees, and expenses to operate and maintain the facility, including costs of insurance and maintenance of reserves for the facility and to reflect changes in the number of occupants, users, or customers of the facility. If the proceeds of the customer facility maintenance charge are remitted to a trustee or another third party as set out in this subsection, the proceeds of the customer facility maintenance charge are not, unless otherwise contractually required, revenue of the state securing any indebtedness. The commissioner may impose charges authorized by this subsection for the international airports by order or by negotiated or competitively offered contract. The department shall provide for public notice and an opportunity to comment before a cha</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-15-091">
            <num>02.15.091</num>
            <heading>Sale and delivery of in-bond merchandise at international airports.</heading>
            <subsection eId="02-15-091__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Under (b) and (c) of this section, the department shall allow the sale and delivery of in-bond merchandise at an international airport only by an exclusive contract.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="02-15-091__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>While the exclusive contracts for the sale and delivery of in-bond merchandise at international airports that exist on June 15, 1982 are in effect, the department may not permit or confer a right on any other person to offer to sell, sell, or deliver in-bond merchandise at an international airport.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="02-15-091__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After the exclusive contracts existing on June 15, 1982 are no longer in effect, the department shall enter into one exclusive contract and, on its expiration, additional successive exclusive contracts for the sale and delivery of in-bond merchandise at each international airport.  Except under the existing and future exclusive contracts described in this section, the department may not permit or confer a right upon any person to offer to sell, sell, or deliver in-bond merchandise at an international airport.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="02-15-091__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall offer the exclusive contracts required by this section by competitive bid or by competitive proposals. If the department offers the exclusive contracts by competitive bid, the department shall award the contracts after considering the generation of maximum revenue for the International Airports Revenue Fund established by
AS 37.15.430
. If the department offers the exclusive contracts by competitive proposals, the department shall award the contracts after considering factors that include depth of management, financial ability, demonstrated experience at other locations, quality of services and products, success in marketing programs, character and improvements of proposed facilities, and the generation of optimum revenue for the fund.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="02-15-091__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall actively supervise the operations under each exclusive contract for the sale and delivery of in-bond merchandise in order to ensure the effectiveness of the operations.  To supervise contract operations under this section, the department shall develop and implement guidelines that provide for review of the reasonableness of price schedules, quality and assortment of merchandise, and customer service.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="02-15-091__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing in this section applies to deliveries of in-bond merchandise as cargo to airlines.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-15-095">
            <num>02.15.095</num>
            <heading>Courtesy cars and airport parking shuttles.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 02.15.095.   Courtesy cars and airport parking shuttles.
Notwithstanding the provisions of
AS 02.15.090
(a), the department may not exclude from the streets, roads, highways, parking facilities, or other portions of a state-operated airport designated for operation or parking of ground transportation vehicles, nor may the department prohibit from picking up and discharging passengers those motor vehicles commonly known as courtesy cars, which are owned or operated by hotels, motels, or other similar places of public accommodation for the transportation of their guests to and from the airport at the request of the guest and for which service no charge is made to the guest, and airport parking shuttles, which provide transportation services between the airport and off-airport rental car offices and remote vehicle parking locations.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-15-100">
            <num>02.15.100</num>
            <heading>Liens.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 02.15.100.   Liens.
The department may enforce the payment of any charges for repairs, improvements, storage, or care of personal property made or furnished by the department or its agents, in connection with the operation of an airport or air navigation facility owned or operated by the state. The state has those lien rights generally allowed by law to secure payment for those services.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-15-102">
            <num>02.15.102</num>
            <heading>Use of airports for utilities.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 02.15.102.   Use of airports for utilities.
A utility facility may be constructed, placed, or maintained across, along, over, under, or within a state airport only in accordance with regulations adopted or procedures prescribed by the department and only if authorized by a written permit issued by the department.  The department may charge a fee for a permit issued under this section.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-15-104">
            <num>02.15.104</num>
            <heading>Relocation of utility facilities incident to airport projects.</heading>
            <subsection eId="02-15-104__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If, incident to the construction of an airport project, the department determines and orders that a utility facility located across, along, over, under, or within a state airport must be changed, relocated, or removed, the utility owning or maintaining the facility shall change, relocate, or remove it in accordance with the order, within a reasonable time set by the department in the order.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="02-15-104__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the utility facility is not changed, relocated, or removed in accordance with the order, a permit authorizing the facility issued by the department under
AS 02.15.102
becomes invalid and the facility will be considered an unauthorized encroachment subject to the provisions of
AS 02.15.114
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="02-15-104__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The cost of change, relocation, or removal, as defined in
AS 02.15.260
, ordered under (a) of this section is to be paid as follows:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="02-15-104__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>by the department as a cost of airport construction, if the utility facility is installed or authorized after June 11, 1986 under a utility permit or a regulation and is installed in the location specified in the permit;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="02-15-104__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>by the department as a cost of airport construction, if the facility was installed before June 11, 1986 under a utility permit or utility easement and is in the location specified in the permit or easement;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="02-15-104__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>by the department as a cost of airport construction, if the utility facility was installed before the location became part of a state airport or before permits were required;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="02-15-104__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>by the department as a cost of airport construction, if the utility permit that requires the utility to pay the relocation cost was issued more than five years before the contract for the airport construction project was first advertised;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="02-15-104__subsec_c__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>by the utility in all other cases unless the commissioner finds it is in the public interest for the cost to be paid by the department.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-15-106">
            <num>02.15.106</num>
            <heading>Encroachment permits.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 02.15.106.   Encroachment permits.
An encroachment may be constructed, placed, changed, or maintained across or within an airport, but only in accordance with regulations or procedures adopted by the department.  An encroachment may not be constructed, placed, maintained, or changed until it is authorized by a written permit issued by the department, unless the department provides otherwise by regulation.  The department may charge a fee for a permit issued under this section.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-15-108">
            <num>02.15.108</num>
            <heading>Relocation or removal of encroachment.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 02.15.108.   Relocation or removal of encroachment.
If, incidental to the construction or maintenance of a state airport, the department determines and orders that an encroachment previously authorized by written permit must be changed, relocated, or removed, the owner of the encroachment shall change, relocate, or remove it within a reasonable time set by the department in the order.  The cost of the change, relocation, or removal shall be paid as provided in
AS 02.15.104
(c).  If the owner does not change, relocate, or remove an encroachment within the time set by the department, the encroachment will be considered an unauthorized encroachment subject to the provisions of
AS 02.15.114
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-15-110">
            <num>02.15.110</num>
            <heading>Unauthorized encroachments.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 02.15.110.   Unauthorized encroachments.
If an unauthorized encroachment exists in, on, under, or over a state airport the department may require the removal of the encroachment, at the expense of the owner, in the manner provided in
AS 02.15.112
 02.15.114.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-15-112">
            <num>02.15.112</num>
            <heading>Notice of removal of unauthorized encroachment.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 02.15.112.   Notice of removal of unauthorized encroachment.
Notice shall be given the owner, occupant, or person in possession of an unauthorized encroachment, or to another person causing or permitting the encroachment to exist, by serving upon any of them a notice demanding the removal of the encroachment within a time limit set by the department.  The notice must describe the encroachment with reasonable certainty as to its character and location.  Service of the notice may be made by certified mail.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-15-114">
            <num>02.15.114</num>
            <heading>Removal at owner's expense after noncompliance; removal expense.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 02.15.114.   Removal at owner's expense after noncompliance; removal expense.
After a failure of the owner of an unauthorized encroachment to comply with a notice or order of the department under
AS 02.15.104
, 02.15.108, or 02.15.112, the department may remove the encroachment, or cause it to be removed.  The owner of the unauthorized encroachment shall pay to the department
(1) the expense of the removal of the encroachment;
(2) all costs and expenses paid by the state as a result of a claim or claims filed against the state by third parties for damages due to delays because the encroachment was not changed, removed, or relocated according to the order of the department; and
(3) costs and expense of suit.
Article 4. Airport Assistance.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-15-120">
            <num>02.15.120</num>
            <heading>Assistance to construct, enlarge, or improve air navigation facilities.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 02.15.120.   Assistance to construct, enlarge, or improve air navigation facilities.
The department may match available funds with those of municipalities, federal agencies, or other state agencies, for project costs relating to the construction, enlargement, or improvement of airports.  The department may assist persons in the construction, enlargement, and improvement of airports and air navigation facilities. The airports and facilities, until they are abandoned as such, shall be at all times available for the use of and accessible to the general public, and maintained as public airports and facilities.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-15-130">
            <num>02.15.130</num>
            <heading>Assistance to the federal government, municipalities, and other persons.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 02.15.130.   Assistance to the federal government, municipalities, and other persons.
The department may make available its engineering, maintenance, and other services, with or without charge, to the federal government, or to a municipality or person in connection with the planning, acquisition, construction, improvement, maintenance, or operation of airports or air navigation facilities.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-15-140">
            <num>02.15.140</num>
            <heading>State financial assistance.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 02.15.140.   State financial assistance.
The department may grant or lend money, subject to the provisions of
AS 02.15.060
, 02.15.070, and 02.15.120, to any person or municipality or to municipalities acting jointly for project costs relating to the planning, acquisition, construction, improvement, maintenance, or operation of an airport owned or controlled or to be owned or controlled by the municipality or municipalities or person.  Grants or loans may be furnished in connection with federal or other financial aid for the same purpose.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-15-150">
            <num>02.15.150</num>
            <heading>Federal aid.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 02.15.150.   Federal aid.
A municipality may not participate under the Federal Airport Act unless the department has approved its application. The department may approve, disapprove, or modify a municipal application for direct participation under the Federal Airport Act.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-15-155">
            <num>02.15.155</num>
            <heading>Project costs defined.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 02.15.155.   Project costs defined.
In
AS 02.15.120
 02.15.155, project costs includes, in addition to costs directly related to the project, the sum total of all costs of financing and carrying out the project including, but not limited to, the costs of all necessary studies, surveys, plans and specifications, architectural, engineering, or other special services, acquisition of real property, site preparation and development, purchase, construction, reconstruction and improvement of real property and the acquisition of machinery and equipment as may be necessary in connection with the project; an allocable portion of the administrative and operating expenses of the grantee; the cost of financing the project, including interest on bonds issued to finance the project; and the cost of other items, including any indemnity and surety bonds and premiums on insurance, legal fees, fees and expenses of trustees, depositaries, financial advisors, and paying agents for the bonds issued as the issuer considers necessary.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-15-160">
            <num>02.15.160</num>
            <heading>Rural airstrip and seaplane facilities.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 02.15.160.   Rural airstrip and seaplane facilities.
The department may construct, maintain, or operate floats and seaplane ramp landing facilities, subject to the provisions of
AS 02.15.060
, 02.15.070, and 02.15.120. The department may construct, maintain, or operate emergency landing fields, or rural airstrips adequate to meet rural needs with or without financial contribution by local interests.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-15-190">
            <num>02.15.190</num>
            <heading>Collection of aeronautical data.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 02.15.190.   Collection of aeronautical data.
The department may collect, assemble, and publish aeronautical data pertinent to the operation of aircraft within the state. This data is for the benefit of the aviation industry and the general public, and may not duplicate data published by any other governmental agency.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-15-200">
            <num>02.15.200</num>
            <heading>Public nature of department activities.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 02.15.200.   Public nature of department activities.
The acquisition of land or interests in land under this chapter, the planning, acquisition, establishment, construction, improvement, maintenance, equipment, and operation of airports and air navigation facilities, whether by the state separately or jointly with any person or municipality, and the exercise of any other powers granted under this chapter to the department are public and governmental functions, exercised for a public purpose, and matters of public necessity. All land and other property and privileges acquired and used by or on behalf of the state in the manner and for the purposes enumerated in this chapter are acquired and used for public and governmental purposes and as a matter of public necessity.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-15-210">
            <num>02.15.210</num>
            <heading>Exclusive rights prohibited.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 02.15.210.   Exclusive rights prohibited.
The department may not grant an exclusive right for the use of an airway, airport, or air navigation facility under its jurisdiction.  This section does not prevent the making of contracts, leases, and other arrangements under
AS 02.15.060
  02.15.100 and 02.15.120, including exclusive contracts for the sale and delivery of in-bond merchandise described in
AS 02.15.091
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-15-220">
            <num>02.15.220</num>
            <heading>Enforcement of aeronautics laws.</heading>
            <subsection eId="02-15-220__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department and its officers and employees, and every state and municipal officer charged with the enforcement of state and municipal laws, shall enforce and assist in the enforcement of this chapter and of all regulations adopted and orders issued under it and any other state regulations or laws pertaining to the operation of aircraft.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="02-15-220__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 14 ch 56 SLA 2001.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-15-230">
            <num>02.15.230</num>
            <heading>Police powers vested.</heading>
            <subsection eId="02-15-230__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The commissioner and those officers and employees of the department whom the commissioner may designate have general police powers in aid of the enforcement of this chapter and the regulations and orders issued under it and all other laws of the state relating to aeronautics.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="02-15-230__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon bilateral agreement, the commissioner may designate individuals licensed under
AS 18.65.400
 18.65.490 and police officers employed by the state or its political subdivisions to be present during the final passenger screening process before the boarding of each flight required to be in compliance with passenger screening regulations of the Federal Aviation Administration. Persons designated under this section, while performing their duties under that agreement, have the general police powers set out in (a) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-15-240">
            <num>02.15.240</num>
            <heading>Penalties.</heading>
            <subsection eId="02-15-240__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person violating a provision of this chapter, or a provision of a regulation adopted or order issued under this chapter is guilty of a misdemeanor, and upon conviction is punishable by a fine of not more than $500, or by imprisonment of not more than 90 days, or by both.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="02-15-240__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For a violation of any section of this chapter, in addition to or in lieu of the penalties provided by (a) of this section, or as a condition to the suspension of a sentence which may be imposed, the court may prohibit the violator from operating an aircraft within the state for a period it may determine but not more than one year. Violation of the prohibition of court may be treated as a separate offense under this section or as a contempt of court.  Whenever a conviction is obtained, the prosecuting authority shall notify the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-15-260">
            <num>02.15.260</num>
            <heading>Definitions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 02.15.260.   Definitions.
In this chapter,
(1) aeronautics means the science and art of flight including but not limited to transportation by aircraft; the operation, construction, repair, or maintenance of aircraft power plants and accessories, including the repair, packing, and maintenance of parachutes; the design, establishment, construction, extension, operation, improvement, repair, or maintenance of airports or other air navigation facilities; and instruction in flying or related ground subjects;
(2) aircraft means a contrivance used or designed for navigation of flight in the air;
(3) airman means an individual engaging as the person in command or as pilot, mechanic, or member of the crew, in the navigation of aircraft while under way; an individual directly in charge of the inspection, maintenance, overhauling, or repair of aircraft, aircraft engines, propellers, or appliances; and an individual serving in the capacity of aircraft dispatcher, or air-traffic control-tower operator; or an individual employed by a manufacturer of aircraft, aircraft engines, propellers, or appliances to perform duties as inspector or mechanic in that connection; or an individual performing inspection or mechanical duties in connection with aircraft owned or operated by the individual in the state of Alaska;
(4) air navigation facility means a facility used, available, or designed for use in aid of air navigation, including structures, mechanisms, lights, beacons, markers, communicating systems, or other instrumentalities or devices used or useful as an aid, or constituting an advantage or convenience to the safe taking-off, navigation and landing of aircraft, or the safe and efficient operation or maintenance of an airport, and any combination of any or all of the facilities;
(5) airport means an area of land or water that is used or intended for use for the landing and take-off of aircraft, and any appurtenant areas that are used or intended for use for airport buildings or other airport facilities or rights-of-way, together with airport buildings and facilities located thereon;
(6) airport hazard means a structure, object of natural growth, or use of land that obstructs the airspace required for the flight of aircraft in landing or taking off at an airport or is otherwise hazardous to the landing or taking off;
(7) cargo means goods carried by an airline that are carried under an agreement between the shipper and the airline other than a passenger ticket, that are accepted, carried, and handled separately from passenger baggage, and that are delivered to a location other than a baggage claim area; cargo does not include goods carried by an airline as baggage, whether belly-loaded or hand-carried and whether accompanied or unaccompanied by a passenger;
(8) civil aircraft means any aircraft other than a public aircraft;
(9) commissioner means the commissioner of transportation and public facilities of the state;
(10) cost of change, relocation, or removal means the entire cost incurred by the utility properly attributed to the change, relocation, or removal of a facility, less the costs for improvements or upgrading over and above the cost of a functionally equal facility; if a facility is to be relocated and replaced with new equipment, there shall also be subtracted from the entire cost the salvage value derived from the old facility;
(11) department means the Department of Transportation and Public Facilities;
(12) encroachment includes a tower, pole, poleline, pipe, pipeline, driveway, private road, fence, billboard, stand, or building, or structure or object of any kind that is or has been placed in, on, under, or over a portion of an airport;
(13) international airport means an international airport owned and operated by the state;
(14) operation of aircraft means the use, navigation, or piloting of aircraft in the airspace over this state or upon an airport inside this state; operate aircraft means to use, navigate, or pilot aircraft in the airspace over this state or upon an airport inside this state;
(15) public aircraft means an aircraft used exclusively in the governmental service of the United States or the state government;
(16) utility includes a corporation, company, individual, or association of individuals, or a lessee, trustee, or court-appointed receiver, that owns, operates, manages, or controls a line, plant, pipeline, or system for furnishing, producing, generating, transmitting, or distributing power, electricity, communications, telecommunications, water, gas, oil, petroleum products, coal or other mineral slurry, steam, heat, light, chemicals, air, sewage, drainage not connected with airport drainage, irrigation, or similar products including publicly owned fire and police signal systems and street lighting systems that directly or indirectly serve the public or a segment of the public; utility also includes a corporation, company, individual, or association of individuals, or a lessee, trustee, or court-appointed receiver that owns, operates, manages, or controls a system for furnishing transportation of goods or persons by means of a railway, tramway, cableway, conveyor, flume, canal, tunnel, pipeline, or a similar means;
(17) utility facility includes poles, plants, lines, trenches, bridges, utilidors, tunnels, pipelines, and any other system for furnishing, producing, generating, transmitting, or distributing power, electricity, communications, telecommunications, water, gas, oil, petroleum products, coal or other mineral slurry, steam, heat, light, chemicals, air, sewage, drainage not connected with an airport drainage system, irrigation, or another substance; utility facility also includes a system for furnishing transportation of goods or persons by means of a railway, tramway, cableway, conveyor, flume, canal, tunnel, pipeline, or a similar means.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_02-15-270">
            <num>02.15.270</num>
            <heading>Short title.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 02.15.270.   Short title.
This chapter may be cited as the Alaska Aeronautics Act of 1949.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>