<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-02"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-02"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="8.02"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-02/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-02/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-02/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-8/chapter-02/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_8">
        <num>8</num>
        <heading>Business and Professions</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_8__chp_02">
          <num>02</num>
          <heading>Miscellaneous Provisions</heading>
          <section eId="sec_08-02-020">
            <num>08.02.020</num>
            <heading>Limitation of liability.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-02-020__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or
AS 08.64.101
(a)(5);</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-02-020__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a recommendation or action in accordance with the prescribed duties of a licensing board, peer review committee established to review a licensing matter, committee appointed under
AS 08.64.336</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-02-020__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or
AS 08.64.101
(a)(5) when the person acts in the reasonable belief that the action or recommendation is warranted by facts known to the person, board, peer review committee, committee appointed under
AS 08.64.336
(c), or contractor or agent of the contractor under
AS 08.01.050</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-02-020__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>or
AS 08.64.101
(a)(5) after reasonable efforts to ascertain the facts upon which the action or recommendation is made; or</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-02-020__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a report made in good faith to a public agency by the person, or participation by the person in an investigation by a public agency or a judicial or administrative proceeding relating to the report, if the report relates to the abuse of alcohol, other drugs, or other substances by a person licensed by a board listed in
AS 08.01.050</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-02-050">
            <num>08.02.050</num>
            <heading>Permits for use of drugs to euthanize domestic animals.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-02-050__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A qualified agency may apply to the department and obtain a permit that authorizes the purchase, possession, and use by the agency of sodium pentobarbital, sodium pentobarbital with lidocaine, and other drugs authorized in regulations adopted by the department for the purpose of euthanizing injured, sick, or abandoned domestic animals in the lawful possession of the agency. To qualify to obtain the permit, the agency shall certify that it will</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-02-050__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>comply with applicable federal laws related to the use of the drugs; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-02-050__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>not permit an employee to administer the drugs unless the employee has successfully completed a euthanasia technician certification course approved by the National Animal Control Association, the American Humane Association, or the Humane Society of the United States.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-02-050__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may revoke or suspend a permit or take another disciplinary action under
AS 08.01.075
if it determines that the agency or an employee of the agency</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-02-050__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>improperly used sodium pentobarbital, sodium pentobarbital with lidocaine, or another drug authorized for use under this section;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-02-050__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>failed to follow federal or state laws regarding proper storage and handling of the drugs;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-02-050__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>allowed an employee to administer the drugs before the employee successfully completed the certification course described in (a)(2) of this section; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-02-050__subsec_b__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>violated this title or a regulation adopted under this title.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-02-050__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, agency means an animal control agency of a municipality or recognized governmental entity or an entity that has contracted with a municipality or recognized governmental entity to perform animal control or animal euthanasia services.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-02-050__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may adopt regulations to implement this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-02-060">
            <num>08.02.060</num>
            <heading>Professional geologist.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.02.060.   Professional geologist.
The commissioner of commerce, community, and economic development shall certify an applicant as a professional geologist if the applicant is certified as a professional geologist by the American Institute of Professional Geologists.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-02-110">
            <num>08.02.110</num>
            <heading>Professional designation requirements.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-02-110__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[See delayed amendment note.]  An acupuncturist licensed under
AS 08.06
, an audiologist or speech-language pathologist licensed under
AS 08.11
, a behavior analyst licensed under
AS 08.15
, a person licensed in the state as a chiropractor under
AS 08.20
, a professional counselor licensed under
AS 08.29
, a dentist under
AS 08.36
, a dietitian or nutritionist licensed under
AS 08.38
, a massage therapist licensed under
AS 08.61
, a marital and family therapist licensed under
AS 08.63
, a medical practitioner or osteopath under
AS 08.64
, a direct-entry midwife certified under
AS 08.65
, a registered or advanced practice registered nurse under
AS 08.68
, an optometrist under
AS 08.72
, a licensed pharmacist under
AS 08.80
, a physical therapist or occupational therapist licensed under
AS 08.84
, a psychologist under
AS 08.86
, or a clinical social worker licensed under
AS 08.95
, shall use as professional identification appropriate letters or a title after that person's name that represents the person's specific field of practice. The letters or title shall appear on all signs, stationery, or other advertising in which the person offers or displays personal professional services to the public. In addition, a person engaged in the practice of medicine or osteopathy as defined in
AS 08.64.380
, or a person engaged in any manner in the healing arts who diagnoses, treats, tests, or counsels other persons in relation to human health or disease and uses the letters M.D. or the title doctor or physician or another title that tends to show that the person is willing or qualified to diagnose, treat, test, or counsel another person, shall clarify the letters or title by adding the appropriate specialist designation, if any, such as dermatologist, radiologist, audiologist, naturopath, or the like.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-02-110__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person subject to (a) of this section who fails to comply with the requirements of (a) of this section shall be given notice of noncompliance by that person's appropriate licensing board or, if the person is not regulated by a board, by the department. If, after a reasonable time, with opportunity for a hearing, the person's noncompliance continues, the board or department, as appropriate, may suspend or revoke the person's license or registration, or administer other disciplinary action which in its determination is appropriate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-02-120">
            <num>08.02.120</num>
            <heading>Access to certain mental health information and records by the state.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-02-120__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding
AS 08.29.200
,
AS 08.63.200
,
AS 08.86.200
,
AS 08.95.900
, another provision of this title, or a regulation adopted under this title, a licensee or an entity employing or contracting with a licensee may disclose confidential patient mental health information, communications, and records to the Department of Health when disclosure is authorized under
AS 47.30.540
, 47.30.590, 47.30.845, or
AS 47.31.032
. Information, communications, and records received by the Department of Health under this section are confidential medical records of patients and are not open to public inspection and copying under
AS 40.25.110
 40.25.120.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-02-120__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, licensee has the meaning given in
AS 08.01.110
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-02-130">
            <num>08.02.130</num>
            <heading>Telehealth.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-02-130__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A health care provider licensed in this state may provide health care services within the health care provider's authorized scope of practice to a patient in this state through telehealth without first conducting an in-person visit.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-02-130__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A physician licensed in another state or an out-of-state member of the physician's multidisciplinary care team may provide health care services through telehealth to a patient located in the state as provided in this subsection, subject to the investigative and enforcement powers of the department under
AS 08.01.087
. A member of a physician's multidisciplinary care team may provide a health care service through telehealth to a patient located in this state if the health care service, as provided by the multidisciplinary care team, is not reasonably available in the state. A physician shall be subject to disciplinary action by the State Medical Board under
AS 08.64.333
, and a member of the physician's multidisciplinary care team shall be subject to disciplinary action by the department under
AS 08.02.140
. The privilege to practice under this subsection extends only to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-02-130__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>ongoing treatment or follow-up care related to health care services previously provided by the physician to the patient and applies only if
(A) the physician and the patient have an established physician-patient relationship; and
(B) the physician has previously conducted an in-person visit with the patient;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-02-130__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a visit regarding a suspected or diagnosed life-threatening condition for which
(A) the patient has been referred to the physician licensed in another state by a physician licensed in this state and that referral has been documented by the referring physician; and
(B) the visit involves communication with the patient regarding diagnostic or treatment plan options or analysis of test results for the life-threatening condition; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-02-130__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>ongoing treatment or follow-up care provided by a physician licensed in another state or a member of the physician's multidisciplinary care team regarding a suspected or diagnosed life-threatening condition.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-02-130__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a health care provider determines in the course of a telehealth encounter with a patient under this section that some or all of the encounter will extend beyond the health care provider's authorized scope of practice, the health care provider shall advise the patient that the health care provider is not authorized to provide some or all of the services to the patient, recommend that the patient contact an appropriate provider for the services the health care provider is not authorized to provide, and limit the encounter to only those services the health care provider is authorized to provide. The health care provider may not charge for any portion of an encounter that extends beyond the health care provider's authorized scope of practice.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-02-130__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A fee for a service provided through telehealth under this section must be reasonable and consistent with the ordinary fee typically charged for that service and may not exceed the fee typically charged for that service.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-02-130__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A physician, podiatrist, osteopath, or physician assistant licensed under
AS 08.64
may prescribe, dispense, or administer through telehealth under this section a prescription for a controlled substance listed in
AS 11.71.140
 11.71.190 if the physician, podiatrist, osteopath, or physician assistant complies with state and federal law governing the prescription, dispensing, or administering of a controlled substance.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-02-130__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An advanced practice registered nurse licensed under
AS 08.68
may prescribe, dispense, or administer through telehealth under this section a prescription for a controlled substance listed in
AS 11.71.140
 11.71.190 if the advanced practice registered nurse complies with state and federal law governing the prescription, dispensing, or administering of a controlled substance.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-02-130__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as authorized under (e) and (f) of this section, a health care provider licensed under this title may not prescribe, dispense, or administer through telehealth under this section a controlled substance listed in
AS 11.71.140
 11.71.190.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-02-130__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A health care provider may not be required to document a barrier to an in-person visit to provide health care services through telehealth. The department or a board may not limit the physical setting from which a health care provider may provide health care services through telehealth.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-02-130__subsec_i">
              <num>(i)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Nothing in this section requires the use of telehealth when a health care provider determines that providing health care services through telehealth is not appropriate or when a patient chooses not to receive health care services through telehealth.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-02-130__subsec_j">
              <num>(j)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-02-130__subsec_j__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>[See delayed amendment note.]  health care provider means
(A) an audiologist or speech-language pathologist licensed under
AS 08.11
; a behavior analyst licensed under
AS 08.15
; a chiropractor licensed under
AS 08.20
; a professional counselor licensed under
AS 08.29
; a dental hygienist licensed under
AS 08.32
; a dentist licensed under
AS 08.36
; a dietitian or nutritionist licensed under
AS 08.38
; a naturopath licensed under
AS 08.45
; a marital and family therapist licensed under
AS 08.63
; a physician licensed under
AS 08.64
; a podiatrist, osteopath, or physician assistant licensed under
AS 08.64
; a direct-entry midwife certified under
AS 08.65
; a nurse licensed under
AS 08.68
; a dispensing optician licensed under
AS 08.71
; an optometrist licensed under
AS 08.72
; a pharmacist licensed under
AS 08.80
; a physical therapist or occupational therapist licensed under
AS 08.84
; a psychologist or psychological associate licensed under
AS 08.86
; or a social worker licensed under
AS 08.95
;
(B) a physician licensed in another state; or
(C)  a member of a multidisciplinary care team who is licensed in another state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-02-130__subsec_j__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>licensed means holding a current license in good standing;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-02-130__subsec_j__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>life-threatening condition means any disease or condition from which the likelihood of death is probable unless the course of the disease or condition is interrupted;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-02-130__subsec_j__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>member of a multidisciplinary care team means an audiologist, speech-language pathologist, behavior analyst, professional counselor, dietitian, nutritionist, naturopath, marital and family therapist, podiatrist, osteopath, physician assistant, nurse, pharmacist, physical therapist, occupational therapist, psychologist or psychological associate, advanced nurse practitioner, or social worker who is a member of a team coordinated by a physician licensed in another state who meets the requirements of (b)(3) of this section;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-02-130__subsec_j__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>telehealth has the meaning given in
AS 47.05.270</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-02-135">
            <num>08.02.135</num>
            <heading>Grounds for imposition of disciplinary sanctions of out-of- state multidisciplinary care team members.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.02.135.   Grounds for imposition of disciplinary sanctions of out-of- state multidisciplinary care team members.
The department may sanction a member of an out-of-state physician's multidisciplinary care team who provides health care services through telehealth under
AS 08.02.130
if the department finds after a hearing that the member
(1) secured a license through deceit, fraud, or intentional misrepresentation;
(2) engaged in deceit, fraud, or intentional misrepresentation while providing professional services or engaging in professional activities;
(3) advertised professional services in a false or misleading manner;
(4) has been convicted, including conviction based on a guilty plea or plea of nolo contendere, of
(A) a class A or unclassified felony or a crime in another jurisdiction with elements similar to a class A or unclassified felony in this jurisdiction;
(B) a class B or class C felony or a crime in another jurisdiction with elements similar to a class B or class C felony in this jurisdiction if the felony or other crime is substantially related to the qualifications, functions, or duties of the member; or
(C) a crime involving the unlawful procurement, sale, prescription, or dispensing of drugs;
(5) has procured, sold, prescribed, or dispensed drugs in violation of a law regardless of whether there has been a criminal action or harm to the patient;
(6) intentionally or negligently permitted the performance of patient care by persons under the member's supervision that does not conform to minimum professional standards even if the patient was not injured;
(7) failed to comply with
AS 08.02.130
 08.02.140, a regulation adopted under
AS 08.02.130
 08.02.140, or an order of the department;
(8) has demonstrated
(A) professional incompetence, gross negligence, or repeated negligent conduct; the department may not base a finding of professional incompetence solely on the basis that a member's practice is unconventional or experimental in the absence of demonstrable physical harm to a patient;
(B) addiction to, severe dependency on, or habitual overuse of alcohol or other drugs that impairs the member's ability to practice safely;
(C) unfitness because of physical or mental disability;
(9) engaged in unprofessional conduct, in sexual misconduct, or in lewd or immoral conduct in connection with the delivery of professional services to patients; in this paragraph, sexual misconduct includes sexual contact, or attempted sexual contact, with a patient outside the scope of generally accepted methods of examination or treatment of the patient, regardless of the patient's consent or lack of consent, during the term of the health care provider-patient relationship, unless the patient was the member's spouse at the time of the contact or, immediately preceding the health care provider-patient relationship, was in a dating, courtship, or engagement relationship with the member;
(10) has violated any code of ethics adopted by the department;
(11) has denied care or treatment to a patient or person seeking assistance from the member if the only reason for the denial is the failure or refusal of the patient to agree to arbitrate as provided in
AS 09.55.535
(a);
(12) has had a license or certificate to practice health care in another state or territory of the United States, or a province or territory of Canada, denied, suspended, revoked, surrendered while under investigation for an alleged violation, restricted, limited, conditioned, or placed on probation unless the denial, suspension, revocation, or other action was caused by the failure of the member to pay fees to that state, territory, or province;
(13) exceeded the scope of the member's privilege to practice in this state under
AS 08.02.130
; or
(14) prescribed, dispensed, or administered through telehealth to a patient located in the state a controlled substance listed in
AS 11.71.140
 11.71.190.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-02-140">
            <num>08.02.140</num>
            <heading>Disciplinary sanctions for an out-of-state multidisciplinary care team member.</heading>
            <subsection eId="08-02-140__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the department finds grounds to sanction a member of an out-of-state physician's multidisciplinary care team under
AS 08.02.135
, the department may</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-02-140__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>permanently prohibit the member from practicing in the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-02-140__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>prohibit the member from practicing in the state for a determinate period;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-02-140__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>censure the member;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-02-140__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>issue a letter of reprimand to the member;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-02-140__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>place the member on probationary status under (c) of this section;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-02-140__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>limit or impose conditions on the member's privilege to practice in the state;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-02-140__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>impose a civil penalty of not more than $25,000;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-02-140__subsec_a__subsec_8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>issue a cease and desist order prohibiting the member from providing health care services through telehealth under
AS 08.02.130
; an order issued under this paragraph remains in effect until the member submits evidence acceptable to the department showing that the violation has been corrected;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-02-140__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>promptly notify the licensing authority in each state in which the member is licensed of a sanction imposed under this subsection.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-02-140__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In a case finding grounds for sanction under
AS 08.02.135</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-02-140__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may place a member on probation under this section until the department finds that the deficiencies that required the imposition of a sanction have been remedied. The department may require a member on probation to</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="08-02-140__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>report regularly to the department on matters involving the reason for which the member was placed on probation;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-02-140__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>limit the member's practice in the state to those areas prescribed by the department;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="08-02-140__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>participate in professional education until the department determines that a satisfactory degree of skill has been attained in areas identified by the department as needing improvement.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-02-140__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may summarily prohibit a member from practicing in the state under
AS 08.02.130
if the department finds that the member, by continuing to practice, poses a clear and immediate danger to public health and safety. A member prohibited from practicing under this subsection is entitled to a hearing conducted by the office of administrative hearings (
AS 44.64.010
) not later than seven days after the effective date of the order prohibiting the member from practicing. The department may lift an order prohibiting a member from practicing if the department finds after a hearing that the member is able to practice with reasonable skill and safety. The member may appeal a decision of the department under this subsection to the superior court.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-02-140__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall take measures to recover from a member the cost of proceedings resulting in a sanction under (a) of this section, including the costs of investigation by the department and hearing costs.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-02-140__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department may prohibit a member from practicing in the state upon receiving a certified copy of evidence that a license or certificate to practice within the member's scope of practice in another state or territory of the United States, or a province or territory of Canada, has been suspended or revoked. The prohibition remains in effect until a hearing can be held by the department.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="08-02-140__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The department shall be consistent in the application of disciplinary sanctions. A significant departure from earlier decisions of the department involving similar situations must be explained in findings of fact or orders made by the department.
Article 4 General Provisions</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_08-02-990">
            <num>08.02.990</num>
            <heading>Definition.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 08.02.990.   Definition.
In this chapter, department means the Department of Commerce, Community, and Economic Development.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>