<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-9/chapter-68"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-9/chapter-68"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="9.68"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-9/chapter-68/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-9/chapter-68/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-9/chapter-68/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-9/chapter-68/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_9">
        <num>9</num>
        <heading>Code of Civil Procedure</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_9__chp_68">
          <num>68</num>
          <heading>Miscellaneous Provisions</heading>
          <section eId="sec_09-68-020">
            <num>09.68.020</num>
            <heading>Successive actions.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 09.68.020.   Successive actions.
Successive actions may be maintained upon the same contract or transaction when a new cause of action arises under the contract.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_09-68-030">
            <num>09.68.030</num>
            <heading>Corporate sureties.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 09.68.030.   Corporate sureties.
When, by the laws of the state or by a charter, ordinance, rule, or regulation of a political subdivision, municipality, public corporation, or by a board, body, organization, court, or judge, a recognizance, stipulation, bond, undertaking, or bail in an action, suit, proceeding, or matter conditioned for the faithful performance of an act or duty or for the doing of an act or thing is permitted or required to be given with one or more sureties, it is sufficient compliance if the instrument is executed by a corporation that has complied with the laws of the state and is authorized by law to act as surety upon instruments and in proceedings, actions, suits, and matters as set out in this section.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_09-68-040">
            <num>09.68.040</num>
            <heading>Parties exempt from giving bond.</heading>
            <subsection eId="09-68-040__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In an action or proceeding in a court in which the state or a municipality is a party or in which the state or a municipality is interested, a bond or undertaking is not required of the state, a municipality, or an officer of the state or municipality.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="09-68-040__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A bond for costs on appeal need not be filed by a party to an action if a court finds that party to be indigent and the appeal not frivolous; this finding may be made upon an affidavit filed by that party showing that the party is unable to pay for a bond and further stating the grounds for the appeal and the belief that the party is entitled to redress.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="09-68-040__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A court in this state may not excuse a litigant requesting the entry of a stay or other interlocutory relief from posting a bond or other security to protect the persons who will be adversely affected if the excuse is based on the nature of the policy or interest advocated by the party, the number of persons affected by the outcome of the case, whether a governmental entity could be expected to bring or participate in the case, the extent of the party's economic incentive to bring the case, or any combination of these factors.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_09-68-050">
            <num>09.68.050</num>
            <heading>Civil liability for malicious claim against state permitted project.</heading>
            <subsection eId="09-68-050__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who initiates or maintains a malicious claim for injunctive relief against a state permitted project is, in addition to any other penalty or sanction provided by law, liable in a civil action to the permittee or owner of the project for all of the following:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="09-68-050__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>actual damages suffered by the permittee or owner of the project as a result of the malicious claim, including
(A) wages and salaries paid to employees or contractors idled or put to nonproductive labor as a result of prosecution of the malicious claim; and
(B) increased material costs caused by prosecution of the malicious claim; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="09-68-050__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>incidental or consequential damages arising under contracts associated with the project that were caused by prosecution of the malicious claim.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="09-68-050__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The liability of a person for damages under this section is in addition to liability for an award of reasonable attorney fees and costs that may be made to a prevailing party under the Alaska Rules of Civil Procedure.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="09-68-050__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of this section, a person initiates or maintains a malicious claim for injunctive relief against a state permitted project if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="09-68-050__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the person initiates or maintains a baseless legal or administrative claim, including an original claim, a counterclaim, or a cross-claim, against a project or activity in the state requiring one or more permits, authorizations, or approvals from a state agency;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="09-68-050__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the claim is rejected by a court or administrative tribunal of competent jurisdiction or otherwise terminated adverse to the person;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="09-68-050__subsec_c__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the claim is initiated or maintained in bad faith for an end other than the end it was designed to accomplish;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="09-68-050__subsec_c__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the person acts with malice in initiating or maintaining the claim; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="09-68-050__subsec_c__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the permittee or owner of the project is damaged by the initiation or maintenance of the claim.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_09-68-060">
            <num>09.68.060</num>
            <heading>Defense not prejudiced by assignment.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 09.68.060.   Defense not prejudiced by assignment.
If there is an assignment of a thing in action, the action by the assignee is without prejudice to a setoff or other defense existing at the time of, or before notice of the assignment. But, this section does not apply to a negotiable promissory note or bill of exchange transferred in good faith and upon valuable consideration before due.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_09-68-110">
            <num>09.68.110</num>
            <heading>Civil liability for shoplifting.</heading>
            <subsection eId="09-68-110__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person who has attained the age of 18 years or an emancipated minor who shoplifts merchandise is, in addition to any criminal penalty provided by law, liable in a civil action to the owner or seller of the merchandise for all of the following:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="09-68-110__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>actual damages;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="09-68-110__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a penalty equal to the retail value of the merchandise or $1,000, whichever is less; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="09-68-110__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a penalty of not less than $100 nor more than $200.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="09-68-110__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person having legal custody of an unemancipated minor who shoplifts merchandise is liable in a civil action to the owner or seller of the merchandise for both of the following:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="09-68-110__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a penalty equal to the retail value of the merchandise or $500, whichever is less; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="09-68-110__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a penalty of not less than $100 nor more than $200.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="09-68-110__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>It is a condition precedent to maintaining an action under this section that the owner or seller of the merchandise send a notice demanding the relief authorized to the defendant by first class mail at the defendant's last known address 15 days or more before the action is commenced.  The Department of Law may adopt regulations prescribing the form of this notice. It is not a condition precedent to maintaining an action under this section that the person who shoplifted merchandise was charged or convicted under any statute or ordinance.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="09-68-110__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Judgments, but not claims, arising under this section may be assigned.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="09-68-110__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For purposes of this section, a person shoplifts merchandise if, without authority and with intent to deprive the owner of the merchandise,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="09-68-110__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the person removes the merchandise of a commercial establishment, not purchased by the person, from the premises of the commercial establishment;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="09-68-110__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the person knowingly conceals on, in, or about the person the merchandise of a commercial establishment, not purchased by the person, while still upon the premises of the commercial establishment; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="09-68-110__subsec_e__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the person knowingly substitutes or alters a price ticket in order to pay less than the indicated retail price.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="09-68-110__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Merchandise found concealed on or about the person which has not been purchased by the person is prima facie evidence of a knowing concealment for purposes of (e)(2) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="09-68-110__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The liability of a person for damages and penalties under this section is in addition to liability for an award of reasonable attorney fees that may be made to the prevailing party in a civil action under Rule 82, Alaska Rules of Civil Procedure.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="09-68-110__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section, emancipated minor means a minor whose disabilities have been removed for general purposes under
AS 09.55.590
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_09-68-115">
            <num>09.68.115</num>
            <heading>Bad check civil penalties.</heading>
            <subsection eId="09-68-115__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In an action against a person who issues a check that is dishonored, the plaintiff may recover damages in an amount equal to $100 or triple the amount of the check, whichever is greater, except that damages recovered under this section may not exceed the amount of the check by more than $1,000 and may be awarded only if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="09-68-115__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the plaintiff makes a written demand for payment of the check at least 15 days before commencing the action; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="09-68-115__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the defendant fails to tender, before the action commences, an amount equal to the amount of the check plus up to a maximum $30 fee.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="09-68-115__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An action under this section may be brought as a small claims action if the amount claimed does not exceed the jurisdictional limits for small claims actions, or may be brought in any other court that has jurisdiction.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="09-68-115__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>After the beginning of an action under this section but before the case is tried, the defendant may satisfy the claim by tendering an amount of money equal to the amount of the check plus court, legal, and service costs incurred by the plaintiff up to a maximum of $150.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="09-68-115__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="09-68-115__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>check has the meaning given in
AS 11.46.280
;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="09-68-115__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>dishonored means the nonpayment of a check because of
(A) lack of funds;
(B) closure or nonexistence of an account; or
(C) a stop payment order issued without cause;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="09-68-115__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>written demand means a written notice to the issuer of a check personally delivered or sent by first class mail to the address shown on the dishonored check, advising the issuer that the check has been dishonored and explaining the civil penalties set out in this section.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_09-68-120">
            <num>09.68.120</num>
            <heading>Definition of death.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 09.68.120.   Definition of death.
An individual is considered dead if, in the opinion of a physician licensed or exempt from licensing under
AS 08.64
or a registered nurse authorized to pronounce death under
AS 08.68.700
, based on acceptable medical standards, or in the opinion of a mobile intensive care paramedic, physician assistant, or emergency medical technician authorized to pronounce death based on the medical standards in
AS 18.08.089
, the individual has sustained irreversible cessation of circulatory and respiratory functions, or irreversible cessation of all functions of the entire brain, including the brain stem. Death may be pronounced in this circumstance before artificial means of maintaining respiratory and cardiac function are terminated.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_09-68-130">
            <num>09.68.130</num>
            <heading>Collection of settlement information.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 09.68.130.   Collection of settlement information.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_09-68-130">
            <num>09.68.130</num>
            <heading>Collection of settlement information.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 09.68.130.   Collection of settlement information.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>