<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act name="AS">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#arch">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-15/chapter-15"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-15/chapter-15"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#alaska-legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="us-ak"/>
          <FRBRnumber value="15.15"/>
          <FRBRname value="AS"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-15/chapter-15/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-15/chapter-15/eng@2025-12-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-15/chapter-15/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ak/act/as/title-15/chapter-15/eng@2025-12-31/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#arch"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#arch">
        <TLCOrganization eId="arch" href="https://cosilico.ai" showAs="Cosilico Arch"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="alaska-legislature" href="https://www.akleg.gov" showAs="Alaska State Legislature"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <body>
      <title eId="title_15">
        <num>15</num>
        <heading>Elections</heading>
        <chapter eId="title_15__chp_15">
          <num>15</num>
          <heading>Elections and Ballots</heading>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-010">
            <num>15.15.010</num>
            <heading>General administrative supervision by director.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.15.010.   General administrative supervision by director.
The director shall provide general administrative supervision over the conduct of state elections, and may adopt regulations under
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act) necessary for the administration of state elections. The director shall adopt regulations that establish for the broadcasting of notices under
AS 15.15.070
the frequency of the broadcasts, appropriate broadcast times, and the locations for the broadcasts. The broadcasting regulations must be reasonably calculated to provide the widest possible exposure of the notices.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-020">
            <num>15.15.020</num>
            <heading>Date of general election.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.15.020.   Date of general election.
The general election is held on the Tuesday after the first Monday in November in every even numbered year.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-025">
            <num>15.15.025</num>
            <heading>Top four nonpartisan open primary.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.15.025.   Top four nonpartisan open primary.
A voter qualified under
AS 15.05
may cast a vote for any candidate for each elective state executive and state and national legislative office, without limitations based on the political party or political group affiliation of either the voter or the candidate.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-030">
            <num>15.15.030</num>
            <heading>Preparation of official ballot.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.15.030.   Preparation of official ballot.
The director shall prepare all official ballots to facilitate fairness, simplicity, and clarity in the voting procedure, to reflect most accurately the intent of the voter, and to expedite the administration of elections. The following directives shall be followed when applicable:
(1) The director shall determine the size of the ballot, the type of print, necessary additional instruction notes to voters, and other similar matters of form not provided by law.
(2) The director shall number ballots in series to ensure simplicity and secrecy and to prevent fraud.
(3) The director shall contract for the preparation of ballots under
AS 36.30
(State Procurement Code).
(4) The director may not include on the ballot, as a part of a candidate's name, any honorary or assumed title or prefix but may include in the candidate's name any nickname or familiar form of a proper name of the candidate.
(5) The names of the candidates shall be placed in separate sections on the state general election ballot under the office designation to which they were nominated. If a candidate is registered as affiliated with a political party or political group, the party affiliation, if any, may be designated after the name of the candidate, upon request of the candidate. If a candidate has requested designation as nonpartisan or undeclared, that designation shall be placed after the name of the candidate. If a candidate is not registered as affiliated with a political party or political group and has not requested to be designated as nonpartisan or undeclared, the candidate shall be designated as undeclared. The lieutenant governor and the governor shall be included under the same section. Provision shall be made for voting for write-in candidates within each section. Paper ballots for the state general election shall be printed on white paper.
(6) The names of the candidates for each office shall be set out in the same order on ballots printed for use in each house district. The director shall randomly determine the order of the names of the candidates for state representative for each house district. The director shall rotate the order of placement of the names of candidates for governor, lieutenant governor, United States senator, United States representative, and state senator on the ballot for each house district.
(7) The general election ballot shall be designed with the names of candidates of each political party, and of any independent candidates qualified under
AS 15.30.026
, for the office of President and Vice-President of the United States placed in the same section on the ballot rather than the names of electors of President and Vice-President.
(8) The general or special election ballot shall be designed with the title and proposition for any initiative, referendum, or constitutional amendment formulated as prescribed by law and placed on the ballot in the manner prescribed by the director. When placed on the ballot, a state ballot proposition or ballot question shall carry the number that was assigned to the petition for the proposition or question. Provision shall be made for marking the proposition Yes or No.
(9) The general or special election ballot shall be designed with the question of whether a constitutional convention shall be called placed on the ballot in the following manner: Shall there be a constitutional convention? Provision shall be made for marking the question Yes or No.
(10) A nonpartisan ballot shall be designed for each judicial district in which a justice or judge is seeking retention in office. The ballot shall be divided into four parts. Each part must bear a heading indicating the court to which the candidate is seeking approval, and provision shall be made for marking each question Yes or No. Within each part, the question of whether the justice or judge shall be approved or rejected shall be set out in substantially the following manner:
(A) Shall ....... be retained as justice of the supreme court for 10 years?;
(B) Shall ....... be retained as judge of the court of appeals for eight years?;
(C) Shall ....... be retained as judge of the superior court for six years?; or
(D) Shall ....... be retained as judge of the district court for four years?
(11) When the legislature by law authorizes a state debt for capital improvements, the director shall place the question of whether the specific authorization shall be ratified by placing the ballot title and question on the next general election ballot, or on the special election ballot if a special election is held for the purpose of ratifying the state debt for capital improvements before the time of the next general election. Unless specifically provided otherwise in the Act authorizing the debt, the ballot title shall, by the use of a few words in a succinct manner, indicate the general subject of the Act. The question shall, by the use of a few sentences in a succinct manner, give a true and impartial summary of the Act authorizing the state debt. The question of whether state debt shall be contracted shall be assigned a letter of the alphabet on the ballot. Provision shall be made for marking the question substantially as follows:
Bonds....... Yes or Bonds....... No,
followed by an appropriate oval.
(12) The director may provide for the optical scanning of ballots where the requisite equipment is available.
(13) The director may provide for voting by use of electronically generated ballots by a voter who requests to use a machine that produces electronically generated ballots.
(14) The director shall include the following statement on the ballot:
A candidate's designated affiliation does not imply that the candidate is nominated or endorsed by the political party or group or that the party or group approves of or associates with that candidate, but only that the candidate is registered as affiliated with the political party or political group.
(15) Instead of the statement provided by (14) of this section, when candidates for President and Vice-President of the United States appear on a general election ballot, the director shall include the following statement on the ballot:
A candidate's designated affiliation does not imply that the candidate is nominated or endorsed by the political party or political group or that the political party or political group approves of or associates with that candidate, but only that the candidate is registered as affiliated with the party or group. The election for President and Vice-President of the United States is different. Some candidates for President and Vice-President are the official nominees of their political party.
(16) The director shall design the general election ballots so that the candidates are selected by ranked-choice voting.
(17) The director shall design the general election ballot to direct the voter to mark candidates in order of preference and to mark as many choices as the voter wishes, but not to assign the same ranking to more than one candidate for the same office.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-032">
            <num>15.15.032</num>
            <heading>Use of electronically generated ballots.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-15-032__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the director provides for voting by use of electronically generated ballots, the director shall provide balloting equipment that would allow voters with disabilities, including those who are blind or visually impaired, to cast private, independent, and verifiable ballots. The director may not provide for more than one machine that produces electronically generated ballots in a precinct or in a regional supervisor's office, except where the director determines that additional machines are needed to accommodate the needs of individuals with disabilities, including individuals with physical limitations or visual impairments.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-15-032__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Software for voting by use of electronically generated ballots shall be tested and certified under
AS 15.20.900
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-15-032__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The director shall provide for a paper record of each electronically generated ballot that can be</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-15-032__subsec_c__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>reviewed and corrected by the voter at the time the vote is cast; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-15-032__subsec_c__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>used for a recount of the votes cast at an election in which electronically generated ballots were used.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-035">
            <num>15.15.035</num>
            <heading>Printing of ballots and other material.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.15.035.   Printing of ballots and other material.
The director may not be required to do business with a printing company while the company is involved in a labor dispute.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-040">
            <num>15.15.040</num>
            <heading>Preparation of other election materials.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-15-040__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The director shall prescribe the form of and prepare tinted sample ballots and all other materials, forms, and supplies required for the election.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-15-040__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The director shall prepare and issue or make available with each sample ballot for a special election the statement provided for in
AS 24.08.037
of the scope of each project included in a proposed general obligation bond issue creating a state debt for capital improvements that is submitted to the electorate for ratification under
AS 15.15.030</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-15-040__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The director shall provide materials, forms, and supplies for each polling place, including information regarding the date of the election and hours the polling place will be open, instructions on how to cast a questioned ballot, instructions for first-time voters who initially registered by mail, general information on voting rights, prohibitions on acts of fraud and misrepresentation, and whom to contact to report violations.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-050">
            <num>15.15.050</num>
            <heading>Distribution of election materials.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.15.050.   Distribution of election materials.
The director shall distribute an adequate supply of sample and official ballots and all other materials, forms, and supplies required for the election to the election supervisors for distribution to chairpersons of election boards in precincts not less than 25 days before the date for the election.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-060">
            <num>15.15.060</num>
            <heading>Polling places, voting booths, and supplies.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-15-060__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Immediately following the appointment of the election board, the election supervisor in conjunction with the election board chair shall secure polling places for holding the election, suitable ballot boxes that will assure security, and an adequate number of voting booths or screens, national flags, pens, and pencils. At every polling place, at least one voting booth shall be furnished and not less than one voting booth or screen shall be furnished for each 100 votes or fractional part of 100 votes cast in the previous election. At every polling place, at least one-half of the voting booths used shall be not less than six feet in height, enclosed on three sides, and provided with a curtain extending from the top of the voting booth to within approximately 30 inches of the floor. The curtain of the voting booth must conceal the voter while voting. The election supervisor and the election board chair may, in an emergency, secure an alternate location for a polling place.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-15-060__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>To assure administrative economy and to protect the secrecy of the ballot, the director may adopt regulations prescribing</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-15-060__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the type of polling place for holding the election;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-15-060__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the requirements regarding ballot boxes, voting screens, national flags, and other supplies; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-15-060__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>subject to the specifications of (a) of this section, the requirements regarding voting booths.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-15-060__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The director shall pay the cost of necessary election expenses incurred in securing a place for holding the election, a suitable ballot box, and an adequate number of voting booths, screens, national flags, and other supplies. The national flag shall be displayed over or near the entrance of each polling place.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-15-060__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When the director determines that there is an area in the state where a voter may be confused as to the voter's correct precinct polling place, the director shall provide each polling place in that area with maps and materials that indicate house district boundaries, precinct boundaries, and polling places.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-15-060__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In each polling place, the director shall require to be posted, in a location conspicuous to a person who will be voting, the following notice, written in bold:
A candidate's designated affiliation does not imply that the candidate is nominated or endorsed by the political party or group or that the party or group approves of or associates with that candidate, but only that the candidate is registered as affiliated with the party or group.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-070">
            <num>15.15.070</num>
            <heading>Public notice of election required.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-15-070__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The director shall give and is authorized to contract to give full public notice of the election. The director may select a manner reasonably calculated to give actual knowledge of the election to the voters.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-15-070__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The notice shall be given by publication at least twice in one or more newspapers of general circulation in each of the four judicial districts. The printed notice must specifically include the date of election, the hours between which the polling places will be open, the offices to which candidates are to be nominated or elected, and the subject of the propositions and questions that are to be voted on.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-15-070__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Public notice shall also be given by posting notices in those communities that do not have newspapers of general circulation where posting of notice is considered necessary by the director. The posted notice must specifically include the date of election, the location of the polling places, the hours between which the polling places will be open, the offices to which candidates are to be nominated or elected, the subject of the propositions and questions that are to be voted on, and other information considered necessary by the director.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-15-070__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The first publication, broadcast, or posting of the notice shall be made not less than 10 days before the election.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-15-070__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 15 ch 82 SLA 2000.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-15-070__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 15 ch 82 SLA 2000.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-15-070__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The director shall pay the cost of election expenses incurred in giving notice of an election.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-15-070__subsec_h">
              <num>(h)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An abbreviated form of the notice published under (b) of this section shall be broadcast on one or more radio or television stations in each of the four judicial districts. The broadcast notice must include at a minimum the date of the election, the hours between which the polling places will be open, and the address and phone number of the election supervisor or supervisors for the judicial district in which the notice is broadcast.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-080">
            <num>15.15.080</num>
            <heading>Time for opening and closing polls.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-15-080__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Except as provided in (b) of this section, on the day of any election, each election board shall open the polls for voting at seven o'clock in the morning, shall close the polls for voting at eight o'clock in the evening, and shall keep the polls open during the time between these hours.  The election board members shall report to the polling place at 6:30 in the morning of an election day.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-15-080__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>On the day of any election that is not a general election, a primary election, a special election, or a federal election held under this title, the director shall require each election board to open the polls for voting at eight o'clock in the morning, shall close the polls for voting at eight o'clock in the evening, and shall keep the polls open during the time between these hours.  The election board members shall report to the polling place one-half hour before the polls are to open on election day.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-090">
            <num>15.15.090</num>
            <heading>Designation of precinct polling place.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.15.090.   Designation of precinct polling place.
The polling place shall be located within the precinct unless the election supervisor and the election board chairperson determine that a building located in an adjoining precinct is more suitable or convenient to the voters.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-100">
            <num>15.15.100</num>
            <heading>Time off for voting.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.15.100.   Time off for voting.
A qualified voter who does not have sufficient time outside working hours within which to vote at a state election may, without loss of pay, take off as much working time as will enable voting.  If any employee has two consecutive hours in which to vote, either between the opening of the polls and the beginning of the employee's regular working shift, or between the end of the regular working shift and the closing of the polls, the employee shall be considered to have sufficient time outside working hours within which to vote.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-110">
            <num>15.15.110</num>
            <heading>General duties and oath of election board.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.15.110.   General duties and oath of election board.
The election board shall supervise the election in the precinct. Before entering upon the duties of office, each election official shall take an oath to honestly, faithfully, and promptly perform the duties of office. Any appointed election official, including an appointed election official who has not personally subscribed to the oath, may administer the oath to another election official. The chairperson of the election board shall rotate the time at which election officials may be relieved for meals.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-120">
            <num>15.15.120</num>
            <heading>Filling vacancies in election board.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.15.120.   Filling vacancies in election board.
If an appointed election board member fails to appear and subscribe to the oath on election day or becomes incapacitated during the time of the election or the counting of the ballots, the election board members present shall elect, by a majority voice vote, a qualified voter to fill the vacancy. The qualified voter elected to fill the vacancy shall be of the same political party as the person for whom the substitution is made unless, after reasonable effort, the election board members determine that a qualified voter of the same political party is not available.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-130">
            <num>15.15.130</num>
            <heading>Majority decision of election board.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.15.130.   Majority decision of election board.
The decision of the majority of election board members determines the action that the election board shall take regarding any question that arises during the course of the election.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-140">
            <num>15.15.140</num>
            <heading>Permitted use of unofficial ballots.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-15-140__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the election board receives an insufficient number of official ballots or official election materials, it shall provide and the voters may use unmarked substitute ballots or other election materials to indicate the intent of the voter.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-15-140__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The election board shall certify the facts which prevented the use of the official ballots and materials and shall include the certificate in the election returns to the director. The initial failure to certify to the facts or include the certificate required does not invalidate any ballots.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-15-140__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>On disclosure that unofficial ballots have been used without the certification required under (b) of this section, the director shall notify the chairperson of the election board by telephone or electronic transmission of the failure to certify the ballots properly.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-15-140__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The director may accept a certificate made by electronic transmission and count the ballots if the certificate is proper and actually received by the director within 10 days after the date that the chairperson of the election board was notified under (c) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-150">
            <num>15.15.150</num>
            <heading>Official opening of polls.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.15.150.   Official opening of polls.
On the day and hour of election, the election board shall announce that the polls are open and receive the voters.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-160">
            <num>15.15.160</num>
            <heading>Prohibition of political discussion by election board.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.15.160.   Prohibition of political discussion by election board.
During the hours that the polls are open, an election board member may not discuss any political party, candidate, or issue while on duty.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-170">
            <num>15.15.170</num>
            <heading>Prohibition of political persuasion near election polls.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.15.170.   Prohibition of political persuasion near election polls.
During the hours the polls are open, a person who is in the polling place or within 200 feet of any entrance to the polling place may not attempt to persuade a person to vote for or against a candidate, proposition, or question. The election officials shall post warning notices at the required distance in the form and manner prescribed by the director.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-180">
            <num>15.15.180</num>
            <heading>Keeping of register.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.15.180.   Keeping of register.
The election officials shall keep a register or registers in which each voter before receiving a ballot shall sign the voter's name and give both a residence and mailing address. A record shall be kept in the registration book in space provided of the names of persons who offer to vote but who actually do not vote, and a brief statement of explanation. The signing of the register constitutes a declaration by the voter that the voter is qualified to vote.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-195">
            <num>15.15.195</num>
            <heading>Voters on official registration list.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.15.195.   Voters on official registration list.
An election official in a precinct shall allow a voter on the official registration list to vote in the precinct unless the voter is questioned in accordance with
AS 15.15.210
.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-198">
            <num>15.15.198</num>
            <heading>Voters not on official registration list.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-15-198__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a voter's name does not appear on the official registration list in the precinct in which the voter seeks to vote, the election official shall affirmatively advise the voter that the voter may cast a questioned ballot, and the voter shall be allowed to vote a questioned ballot. At the time the voter casts a questioned ballot, the voter shall be given written information stating that the voter will be able to ascertain whether the ballot was counted and, if not counted, the reason the ballot was not counted.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-15-198__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A person whose registration is inactive under
AS 15.07.130</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-15-198__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>and who votes a questioned or absentee ballot shall have the ballot counted if</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-15-198__subsec_b__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the person was registered to vote in the last four calendar years;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-15-198__subsec_b__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the person signs a statement to that effect; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-15-198__subsec_b__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the earlier registration is verified by the director.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-210">
            <num>15.15.210</num>
            <heading>Questioning of voters of suspect qualification.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.15.210.   Questioning of voters of suspect qualification.
Every election official shall question, and every watcher and any other person qualified to vote in the precinct may question, a person attempting to vote if the questioner has good reason to suspect that the questioned person is not qualified under
AS 15.05
. All questions regarding a person's qualifications to vote shall be made in writing setting out the reason the person has been questioned. A questioned person shall, before voting, subscribe to a declaration in a form provided by the director attesting to the fact that in each particular the person meets all the qualifications of a voter, is not disqualified, and has not voted at the same election, and certifying that the person understands that a false statement on the declaration may subject the person to prosecution for a misdemeanor under this title or
AS 11
. After the questioned person has executed the declaration, the person may vote. If the questioned person refuses to execute the declaration, the person may not vote.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-215">
            <num>15.15.215</num>
            <heading>Disposition of questioned votes.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-15-215__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A voter who casts a questioned ballot shall vote the ballot in the same manner as prescribed for other voters. The voter shall insert the ballot into a secrecy sleeve and put the secrecy sleeve into an envelope on which the statement the voter previously signed is located. The envelope shall be sealed and deposited in the ballot box. When the ballot box is opened, the envelopes shall be segregated, counted, compared to the voting list, and delivered to the official or body supervising the election. The merits of the question shall be determined by this official or body in accordance with the procedure prescribed for questioned votes in
AS 15.20.207
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-15-215__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 231 ch 100 SLA 1980.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-220">
            <num>15.15.220</num>
            <heading>Administration of oaths.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.15.220.   Administration of oaths.
Any election official may administer to a voter any oath that is necessary in the administration of the election.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-225">
            <num>15.15.225</num>
            <heading>Voter identification at polls.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-15-225__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before being allowed to vote, each voter shall exhibit to an election official one form of identification, including</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-15-225__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an official voter registration card, driver's license, state identification card, current and valid photo identification, birth certificate, passport, or hunting or fishing license; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-15-225__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>an original or a copy of a current utility bill, bank statement, paycheck, government check, or other government document; an item exhibited under this paragraph must show the name and current address of the voter.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-15-225__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>An election official may waive the identification requirement if the election official knows the identity of the voter. The identification requirement may not be waived for voters who are first-time voters who initially registered by mail or by facsimile or other electronic transmission approved by the director under
AS 15.07.050
, and did not provide identification as required in
AS 15.07.060
.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-15-225__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A voter who cannot exhibit a required form of identification shall be allowed to vote a questioned ballot.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-230">
            <num>15.15.230</num>
            <heading>Providing ballot to voter.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.15.230.   Providing ballot to voter.
When the voter has qualified to vote, the election official shall give the voter an official ballot. The voter shall retire to a booth or private place to mark the ballot.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-240">
            <num>15.15.240</num>
            <heading>Voter assistance.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.15.240.   Voter assistance.
A qualified voter needing assistance in voting may request an election official, a person, or not more than two persons of the voter's choice to assist. If the election official is requested, the election official shall assist the voter. If any other person is requested, the person shall state upon oath before the election official that the person will not divulge the vote cast by the person assisted.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-250">
            <num>15.15.250</num>
            <heading>Disposition of spoiled ballot.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.15.250.   Disposition of spoiled ballot.
If a voter improperly marks, damages, or otherwise spoils a ballot, the voter may request and the election board shall provide another ballot, with a maximum of three. The board shall record on the precinct register that there was a spoiled ballot and destroy the spoiled ballot immediately without examining it.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-260">
            <num>15.15.260</num>
            <heading>Placing ballot in ballot box by voter.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.15.260.   Placing ballot in ballot box by voter.
When the voter has marked a ballot, the voter shall inform the election official. The ballot shall be deposited in the ballot box by the voter in the presence of the election official unless the voter requests the election official to deposit the ballot on the voter's behalf. Separate ballot boxes may be used for separate ballots.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-270">
            <num>15.15.270</num>
            <heading>Leaving polling place with ballot prohibited.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.15.270.   Leaving polling place with ballot prohibited.
A voter may not leave the polling place with the official ballot that the voter received to mark.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-280">
            <num>15.15.280</num>
            <heading>Prohibiting the exhibition of marked ballots.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.15.280.   Prohibiting the exhibition of marked ballots.
Subject to
AS 15.15.240
a voter may not exhibit the voter's ballot to an election official or any other person so as to enable any person to ascertain how the voter marked the ballot.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-290">
            <num>15.15.290</num>
            <heading>Prohibiting the identification of ballots.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.15.290.   Prohibiting the identification of ballots.
While the polls are open, an election official may not open any ballot received from a voter, or mark a ballot by folding or otherwise so as to be able to recognize it, or otherwise attempt to learn how a voter marked a ballot, or allow the same to be done by another person.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-300">
            <num>15.15.300</num>
            <heading>Prohibiting the count of exhibited ballots.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.15.300.   Prohibiting the count of exhibited ballots.
An election official may not allow a ballot to be placed in the ballot box that the official knows to have been unlawfully exhibited by the voter.  A ballot unlawfully exhibited shall be recorded as a spoiled ballot and destroyed.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-310">
            <num>15.15.310</num>
            <heading>Official closing of polls.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.15.310.   Official closing of polls.
Fifteen minutes before and at the time of closing the polls, the election board shall announce the present time and the time of closing the polls.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-320">
            <num>15.15.320</num>
            <heading>Voters in line when polls close.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.15.320.   Voters in line when polls close.
Every qualified voter present and in line at the time prescribed for closing the polls may vote.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-330">
            <num>15.15.330</num>
            <heading>Commencement of ballot count.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.15.330.   Commencement of ballot count.
When the polls are closed and the last vote has been cast in a hand-count precinct, the election board shall immediately proceed to open the ballot box and to count the votes cast. In all cases, the election board shall cause the count to be continued without adjournment until the count is complete.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-340">
            <num>15.15.340</num>
            <heading>Duties, oath, and vacancies of additional election officials.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.15.340.   Duties, oath, and vacancies of additional election officials.
Additional election officials shall report to the election board at the polls at the time designated by the election supervisor or the chairperson of the election board to assume their duties to assist the election board in counting the vote. Before undertaking the duties of office, each additional election official shall subscribe to an oath to honestly, faithfully, impartially, and promptly carry out the duties of the position. If an additional election official fails to appear and subscribe to the oath at the time designated by the election supervisor, the election board shall appoint any qualified voter to fill the vacancy.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-350">
            <num>15.15.350</num>
            <heading>General procedure for ballot count.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-15-350__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The director may adopt regulations prescribing the manner in which the precinct ballot count is accomplished so as to ensure accuracy in the count and to expedite the process. The election board shall account for all ballots by completing a ballot statement containing (1) the number of official ballots received; (2) the number of official ballots voted; (3) the number of official ballots spoiled; (4) the number of official ballots unused and either destroyed or returned for destruction to the elections supervisor or the election supervisor's designee. The board shall count the number of questioned ballots and compare that number to the number of questioned voters in the register. Discrepancies shall be noted and the numbers included in the certificate prescribed by
AS 15.15.370
. The election board, in hand-count precincts, shall count the ballots in a manner that allows watchers to see the ballots when opened and read. A person handling the ballot after it has been taken from the ballot box and before it is placed in the envelope for mailing may not have a marking device in hand or remove a ballot from the immediate vicinity of the polls.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-15-350__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Ballots may not be counted before 8:00 p.m., local time, on the day of the election.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-15-350__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>All general elections shall be conducted by ranked-choice voting.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-15-350__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When counting ballots in a general election, the election board shall initially tabulate each validly cast ballot as one vote for the highest-ranked continuing candidate on that ballot or as an inactive ballot. If a candidate is highest-ranked on more than one-half of the active ballots, that candidate is elected and the tabulation is complete. Otherwise, tabulation proceeds in sequential rounds as follows:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-15-350__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if two or fewer continuing candidates remain, the candidate with the greatest number of votes is elected and the tabulation is complete; otherwise, the tabulation continues under (2) of this subsection;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-15-350__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if the candidate with the fewest votes is defeated, votes cast for the defeated candidate shall cease counting for the defeated candidate and shall be added to the totals of each ballot's next-highest-ranked continuing candidate or considered an inactive ballot under (g)(2) of this section, and a new round begins under (1) of this subsection.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-15-350__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>When counting general election ballots,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-15-350__subsec_e__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a ballot containing an overvote shall be considered an inactive ballot once the overvote is encountered at the highest ranking for a continuing candidate;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-15-350__subsec_e__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if a ballot skips a ranking, then the election board shall count the next ranking. If the next ranking is another skipped ranking, the ballot shall be considered an inactive ballot once the second skipped ranking is encountered; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-15-350__subsec_e__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in the event of a tie between the final two continuing candidates, the procedures in
AS 15.15.460
and
AS 15.20.430
 15.20.530 shall apply to determine the winner of the general election; in the event of a tie between two candidates with the fewest votes, the tie shall be resolved by lot to determine which candidate is defeated.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-15-350__subsec_f">
              <num>(f)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The election board may not count an inactive ballot for any candidate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-15-350__subsec_g">
              <num>(g)</num>
              <content>
                <p>In this section,</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-15-350__subsec_g__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>continuing candidate means a candidate who has not been defeated;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-15-350__subsec_g__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>inactive ballot means a ballot that is no longer tabulated, either in whole or in part, by the division because it does not rank any continuing candidate, contains an overvote at the highest continuing ranking, or contains two or more sequential skipped rankings before its highest continuing ranking;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-15-350__subsec_g__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>overvote means an instance where a voter has assigned the same ranking to more than one candidate;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-15-350__subsec_g__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>ranking or ranked means the number assigned by a voter to a candidate to express the voter's choice for that candidate; a ranking of 1 is the highest ranking, followed by 2, and then 3, and so on;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-15-350__subsec_g__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>round means an instance of the sequence of voting tabulation in a general election;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-15-350__subsec_g__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>skipped ranking means a blank ranking on a ballot on which a voter has ranked another candidate at a subsequent ranking.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-360">
            <num>15.15.360</num>
            <heading>Rules for counting ballots.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-15-360__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The election board shall count ballots according to the following rules:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-15-360__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A voter may mark a ballot only by filling in, making X marks, diagonal, horizontal, or vertical marks, solid marks, stars, circles, asterisks, checks, or plus signs that are clearly spaced in the oval opposite the name of the candidate, proposition, or question that the voter desires to designate. In a general election, a voter may mark a ballot that requires the voter to vote for candidates in order of ranked preference by the use of numerals that are clearly spaced in one of the ovals opposite the name of the candidate that the voter desires to designate.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-15-360__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A failure to properly mark a ballot as to one or more candidates does not itself invalidate the entire ballot.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-15-360__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>If a voter marks more names than there are persons to be elected to the office, the votes for candidates for that office may not be counted.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-15-360__subsec_a__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The mark specified in (1) of this subsection shall be counted only if it is substantially inside the oval provided, or touching the oval so as to indicate clearly that the voter intended the particular oval to be designated.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-15-360__subsec_a__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Improper marks on the ballot may not be counted and do not invalidate marks for candidates properly made.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-15-360__subsec_a__subsec_6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>An erasure or correction invalidates only that section of the ballot in which it appears.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-15-360__subsec_a__subsec_7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A vote marked for the candidate for President or Vice-President of the United States is considered and counted as a vote for the election of the presidential electors.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-15-360__subsec_a__subsec_9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>[Repealed, § 3 ch 10 SLA 2011.]</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-15-360__subsec_a__subsec_10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>[Repealed, § 3 ch 10 SLA 2011.]</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-15-360__subsec_a__subsec_11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>[Repealed, § 3 ch 10 SLA 2011.]</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-15-360__subsec_a__subsec_12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>[Repealed, § 3 ch 10 SLA 2011.]</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-15-360__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The rules set out in this section are mandatory and there are no exceptions to them. A ballot may not be counted unless marked in compliance with these rules.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-15-360__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>[Repealed, § 24 ch 113 SLA 2003.]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-15-360__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Write-in votes shall be counted according to the following rules:</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-15-360__subsec_d__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>writing in the name of a candidate whose name is printed on the ballot does not invalidate a write-in vote unless the director determines, on the basis of other evidence, that the ballot was so marked for the purpose of identifying the ballot;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-15-360__subsec_d__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in order to vote for a write-in candidate, the voter must write in the candidate's name in the space provided and fill in the oval opposite the candidate's name in accordance with (a)(1) of this section;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-15-360__subsec_d__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a vote for a write-in candidate, other than a write-in vote for governor and lieutenant governor, shall be counted if the oval is filled in for that candidate and if the name of the candidate, as it appears on the write-in declaration of candidacy, or the last name of the candidate is written in the space provided;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-15-360__subsec_d__subsec_4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if the write-in vote is for governor and lieutenant governor, the vote shall be counted if the oval is filled in and the names of the candidates for governor and lieutenant governor, as they appear on the write-in declaration of candidacy, or the last names of the candidates for governor and lieutenant governor, or the name of the candidate for governor, as it appears on the write-in declaration of candidacy, or the last name of the candidate for governor is written in the space provided;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-15-360__subsec_d__subsec_5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in counting votes for a write-in candidate, the director shall disregard any abbreviation, misspelling, or other minor variation in the form of the name of a candidate if the intention of the voter can be ascertained.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-361">
            <num>15.15.361</num>
            <heading>Stickers.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.15.361.   Stickers.
Affixing stickers on a ballot in an election to vote for a write-in candidate is prohibited.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-365">
            <num>15.15.365</num>
            <heading>Counting of write-in votes in general election.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-15-365__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Write-in votes on a general election ballot shall be counted for a candidate only if the aggregate of all votes cast for all write-in candidates for the particular office is</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-15-365__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the highest number of votes received by any candidate for the office; or</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-15-365__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the second highest number of votes received by any candidate and the difference between the total number of votes received by the candidate having the highest number of votes and the aggregate of all votes cast for all write-in candidates for the office is less than the percentage necessary for a recount at the state's cost under
AS 15.20.450
.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-15-365__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Write-in votes that do not meet the requirements of this section may not be individually counted under this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-15-365__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the director determines that the requirements of (a) of this section have been met, the director shall establish the date for counting those write-in votes, and the director, or a designee of the director, shall count all write-in ballots under
AS 15.15.360
(d).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-15-365__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>This section does not apply to the counting of federal write-in absentee ballots submitted under 42 U.S.C. 1973ff.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-15-365__subsec_e">
              <num>(e)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Write-in ballots shall be counted by the director, or a designee of the director, in a public place at the location where write-in ballots are sent for counting following an election.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-370">
            <num>15.15.370</num>
            <heading>Completion of ballot count; certificate.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.15.370.   Completion of ballot count; certificate.
When the count of ballots is completed, and in no event later than the day after the election, the election board shall make a certificate in duplicate of the results. The certificate includes the number of votes cast for each candidate, including, for a candidate in a general election, the number of votes at each round of the ranked-choice tabulation process under
AS 15.15.350
, the number of votes for and against each proposition, yes or no on each question, and any additional information prescribed by the director. The election board shall, immediately upon completion of the certificate or as soon thereafter as the local mail service permits, send in one sealed package to the director one copy of the certificate and the register. In addition, all ballots properly cast shall be mailed to the director in a separate, sealed package. Both packages, in addition to an address on the outside, shall clearly indicate the precinct from which they come. Each board shall, immediately upon completion of the certification and as soon thereafter as the local mail service permits, send the duplicate certificate to the respective election supervisor. The director may authorize election boards in precincts in those areas of the state where distance and weather make mail communication unreliable to forward their election results by telephone or radio. The director may authorize the unofficial totaling of votes on a regional basis by election supervisors, tallying the votes as indicated on duplicate certificates. To ensure adequate protection, the director shall prescribe the manner in which the ballots, registers, and all other election records and materials are thereafter preserved, transferred, and destroyed.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-380">
            <num>15.15.380</num>
            <heading>Payment of election board members.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.15.380.   Payment of election board members.
The director shall pay each election board member for time spent at election duties, including the receiving of instructions. Election board chairpersons and the chairperson and members of the absentee ballot, questioned ballot, and state ballot counting review boards shall be paid for time spent at their election duties.  The director shall set the compensation to be paid under this section by regulation.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-390">
            <num>15.15.390</num>
            <heading>Election expenses.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.15.390.   Election expenses.
The director shall prescribe the manner of certifying, auditing, and paying election expenses, including the cost of giving notice, renting polling places, paying election officials, securing a ballot box, postage, and stationery, and obtaining similar election necessities.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-400">
            <num>15.15.400</num>
            <heading>Preparation of voter list.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.15.400.   Preparation of voter list.
The director shall prepare both a statewide list and a list by precinct of the names and addresses of all persons who voted in the election and their political party affiliation.  Any person may obtain a copy of the list, or a part of the list, or a computer tape containing both residence and mailing addresses of voters, by applying to the director and paying to the state treasury a fee as determined by the director.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-410">
            <num>15.15.410</num>
            <heading>Plural voting.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.15.410.   Plural voting.
Upon a determination that a person has voted more than once in the same election, the director shall notify the attorney general.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-420">
            <num>15.15.420</num>
            <heading>Duty to review the ballot counting.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.15.420.   Duty to review the ballot counting.
The director shall review the counting of the ballots with the assistance of and in the presence of the appointed representatives from the political parties.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-430">
            <num>15.15.430</num>
            <heading>Scope of the review of ballot counting.</heading>
            <subsection eId="15-15-430__subsec_a">
              <num>(a)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The review of ballot counting by the director shall include only</p>
              </content>
              <paragraph eId="15-15-430__subsec_a__subsec_1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a review of the precinct registers, tallies, and ballots cast;</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-15-430__subsec_a__subsec_2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>a review of absentee and questioned ballots as prescribed by law; and</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph eId="15-15-430__subsec_a__subsec_3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>unless the ballot for the house district contains nothing but uncontested offices, a hand count of ballots from one randomly selected precinct in each house district that accounts for at least five percent of the ballots cast in that district.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-15-430__subsec_b">
              <num>(b)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If, following the ballot review set out in (a) of this section, the director finds there is a discrepancy of more than one percent between the results of the hand count under (a)(3) of this section and the count certified by the election board, the director shall conduct a hand count of the ballots from that district.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-15-430__subsec_c">
              <num>(c)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the director finds an unexplained discrepancy in the ballot count in any precinct, the director may count the ballots from that precinct.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection eId="15-15-430__subsec_d">
              <num>(d)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The director shall certify in writing to the state ballot counting review board and publish on the division's Internet website any changes resulting from a count performed under (b) or (c) of this section.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-440">
            <num>15.15.440</num>
            <heading>State ballot counting review.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.15.440.   State ballot counting review.
The state ballot counting review shall begin as soon as practicable after the election is completed and not later than 16 days after an election and shall be continued until completed. The director may designate the hours each day during which the state ballot counting review board is to conduct its ballot counting review. The director shall close the review when the director is satisfied that no missing precinct certificate of election would, if received, change the result of the election. If no election certificate has been received from a precinct, the director may secure from the election supervisors and may count a certified copy of the duplicate election certificate of the precinct. If no election materials have been received, but election results have been received by telephone or radio, the director shall count the election results so received. If the director has reason to believe that a missing precinct certificate, if received, would affect the result of the election, the director shall await the receipt of the certificate until the close of business on the 15th day after the date of election. A certificate not actually delivered to the director by the close of business on the 15th day after the election may not be counted at the state ballot counting review.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-450">
            <num>15.15.450</num>
            <heading>Certification of state ballot counting review.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.15.450.   Certification of state ballot counting review.
Upon completion of the state ballot counting review the director shall certify the person receiving the largest number of votes for the office for which that person was nominated or elected, as applicable, and shall certify the approval of a justice or judge not rejected by a majority of the voters voting on the question. The director shall issue to the elected candidates and approved justices and judges a certificate of their election or approval. The director shall also certify the results of a proposition and other question except that the lieutenant governor shall certify the results of an initiative, referendum, or constitutional amendment.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-460">
            <num>15.15.460</num>
            <heading>Tie votes.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.15.460.   Tie votes.
If two or more candidates tie in having the highest number of votes for the same office for which there is to be elected only one candidate, the director shall so notify the candidates who are tied. The director shall immediately proceed with the recount of votes in the manner provided by
AS 15.20.430
 15.20.530.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-470">
            <num>15.15.470</num>
            <heading>Preservation of election ballots, papers, and materials.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.15.470.   Preservation of election ballots, papers, and materials.
The director shall preserve all precinct election certificates, tallies, and registers for four years after the election. All ballots and stubs for elections other than national elections may be destroyed 30 days after the certification of the state ballot counting review unless an application for recount has been filed and not completed, or unless their destruction is stayed by an order of the court. All ballots for national elections may be destroyed in accordance with federal law. The director may permit the inspection of election materials upon call by the Congress, the state legislature, or a court of competent jurisdiction.</p>
            </content>
          </section>
          <section eId="sec_15-15-480">
            <num>15.15.480</num>
            <heading>Security of ballots.</heading>
            <content>
              <p>Sec. 15.15.480.   Security of ballots.
All official ballots in the possession of election officials, whether voted or not voted, shall be kept in a secure manner until destroyed in accordance with law.  The director shall provide for the security of ballots during transportation and storage under
AS 44.62
(Administrative Procedure Act).</p>
            </content>
          </section>
        </chapter>
      </title>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>